<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="astell-serious-proposal">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Serious Proposal To the Ladies, For the Advancement of their
                    true and greatest Interest</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n83124681">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <surname>Astell</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>

                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name>
                            <forename>John </forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien </surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Markup and correction</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#RR">Students and Staff of the University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Rachel Retica</name>
                </respStmt>

                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Literature in Context </publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> 434-924-7105 </addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported Licence </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename>Mary</forename>
                                <surname>Astell</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title>A Serious Proposal To the Ladies, For the Advancement of their true
                            and greatest Interest</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed for R. Wilkin at the King's Head in St. Paul's
                                Church-Yard</publisher>
                            <date when="1694">1694</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">This text is based on transcriptions
                                created by the Early English Books Online Texts Creation
                                Partnership, a library-based project directed by the University of
                                Michigan and Oxford University, via <ref
                                    target="http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A26092.0001.001"
                                    >http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A26092.0001.001</ref>. </note>
                            <note>Page images are sourced from Yale University's Beineke
                                Library.</note>
                        </imprint>

                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Online</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Beineke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</publisher>
                            <date>nd</date>
                            <note>Selected page images are drawn from this edition, available in
                                full from Yale's digital collections online at <ref
                                    target="https://collections.library.yale.edu/catalog/16590941"
                                    >https://collections.library.yale.edu/catalog/16590941</ref>.</note>
                        </imprint>

                        <extent>[6], 73, [1] p</extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="philosophy">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
                    <time from="1666" to="1731">Late 17th, Early 18th Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-10-04" who="Rachel Retica">created LiC text</change>
            <change when="2023-10-31" who="editors.xml#TH">Updated sources and added page
                images</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[TP]" facs="pageImages/astell_TP.jpg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>A Serious<lb/> PROPOSAL<lb/>To the<lb/>Ladies,<lb/><hi rend="italic"
                            >For the Advancement of their true and greatest
                        Interest.<lb/></hi></titlePart>
                    <titlePart>By a Lover of her SEX.<lb/></titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="tgn" key="7011781"><hi rend="italic"
                            >LONDON<lb/></hi></placeName></pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed for <persName><hi rend="italic">R. Wilkin</hi></persName>
                        at<lb/> the <placeName><hi rend="italic">King's Head</hi></placeName> in
                                <placeName><hi rend="italic">St.
                            Paul's<lb/>Churchyard</hi></placeName>,</publisher>
                    <docDate>1694.</docDate>
                    <lb/>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/astell_1.jpg"/>
                <head type="main">A Serious<lb/>PROPOSAL<lb/>To the Ladies,<lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >For the Advancement of their<lb/> true and greatest Interest</hi></head>
                <p>LADIES,</p>
                <p>Since the Profitable Adventures that have gone abroad in the World,<pb n="2"
                    />have met with so great Encouragement, tho' the highest advantage they can
                    propose, is an uncertain Lot for such matters as Opinion (not real worth) gives
                    a value to; things which if obtain'd, are as flitting and fickle, as that Chance
                    which is to dispose of them. I therefore persuade my self, you will not be less
                    kind to a Proposition that comes attended with more certain and substantial
                    Gain; whose only design is to improve your Charms and heighten your Value, by
                    suffering you no longer to be cheap and contemptible. Itwouls aim<pb n="3"/>is
                    to fix that Beauty, to make it lasting and permanent, which Nature with all the
                    helps of Art, cannot secure: And to place it out of the reach of Sickness and
                    Old Age, by transferring it from a corruptible Body to an immortal Mind. An
                    obliging Design, which wou'd procure them <hi rend="italic">inward</hi> Beauty,
                    to whom Nature has unkindly denied the <hi rend="italic">outward;</hi> and not
                    permit those Ladies who have comely Bodies, to tarnish their Glory with deformed
                    Souls. Wou'd have you all be wits, or what is better Wise. Raise you above the
                    Vulgar <pb n="4"/>by something more truely illustrious, than a founding Title,
                    or a great Estate. Wou'd excite in you a generous Emulation to excel in the best
                    things, and not in such Trifles as every mean person who has but Mony enough,
                    may purchase as well as you. Not suffer you to take up with the low thought of
                    distinguishing your selves by any thing that is not truly valuable; and procure
                    you such Ornaments as all the Treasures of the <hi rend="italic">Indies</hi> are
                    not able to purchase. Wou'd help you to surpass the Men as much in Vertue and
                    Ingenuity, <pb n="5"/>as you do in Beauty; that you may not only be as lovely,
                    but as wise as Angels. Exalt and Establish your Fame, more than the best wrought
                        <hi rend="italic">Poems,</hi> and loudest <hi rend="italic"
                        >Panegyricks,</hi> by ennobling your Minds with such Graces as really
                    deserve it. And instead of the Fustian Complements and Fulsome Flatteries of
                    your Admirers, obtain for you the Plaudit of Good Men and Angels, and the
                    approbation of him who cannot err. In a word, render you the Glory and Blessing
                    of the present Age, and the Admiration and Pattern of the next.</p>

                <p><pb n="6"/>And sure, I shall not need many words to persuade you to close with
                    this Proposal. The very offer is a sufficient inducement; nor does it need the
                    set-off's of <hi rend="italic">Rhetorick</hi> to recommend it, were I capable,
                    which yet I am not, of applying them with the greatest force. Since you cannot
                    be so unkind to your selves, as to refuse your <hi rend="italic">real</hi>
                    Interest; I only entreat you to be so wise as to examine wherein it consists;
                    for nothing is of worser consequence than to be deceiv'd in a matter of so great
                    concern. 'Tis as little beneath your Grandeur as your Prudence, to examine<pb
                        n="7"/>curiously what is in this case offer'd you; and to take care that
                    cheating Hucksters don't impose upon you with deceitful Ware. This is a matter
                    infinitely more worthy your Debates, than what Colours are most agreeable, or
                    whats the Dress becomes you best? Your <hi rend="italic">Glass</hi> will not do
                    you half so much service as a serious reflection on your own Minds; which will
                    discover Irregularities more worthy your Correction, and keep you from being
                    either too much elated or depress'd by the representations of the other. 'Twill
                    not be near so advantagious <pb n="8"/>to consult with your Dancing-master as
                    with your own Thoughts, how you may with greatest exactness tread in the Paths
                    of Vertue, which has certainly the most attractive <hi rend="italic">Air,</hi>me
                    and Wisdom the most graceful and becoming <hi rend="italic">Meen:</hi> Let these
                    attend you, and your Carriage will be always well compos'd, and ev'ry thing you
                    do will carry its Charm with it. No solicitude in the adornation of your selves
                    is discommended, provided you employ your care about that which is really your
                        <hi rend="italic">self;</hi> and do not neglect that particle of Divinity
                    within <pb n="9"/>you, which must survive, and may (if you please) be happy and
                    perfect when it's unsuitable and much inferiour Companion is mouldring into
                    Dust. Neither will any pleasure be denied you, who are only desir'd not to catch
                    at the Shadow and let the Substance go. You may be as ambitious as you please,
                    so you aspire to the best <hi rend="italic">things;</hi> and contend with your
                    Neighbours as much as you can, that they may not outdo you in any commendable
                    Quality. Let it never be said, that they to whom preeminence is so very
                    agreeable, can be tamely content <pb n="10"/> that others shou'd surpass them in
                        <hi rend="italic">this,</hi> and precede them in a <hi rend="italic"
                        >better</hi> World! Remember, I pray you, the famous Women of former Ages,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Orinda</hi>'s of late, and the more Modern <hi
                        rend="italic">D'acier</hi> and others, and blush to think how much is now,
                    and will hereafter be said of them, when you your selves (as great a Figure as
                    you make) must be buried in silence and forgetfulness! Shall your Emulation fail
                        <hi rend="italic">there only,</hi> where it is commendable? Why are you so
                    preposterously humble, as not to contend for one of the highest Mansions in the
                    Court of Heav'n? Believe <pb n="11"/>me Ladies, this is the only <hi
                        rend="italic">Place</hi> worth contending for; you are neither better nor
                    worse in your selves for going before, or coming after <hi rend="italic"
                        >now;</hi> but you are really so much the better, by how much the higher
                    your station is in an Orb of Glory. How can you be content to be in the world
                    like Tulips in a Garden, to make a fine <hi rend="italic">shew</hi> and be good
                    for nothing; have all your Glories set in the grave, or perhaps much sooner?
                    What your own sentiments are, I know not, but I cannot without pity and
                    resentment reflect, that those Glorious Temples on which <pb n="12"/>your kind
                    Creator has bestow'd such exquisite workmanship, shou'd enshrine no better than
                        <hi rend="italic">Egyptian</hi> Deities; be like a garnish'd Sepulchre,
                    which for all it's glittering, has nothing within but Emptiness or Putrifaction!
                    What a pity it is, that whilst your Beauty casts a lustre round about, your
                    Souls which are infinitely more bright and radiant (of which if you had but a
                    clear Idea, as lovely as it is, and as much as you now value it, you wou'd then
                    despise and neglect the mean <hi rend="italic">Case</hi> that encloses it)
                    shou'd be suffer'd to overrun with Weeds, lye fallow<pb n="13"/>and neglected,
                    unadorn'd with any Grace! Altho the Beauty of the Mind is necessary to secure
                    those Conquests which your Eyes have gain'd; and Time that mortal Enemy to
                    handsome Faces, has no influence on a lovely Soul, but to better and improve it.
                    For shame, let us abandon that <hi rend="italic">Old</hi>, and therefore one
                    wou'd think, unfashionable employment of pursuing Butterflies and Trifles! No
                    longer drudge on in the dull beaten road of Vanity and Folly so many have gone,
                    before us; but dare to break the enchanted Circle that custom has <pb n="14"/>
                    plac'd us in, atnd scorn the vulgar way of imitating all the Impertinencies of
                    our Neighbours. Let us learn to pride our selves in something more excellent
                    than the invention of a Fashion: And not entertain such a degrading thought of
                    our own <hi rend="italic">worth,</hi> as to imagine that our Souls were given us
                    only for the service of our Bodies, and that the best improvement we can make of
                    these, is to attract the eyes of men. We value <hi rend="italic">them</hi> too
                    much, and our selves too little, if we place any part of our worth in their
                    Opinion; and do not think our <hi rend="italic">selves</hi> capable of <pb
                        n="15"/>Nobler Things than the pitiful Conquest of some worthless heart. She
                    who has opportunities of making an interest in Heav'n, of obtaining the love and
                    admiration of GOD and Angels, is too prodigal of her Time, and injurious to her
                    Charms, to throw them away on vain insignificant men. She need not make her self
                    so cheap, as to descend to Court their Applauses; for at the greater distance
                    she keeps, and the more she is above them, the more effectually she secures
                    their esteem and wonder. Be so generous then Ladies, as to do nothing unworthy
                    of you; so <pb n="16"/> true to your Interest as not to lessen your Empire, and
                    depreciate your Charms. Let not your Thoughts be wholly busied in observing what
                    respect is paid you, but a part of them at least, in studying to deserve it. And
                    after all, remember, <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Goodness is the truest
                    Greatness, to be wise for your selves, the greatest Wit, and that Beauty the
                    most desirable, which will endure to Eternity.</p>

                <p>Pardon me the seeming rudeness of this Proposal, which goes upon a supposition
                    that there is something amiss in you, which it is <pb n="17"/>intended to amend.
                    My design is not to expose, but to rectify your Failures. To be exempt from
                    mistake, is a priviledge few can pretend to, the greatest is to be past
                    Conviction, and too obstinate to reform. Even the <hi rend="italic">Men,</hi> as
                    exact as they wou'd seem, and as much as they divert themselves with our
                    Miscarriages, are very often guilty of greater faults; and such as considering
                    the advantages they enjoy, are much more inexcusable. But I will not pretend to
                    correct their Errors, who either are or at least <hi rend="italic">think</hi>
                    themselves too wise to receive Instruction <pb n="18"/> from a Womans Pen. My
                    earnest desire is, that you Ladies, would be as perfect and happy as 'tis
                    possible to be in this imperfect state; for I love you too well to endure a spot
                    upon your Beauties, if I can by any means remove and wipe it off. I would have
                    you live up to the dignity of your Nature, and express your thankfulness to GOD
                    for the benefits you enjoy by a due improvement of them: As I know very many of
                    you do, who countenance that Piety which the men decry, and are the brightest
                    Patterns of Religion that <pb n="19"/> the Age affords; 'tis my grief that all
                    the rest of our Sex do not imitate such illustrious Patterns, and therefore I
                    would have them encreas'd and render'd more conspicuous, that Vice being put out
                    of countenance, (because Vertue is the only thing in fashion) may sneak out of
                    the world, and it's darkness be dispell'd by the confluence of so many shining
                    Graces. Some perhaps will cry out that I teach you false Doctrine; for because
                    by their seductions, some amongst us are become very mean and contemptible, they
                    would fain persuade the rest to be as despicable <pb n="20"/> and forlorn as
                    they. We are indeed oblig'd to them for their management, in endeavouring to
                    make us so; who use all artifice they can to spoil, and deny us the means of
                    improvement. So that instead of inquiring why all Women are not wise and good,
                    we have reason to wonder that there are any so. Were the men as much neglected,
                    and as little care taken to cultivate and improve them, perhaps they wou'd be so
                    far from surpassing those whom they now despise, that they themselves wou'd sink
                    into the greatest stupidity and brutality. The <pb n="21"/> preposterous returns
                    that the most of them make, to all the care and pains that is bestow'd on them,
                    renders this no uncharitable, nor improbable Conjecture. One wou'd therefore
                    almost think, that the wise disposer of all things, foreseeing how unjustly
                    Women are denied opportunities of improvement from <hi rend="italic"
                        >without,</hi> has therefore by way of compensation endow'd them with
                    greater propensions to Vertue, and a natural goodness of Temper <hi
                        rend="italic">within,</hi> which if duly manag'd, would raise them to the
                    most eminent pitch of Heroick Vertue. Hither Ladies, I desire you <pb n="22"/>
                    wou'd aspire, 'tis a noble and becoming Ambition; and to remove such Obstacles
                    as lye in your way, is the design of this Paper. We will therefore enquire what
                    it is that stops your flight, that keeps you groveling here below, like <hi
                        rend="italic">Domitian</hi> catching Flies, when you should be busied in
                    obtaining Empires?</p>

                <p>Whatever has been said by Men of more Wit than Wisdom, and perhaps of more malice
                    than either, that Women are naturally Incapable of acting Prudently, or that
                    they are necessarily determined to folly, I must by no means <pb n="22"/> grant
                    it; that Hypothesis would render my endeavours impertinent, for then it would be
                    in vain to advise the one, or endeavour the Reformation of the other. Besides,
                    there are Examples in all Ages, which sufficiently confute the Ignorance and
                    Malice of this Assertion.</p>
                <pb n="23"/>
                <p>The Incapacity, if there be any, is acquired not natural; and none of their
                    Follies are so necessary, but that they might avoid them if they pleased
                    themselves. Some disadvantages indeed they labour under, &amp; what these are we
                    shall see by and by, and endeavour <pb n="23"/> to surmount; but Women need not
                    take up with mean things, since (if they are not wanting to themselves) they are
                    capable of the best. Neither God nor Nature have excluded them from being
                    Ornaments to their Families, and useful in their Generation; there is therefore
                    no reason they should be content to be Cyphers in the World, useless at the
                    best, and in a little time a burden and nuisance to all about them. And 'tis
                    very great pity that they who are so apt to over-rate themselves in smaller
                    matters, shou'd, where it most concerns <pb n="25"/> them to know, and stand
                    upon their Value, be so insensible of their own worth.</p>

                <p>The cause therefore of the defects we labour under, is, if not wholly, yet at
                    least in the first place, to be ascribed to the mistakes of our Education; which
                    like an Error in the first Concoction, spreads its ill Influence thro' all our
                    Lives.</p>
                <p>The Soil is rich and would, if well cultivated, produce a noble Harvest, if then
                    the Unskilful Managers not only permit, but incourage noxious Weeds, tho' we
                    shall suffer by their Neglect, yet <pb n="26"/> they ought not in justice to
                    blame any but themselves, if they reap the Fruit of their own Folly. Women are
                    from their very Infancy debar'd those Advantages, with the want of which, they
                    are afterwards reproached, and nursed up in those Vices which will hereafter be
                    upbraided to them. So partial are Men as to expect Brick where they afford no
                    straw; and so abundantly civil as to take care we shou'd make good that obliging
                    Epithet of <hi rend="italic">Ignorant,</hi> which out of an excess of good
                    Manners, they are pleas'd to bestow on us!</p>


                <p><pb n="27"/>One wou'd be apt to think indeed, that Parents shou'd take all
                    possible care of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> Childrens Education, not only for
                    their sakes, but even for their <hi rend="italic">own.</hi> And tho the Son
                    convey the Name to Posterity, yet certainly a great Part of the Honour of their
                    Families depends on their Daughters. 'Tis the kindness of Education that binds
                    our duty fastest on us: For the being instrumental to the bringing us into the
                    world, is no matter of choice, and therefore the less obliging: But to procure
                    that we may live wisely and happily in it, and be capable of <pb n="28"/>
                    endless Joys hereafter, is a benefit we can never sufficiently acknowledge. To
                    introduce poor Children into the world, and neglect to fence them against the
                    temptations of it, and so leave them expos'd to temporal and eternal Miseries,
                    is a wickedness, for which I want a Name; 'tis beneath Brutality, the Beasts are
                    better natur'd, for they take care of their off-spring, till they are capable of
                    caring for themselves. And, if Mothers had a due regard to their Posterity, how
                        <hi rend="italic">Great</hi> soever they are, they wou'd not think
                    themselves too <hi rend="italic">Good</hi> to perform what Nature <pb n="29"/>
                    requires, nor thro' Pride and Delicacy remit the poor little one to the care of
                    a Foster Parent. Or, if necessity inforce them to depute another to perform
                    their Duty, they wou'd be as choice at least in the Manners and Inclinations, as
                    they are in the complections of their Nurses, least with their Milk they
                    transfuse their Vices, and form in the Child such evil habits as will not easily
                    be eradicated.</p>

                <p>Nature as bad as it is, and as much as it is complain'd of, is so far improveable
                    by the grace of GOD, upon our honest and hearty endeavours, that if we are not
                        <pb n="30"/> wanting to our selves, we may all in <hi rend="italic"
                        >some,</hi> tho not in an <hi rend="italic">equal</hi> measure, be
                    instruments of his Glory, Blessings to this world, and capable of eternal
                    Blessedness in that to come. But if our Nature is spoil'd, instead of being
                    improv'd at first; if from our Infancy, we are nurs'd up in Ignorance and
                    Vanity; are taught to be Proud and Petulent, Delicate and Fantastick, Humorous
                    and Inconstant, 'tis not strange that the ill effects of this Conduct appears in
                    all the future Actions of our Lives. And seeing it is Ignorance, either habitual
                    or actual, which is <pb n="31"/> the cause of all sin, how are they like to
                    escape <hi rend="italic">this,</hi> who are bred up in <hi rend="italic"
                        >that?</hi> That therefore women are unprofitable to most, and a plague and
                    dishonour to some men is not much to be regretted on account of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Men,</hi> because 'tis the product of their own folly, in
                    denying them the benefits of an ingenuous and liberal Education, the most
                    effectual means to direct them into, and to secure their progress in the ways of
                    Vertue.</p>

                <p>For that Ignorance is the cause of most Feminine Vices may be instanc'd in that
                    Pride and Vanity which is usually imputed to us, and <pb n="32"/> which, I
                    suppose, if throughly sifted, will appear to be some way or other, the rise and
                    Original of all the rest. These, tho very bad Weeds, are the product of a good
                    Soil; they are nothing else but Generosity degenerated and corrupted. A desire
                    to advance and perfect its Being, is planted by GOD in all Rational Natures, to
                    excite them hereby to every worthy and becoming Action; for certainly, next to
                    the Grace of GOD, nothing does so powerfully restrain people from Evil, and stir
                    them up to Good, as a generous Temper. And therefore to be ambitious of
                    perfections <pb n="33"/> is no fault; tho to assume the Glory of our
                    Excellencies to our selves, or to Glory in such as we really have not, are. And
                    were Womens haughtiness express'd in disdaining to do a mean and evil thing;
                    wou'd they pride themselves in somewhat truly perfective of a Rational Nature,
                    there were no hurt in it. But then they ought not to be denied the means of
                    examining and judging what is so; they should not be impos'd on with tinsel
                    ware. If by reason of a false Light, or undue Medium, they chuse amiss; theirs
                    is the loss, but the Crime is the <pb n="34"/> Deceivers. She who rightly
                    understands wherein the perfection of her Nature consists, will lay out her
                    Thoughts and Industry in the acquisition of such Perfections. But she who is
                    kept ignorant of the matter, will take up with such Objects as first offer
                    themselves, and bear any plausible resemblance to what she desires; a shew of
                    advantage is sufficient to render them agreeable baits to her, who wants
                    Judgment and skill to discern between reality and pretence. From whence it
                    easily follows, that she who has nothing else to <pb n="35"/> value her self
                    upon, will be proud of her Beauty, or Money, and what that can purchase; and
                    think her self mightily oblig'd to him, who tells her she has those Perfections
                    which she naturally longs for. Her imbred self-esteem, and desire of good, which
                    are degenerated into Pride, and mistaken self-love, will easily open her Ears to
                    whatever goes about to nourish and delight them; and when a cunning designing
                    Enemy from without, has drawn over to his Party these Traytors within, he has
                    the Poor unhappy Person at his Mercy, who now very glibly <pb n="36"/> swallows
                    down his Poyson, because 'tis presented in a Golden Cup; and credulously
                    hearkens to the most disadvantagious Proposals, because they come attended with
                    a seeming esteem. She whose Vanity makes her swallow praises by the whole sale,
                    without examining whether she deserves them, or from what hand they come, will
                    reckon it but gratitude to think well of him who values her so much; and think
                    she must needs be merciful to the poor dispairing Lover whom her Charms have
                    reduc'd to die at her feet. Love and Honour are what every <pb n="37"/> one of
                    us naturally esteem; they are excellent things in themselves, and very worthy
                    our regard; and by how much the readier we are to embrace what ever resembles
                    them, by so much the more dangerous, it is that these venerable Names should be
                    wretchedly abus'd, and affixt to their direct contraries, yet this is the Custom
                    of the World: And how can she possibly detect the fallacy, who has no better
                    Notion of either, but what she derives from Plays and Romances? How can she be
                    furnished with any solid Principles whose very Instructors are Froth <pb n="38"
                    /> and emptiness? Whereas Women were they rightly Educated, had they obtain'd a
                    well inform'd and discerning Mind, they would be proof against all these
                    Batteries, see through and scorn those little silly Artifices which are us'd to
                    ensnare and deceive them. Such an one would value her self only on her Vertue,
                    and consequently be most chary of what she esteems so much. She would know, that
                    not what others say, but what she her self does, is the true Commendation, and
                    the only thing that exalts her; the loudest Encomiums being not half so
                    satisfactory <pb n="39"/> as the calm and secret Plaudit of her own Mind; which
                    moving on true Principles of Honour and Vertue, wou'd not fail on a review of it
                    self to anticipate that delightful Eulogy she shall one day hear.</p>

                <p>Whence is it but from ignorance, from a want of understanding to compare and
                    judge of things, to chuse a right end, to proportion the means to the end, and
                    to rate ev'ry thing according to its proper value; that we quit the Substance
                    for the Shadow, Reality for Appearance, and embrace those very things, which if
                    we understood, we shou'd hate and <pb n="40"/> fly, but now are reconcil'd to,
                    merely because they usurp the Name, tho they have nothing of the Nature of those
                    venerable Objects we desire and seek? Were it not for this delusion, is it
                    probable a Lady who passionately desires to be admir'd, shou'd ever consent to
                    such Actions as render her base and contemptible? Wou'd she be so absurd as to
                    think either to get love, or to keep it, by those methods which occasion
                    loathing, and consequently end in hatred? Wou'd she reckon it a piece of her
                    Grandeur, or hope to gain esteem by such excesses as really lessen her in the
                    eyes of all considerate <pb n="41"/> and judicious persons? Wou'd she be so
                    silly as to look big, and think her self the better person, because she has more
                    Mony to bestow profusely, or the good luck to have a more ingenious Taylor or
                    Milliner than her Neighbour? Wou'd she who by the regard she pays to Wit, seems
                    to make some pretences to it, undervalue her Judgment so much as to admit the
                    Scurrility and profane noisy Nonsense of men, whose Fore-heads are better than
                    their Brains to pass under that Character? Wou'd she be so weak as to imagine
                    that a few airy Fancies, joyn'd with a great deal of <pb n="42"/> Impudence (the
                    right definition of modern Wit) can be speak him a Man of sense, who runs
                    counter to all the sense and reason that ever appear'd in the world? than which
                    nothing can be an Argument of greater shallowness, unless it be to regard and
                    esteem him for it. Wou'd a woman, if she truly understood her self, be affected
                    either with the praises or calumnies of those worthless persons, whose Lives are
                    a direct contradiction to Reason, a very sink of corruption; by whom one wou'd
                    blush to be commended, lest they shou'd be mistaken for Partners or <pb n="43"/>
                    Connivers at their Crimes? Will she who has a jot of discernment think to
                    satisfy her greedy desire of Pleasure, with those promising nothings that have
                    again &amp; again deluded her? Or, will she to obtain such Bubbles, run the
                    risque of forfeiting Joys, infinitely satisfying and eternal? In sum, did not
                    ignorance impose on us, we would never lavish out the greatest part of our Time
                    and Care, on the decoration of a Tenement, in which our Lease is so very short,
                    and which for all our industry, may lose it's Beauty e're that Lease be out, and
                    in the mean while neglect a <pb n="44"/> more glorious and durable Mansion! We
                    wou'd never be so curious of the House, and so careless of the Inhabitant, whose
                    beauty is capable of great improvement, and will endure for ever without
                    diminution or decay!</p>

                <p>Thus Ignorance and a narrow Education, lay the Foundation of Vice, and imitation
                    and custom rear it up. Custom, that merciless torrent that carries all before.
                    And which indeed can be stem'd by none but such as have a great deal of Prudence
                    and a rooted Vertue. For 'tis but Decorous that she who is not capable of <pb
                        n="45"/> giving better Rules, shou'd follow those she sees before her, lest
                    she only change the instance, and retain the absurdity. 'T wou'd puzzle a
                    considerate Person to account for all that Sin and Folly that is in the World,
                    (whcih certainly has nothing in it self to recommend it,) did not custom help to
                    solve the difficulty. For Vertue without question has on all accounts the
                    preeminence of Vice 'tis abundantly more pleasant in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Act,</hi> as well as more advantagious in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >consequences,</hi> as any one who will but rightly use her reason, in a
                    serious reflection on her self, and the <pb n="46"/> nature of things, may
                    easily perceive. 'Tis custom therefore, that Tyrant Custom, which is the grand
                    motive to all those irrational choices which we daily see made in the World, so
                    very contrary to our <hi rend="italic">present</hi> interest and pleasure, as
                    well as to our Future. We think it an unpardonable mistake, not to do what
                    others do round about us, and part with our Peace and Pleasure as well as our
                    Innocence &amp; Vertue, meerly in complyance with an unreasonable Fashion. And
                    having inur'd our selves to Folly, we know not how to quit it; we go on in Vice,
                    not because we find satisfaction <pb n="47"/> in it, but because we are
                    unacquainted with the Joys of Vertue.</p>

                <p>Add to this the hurry and noise of the world, which does generally so busy and
                    pre-ingage us, that we have little time, and less inclination to stand still and
                    reflect on our own Minds. Those impertinent Amusements which have seiz'd us,
                    keep their hold so well, and so constantly buz about our Ears, that we cannot
                    attend to the Dictates of our Reason, nor to the soft whispers and winning
                    persuasives of the divine Spirit, by whose assistance were we dispos'd to make
                    use of it, we might <pb n="48"/> shake off these Follies, and regain our
                    Freedom. But alas! to complete our misfortunes, by a continual application to
                    Vanity and Folly, we quite spoil the contexture and frame of our Minds; so
                    loosen and dissipate, that nothing solid and substantial will stay in it. By an
                    habitual inadvertency we render our selves incapable of any serious &amp;
                    improving thought, till our minds themselves become as light and frothy as those
                    things they are conversant about. To all which, if we further add the great
                    industry that bad people use to corrupt the good, and that unaccountable <pb
                        n="49"/> backwardness that appears in too many good persons, to stand up
                    for, and propagate the Piety they profess; (so strangely are things transposed,
                    that Vertue puts on the blushes, which belong to Vice, and Vice insults with the
                    authority of Vertue!) and we have a pretty fair account of the Causes of our
                    non-improvement.</p>

                <p>When a poor Young Lady is taught to value her self on nothing but her Cloaths,
                    and to think she's very fine when well accoutred. When she hears say, that 'tis
                    Wisdom enough for her to know how to dress <pb n="50"/> her self, that she may
                    become amiable in his eyes, to whom it appertains to be knowing and learned; who
                    can blame her if she lay out her Industry and Money on such Accomplishments, and
                    sometimes extends it farther than her misinformer desires she should? When she
                    sees the vain and the gay, making Parade in the World, and attended with the
                    Courtship and admiration of all about them, no wonder that her tender Eyes are
                    dazled with the Pageantry; and wanting Judgment to pass a due Estimate on them
                    and their Admirers, longs to be such a fine and celebrated <pb n="51"/> thing as
                    they! What tho' she be sometimes told of another World, she has however a more
                    lively perception of this, and may well think, that if her Instructors were in
                    earnest, when they tell her of <hi rend="italic">hereafter,</hi> they would not
                    be so busied and concerned about what happens <hi rend="italic">here.</hi>  She
                    is, it may be, taught the Principles and Duties of Religion, but not acquainted
                    with the Reasons and Grounds of them; being told, 'tis enough for her to
                    believe, to examin why, and wherefore belongs not to her. And therefore, though
                    her Piety may be tall and spreading, <pb n="52"/> yet because it wants
                    foundation and Root, the first rude Temptation overthrows and blasts it; or
                    perhaps the short liv'd Gourd decays and withers of its own accord. But why
                    should she be blamed for setting no great value on her Soul, whose noblest
                    Faculty, her Understanding is render'd useless to her? Or censur'd for
                    relinquishing a course of Life, whose Prerogatives she was never acquainted
                    with, and tho highly reasonable in it self, was put upon the embracing it, with
                    as little reason as she now forsakes it? For if her Religion it self, be taken
                    up as the Mode of the <pb n="53"/> Country, 'tis no strange thing that she lays
                    it down again, in conformity to the Fashion. Whereas she whose Reason is
                    suffer'd to display it self, to inquire into the grounds and Motives of
                    Religion, to make a disquisition of its Graces, and search out its hidden
                    Beauties; who is a Christian out of Choice, not in conformity to those about
                    her; and cleaves to Piety, because 'tis her Wisdom, her Interest, her Joy, not
                    because she has been accustom'd to it; she who is not only eminently and
                    unmoveably good, but able to give a Reason <hi rend="italic">why</hi> she is so;
                    is too firm and stable <pb n="54"/> to be mov'd by the pitiful Allurements of
                    sin, too wise and too well bottom'd to be undermin'd and supplanted by the
                    strongest Efforts of Temptation. Doubtless a truly Christian Life requires a
                    clear Understanding, as well as regular Affections, that both together may move
                    the Will to a direct choice of Good, and a stedfast adherence to it. For tho the
                    heart may be honest, it is but by chance that the Will is right, if the
                    Understanding be ignorant and Cloudy. And whats the reason that we sometimes
                    unhappily see persons falling off from their Piety, but <pb n="55"/> because
                    'twas their Affections, not their Judgment, that inclin'd them to be Religious?
                    Reason and Truth are firm and immutable, she who bottoms on them is on sure
                    ground: Humour and Inclination are sandy Foundations; and she who is sway'd by
                    her Affections more than by her Judgment, owes the happiness of her Soul in a
                    great measure to the temper of her Body; her Piety may perhaps blaze higher, but
                    will not last so long. For the Affections are various and changeable, mov'd by
                    every Object, and the last comer easily undoes whatever <pb n="56"/> its
                    Predecessor had done before it. Such Persons are always in extreams; they are
                    either violently good, or quite cold and indifferent, a perpetual trouble to
                    themselves &amp; others, by indecent Raptures, or unnecessary Scruples; there is
                    no Beauty and order in their lives, all is rapid and unaccountable; they are now
                    very furious in such a course, but they cannot well tell why, &amp; anon as
                    violent in the other extream. Having more <hi rend="italic">Heat</hi> than <hi
                        rend="italic">Light,</hi> their Zeal out runs their knowledge and instead of
                    representing Piety as it is in it self, the most lovely and inviting <pb n="57"
                    /> thing imaginable, they expose it to the contempt and ridicule of the
                    censorious World. Their Devotion being ricketed, starv'd and contracted in some
                    of it's vital parts, and disproportioned and over grown in less material
                    instances; whilst one Duty is <hi rend="italic">over done,</hi> to commute for
                    the neglect of another, and the mistaken Person thinks the being often on her
                    knees, attones for all the miscarriages of her Conversation: Not considering
                    that 'tis in vain to Petition for those Graces which we take no care to
                    Practice, and a mockery to adore those Perfections we <pb n="58"/> run counter
                    to: and that the true end of all our Prayers and external Observances, is to
                    work our minds into a truly Christian temper, to obtain for us the Empire of our
                    Passions, and to reduce all irregular Inclinations, that so we may be as like
                    GOD in Purity, Charity, and all his imitable excellencies, as is consistent with
                    the imperfection of a Creature.</p>

                <p>And now having discovered the Disease and its cause, 'tis proper to apply a
                    Remedy; single Medicines are too weak to cure such complicated Distempers, they
                    require a full Dispensatory; and what wou'd a good woman <pb n="59"/> refuse to
                    do, could she hope by that to advantage the greatest part of the world, and
                    improve her Sex in Knowledge and true Religion? I doubt not Ladies, but that the
                    Age, as bad as it is, affords very many of you who will readily embrace whatever
                    has a true tendency to the Glory of GOD, and your mutual Edification, to revive
                    the antient Spirit of Piety in the World, and to transmit it to succeeding
                    Generations. I know there are many of you who so ardently love GOD, as to think
                    no time too much to spend in his service, nor any thing too difficult to do <pb
                        n="60"/> for his sake; and bear such a hearty good-will to your Neighbours,
                    as to grudge no Prayers or Pains to reclaim and improve them. I have therefore
                    no more to do, but to make the Proposal, to prove that it will answer these
                    great and good Ends, and then 'twill be easy to obviate the Objections that
                    Persons of more Wit than Vertue may happen to raise against it.</p>

                <p>Now as to the Proposal, it is to erect a <hi rend="italic">Monastry,</hi> or if
                    you will (to avoid giving offence to the scrupulous and injudicious, by names
                    which tho innocent in themselves, have been abus'd by superstitious <pb n="61"/>
                    Practices.) we will call it a <hi rend="italic">Religious Retirement,</hi> and
                    such as shall have a double aspect, being not only a Retreat from the World for
                    those who desire that advantage; but likewise, an institution and previous
                    discipline, to fit us to do the greatest good in it; such an institution as this
                    (if I do not mightily deceive my self,) would be the most probable method to
                    amend the present, and improve the future Age. For here, those who are convinc'd
                    of the emptiness of earthly Enjoyments, who are sick of the vanity of the world,
                    and its impertinencies, may find more <pb n="62"/> substantial and satisfying
                    entertainments, and need not be confin'd to what they justly loath. Those who
                    are desirous to know and fortify their weak side, first do good to themselves,
                    that hereafter they may be capable of doing more good to others; or for their
                    greater security are willing to avoid <hi rend="italic">temptation,</hi> may get
                    out of that danger which a continual stay in view of the Enemy, and the
                    familiarity and unwearied application of the Temptation may expose them to; and
                    gain an opportunity to look into themselves, to be acquainted at home, and no
                    longer the greatest strangers <pb n="63"/> to their own hearts. Such as are
                    willing in a more peculiar and undisturb'd manner, to attend the great business
                    they came into the world about, the service of GOD, and improvement of their own
                    Minds, may find a convenient and blissful recess from the noise and hurry of the
                    world. A world so cumbersom, so infectious, that altho' thro' the grace of GOD,
                    and their own strict watchfulness, they are kept from sinking down into its
                    corruptions, 'twill however damp their flight to heav'n, hinder them from
                    attaining any eminent pitch of Vertue.</p>

                <p><pb n="64"/> You are therefore Ladies, invited into a place, where you shall
                    suffer no other confinement, but to be kept out of the road of sin: You shall
                    not be depriv'd of your grandeur, but only exchange the vain Pomps and Pageantry
                    of the world, empty Titles and Forms of State, for the true and solid Greatness
                    of being able to dispise <hi rend="italic">them.</hi>  You will only quit the
                    Chat of insignificant people, for an ingenious Conversation; the froth of flashy
                    wit for real wisdom; idle tales for instructive discourses. The deceitful
                    Flatteries of those who under pretence of loving and admiring you, really served
                        <pb n="65"/> their <hi rend="italic">own</hi> base ends, for the seasonable
                    Reproofs and wholsom Counsels of your hearty well-wishers and affectionate
                    Friends; which will procure you those perfections your feigned lovers pretended
                    you had, and kept you from obtaining. No uneasy task will be enjoyn'd you, all
                    your labour being only to prepare for the highest degrees of that Glory, the
                    very lowest of which, is more than at present you are able to conceive, and the
                    prospect of it sufficient to out-weigh all the Pains of Religion, were there any
                    in it, as really there is none. All that is requir'd of <pb n="66"/> you, is
                    only to be as happy as possibly you can, and to make sure of a Felicity that
                    will fill all the capacities of your Souls! A happiness, which when once you
                    have tasted, you'l be fully convinc'd, you cou'd never do too much to obtain it;
                    nor be too solicitous to adorn your Souls, with such tempers and dispositions,
                    as will at present make you in some measure such holy and Heavenly Creatures, as
                    you one day hope to be in a more perfect manner; without which Qualifications
                    you can neither reasonably <hi rend="italic">expect,</hi> nor are <hi
                        rend="italic">capable</hi> of enjoying the Happiness of the <pb n="67"/>
                    Life to come. Happy Retreat! which will be the introducing you into such a <hi
                        rend="italic">Paradise</hi> as your Mother <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>
                    forfeited, where you shall feast on Pleasures, that do not, like those of the
                    World, disappoint your expectations, pall your Appetites, and by the disgust
                    they give you, put you on the fruitless search after new Delights, which when
                    obtain'd are as empty as the former; but such as will make you truly happy <hi
                        rend="italic">now,</hi> and prepare you to be <hi rend="italic"
                        >perfectly</hi> so hereafter. Here are no Serpents to deceive you, whilst
                    you entertain your selves in these delicious Gardens. <pb n="68"/> No
                    Provocations are given in this Amicable Society, but to Love and to good Works,
                    which will afford such an entertaining employment, that you'l have as little
                    inclination as leisure to pursue those Follies which in the time of your
                    ignorance pass'd with you under the name of love; altho' there is not in nature
                    two more different things, than <hi rend="italic">true Love,</hi> and that <hi
                        rend="italic">brutish Passion</hi> which pretends to ape it. Here will be no
                    Rivalling but for the love of GOD, no ambition but to procure his Favour, to
                    which nothing will more effectually recommend you, <pb n="69"/> than a great and
                    dear affection to each other. Envy, that Canker, will not here disturb your
                    Breasts; for how can she repine at anothers wel-fare, who reckons it the
                    greatest part of her own? No Covetousness will gain admittance in this blest
                    abode, but to amass huge Treasures of good Works, and to procure one of the
                    brightest Crowns of Glory. You will not be solicitous to encrease your Fortunes,
                    but enlarge your Minds; esteeming no Grandeur like being conformable to the meek
                    and humble JESUS. So that you only withdraw from the noise and trouble, <pb
                        n="70"/> the folly and temptation of the world, that you may more peaceably
                    enjoy your selves, and all the innocent Pleasures it is able to afford you, and
                    particularly that which is worth all the rest, a noble, Vertuous and
                    Disinteress'd Friendship. And to compleat all that <hi rend="italic">acme</hi>
                    of delight which the devout Seraphic Soul enjoys, when dead to the World, she
                    devotes her self entirely to the contemplation and fruition of her Beloved; when
                    having disengag'd her self from all those Lets which hindred her from without,
                    she moves in a direct and vigorous motion towards her <pb n="71"/> true and only
                    Good, whom now she embraces and acquiesces in, with such an unspeakable
                    pleasure, as is only intelligible to them who have tried and felt it, which we
                    can no more describe to the dark and sensual part of Mankind, than we can the
                    beauty of Colours, and harmony of Sounds, to the Blind and Deaf. In fine, the
                    place to which you are invited will be a Type and Antipast of Heav'n, where your
                    Employment will be as there, to magnify GOD, and to love one another, and to
                    communicate that useful <hi rend="italic">knowledge,</hi> which by the due
                    improvement of <pb n="72"/> your time in Study and Contemplation you will
                    obtain; and which when obtain'd, will afford you a much sweeter and durable
                    delight, than all those pitiful diversions, those revellings and amusements,
                    which now thro your ignorance of better, appear the only grateful and relishing
                    Entertainments.</p>

                <p>But because we were not made for our selves, nor can by any means so effectually
                    glorify GOD, and do good to our own Souls, as by doing Offices of Charity and
                    Beneficence to others; and to the intent, that every Vertue, and the highest
                    degrees of every Vertue, may be exercis'd <pb n="73"/> &amp; promoted the most
                    that may be; your Retreat shall be so manag'd as not to exclude the good Works
                    of an <hi rend="italic">Active,</hi> from the pleasure and serenity of a <hi
                        rend="italic">contemplative</hi> Life, but by a due mixture of both, retain
                    all the advantages, and avoid the inconveniencies that attend either. It shall
                    not so cut you off from the world, as to hinder you from bettering and improving
                    it; but rather qualify you to do it the greatest Good, and be a Seminary to
                    stock the Kingdom with pious and prudent Ladies; whose good Example it is to be
                    hop'd, will so influence the rest of their Sex, that Women may no longer pass
                    for those little <pb n="74"/> useless and impertinent Animals, which the ill
                    conduct of too many, has caus'd them to be mistaken for.</p>

                <p>We have hitherto consider'd our Retirement only in relation to Religion, which is
                    indeed its <hi rend="italic">main,</hi> I may say, its <hi rend="italic"
                        >only</hi> design; nor can this be thought too contracting a word, since
                    Religion is the adequate business of our lives; and largely consider'd, takes in
                    all we have to do; nothing being a fit employment for a rational Creature, which
                    has not either a <hi rend="italic">direct</hi> or <hi rend="italic">remote</hi>
                    tendency to this great and <hi rend="italic">only</hi> end. But because, as we
                    have all along observ'd, Religion never appears in it's true Beauty, but when it
                    is accompanied <pb n="75"/> with Wisdom and Discretion; and that without a good
                    Understanding, we can scarce be <hi rend="italic">truly,</hi> but never <hi
                        rend="italic">eminently</hi> Good; being liable to a thousand seductions and
                    mistakes; for even the men themselves, if they have not a competent degree of
                    Knowledge, they are carried about with every wind of Doctrine. Therefore, one
                    great end of this institution, shall be to expel that cloud of Ignorance, which
                    custom has involv'd us in, to furnish our minds with a stock of solid and useful
                    Knowledge, that the Souls of women may no longer be the only unadorn'd and
                    neglected things. It is not intended <pb n="76"/> that our Religious shou'd
                    waste their time, and trouble their heads about such unconcerning matters, as
                    the vogue of the world has turn'd up for Learning; the impertinency of which has
                    been excellently expos'd by an ingenious Pen, but busy themselves in a serious
                    enquiry after <hi rend="italic">necessary</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >perfective</hi> truths; something which it <hi rend="italic">concerns</hi>
                    them to know, and which tends to their real interest and perfection, and what
                    that is, the excellent Author just now mention'd, will sufficiently inform them,
                    such a course of Study will neither be too troublesome nor out of the reach of a
                    Female Virtuoso; <pb n="77"/> for it is not intended she shou'd spend her hours
                    in learning <hi rend="italic">words</hi> but <hi rend="italic">things,</hi> and
                    therefore no more Languages than are necessary to acquaint her with useful
                    Authors Nor need she trouble her self in turning over a huge number of Books,
                    but take care to understand and digest a few well-chosen and good ones. Let her
                    but obtain right Ideas, and be truly acquainted with the nature of those Objects
                    that present themselves to her mind, and then no matter whether or no she be
                    able to tell what fanciful people have said about them: And throughly to
                    understand Christianity as profess'd by the <hi rend="italic">Church</hi> of <pb
                        n="78"/><hi rend="italic">England,</hi> will be sufficient to confirm her in
                    the truth, tho she have not a Catalogue of those particular errors which oppose
                    it. Indeed a Learned Education of the Women will appear so unfashionable, that I
                    began to startle at the singularity of the proposition, but was extreamly
                    pleas'd when I found a late ingenious Author (whose Book I met with since the
                    writing of this) agree with me in my Opinion. For speaking of the Repute that
                    Learning was in about 150 years ago: <hi rend="italic">It</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">was so very modish</hi> <ref target="a_Wotton"
                        corresp="Wotton">(says he)</ref>
                    <note xml:id="Wotton" target="a_Wotton"> Astell herself (or a later editor) included a marginal citation here:
                        Mr. Wotton's Reflec. on Ant. and Mod. Learn.p.349, 350.</note> that <hi rend="italic"
                            >that the fair Sex seem'd to believe that</hi> Greek <hi rend="italic"
                            >and</hi> Latin <hi rend="italic">added</hi>
                        <pb n="79"/><hi rend="italic">to their Charms; and</hi> Plato <hi
                            rend="italic">and </hi>Aristotle <hi rend="italic"> untranslated, were
                            frequent Ornaments of their Closets. One wou'd think by the effects,
                            that it was a proper way of Educating them, since there are no accounts
                            in History of so many great Women in any one Age, as are to be found
                            between the years</hi> 15 <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 1600.
                </p>

                <p>For, since GOD has given Women as well as Men intelligent Souls, why should they
                    be forbidden to improve them? Since he has not denied us the faculty of
                    Thinking, why shou'd we not (at least in gratitude to him) employ our Thoughts
                    on himself, their noblest Object, and not unworthily bestow them on Trifles and
                    Gaities <pb n="80"/> and secular Affairs? Being the Soul was created for the
                    contemplation of Truth, as well as for the fruition of Good, is it not as cruel
                    and unjust to preclude Women from the knowledge of the one, as well as from the
                    enjoyment of the other? Especially since the Will is blind, and cannot chuse but
                    by the direction of the Understanding; or to speak more properly, since the Soul
                    always Wills according as she nderstands, so that, if she <hi rend="italic"
                        >Understands,</hi> amiss she <hi rend="italic">Wills</hi> amiss: And as
                    Exercise enlarges and exalts any Faculty, so thro' want of using, it becomes
                    crampt and lessened; if we make little or no use of our <pb n="81"/>
                    Understandings we shall shortly have none to use; and the more contracted, and
                    unemploy'd the deliberating and directive Power is, the more liable is the
                    elective to unworthy and mischievous options. What is it but the want of an
                    ingenious Education that renders the generality of Feminine Conversations so
                    insipid and foolish, and their solitude so <hi rend="italic">insupportable?</hi>
                    Learning is therefore necessary to render them more agreeable and useful in
                    company, and to furnish them with becoming entertainments when alone, that so
                    they may not be driven to those miserable shifts, which too many make use of to
                    put off their time, <pb n="82"/> that precious Talent that never lies on the
                    hands of a judicious Person. And since our Happiness in the next world depends
                    so far on those dispositions which we carry along with us out of this, that
                    without a right habitude and temper of mind, we are not capable of Felicity; and
                    seeing our Beatitude consists in the contemplation of the divine Truth and
                    Beauty, as well as in the fruition of his Goodness, can Ignorance be a fit
                    preparative for Heaven? Is't likely that she whose Understanding has been busied
                    about nothing but froth and trifles, shou'd be capable of delighting her self in
                    noble and sublime <pb n="83"/> Truths? Let such therefore as deny us the
                    improvement of our Intellectuals, either take up <hi rend="italic"
                    >his</hi> Paradox, who said, <hi rend="italic">That Women have no Souls;</hi>
                    which at this time a day, when they are allow'd to Brutes, wou'd be as
                    unphilosophical as it is unmannerly; or else let them permit us to cultivate and
                    improve them. There is a sort of Learning indeed which is worse than the
                    greatest Ignorance: A woman may study Plays and Romances all her days, &amp; be
                    a great deal more knowing, but never a jot the wiser. Such a Knowledge as this
                    serves only to instruct and put her forward in the practice of the greatest
                    Follies; <pb n="84"/> yet how can they justly blame her, who forbid, or at
                    least, won't afford opportunity of better? A rational mind will be employ'd, it
                        <hi rend="italic">will</hi> never be satisfy'd in doing nothing; and if you
                    neglect to furnish it with good materials, 'tis like to take up with such as
                    come to hand.</p>

                <p>We pretend not that Women shou'd teach in the Church, or usurp Authority where it
                    is not allow'd them; permit us only to understand our <hi rend="italic">own</hi>
                    duty, and not be forc'd to take it upon trust from others; to be at least so far
                    learned, as to be able to form in our minds a true Idea of Christianity, it
                    being so very necessary to fence us against <pb n="85"/> the danger of these <hi
                        rend="italic">last</hi> and <hi rend="italic">perilous days,</hi> in which
                    Deceivers, a part of whose Character is, to <hi rend="italic">lead captive silly
                        Women,</hi> need not <hi rend="italic">creep into Houses,</hi> since they
                    have Authority to proclaim their Errors on the <hi rend="italic">House
                    top.</hi>  And let us also acquire a true Practical Knowledge, such as will
                    convince us of the absolute necessity of <hi rend="italic">Holy Living,</hi> as
                    well as of <hi rend="italic">Right Believing,</hi> and that no Heresy is more
                    dangerous, than that of an ungodly and wicked Life. And since the <hi
                        rend="italic">French Tongue</hi> is understood by most Ladies, methinks they
                    may much better improve it by the study of Philosophy (as I hear the <hi
                        rend="italic">French Ladies</hi> do,) <hi rend="italic">Des Cartes,</hi><pb
                        n="86"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Malebranch,</hi> and others, than by reading idle <hi
                        rend="italic">Novels</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Romances.</hi>  'Tis strange
                    we shou'd be so forward to imitate their Fashions and Fopperies, and have no
                    regard to what is truly imitable in them! And why shall it not be thought as
                    genteel, to understand <hi rend="italic">French Philosophy,</hi> as to be
                    accoutred in a <hi rend="italic">French Mode?</hi> Let therefore the famous
                    Madam <hi rend="italic">D'acier, &amp;c.</hi>, and our own incomparable <hi
                        rend="italic">Orinda,</hi> excite the Emulation of the English Ladies.</p>

                <p>The Ladies, I'm sure, have no reason to dislike this Proposal, but I know not how
                    the Men will resent it, to have their enclosure broke down, and Women invited
                        <pb n="87"/> to tast of that Tree of Knowledge they have so long unjustly
                        <hi rend="italic">monopoliz'd.</hi> But they must excuse me, if I be as
                    partial to my own Sex as they are to theirs, and think Women as capable of
                    Learning as Men are, and that it becomes them as well. For I cannot imagine
                    wherein the hurt lyes, if instead of doing mischief to one another, by an
                    uncharitable and vain Conversation, women be enabled to inform and instruct
                    those of their own Sex at least; the Holy Ghost having left it on record, that
                        <hi rend="italic">Priscilla</hi> as well as her Husband catechis'd the
                    eloquent <hi rend="italic">Apollos,</hi> and the great Apostle found no fault
                    with her. It will therefore <pb n="88"/> be very proper for our Ladies to spend
                    part of their time in this Retirement, in adorning their minds with useful
                    Knowledge.</p>

                <p>To enter into the detail of the particulars concerning the Government of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Religious,</hi> their Offices of Devotion, Employments, Work,
                        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> is not now necessary. Suffice it at present
                    to signify, that they will be more than ordinarily careful to redeem their time,
                    spending no more of it on the Body than the necessities of Nature require, but
                    by a judicious choice of their Employment, and a constant industry about it, so
                    improve this invaluable Treasure, that it may neither <pb n="89"/> be buried in
                    Idleness, nor lavish'd out in unprofitable concerns. For a stated portion of it
                    being daily paid to GOD in Prayers and Praises, the rest shall be employ'd in
                    innocent, charitable, and useful Business; either in study (in learning
                    themselves, or instructing others; for it is design'd that part of their
                    Employment be the Education of those of their own Sex) or else in spiritual and
                    corporal Works of Mercy, relieving the Poor, healing the Sick, mingling Charity
                    to the Soul with that they express to the Body, instructing the Ignorant,
                    counselling the Doubtful, comforting the Afflicted, and correcting those that
                    err and do amiss.</p>

                <p><pb n="90"/> And as it will be the business of their lives, their meat and drink
                    to <hi rend="italic">know</hi> and <hi rend="italic">do</hi> the Will of their
                    heavenly Father, so will they pay a strict conformity to all the Precepts of
                    their holy Mother the <hi rend="italic">Church,</hi> whose sacred Injunctions
                    are too much neglected, even by those who pretend the greatest zeal for her.
                    For, besides the daily performance of the Publick Offices after the Cathedral
                    manner, in the most affecting and elevating way, the celebration of the Holy
                    Eucharist every Lords Day and Holyday, and a course of solid instructive
                    Preaching and Catechizing; our Religious, considering that the holy JESUS
                    punctually <pb n="91"/> observ'd the innocent usages of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jewish</hi> Church; and tho in many instances the <hi rend="italic"
                        >reason</hi> of the Command ceas'd as to him, yet he wou'd obey the <hi
                        rend="italic">letter</hi> to avoid giving offence, and to set us an
                    admirable pattern of Obedience; therefore, tho' it may be thought such pious
                    Souls have little occasion for the severities of fasting and mortification; yet,
                    they will consider it as a special part of their Duty, carefully to observe all
                    the Fasts of the Church,<hi rend="italic">viz. Lent, Ember,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Rogation-days, Fridays</hi>, Fridays and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vigils;</hi> times so little heeded by the most, that one wou'd scarce
                    believe them set apart for Religious Purposes, did <pb n="92"/> we not find them
                    in the antiquated Rubricks. And their Devotion will be regular, so shall it
                    likewise be solid and substantial. They will not rest in the mere out-side of
                    Duty, nor fancy the performance of their Fasts and Offices will procure them
                    license to indulge a darling Vice. But having long since laid the Ax to the root
                    of sin, and destroy'd the whole body of it, they will look upon these holy times
                    of recollection and extraordinary Devotion (without which Fasting signifies
                    little) as excellent means to keep it down, and to pluck up every the least
                    Fibre that may happen to remain in them. But we intend <pb n="93"/> not by this
                    to impose any intolerable burden on tender Constitutions, knowing that our Lord
                    has taught us, that Mercy is to be prefer'd before Sacrifice; and that Bodily
                    Exercise profiteth but a little, the chief business being to obtain a divine and
                    God-like temper of Mind.</p>

                <p>And as this institution will strictly enjoyn all pious and profitable
                    Employments, so does it not only permit but recommend harmless and ingenious
                    Diversions, Musick particularly, and such as may refresh the Body, without
                    enervating the mind. They do a disservice to Religion who make it an enemy to
                    innocent <pb n="95"/> Nature, and injure the Almighty when they represent him as
                    imposing burdens that are not to be born. Neither GOD nor Wise men will like us
                    the better, for an affected severity and waspish sourness. Nature and Grace will
                    never disagree, provided we mistake not the one, nor indulge the petulency of
                    the other; there being no Displacencies in Religon, but what we our selves have
                    unhappily made. For true Piety is the most sweet and engaging thing imaginable,
                    as it is most obliging to others, so most easie to our selves. 'Tis in truth the
                    highest <hi rend="italic">Epicurism,</hi> exalting our Pleasures by resining <pb
                        n="94"/> them; keeping our Appetites in that due regularty which not only
                    Grace, but Nature and Reason require, in the breach of which, tho' there may be
                    a Transport, there can be no true and substantial delight.</p>

                <p>As to <hi rend="italic">Lodging, Habit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Diet,</hi> they
                    may be quickly resolv'd on by the Ladies who shall subscribe; who I doubt not
                    will make choice of what is most plain and decent, what Nature, not Luxury
                    requires. And since neither Meat nor Cloaths commend us unto GOD, they'l content
                    themselves with such things as are fit and convenient, without occasioning
                    scruple to themselves, or giving any <pb n="96"/> trouble or offence to others.
                    She who considers to how much better account that Money will turn, which is
                    bestow'd on the Poor, then that which is laid out in unnecessary Expences on her
                    self, needs no Admonitions against superfluities: She who truly loves her self,
                    will never waste that Money on a decaying Carkass, which if prudently disburs'd,
                    wou'd procure her an eternal Mansion. She will never think her self so fine, as
                    when the backs of the Poor do bless her; and never feast so luxuriously as when
                    she treats an hungry person. No perfume will be thought so grateful as the Odour
                    of Good <pb n="97"/> Works; nor any Wash so beautifying as her own tears. For
                    her Heroic Soul is too great to ambition any Empire but that of her own Breast;
                    or to regard any other Conquest than the rescuing poor unhappy-Souls from the
                    slavery of Sin and Satan, those only unsupportable Tyrants; and therefore what
                    Decays she observes in her Face will be very unconcerning, but she will with
                    greatest speed and accuracy rectify the least Spot that may prejudice the beauty
                    of her lovely Soul.</p>

                <p>In a word, this happy Society will be but one Body, whose Soul is love, animating
                    and informing it, and perpetually <pb n="98"/> breathing forth it self in flames
                    of holy desires after GOD, and acts of Benevolence to each other. Envy and
                    Uncharitableness are the Vices only of little and narrow hearts, and therefore
                    'tis suppos'd, they will not enter here amongst persons whose Dispositions as
                    well as their Births are to be Generous. Censure will refine into Friendly
                    Admonition, all Scoffing and offensive Railleries will be abominated and
                    banish'd hence; where not only the Words and Actions, but even the very Thoughts
                    and Desires of the Religious, tend to promote the most endearing Love, and
                    universal Good- <pb n="99"/>will; for tho' there may be particular Friendships,
                    they must by no means prejudice the general Amity. Thus these innocent and holy
                    Souls shou'd run their Race, measuring their hours by their Devotions, and their
                    days by the charitable Works they do. Thus wou'd they live the life of Heaven
                    whilst on Earth, and receive an Earnest of its Joys in their hearts. And now,
                    what remains for them to do at Night, but to review the Actions of the Day? to
                    examine what Passions have been stirring? How their Devotions were perform'd? in
                    what temper their Hearts are? what good they have done? and what <pb n="100"/>
                    progress made towards Heaven? and with the plaudit of a satisfied Conscience
                    sweetly to sleep in peace and safety, Angels pitching their Tents round about
                    them, and he that neither slumbers nor sleeps, rejoycing over them to do them
                    good!</p>



                <p>And to the end, that these great designs may be the better pursu'd, and
                    effectually obtain'd, care shall be taken that our Religious be under the
                    tuition of persons of irreproachable Lives, of a consummate Prudence, sincere
                    Piety, and unaffected Gravity. No Novices in Religion, but such as have spent
                    the greatest part of their lives in the study and practice of <pb n="101"/>
                    Christianity; who have lived <hi rend="italic">much,</hi> whatever the time of
                    their abode in the world has been. Whose understandings are clear and
                    comprehensive, as well as their Passions at command, and Affections regular; and
                    their knowledge able to govern their Zeal. Whose scrutiny into their own hearts
                    has been so exact, that they fully understand the weaknesses of human Nature,
                    are able to bear with its defects, and by the most prudent methods procure its
                    Amendment. Plentifully furnish'd with instructions for the ignorant, and comfort
                    for the disconsolate. Who know how to quicken the slothful, to awaken <pb
                        n="102"/> the secure, and to dispel the doubts of the Scrupulous. Who are
                    not ignorant when to use the Spur, and when the Rein, but duly qualified to
                    minister to all the spiritual wants of their Charge. Watching over their Souls
                    with tenderness and prudence; applying fitting Medicines with sweetness &amp;
                    affability. Sagacious in discovering the very approaches of a fault, wise in
                    preventing, and charitable in bearing with all pityable Infirmities. The
                    sweetness of whose Nature is commensurate to all the rest of their good
                    Qualities, and all conspire together to make them lov'd and reverenc'd. Who have
                    the <pb n="103"/> perfect government of themselves, and therefore rule according
                    to Reason, not Humour, consulting the good of the Society, not their own
                    arbitrary sway. Yet know how to assert their Authority when there is just
                    occasion for it, and will not prejudice their Charge, by an indiscreet
                    remissness and loosning the Reins of discipline. Yet what occasion will there be
                    for rigour, when the design is to represent Vertue in all her Charms and native
                    Loveliness, which must needs attract the eyes, and enamour the hearts of all who
                    behold her? To joyn the sweetness of Humanity to the strictness of Philosophy,
                    that both together <pb n="104"/> being improv'd and heighten'd by grace, may
                    make up an accomplish'd <hi rend="italic">Christian;</hi> who (if truly so) is
                    certainly the best-bred and best-natur'd person in the world, adorn'd with a
                    thousand Charms, most happy in her self, and most agreeable and beneficial to
                    all about her. And that every one who comes under this holy Roof, may be such an
                    amiable, such a charming Creature, what faults they bring with them shall be
                    corrected by sweetness, not severity; by friendly Admonitions, not magisterial
                    Reproofs; Piety shall not be roughly impos'd, but wisely insinuated by a
                    perpetual Display of the <pb n="105"/> Beauties of Religion in an exemplary
                    Conversation, the continual and most powerful Sermon of an holy Life. And since
                    Inclination can't be forc'd, (and nothing makes people more uneasy than the
                    fettering themselves with unnecessary Bonds) there shall be no Vows or
                    irrevocable Obligations, not so much as the fear of Reproach to keep our Ladies
                    here any longer than they desire. No: Ev'ry act of our Religious Votary shall be
                    voluntary and free, and no other tye but the Pleasure, the Glory and Advantage
                    of this blessed Retirement, to confine her to it.</p>

                <p>And now, I suppose, you will save me the labour of <pb n="106"/> proving, that
                    this institution will very much serve the ends of Piety and Charity; it is
                    methinks self-evident, and the very Proposal sufficient proof. But if it will
                    not promote these great ends, I shall think my self mightily oblig'd to him that
                    will shew me what will; for provided the good of my Neighbour be advanc'd, 'tis
                    very indifferent to me, whether it be by my method or by anothers. Here will be
                    no impertinent Visits, no foolish Amours, no idle Amusements to distract our
                    Thoughts, and waste our precious time; a very little of which is spent in
                    Dressing, that grand devourer, and its concomitants; <pb n="107"/> and no more
                    than necessity requires in sleep and eating; so that here's an huge Treasure
                    gain'd, which for ought I know, may purchase an happy Eternity. But we need not
                    rest in generals, a cursory view of some particulars will sufficiently
                    demonstrate the great usefulness of such a Retirement; which will appear by
                    observing first, a few of those inconveniences to which Ladies are expos'd, by
                    living in the world, and in the next place the positive advantages of a
                    Retreat.</p>

                <p>And first, as to the inconveniences of living in the World; no very small one is
                    that strong <hi rend="italic">Idea</hi> and warm perception it gives us of its
                        <pb n="108"/> Vanities; since these are ever at hand, constantly thronging
                    about us, they must necessarily push aside all other Objects, and the Mind being
                    prepossess'd and gratefully entertain'd with those pleasing Perceptions which
                    external Objects occasion, takes up with them as its only Good, is not at
                    leisure to taste those delights which arise from a Reflection on it self, nor to
                    receive the <hi rend="italic">Ideas</hi> which such a Reflection conveys, and
                    consequently forms all its Notions by such <hi rend="italic">Ideas</hi> only as
                    sensation has furnish'd it with, being unacquainted with those more excellent
                    ones which arise from its own <pb n="109"/> operations and a serious reflection
                    on them, and which are necessary to correct the mistakes, and supply the defects
                    of the other. From whence arises a very partial knowledge of things, nay, almost
                    a perfect ignorance in things of the greatest moment. For tho we are acquainted
                    with the Sound of some certain words,<hi rend="italic">v. g. God, Religion,
                        Pleasure</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pain, Honour</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dishonour,</hi> and the like; yet having no other <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ideas</hi> but what are convey'd to us by those Trifles we converse with,
                    we frame to our selves strange &amp; awkard notions of them, conformable only to
                    those <hi rend="italic">Ideas</hi> sensation has furnish'd us with, which <pb
                        n="110"/> sometimes grow so strong and fixt, that 'tis scarce possible to
                    introduce a new Scheme of Thoughts, and so to disabuse us, especially whilst
                    these Objects are thick about us.</p>

                <p>Thus she who sees her self and others respected in proportion to that Pomp and
                    Bustle they make in the world, will form her Idea of Honour accordingly. She who
                    has relish'd no Pleasures but such as arise at the presence of outward Objects,
                    will seek no higher than her Senses for her Gratification. And thus we may
                    account for that strange insensibility that appears in some people when you
                    speak to them of any serious <pb n="111"/> religious matter. They are then so
                    dull you'l have much ado to make them understand the clearest Truth: Wheras if
                    you rally the same persons, or chat with them of some Mode or Foppery, they'll
                    appear very quick, expert, and ingenious. I have sometimes smil'd to hear Women
                    talk as gravely and concernedly about some trifling disappointment from their
                    Milliner or Taylor, as if it had related to the weightiest concerns of their
                    Soul, nay, perhaps more seriously than others who wou'd pass for Good, do about
                    their eternal Interest; but turn the talk that way, and they grow as heavy and
                    cold as <pb n="112"/> they were warm and sensible before. And whence is this,
                    but because their heads are full of the one, and quite destitute of such Ideas
                    as might give them a competent notion of the other; and therefore to discourse
                    of such matters, is as little to the purpose as to make Mathematical
                    Demonstrations to one who knows not what an Angle or Triangle means. (Hence by
                    the way, will appear the great usefulness of judicious Catechizing, which is
                    necessary to stir up clear Idea's in the mind, without which it can receive but
                    little benefit from the Discourses of the Pulpit, and perhaps the neglect of the
                    former <pb n="113"/> is the reason that the great plenty of the latter has no
                    better effect.) By all which it appears, that if we wou'd not be impos'd on by
                    false Reprefentations and Impostures, if we wou'd obtain a due knowledge of the
                    most important things, we must remove the little Toys and Vanities of the world
                    from us, or our selves from them; enlarge our Ideas, seek out new Fields of
                    Knowledge, whereby to rectify our first mistakes.</p>

                <p>From the same Original, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the constant flattery of
                    external Objects, arises that querulousness and delicacy observable in most
                    Persons of Fortune, and which betrays <pb n="114"/> them to many
                    inconveniencies. For besides that, it renders them altogether unfit to bear a
                    change, which considering the great uncertainty, the swift vicissitudes of
                    worldly things, the Greatest and most established, ought not to be unprepar'd
                    for; besides this, it makes them perpetually uneasy, abates the delight of their
                    enjoyments, for such persons will very rarely find all things to their mind, and
                    then some little disorder which others wou'd take no notice of, like an aching
                    Tooth or Toe, spoils the relish of their Joys. And tho many great Ladies affect
                    this temper, mistaking it for a <pb n="115"/> piece of Grandeur, 'tis so far
                    from that, that it gives evidence of a poor weak Mind; a very childish Humour,
                    that must be cocker'd and fed with Toys and Baubles to still its frowardness;
                    &amp; is like the crazy stomach of a sick Person, which no body has reason to be
                    fond of or desire.</p>

                <p>This also disposes them to Inconstancy, (for she who is continually supply'd with
                    variety, knows not where to fix,) a Vice which some women seem to be proud of,
                    and yet nothing in the world so reproachsul and degrading, because nothing is a
                    stronger evidence of a weak and injudicious mind. For it supposes us either so
                    ignorant as <pb n="116"/>to make a wrong Choice at first, or else so silly as
                    not to know and stick to it, when we have made a right one. It bespeaks an
                    unthinking inconsiderate Mind, one that lives at Random, without any design or
                    end; who wanting judgment to discern where to fix, or to know when she's well,
                    is ever fluctuating and uncertain, undoing to day what she had done yesterday,
                    which is the worst Character that can be given of ones Understanding.</p>

                <p>A constant Scene of Temptations, and the infection of ill company, is another
                    great danger, which conversing in the world exposes to. 'Tis a dangerous thing
                    to have all <pb n="117"/> the opportunities of sinning in our power, and the
                    danger is increas'd by the ill Precedents we daily see of those who take them.
                        <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> (as some body says) <hi rend="italic">will
                        corrupt an Angel.</hi>  And tho it is indeed more glorious to conquer than
                    to fly, yet since our Vertue is so visibly weakned in other instances, we have
                    no reason to presume on't in this. 'Tis become no easy matter to secure our
                    Innocence in our necessary Civilities and daily Conversations; in which, if we
                    have the good luck to avoid such as bring a necessity on us, either of seeming
                    rude to them, or of being really so to GOD Almighty, whilst <pb n="118"/> we
                    tamely hear him, our best Friend and Benefactor affronted, and swallow'd it, at
                    the same time, that we wou'd reckon't a very pitiful Spirit to hear an
                    Acquaintance traduc'd and hold our Tongue; yet, if we avoid this Trial, our
                    Charity is however in continual danger, Censoriousness being grown so modish,
                    that we can scarce avoid being active or passive in it; so that she who has not
                    her pert jest ready to pass upon others, shall as soon as her back is turn'd,
                    become a Jest her self for want of Wit.</p>

                <p>In consequence of all this, we are insensibly betray'd to a great loss of time, a
                    Treasure <pb n="119"/> whose value we are too often quite ignorant of, till it
                    be lost past redemption. And yet, considering the shortness and uncertainty of
                    Life, the great work we have to do, and what advantages accrew to us by a due
                    management of our time, we cannot reconcile it with prudence to suffer the least
                    minute to escape us. But besides our own lavish Expences (concerning which one
                    may ask as <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi> does of Labour, <hi rend="italic">What
                        Fruit have we of all that Sport and Pastime we have taken under the
                        Sun?)</hi> So unreasonable is the humour of the World, that those who wou'd
                    reckon it a rudeness to make so bold with <pb n="120"/> our Mony, never scruple
                    to waste, and rob us of this infinitely more precious Treasure.</p>

                <p>In the last place, by reason of this loss of time and the continual hurry we are
                    in, we can find no opportunities for thoughtfulness and recollection; we are so
                    busied with what passes abroad, that we have no leisure to look at home, nor to
                    rectify the disorders there. And such an unthinking mechanical way of living,
                    when like Machins we are condemn'd every day to repent the impertinencies of the
                    day before; shortens our Views, contracts our Minds, exposes to a thousand
                    practical Errors, and renders <pb n="121"/> Improvement impossible, because it
                    will not permit us to consider and recollect, which is the only means to attain
                    it. So much for the inconveniences of living in the World; if we enquire about
                    Retirement, we shall find it does not only remove all these, but brings
                    considerable advantages of its own.</p>

                <p>For first, it helps us to mate custom, and delivers us from its Tyranny, which is
                    the most considerable thing we have to do, it being nothing else but the
                    habituating our selves to Folly that can reconcile us to it. But how hard is it
                    to quit an old road? What courage as well as prudence <pb n="122"/> does it
                    require? How clear a Judgment to overlook the Prejudices of Education and
                    Example, and to discern what is best, and how strong a resolution,
                    notwithstanding all the Scoffs and Noises of the world to adhere to it! For
                    Custom has usurpt such an unaccountable Authority, that she who wou'd endeavour
                    to put a stop to its Arbitrary Sway, and reduce it to Reason, is in a fair way
                    to render her self the <hi rend="italic">Butt</hi> for all the Fops in Town to
                    shoot their impertinent Censures at. And tho a wise Woman will not value their
                    Censure, yet she cares not to be the subject of their Discourse. The only <pb
                        n="123"/> way then is to retire from the world, as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Israelites</hi> did out of <hi rend="italic">Egypt,</hi> lest the Sacrifice
                    we must make of its Follies, shou'd provoke its Spleen.</p>

                <p>This also puts us out of the road of temptation, and very much redeems our Time,
                    cutting off those extravagancies on which so much of it was squandred away
                    before. And furnishing us constantly with good employment, secures us from being
                    seduc'd into bad. Great are the Benefits of holy Conversation which will be here
                    enjoy'd: As Vice is, so Vertue may be catching; and to what heights of Piety
                    will not she advance, who is plac'd where the sole Business <pb n="124"/> is to
                    be Good, where there is no pleasure but in Religion, no contention but to excel
                    in what is truly commendable; where her Soul is not defil'd nor her Zeal
                    provok'd, by the sight or relation of those Villanies the World abounds
                    with?</p>

                <p>And by that Learning which will be here afforded, and that leisure we have, to
                    enquire after it, and to know and reflect on our own minds, we shall rescue our
                    selves out of that woful incogitancy we have slipt into, awaken our sleeping
                    Powers, and make use of that reason which GOD has given us. We shall then begin
                    to wonder at our Folly, that amongst <pb n="125"/> all the pleasures we formerly
                    pursued, we never attended to that most noble and delicious one which the chase
                    of truth affords us; and bless our selves at last, that our eyes are open'd to
                    discern how much more pleasantly we may be entertain'd by our own Thoughts, than
                    by all the Diversions which the world affords us. By this means we are fitted to
                    receive the influences of the holy Spirit, and are put in a due frame of
                    Devotion. No doubt but he has often knock'd at the door of our hearts, when the
                    croud and noise of our Vanities would not suffer us to regard or hear him; and
                    could find no admittance <pb n="126"/> when our house was so fill'd with other
                    company. Here therefore is the fittest place for his Entertainment, when we are
                    freed from outward disturbances, and entirely at leisure to attend so divine a
                    Guest. Our Devotions will be perform'd with due attention, those Objects that
                    used to distract being now remov'd from us; simplicity of desire will beget
                    simplicity of thought, and that will make our minds most intense and elevated,
                    when we come to address our selves to the Throne of Grace. Being dead to the
                    things of this world, we shall with greater fervour petition for those of
                    another; and living always in a lively <pb n="127"/> and awful sense of the
                    divine Majesty, our hearts will ever be dispos'd to approach him in the most
                    solemn, serious and reverent manner. 'Tis a very unseemly thing to jump from our
                    Diversions to our Prayers; as if when we have been entertaining our selves and
                    others with Vanity, we were instantly prepar'd to appear in the sacred presence
                    of GOD. But a Religious Retirement and holy Conversation, will procure us a more
                    serious Temper, a graver Spirit, and so both make us constantly sit to approach,
                    and likewise stir us up to be more careful in our preparations when we do. For
                    besides all other <pb n="128"/> improvements of knowledge, we shall hereby
                    obtain truer Notions of GOD than we were capable of before, which is of very
                    great consequence, since the want of right apprehensions concerning him, is the
                    general cause of mistakes in Religion, and Errors in Practice; for as he is the
                    noblest Object of our Understanding, so nothing is more necessary or of such
                    consequence to us as to busy our thoughts about him. And did we rightly consider
                    his Nature, we shou'd neither dare to forget him, nor draw near to him with
                    unclean hands, and unholy hearts.</p>

                <p>From this sacred Mountain where the world will <pb n="129"/> be plac'd at our
                    feet, at such a distance from us, that the steams of its corruptions shall not
                    obscure our eyesight; we shall have a right prospect of it, and clearly discern
                    that all its Allurements, all those Gaities and Pageantries which at present we
                    admire so much, are no better than insignificant Toys, which have no value but
                    what our perverse Opinion imposes on them. Things which contribute so very
                    little to our real Good, that even at <hi rend="italic">present,</hi> which is
                    their only season, we may live much happier without than with them; and which
                    are so far from being necessary to true Felicity, that they <pb n="130"/> shall
                    vanish and be no more when that is consummate and perfect. Many are the Topic's
                    from whence we might declaim against the vanity of the world, but methinks
                    Experience is so convincing, that it supersedes all the rest, and wou'd
                    certainly reclaim us from the immoderate love of earthly enjoyments, did we but
                    seriously hearken to it. For tell me Ladies, if your greatest Pleasures are not
                    attended with a greater sting; when you think to grasp them, do they not either
                    vanish into froth, or gall your fingers? To want, or to enjoy them, is equally
                    tormenting; the one produces in you the Pain <pb n="131"/> of Hunger, the other
                    of Loathing. For in reality, there is no good in them, nothing but the Shadow
                    and Appearance; if there were, you cou'd not so easily loath your old Delights,
                    and be so fond of variety, what is truly desirable never ending in disgust. They
                    are not therefore Pleasures but Amusements which you now pursue, and which,
                    through your ignorance of better Joys, pretend to fill their place; toll you on
                    with fair pretences, and repay your Labour with defeated Hopes. Joys, not near
                    so lasting as the slightest toy you wear; the most capricious Humorist among you
                    is more constant far than <pb n="132"/> they. Come hither therefore and take a
                    true view of 'em, that you may no longer deceive your selves with that which
                    profits not; but spurning away these empty nothings, secure a portion in such a
                    Bliss as will not fail, as cannot disappoint you! A Felicity which depending on
                    GOD only and your own Minds, is out of Fortunes reach, will place you above the
                    Batteries of the world, above its Terrors and Allurements, and enable you at
                    once to triumph over, and despise it. And what can be more glorious, than to
                    have a mind unshaken by the blandishments of Prosperity, or the rough shocks of
                    Adversity; <pb n="133"/> that passes thro both with the same indifferency and
                    integrity, is not to be tempted by either to a mean unworthy and indecent
                    Action?</p>

                <p>Farther yet, besides that holy emulation which a continual view of the brightest
                    and most exemplary Lives will excite in us; we shall have opportunity of
                    contracting the purest and noblest Friendship; a Blessing, the purchase of which
                    were richly worth all the world besides! For she who possesses a worthy Person,
                    has certainly obtain'd the richest Treasure! a Blessing that Monarchs may envy,
                    and she who enjoys is happier than <pb n="134"/> she who fills a Throne! a
                    Blessing, which next to the love of GOD, is the choicest Jewel in our Caelestial
                    Diadem, which, were it duly practic'd, wou'd both fit us for heav'n, and bring
                    it down into our hearts whilst we tarry here. For Friendship is a Vertue which
                    comprehends all the rest; none being fit for this, who is not adorn'd with every
                    other Vertue. Probably one considerable cause of the degeneracy of the present
                    Age, is the little true Friendship that is to be found in it; or perhaps you
                    will rather say, that this is the effect of our corruption. The cause and the
                    effect are indeed reciprocal; <pb n="135"/> for were the world better, there
                    wou'd be more Friendship, and were there more Friendship we shou'd have a better
                    world. But because <hi rend="italic">Iniquity abounds,</hi> therefore the <hi
                        rend="italic">love of many</hi> is not only <hi rend="italic">waxen
                        cold,</hi> but quite benum'd and perish'd. But if we have such narrow
                    hearts, be so full of mistaken Self-love, so unreasonably fond of our selves,
                    that we cannot spare a hearty Good-will to one or two choice Persons, how can it
                    ever be thought, that we shou'd well acquit our selves of that Charity which is
                    due to all mankind? For Friendship is nothing else but Charity contracted; it is
                    (in the words of an admired Author) <pb n="136"/> a kind of revenging our selves
                    on the narrowness of our Faculties, by exemplyfying that extraordinary charity
                    on one or two, which we are willing, but not able to exercise towards all. And
                    therefore 'tis without doubt, the best Instructor to teach us our duty to our
                    Neighbour, and a most excellent Monitor to excite us to make payment as far as
                    our power will reach. It has a special force to dilate our hearts, to deliver
                    them from that vicious selfishness and the rest of those <hi rend="italic"
                        >sordid passions,</hi> which express a narrow illiberal temper, and are of
                    such pernitious consequence to mankind. That institution therefore, <pb n="137"
                    /> must needs be highly beneficial, which both disposes us to be friends our
                    selves, and helps to find them. But by Friendship I do not mean any thing like
                    those intimacies that are about in the world, which are often combinations in
                    evil, and at best but insignificant dearnesses; as little resembling true
                    Friendship, as Modern Practice does Primitive Christianity. But I intend by it
                    the greatest usefulness, the most refin'd and disinteress'd Benevolence, a love
                    that thinks nothing within the bounds of Power and Duty, too much to do or
                    suffer for its Beloved: And makes no distinction <pb n="138"/> betwixt its
                    Friend and its self, except that in Temporals it prefers her interest. But tho
                    it be very desirable to obtain such a Treasure, such a Medicine of Life, (as the
                    wise man speaks) yet the danger is great, least being deceiv'd in our choice, we
                    suck in Poyson where we expected Health. And considering how apt we are to
                    disguise our selves, how hard it is to know our own hearts, much less anothers,
                    it is not advisable to be too hasty in contracting so important a Relation;
                    before that be done, it were well if we could look into the very Soul of the
                    beloved Person, to discover what resemblance <pb n="139"/> it bears to our own,
                    and in this Society we shall have the best opportunities of doing so. There are
                    no interests here to serve, no contrivances for another to be a stale to; the
                    Souls of all the Religious will be open and free, and those particular
                    Friendships must be no prejudice to the general Amity. But yet, as in Heav'n,
                    that region of perfect Love, the happy Souls (as some are of opinion) now and
                    then step aside from more general Conversations, to entertain themselves with a
                    peculiar friend; so, in this little emblem of this blessed place, what shoud
                    hinder, but that two Persons of a sympathizing disposition <pb n="140"/> the <hi
                        rend="italic">make</hi> and <hi rend="italic">frame</hi> of whose Souls
                    bears an exact conformity to each other, and therefore one wou'd think, were
                    purposely design'd by Heaven to unite and mix; what shou'd hinder them from
                    entring into an holy combination to watch over each other for Good, to advise,
                    encourage and direct, and to observe the minutest fault in order to its
                    amendment. The truest effect of love being to endeavour the bettering the
                    beloved Person. And therefore nothing is more likely to improve us in Vertue,
                    and advance us to the very highest pitch of Goodness, than unfeigned Friendship,
                    which is the most <pb n="141"/> beneficial, as well as the most pleasant thing
                    in the world.</p>

                <p>But to hasten; such an institution will much confirm us in Vertue, and help us to
                    persevere to the end, and by that substantial Piety and solid Knowledge, we
                    shall here acquire, fit us to propagate it when we return into the World. An
                    habitual Practice of Piety for some years will so root and establish us in it,
                    that Religion will become a second Nature, and we must do strange violences to
                    our selves, if after that we dare venture to oppose it. For besides all the
                    other Advantages that Vertue has over Vice, this will disarm it of <hi
                        rend="italic">Custom,</hi> the only thing <pb n="142"/> that recommends it,
                    bravely win its strongest Fort, and turn its own Cannon against it self. How
                    almost impossible wou'd it be for her to sin, whose Understanding being clearly
                    illuminated with the knowledge of the Truth, is too wise to be impos'd on by
                    those false <hi rend="italic">representations</hi> that sin wou'd deceive it
                    with; whose will has found out and united it self to its true <hi rend="italic"
                        >Centie;</hi> and having been long habituated to move in a <hi rend="italic"
                        >right</hi> line, has no temptation to decline to an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Oblique.</hi> Whose affections have daily regaled on those delicious
                    Fruits of Paradice, which Religion presents them with, and are therefore too
                    sublime and refin'd <pb n="143"/> to relish the muddy Pleasures of sensual
                    Delights. It must certainly be a Miracle if such an one relinquish her Glory and
                    Joy; she must be as bad as <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> himself who after such
                    Enjoyments can forsake her Heaven. 'Tis too unreasonable to imagine such an
                    Apostacy, the supposition is monstrous, &amp; therefore we may conclude will
                    never, or very rarely happen. And then what a blessed world shou'd we have,
                    shining with so many stars of Vertue! Who, not content to be happy themselves,
                    for that's a narrowness of mind too much beneath their Godlike temper, would
                    like the glorious Lights of Heav'n, or <pb n="144"/> rather like him who made
                    them, diffuse their benign Influences round about. Having gain'd an entrance
                    into Paradise themselves, they wou'd both shew the way and invite all others to
                    partake of their felicity. Instead of that froth and impertinence, that Censure
                    and Pragmaticalness, with which Feminine Conversations so much abound, we should
                    hear their tongues employ'd in making Proselytes to heaven, in running down
                    Vice, in establishing Vertue, and proclaiming their Makers Glory. 'Twou'd be
                    more genteel to give and take instructions about the ornaments of the Mind, than
                    to <pb n="145"/> enquire after the Mode; and a Lecture on the Fashions wou'd
                    become as disagreeable as at present any serious discourse is. Not the Follies
                    of the Town, but the Beauties and the Love of JESUS wou'd be the most polite and
                    delicious Entertainment. 'Twould be thought as rude and barbarous to send our
                    Visitors away uninstructed, as our foolishness at present reckons it to
                    introduce a pertinent and useful Conversation. Ladies of Quality wou'd be able
                    to distinguish themselves from their Inferiors by the blessings they
                    communicated, and the good they did. For this is their grand Prerogative, their
                        <hi rend="italic">distinguishing Character,</hi> that they are plac'd in a
                    condition which makes that which is every ones chief business, to be their only
                    employ. They have nothing to do but to glorify GOD, and to <pb n="146"/> benefit
                    their Neighbours, and she who does not thus improve her Talent, is more vile and
                    despicable than the meanest Creature about her.</p>

                <p>And if after so many spiritual Advantages, it be convenient to mention Temporals,
                    here Heiresses and Persons of Fortune may be kept secure, from the rude attempts
                    of designing Men; And she who has more Mony than Discretion, need not curse her
                    Stars, for being expos'd a prey to bold importunate and rapacious Vultures. She
                    will not here be inveigled and impos'd on, will neither be bought nor sold, nor
                    be forc'd to marry for her own quiet, when she has no inclination to it, but
                    what the being tir'd out with a restless importunity occasions. Or if she be
                    dispos'd to marry, here she may remain in safety till a convenient Match <pb
                        n="147"/> be offer'd by her Friends, and be freed from the danger of a
                    dishonourable one. Modesty requiring that a Woman should not love before
                    Marriage, but only make choice of one whom she can love hereafter: She who has
                    none but innocent affections, being easily able to fix them where Duty
                    requires.</p>

                <p>And tho at first I propos'd to my self to speak nothing in particular of the
                    employment of the Religious, yet to give a Specimen how useful they will be to
                    the World, I am now inclin'd to declare, that it is design'd a part of their
                    business shall be to give the best Education to the Children of Persons of
                    Quality, who shall be attended and instructed in lesser matters by meaner
                    persons deputed to that Office, but the forming of their minds shall be the
                    particular care of those of <pb n="148"/> their own Rank; who cannot have a more
                    pleasant and useful employment than to exercise and encrease their own
                    knowledge, by instilling it into these young ones, who are most like to profit
                    under such Tutors. For how can their little Pupils forbear to credit them, since
                    they do not decry the World (as others may be thought to do) because they cou'd
                    not enjoy it; but when they had it in their power, were courted and caress'd by
                    it, for very good Reasons, and on mature deliberation, thought fit to relinquish
                    and despise its offers for a better choice? Nor are mercenary people on other
                    accounts capable of doing so much good to young Persons, because, having often
                    but short views of things themselves, sordid and low Spirits, they are not like
                    to form a generous temper in the minds of the <pb n="149"/> Educated. Doubtless
                    'twas well consider'd of him, who wou'd not trust the breeding of his Son to a
                    Slave, because nothing great or excellent could be expected from a person of
                    that condition.</p>

                <p>And when by the increase of their Revenue, the Religious are enabled to do such a
                    work of Charity, the Education they design to bestow on the Daughters of
                    Gentlemen who are fallen into decay, will be no inconsiderable advantage to the
                    Nation. For hereby many Souls will be preserv'd from great Dishonours, and put
                    in a comfortable way of subsisting, being either receiv'd into the House, if
                    they incline to it, or otherwise dispos'd of. It being suppos'd that prudent men
                    will reckon the endowments they here acquire a sufficient <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dowry;</hi> and that a disereet and vertuous Gentlewoman will make a better
                        <pb n="150"/> Wife than she whose mind is empty, tho her Purse be full.</p>

                <p>But some will say, May not people be good without this confinement? may they not
                    live at large in the world, and yet serve GOD as acceptably as here? 'tis
                    allow'd they may; truly wise and vertuous Souls will do it by the assistance of
                    GODS Grace, in despite of all temptations; and I heartily wish, that all Women
                    were of this temper. But it is to be consider'd, that there are <hi
                        rend="italic">tender</hi> Vertues, who need to be screened from the ill Airs
                    of the world: Many persons who had <hi rend="italic">begun</hi> well might have
                    gone to the Grave in peace and innocence, had it not been their misfortune to be
                    violently tempted. For those who have honest Hearts have not always the
                    strongest Heads; and sometimes the enticements of the world, and the subtil
                    insinuations <pb n="151"/> of such as lye in wait to deceive, may make their
                    Heads giddy, stagger their Resolutions, and overthrow all the fine hopes of a
                    promising beginning. 'Tis fit therefore, such tender <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cyons</hi> shou'd be transplanted, that they may be supported by the prop
                    of Vertuous Friendship, and confirm'd in Goodness by holy Examples, which alas!
                    they will not often meet with in the world. And, such is the weakness of human
                    Nature, that bad people are not so apt to be better'd by the Society of the
                    Good, as the Good are to be corrupted by theirs. Since therefore we daily pray
                    against temptation, it cannot be amiss if we take all prudent care to avoid it,
                    and not out of a vain presumption face the danger, which GOD may justly permit
                    to overcome us for a due correction of our Pride. It is not impossible <pb
                        n="152"/> for a man to live in an infected House or Town, and escape with
                    Life and Health; yet if he have a place in the Country to retire to, he will not
                    make slight of that advantage; and surely the Health of our Souls is of greater
                    consideration than the health of our Bodies. Besides, she has need of an
                    establish'd Vertue and consummated Prudence, who so well understands the great
                    end she was sent into the world about, and so faithfully pursues it, that not
                    content to be wise and good her self alone, she endeavours to propagate Wisdom
                    and Piety to all about her. But neither this Prudence nor heroic Goodness are
                    easily attainable amidst the noise and hurry of the world, we must therefore
                    retire a while from its clamour and importunity, if we generously design to do
                    it good; and having <pb n="153"/> calmly and sedately observ'd and rectify'd
                    what is amiss in our selves, we shall be fitter to promote a Reformation in
                    others. A devout Retirement will not only strengthen and confirm our Souls, that
                    they be not insected by the worlds Corruptions, but likewise so purity and
                    resite them, that they will become Antidotes to expel the Poyson in others, and
                    spread a salutary Air round about them.</p>

                <p>If any object against a Learned Education, that it will make Women vain and
                    assuming, and instead of correcting, encrease their Pride: I grant, that a
                    smattering in Learning may; for it has this effect on the Men, none so
                    Dogmatical, and so forward to shew their Parts as your little <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pretenders</hi> to Science. But I wou'd not have the Ladies content
                    themselves with the <hi rend="italic">shew,</hi> my <pb n="154"/> desire is,
                    that they shou'd not rest till they obtain the <hi rend="italic">Substance.</hi>
                    And then she who is most knowing, will be forward to own with the wise <hi
                        rend="italic">Socrates,</hi> that she knows nothing: nothing that is matter
                    of Pride and Ostentation; nothing but what is attended with so much ignorance
                    and imperfection, that it cannot reasonably elate and puff her up. The more she
                    knows, she will be the less subject to talkativeness and its sister Vices,
                    because she discerns, that the most difficult piece of Learning is, to know when
                    to use and when to hold ones Tongue, and never to speak but to the purpose.</p>

                <p>But the men if they rightly understand their own interest, have no reason to
                    oppose the ingenious Education of the Women, since 'twou'd go a great way
                    towards reclaming the men; great <pb n="155"/> is the influence we have over
                    them in their Childhood, in which time, if a Mother be discreet and knowing as
                    well as devout, she has many opportunities of giving such a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Form</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Season</hi> to the tender Mind of the
                    Child, as will shew its good effects thro' all the stages of his Life. But tho'
                    you should not allow her capable of doing <hi rend="italic">good,</hi> 'tis
                    certain, she may do <hi rend="italic">hurt:</hi> If she do not <hi rend="italic"
                        >make</hi> the Child, she has power to <hi rend="italic">marr</hi> him, by
                    suffering her fondness to get the better of discreet affection. But besides
                    this, a good and prudent Wife, wou'd wonderfully work on an ill man; he must be
                    a Brute indeed, who cou'd hold out against all those innocent Arts, those gentle
                    persuasives, and obliging methods she wou'd use to reclaim him. Piety is often
                    offensive, when it is accompanied with indiscretion: but <pb n="156"/> she who
                    is as Wise as Good, possesles such Charms as can hardly fail of prevailing.
                    Doubtless, her Husband is a much happier Man, and more likely to abandon all his
                    ill Courses, than he who has none to come home to, but an ignorant, froward and
                    fantastick Creature. An ingenious Conversation will make his life comfortable,
                    and he who can be so well entertain'd at home, needs not run into Temptations in
                    search of Diversions abroad. The only danger is, that the Wife be more knowing
                    than the Husband; but if she be, 'tis his own fault, since he wants no
                    opportunities of improvement; unless he be a natural <hi rend="italic"
                        >Blockhead,</hi> and then such an one will need a wise Woman to govern him,
                    whose prudence will conceal it from publick Observation, and at once both cover
                    and supply his defects. Give <pb n="157"/> me leave therefore to hope, that no
                    Gentleman who has honourable designs, will henceforward decry Knowledge and
                    Ingenuity in her he wou'd pretend to Honour: Or if he does, it may serve for a
                    Test to distinguish the feigned and unworthy from the real Lover.</p>

                <p>Now, who that has a Spark of of Piety, will go about to oppose so Religious a
                    design? What generous Spirit that has a due regard to the good of Mankind, will
                    not be forward to advance and perfect it? Who will think 500 pounds too much to
                    lay out for the purchase of so much Wisdom and Happiness? Certainly, we shou'd
                    not think them too dearly paid for by a much greater Sum, did not our pitiful
                    and sordid Spirits set a much higher value on Money than it deserves. But
                    granting so much of that dear <pb n="158"/>Idol is given away, a person thus
                    bred, will easily make it up by her Frugality and other Vertues: if she bring
                    less, she will not waste so much, as others do in superfluous and vain Expences.
                    Nor can I think of any expedient so useful as this to Persons of Quality, who
                    are over-stock'd with Children; for thus they may honourably dispose of them
                    without impairing their Estates. Five or six hundred pounds may be easily spar'd
                    with a Daughter, when so many thousand would go deep; and yet as the world goes
                    be a very inconsiderable Fortune for Ladies of their Birth; neither maintain
                    them in that <hi rend="italic">Port</hi> which Custom makes almost necessary,
                    nor procure them an equal Match; those of their own Rank (contrary to the
                    generous custom of the <hi rend="italic">Germans</hi>) chusing rather to fill
                    their Coffers than <pb n="159"/> to preserve the purity of their Blood, and
                    therefore think a weighty Bag the best Gentility, preferring a wealthy Upstart
                    before the best Descended and best Qualifyed Lady: Their own extravagancies
                    perhaps having made it necessary, that they may keep up an empty shadow of
                    Greatness, which is all that remains to shew what their Ancestors have been.</p>

                <p>Does any think their money lost to their Families, when 'tis put in here? I will
                    only ask what course they can take to save it, and at once to preserve their
                    Money, their Honour and their Daughters too? Were they sure the Ladies wou'd die
                    unmarried, I shou'd commend their Thrift; but Experience has too often shewn us
                    the vanity of this expectation. For the poor Lady having past the prime of her
                        <pb n="160"/> years in Gaity and Company, in running the Circle of all the
                    Vanities of the Town, having spread all her Nets and us'd all her Arts for
                    Conquest, and finding that the Bait fails where she wou'd have it take, and
                    having all this while been so over-careful of her Body, that she had no time to
                    improve her mind, which therefore affords her no safe retreat now she meets with
                    Disappointments abroad, and growing every day more and more sensible that the
                    respect which us'd to be paid her, decays as fast as her Beauty; quite terrified
                    with the dreadful name of <hi rend="italic">Old Maid,</hi> which yet none but
                    Fools will reproach her with, nor any wise Woman be afraid of; to avoid this
                    terrible <hi rend="italic">Mormo,</hi> and the scoffs that are thrown on
                    superannuated Virgins, she flies to some dishonourable Match <pb n="161"/> as
                    her last, tho much mistaken Refuge, to the disgrace of her Family, and her own
                    irreparable Ruin. And now let any person of Honour tell me, if it were not
                    richly worth some thousand Pounds, to prevent all this mismischief, and the
                    having an idle Fellow, and perhaps a race of beggarly Children to hang on him,
                    and to provide for?</p>

                <p>Cou'd I think of any other objection, I wou'd consider it; theres nothing indeed
                    which witty persons may not argue <hi rend="italic">for</hi> &amp; <hi
                        rend="italic">against,</hi> but they who duly weigh the Arguments on both
                    sides, unless they be extreamly prejudiced, will casily discern the great
                    usefulness of this Institution. The <hi rend="italic">Beaux</hi> perhaps, and
                    topping Sparks of the Town, will ridicule and laugh at it. For Vertue her self
                    as bright as she is, can't escape the lash of scurrilous <pb n="162"/> Tongues;
                    the comfort is, whilst they impotently endeavour to throw dirt on her, they are
                    unable to soil her Beauty, and only render themselves the more contemptible.
                    They may therefore if they please, hug themselves in their own dear folly, and
                    enjoy the diversion of their own insipid Jests. She has but little Wisdom and
                    less Vertue, who is to be frighted from what she judges reasonable by the scoffs
                    and insignificant noises of ludicrous Wits, and pert Buffoons. And no <hi
                        rend="italic">wonder</hi> that such as they, (who have nothing to shew for
                    their pretences to Wit, but some scraps of Plays, and blustring Non-sence; who
                    fancy a well adjusted Peruke is able to supply their want of Brains, and that to
                    talk <hi rend="italic">much</hi> is a sign of Ingenuity, tho't be never so
                    little to the purpose,) object against our Proposal; 'twould <pb n="163"/>
                    indeed spoil the Trade of the gay fluttering Fops, who wou'd be at a loss, had
                    they no body as impertinent as themselves to talk with. The Criticism of their
                    Dress wou'd be useless, and the labour of their <hi rend="italic">Valet de
                        Chambre</hi> lost, unless they cou'd peaceably lay aside their Rivalling,
                    and one Ass be content to complement and admire another. For the Ladies wou'd
                    have more discernment than to esteem a Man for such Follies as shou'd rather
                    incline them to scorn and despise him. They wou'd never be so sottish as to
                    imagine, that he who regards nothing but his own brutish Appetite, shou'd have
                    any real affection for them, nor ever expect Fidelity from one who is unfaithful
                    to GOD and his own Soul. They wou'd not be so absurd as to suppose, that man can
                    esteem them who neglects his <pb n="164"/> Maker; for what are all those fine
                    Idolatries, by which he wou'd recommend himself to his pretended Goddess; but
                    mockery and delusion from him who forgets and affronts the true Deity? They
                    wou'd not value themselves on account of the Admiration of such incompetent
                    Judges, nor consequently make use of those little trifling Arts that are
                    necessary to recommend them to such Admirers: Neither wou'd they give
                    opportunity to profess themselves their Slaves so long, till at last they become
                    their Masters.</p>

                <p>What now remains, but to reduce to Practice that which tends so very much to our
                    advantage. Is Charity so dead in the world that none will contribute to the
                    saving their own and their neighbours Souls? Shall we freely expend our Money to
                    purchase Vanity, <pb n="165"/> and often times both present and future Ruin, and
                    find none for such an eminent good Work, which will make the Ages to come arise
                    and call us Blessed? I wou'd fain persuade my self better things, and that I
                    shall one day see this <hi rend="italic">Religious Retirement</hi> happily
                    setled, and its great designs wisely and vigorously pursu'd; and methinks I have
                    already a Vision of that lustre and glory our Ladies cast round about them! Let
                    me therefore intreat the rest of our Sex, who tho at liberty in the world, are
                    the miserable Slaves of their own vile affections; let me entreat them to lay
                    aside their Prejudices, and whatever borders on Envy and Malice, and with
                    impartial eyes to behold the Beauties of our <hi rend="italic">Religious.</hi>
                    The native innocency and unaffectedness of whose Charms, and the unblameable <pb
                        n="166"/> Integrity of their Lives, are abundantly more taking than all the
                    curious Artifices and studied Arts the other can invent to recommend them, even
                    bad men themselves being Judges, who often betray a secret Veneration for that
                    vertue they wou'd seem to despise and endeavour to corrupt. As there is not any
                    thing, no not the least shadow of a motive to recommend vice, but its
                    fashionableness, and the being accustom'd to it; so there is nothing at all
                    forbidding in vertue but her uncouthness. Acquaint your selves with her a
                    little, and you'l wonder how you cou'd be so foolish as to delight in any thing
                    besides! For you'l find her Conversation most sweet and obliging; her Precepts
                    most easy and beneficial; her very tasks Joys, and her Injunctions the highest
                    Pleasures. She will not <pb n="167"/> rob you of any innocent delight, not
                    engage you to any thing beneath your Birth and Breeding: But will put a new and
                    more grateful relish into all your Enjoyments, and make them more delicious with
                    her Sweetness She'll preserve and augment your Honour, by allying you to the
                    King of Heaven; secure your Grandeur by fixing it on a firm bottom, such as the
                    caprice of Fortune cannot shake or overthrow; she'll enlarge your souls, raise
                    them above the common level, and encourage that allowable Pride of Scorning to
                    do a base unworthy action. Make you truly amiable in the eyes of GOD and Man,
                    preserve even the Beauty of your Bodies as long as 'tis possible for such a
                    brittle thing to last; and when it must of necessity decay, impress such a
                    loveliness on your Minds, <pb n="168"/> as will shine thro' and brighten your
                    very Countenances; enriching you with such a stock of Charms, that Time which
                    devours every other thing, shall never be able to decay. In a word, 'tis Vertue
                    only which can make you truly happy in this world as well as in the next.</p>

                <p>There is a sort of Bravery and Greatness of Soul, which does more truly ennoble
                    us than the highest Title, and it consists in the living up to the dignity of
                    our Natures, scorning to do a mean unbecoming thing; in passing differently
                    thro' Good and Evil Fortune, without being corrupted by the one or deprest by
                    the other. For she that can do so, gives evidence that her Happiness depends not
                    on so mutable a thing as this world; but, in a due subserviency to the Almighty,
                    is bottom'd only on <pb n="169"/> her own great Mind. This is the richest
                    Ornament, and renders a Woman glorious in the lowest Fortune: So shining is real
                    worth, that like a Diamond it loses not its lustre, tho cast on a Dunghill.
                    Whereas, she who is advanc'd to some eminent Station, and wants this natural and
                    solid Greatness, is no better than Fortunes <hi rend="italic">May-game,</hi>
                    rendered more conspicuous, that she may appear the more contemptible. Let those
                    therefore who value themselves only on external Accomplishments, consider how
                    liable they are to decay, and how soon they may be depriv'd of them, and that
                    supposing they shou'd continue, they are but sandy Foundations to build Esteem
                    upon. What a disappointment will it be to a Ladies Admirer as well as to her
                    self, that her Conversation shou'd lose and endanger <pb n="170"/> the Victory
                    her eyes had gain'd! For when the Passion of a Lover is evaporated into the cool
                    temper of a Husband, and a frequent review has lessen'd the wonder which her
                    Charms at first had rais'd, she'll retain no more than such a formal respect as
                    decency and good breeding will require, and perhaps hardly that; but unless he
                    be a very good Man (and indeed the world is not over full of 'em) her
                    worthlesness has made a forfeit of his Affections, which are seldom fixt by any
                    other thing than Veneration and Esteem. Whereas, a wise and good Woman is useful
                    and valuable in all Ages and Conditions; she who chiefly attends the <hi
                        rend="italic">one thing needful,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">good part which
                        shall not be taken from her,</hi> lives a cheerful and pleasant Life,
                    innocent and sedate, calm and tranquile, <pb n="171"/> and makes a glorious
                    Exit; being translated from the most happy life on Earth, to unspeakable
                    happiness in heaven; a fresh and fragrant Name, embalming her Dust, and
                    extending its Perfume to succeeding Ages. Whilst the Fools, and the worst sort
                    of them the wicked, <hi rend="italic">live</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic"
                        >die</hi> in Misery, go out in a snuff, leaving nothing but stench and
                    putrefaction behind them.</p>

                <p>To close all, if this <hi rend="italic">Proposal</hi> which is but a rough
                    draught and rude Essay, and which might be made much more beautiful by a better
                    Pen, give occasion to wiser heads to improve and perfect it, I have my end. For
                    imperfect as it is, it seems so desirable, that she who drew the Scheme is full
                    of hopes, it will not want kind hands to perform and compleat it. But if it miss
                        <pb n="172"/> of that, it is but a few hours thrown away, and a little
                    labour in vain, which yet will not be lost, if what is here offer'd may serve to
                    express her hearty Good-will, and how much she desires your Improvement, who
                    is</p>


                <p>LADIES,</p>
                <p>Your very humble Servant.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
