<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="johns-ramb4">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Rambler No. 4</title>
                <author>
                    <person type="lccn" key="n78095825"><surname>Johnson</surname>, <forename>Samuel</forename></person>
                        <birth when="1709-09-18">18 September 1709 [O.S. 7 September]</birth>
                        <death when="1784-12-13">13 December 1784</death>
                        <occupation>Lexicographer</occupation>
                        <occupation>Essayist</occupation>
                        <occupation>Critic</occupation>
                        <occupation>Writer</occupation>
                        <trait type="Marital Status">Married</trait>
                        <nationality>English</nationality>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">Tonya Howe</persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093"><forename>Tonya</forename> <surname>Howe</surname></persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Novels in Context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Marymount University Department of Literature and Languages</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>2807 N. Glebe Road</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Arlington, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22207</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>thowe@marymount.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>johns-ramb4</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
                <textDesc>
                    <constitution status="incomplete">This text is incomplete and reqiures further
                        correction, annotation, and standardization.</constitution>
                </textDesc>
                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"The Rambler, No. 4"</title>
                        <date when="1750-03-31">Saturday, March 31, 1750</date>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <person><surname>Johnson</surname>, <forename>Samuel</forename> 1709-1784</person>
                        </author>
                        <title>The Rambler</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed for J. PAYNE, and J. Boquet, in Pater-Noster Row; where Letters for the RAMBLER are received.</publisher>
                            <date when="c.1751">c.1751</date>
                            <extent>c30 cm (folio)<idno type="lcc">XX Folio PR1365 .R3</idno></extent>
                            <note>This issue appears in a two-volume collection of first printings housed in the Michigan State University Special Collections; accompanying page images are sourced from this first edition.</note>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope>pp 19-24</biblScope>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Public domain electronic imile copy</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Google eBook</publisher>
                            <extent type="online">http://books.google.com/books?id=7ZYDAAAAQAAJ</extent>
                            <note>This electronic edition is a reprint of the first collected UK edition.</note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi> project,
                which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
                relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th
                century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
                developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p></projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible
                    resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                    knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If
                    you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                    lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p></interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has
                    been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                    the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running
                    headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                    where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lccn">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
                    <change when="2018-06-05" who="#TH">First complete XML version</change>
                    <change when="2018-10-15" who="#TH">Correction against first edition page images.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[19]" facs="images/019.jpg"/>
            <p><head type="title"><h1>THE <lb/>RAMBLER.</h1></head></p>
            <p><span class="text-left">NUMB. 4.</span><span class="text-right">Price 2 <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.<ref target="a020" corresp="n020"/><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">Information about prices.</note></span></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">To be Continued on </hi>TUESDAYS <hi rend="italic">and</hi> SATURDAYS</p>
            <p><dateline>SATURDAY, 31 March 1750</dateline></p>
            <epigraph xml:lang="la">
                <cit>
                    <quote xml:lang="la">
                        <l><hi rend="italic">Simul et jucunda et idonea dicere Vitae.</hi><ref target="a001" corresp="n001"/><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">From Horace's <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0065%3Acard%3D309">Ars Poetica 334</ref>: 'to deliver at once both the pleasures and the necessaries of life" (Perseus Project).</note></l>
                    </quote>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>HOR[ace]</author><ref target="a014" corresp="n014"/><note xml:id="n014" target="a014"><graphic url="https://media1.britannica.com/eb-media/30/10930-004-C1C3F179.jpg"/>Quintus Horatius Flaccus, or Horace, was a Roman lyric poet of the 1st century BCE. The image above is a broze portrait medal containing his likeness, dating to the 4th century CE, housed in the Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris (<ref target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Horace-Roman-poet">Encyclopedia Britannica</ref>). </note>
                    </bibl>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>THE Works of Fiction, with which the present Generation seems more particularly
                  delighted, are such as exhibit
                     Life in its true State, diversified only by Accidents that daily happen in the
                     World, and influenced by those Passions and Qualities which are really to be found in
                     conversing with Mankind.
            </p>
            <p>THIS Kind of Writing may be termed not improperly the 
                    Comedy of
                        Romance, and is to be conducted nearly by the Rules of Comic
                     Poetry. Its Province is to bring about natural Events by easy Means, and to keep up
                     Curiosity without the Help of Wonder: it is therefore precluded from the
                     Machines and Expedients of the Heroic Romance,<ref target="a002" corresp="n002"/>
                <note xml:id="n002" target="a001">Heroic romance is a genre that flourished during the 17th century and remained popular, as parodied by Charlotte Lennox in <hi rend="italic>">The Female Quixote</hi>, into the 18th. It had a profound influence on the development of the novel, though many writers of the 18th century would work to dissociate the genres, as Johnson does here. Formaally loose in structure, heroic romances also "deliberately eschew[ed] contemporaneity"; their plots featured courtly lovers engaged in "heroic stories of love and war in a remote and idealized past" (<ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=FPdRAwAAQBAJ">Shellinger, <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia of the Novel</hi>, 1046)</ref>. Some representative heroic romances include <hi rend="italic">Euphues</hi> by John Lyly, <hi rend="italic">L'Astree</hi> by Honore d'Urfe, and <hi rend="italic">Clelie</hi> by Madame de Scudery.</note> and can neither employ Giants to snatch away a Lady from the nuptial Rites, nor Knights to bring her back from Captivity; it
                  can neither bewilder its Personages in Desarts,
                     nor lodge them in imaginary Castles. </p>
            <p>I REMEMBER a Remark made by 
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        Scaliger<ref target="a003" corresp="n003"/><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Likely a reference to <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Joseph-Justus-Scaliger">Joseph Justus Scaliger</ref>, a Dutch philologist and historian of the Renaissance. Identification uncertain.</note>
                </hi> upon <hi rend="italic">Potanus</hi>, that all his Writings are filled with
                     Images, and that <pb n="20" facs="images/020.jpg"/> if you take from him his Lillies and his Roses, his
                     Satyrs and his Dryads, he will have nothing left that can be called Poetry. In
                     like Manner, almost all the Fictions of the last Age will vanish, if you
                     deprive them of a Hermit and a Wood, a Battle and a Shipwreck.
            </p>
            <p>WHY this wild Strain of Imagination
                  found Reception so long, in polite and learned Ages, it is not easy to conceive;
                  but we cannot wonder that, while Readers could
                     be procured, the Authors were willing to continue it: For when a Man had, by Practice, gained some Fluency of Language,
                     he had no farther Care than to retire to
                        his Closet, let loose his Invention, and heat his Mind with Incredibilities; and a Book
                     was thus produced without Fear of Criticism, without the Toil of Study, without Knowledge of Nature,
                        or Acquaintance with Life.
                
            </p>
            <p>
                THE Task of our present Writers is very
                     different; it requires, together with that Learning which is to be gained from
                     Books, that Experience which can never be
                        attained by solitary Diligence, but must arise from general Converse,
                     and accurate Observation of the living
                     World. Their Performances have, as <hi rend="italic">Horace</hi><ref target="a004" corresp="n004"/><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Quintus Horatius Flaccus, Roman lyric poet of the 1st century BCE</note> expresses it, 
                        <cit>
                    <quote xml:lang="la">
                        <hi rend="italic">plus oneris quantum veniae minus, </hi><ref target="a005" corresp="n005"/><note xml:id="n005" target="a005"><ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0539%3Abook%3D2%3Apoem%3D1">In Horace's <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi> 2.1</ref>, this quote appears at line 170. In this epistle to Augustus, Horace is mounting a defense of contemporary poetry and decrying the poor taste of the public. In particular he argues that though comic subjects are thought easier to write, they are actually more challenging than tragic subjects because readers give them less "indulgence." Johnson will put this "indulgence" in terms of the readers' familiarity with the more common subjects of comedy (Perseus Project).</note>
                    </quote>
                    <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en"> little
                        Indulgence, and therefore more Difficulty.</cit>
                </cit>
               They are engaged in Portraits of which every one
                     knows the Original, and can detect any Deviation from Exactness of
                     Resemblance. Other Writings are safe, except from the Malice of
                  Learning; but these are in danger from every
                  common Reader<ref target="#a015" corresp="#n015"/><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">\Johnson alludes here to a story from <ref target="http://data.perseus.org/citations/urn:cts:latinLit:phi0978.phi001.perseus-eng1:35.36">Pliny the Elder's <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi> (35.36)</ref>.</note>; as the Slipper ill
                     executed was censured by a Shoemaker who happened to stop in his way at the
                    <hi rend="italic">
                    Venus
                    </hi><ref target="a006" corresp="n006"/><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Roman counterpart to the Greek goddess Aphrodite, Venus is a signifier of love, sex, propsperity, and desire (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venus_%28mythology%29">Wikipedia</ref>).</note> of Apelles.<ref target="a006" corresp="n006"/><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Apelles of Kos, a Greek painter of the 4th century BCE (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apelles">Wikipedia</ref>). Johnson here alludes to a lost painting of Venus Anadyomenes, or Venus rising from the sea.</note>
            </p>
            <p>BUT the Danger of not being approved as just
                     Copyers of human Manners, is not the most important Apprehension that an
                     author of this Sort ought to have before him.  These Books are written chiefly to the Young, the Ignorant, and the Idle,<ref target="a008" corresp="n008"/><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">This is one of the most-quoted moments in the essay. Here, Johnson is making the case that the young, untutored, inexperienced minds that form the primary audience of the novel are easily led astray by the familiarity of their subjects and the verisimilitude of their style.</note> to
                     whom they serve as Lectures of Conduct, and
                        Introductions into Life. They
                     are the Entertainment of Minds unfurnished with Ideas, and therefore
                      <pb n="21" facs="images/021.jpg"/>
                          easily susceptible of Impressions;
                    not fixed by Principles, and therefore
                     easily following the Current of Fancy; 
                    not informed by
                        Experience, and consequently open to every false Suggestion and partial
                        Account.
            </p>
            <p>
                THAT the highest Degree of Reverence should be
                     paid to Youth, and that nothing indecent or unseemly should be suffered to approach their
                     Eyes or Ears, are Precepts extorted by Sense and Virtue from an ancient Writer
                     by no Means eminent for Chastity of Thought.<ref target="a12" corresp="n012"/><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">Who is this?</note> The same Kind, tho' not the same Degree of
                        Caution, is required in every thing which is laid before them, to secure
                        them from unjust Prejudices, perverse Opinions, and improper Combinations
                        of Images.
            </p>
            <p>
                IN the Romances formerly written, every
                     Transaction and Sentiment was so remote from all that passes among Men, that
                     the Reader was in very little danger of making any Applications to
                     himself; the Virtues and Crimes were equally beyond his Sphere of Activity;
                  and he amused himself with Heroes and with
                     Traitors, Deliverers and Persecutors, as with Beings of another Species,
                  whose Actions were regulated upon Motives of their own, and who had 
                  neither Faults nor Excellences in common with
                     himself. </p>
            <p>
               BUT when an Adventurer is levelled with the rest
                     of the World, and acts in such Scenes of the universal Drama, as may be the Lot
                     of any other Man; young Spectators fix their Eyes upon him with closer
                  Attention, and hope by observing his Behaviour
                     and Success to regulate their own Practices, when they shall be engaged in the
                     like Part. </p>
            <p>FOR this Reason these familiar Histories<ref target="a013" corresp="n013"/><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Johnson here uses the term "familiar history" to describe the probable fictions produced by "our present Writers." The term suggests the truth-value associated with many eighteenth-century fictions that, like <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi> (1719) or <hi rend="italic">Pamela</hi> (1740), were advertised as having been largely written by the characters themselves. These are supposedly true histories, memoirs, or other accounts of people who would seem familiar to contemporary audiences..</note> may
                  perhaps be made of greater Use than the
                     Solemnities of professed Morality, and convey the Knowledge of Vice and Virtue
                     with more Efficacy than Axioms and Definitions. 
                     But if the Power of Example is so great, as to take
                     Possession of the Memory by a kind of Violence, and produce Effects almost
                     without the Intervention of the Will,<ref target="a009" corresp="n009"/><note xml:id="n009" target="a009"> Here Johnson argues that representations which are rendered in so familiar and realistic a manner are especially dangerous to untutored minds because they seem to be truth rather than fiction; he therefore cautions that authors provide the best models for behavior and the cultivation of the mind. Johnson references eighteenth-century thought about the power of the imagination to affect the body regardless of the will, like that discussed by <ref target="https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/m/gne/michel/essays/complete.html#book1.20">Michele de Montaigne in "Of the Power of the Imagination."</ref> For information about the power of the female imagination to create monstrous beings, see, among other works, <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=_nQredXpwaUC">>Marie Hélène Huet's <hi rend="italic">Monstrous Imagination</hi> (1993)</ref>.</note> Care ought 
                         <pb n="22" facs="images/022.jpg"/>
                         to be taken that, when the
                     Choice is unrestrained, the best Examples only should be exhibited; and that
                     which is likely to operate so strongly, should not be mischievous or uncertain
                     in its Effects.
            </p>
            <p>
                THE chief Advantages which these Fictions have
                     over real Life is, that their Authors are
                        at liberty, tho' not to invent, yet to select Objects, and to cull from the
                        Mass of Mankind, those Individuals upon which the Attention ought most to be
                        employ'd; as a
                     Diamond, though it cannot be made, may be polished by Art, and placed in such a
                     Situation, as to display that Lustre which before was buried among common
                     Stones. </p>
            <p>
                IT is justly considered as the greatest
                     Excellency of Art, to imitate Nature; but 
                     it is necessary to distinguish those Parts of
                     Nature, which are most proper for Imitation:
                     Greater Care is still required in representing Life,
                     which is so often discoloured by Passion, or 
                     deformed by Wickedness. If the World be promiscuously<ref target="a016" corresp="n016"/><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">"Promiscuous" here refers to a lack of distinction or discrimination; it is not primarily sexual. See this <ref target="https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=promiscuous">Google N-Gram graph charting the usage of the term over time</ref>.</note>
                     described, I cannot see of what Use it can be to read the Account; or why it
                     may not be as safe to turn the Eye immediately upon Mankind, as upon a Mirrour
                     which shows all that presents itself without Discrimination.
            </p>
            <p>
                IT is therefore not a sufficient Vindication
                     of a Character, that it is drawn as it appears; for many Characters ought never
                     to be drawn; nor of a Narrative, that the Train of Events is agreeable
                  to Observation and Experience; for that Observation which is called Knowledge of
                  the World, will be found much more frequently to make Men cunning than good. 
                  The Purpose of these Writings is surely not only to
                     show Mankind, but to provide that they may be seen hereafter with less Hazard;
                     to teach the means of avoiding the Snares which are laid by TREACHERY for
                     INNOCENCE, without infusing any Wish for that Superiority with which the
                     Betrayer flatters his Vanity; to give the Power of counteracting Fraud without
                     the Temptation to practise it; to initiate Youth by mock Encounters in the
                     Art of necessary Defense, and to increase Prudence without impairing
                     Virtue.<ref target="a010" corresp="n010"/><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">In this passage, Johnson articulates his sense of the purpose of novelistic writing. For him, the purpose of fiction is education, as it provides a kind of experience that is protected from the dangers that might accompany such actions in real life.</note><pb n="23" facs="images/023.jpg"/>
               
            </p>
            <p>MANY Writers, for the sake of following Nature, 
            so mingle good and bad Qualities in their 
            principal Personages, that they
                     are both equally conspicuous; and as we
                     accompany them through their Adventures with Delight, and are led by Degrees to
                     interest ourselves in their Favour, we lose the Abhorrence of their Faults,
                     because they do not hinder our Pleasure, or, perhaps, regard them with some
                     Kindness for being united with so much Merit. </p>
            <p>THERE have been Men indeed splendidly wicked, whose Endowments threw a Brightness
                  on their Crimes, and whom scarce any Villainy made perfectly detestable, because
                  they never could be wholly divested of their Excellencies; but such have been in
                  all Ages the great Corruptors of the World, and their Resemblance ought no more to be preserved, than the Art of murdering
                     without Pain.</p>
            <p>
                SOME have advanced, without due Attention to
                     the Consequences of this Notion, that certain Virtues have their correspondent
                     Faults, and therefore that to exhibit either apart is to deviate from
                     Probability.
                     Thus Men are observed by <hi rend="italic">Swift</hi><ref target="a011" corresp="n011"/><note xml:id="n011" target="a011"><graphic url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/43/Gullivers_travels.jpg"/>Jonathan Swift, an Anglo-Irish satiric author of the early 18th century, is most well-known today for writing <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi>. The title page to the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi>, reproduced from Wikimedia Commons, is above. For more information on Swift, see <ref target="https://www.tcd.ie/trinitywriters/writers/jonathan-swift/">this biographical essay by Ian Campbell Ross (2016)</ref>, and readers may also be interested in <ref target="https://www.tcd.ie/library/exhibitions/swift/">this 2017 online exhibition about Swift from the Library of Trinity College, Dublin</ref>.</note> to be 
                   grateful in the same Degree as they are
                   resentful.<ref target="a017" corresp="n017"/><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">From the second volume of the <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies</hi>, compiled by Jonathan Swift and Alexander Pope, this particular quotation is from <ref target="http://estc.bl.uk/T39472">Thoughts on Various Subjects,"</ref> a collection of witty aphorisms by Pope and contained in the second volume. </note>
                This Principle, with others of the same
                     Kind, supposes Man to act from a brute Impulse, and persue a certain Degree of
                     Inclination, without any Choice of the Object; for, otherwise, though it
                  should be allowed that Gratitude and Resentment arise from the same Constitution
                  of the Passions, it follows not that they will be equally indulged when Reason is
                  consulted; yet unless that Consequence be admitted, this sagacious Maxim becomes
                  an empty Sound, without any Relation to Practice
                     or to Life.</p>
            <p>NOR is it evident that even the first Motions to these Effects are always in the
                  same Proportion. For Pride, which produces Quickness of Resentment, will frequently obstruct
                  Gratitude, by Unwillingness to admit that Inferiority which Obligation implies;
                  and it is very unlikely, that he who cannot think he receives a Favour will
                  ever acknowledge it.</p> <pb n="24" facs="images/024.jpg"/>
            <p>IT is of the utmost Importance to
                  Mankind, that Positions of this Tendency should be laid open and confuted;
                  for while Men consider Good and Evil as springing from the same Root, they will
                  spare the one for the sake of the other, and in judging, if not of others at least
                  of themselves, will be apt to estimate their Virtues by their Vices. To this fatal Error all those will contribute, who
                     confound the Colours of Right and Wrong, and instead of helping to settle their
                     Boundaries, mix them with so much Art, that no common Mind is able to disunite
                     them.
            </p>
            <p>
                IN Narratives, where historical Veracity has
                     no Place, I cannot discover why there should not be exhibited the most perfect
                     Idea of Virtue; of Virtue not angelical, nor above Probability; for what we
                     cannot credit we shall never imitate; but the highest and purest Kind that Humanity
                     can reach, which, when exercised in such Trials as the various Revolutions of Things
                     shall bring upon it, may, by conquering some Calamities, and enduring others,
                     teach us what we may hope, and what we can perform.
                Vice, for Vice is necessary to be shewn, should
                     always disgust; nor should the Graces of Gaiety, or the Dignity of
                  Courage, be so united with it, as to reconcile it to the Mind. Wherever it appears, it should raise Hatred by the
                     Malignity of its Practices; and Contempt, by the Meanness of its Stratagems; for
                     while it is supported by either Parts<ref target="a018" corresp="n018"/><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">According to the <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi>, "part" used in this sense (II.15) refers to "A personal quality or attribute, esp. of an intellectual kind; an ability, gift, or talent." See <ref target="http://andromeda.rutgers.edu/~jlynch/C18Guide.pdf">Jack Lynch's "Guide to Eighteenth-Century Vocabulary,"</ref> which includes a definition of this word.</note> or Spirit, it will be seldom heartily
                     abhorred. The <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi> Tyrant was content to be hated, if he was but
                  feared; and there are Thousands of the Readers of Romances willing to be thought
                  wicked, if they may be allowed to be Wits.<ref target="a019" corresp="n019"/><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">To be a "wit" in the eighteenth century was to be clever. But it could also be a term of derision, referring to a set of people who claimed false cleverness. Here, Johnson is suggesting that such people would rather be thought by others to be clever, even at the expense of being thought wicked. See <ref target="http://andromeda.rutgers.edu/~jlynch/C18Guide.pdf">Jack Lynch's "Guide to Eighteenth-Century Vocabulary,"</ref> which includes a definition of this word.</note> It
                     is therefore to be always inculcated, that Virtue is the highest Proof of a superior Understanding, and the only solid
                     Basis of Greatness; and that Vice is the natural Consequence of narrow
                     Thoughts; that it begins in Mistake, and ends in Ignominy.
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
        <p><hi rend="italic">LONDON:</hi></p>
        <p>Printed for J. PAYNE, and J. BOQUET, in Pater-noster-Row;</p>
        <p>where Letters for the RAMBLER are received.</p>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>