<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="poe-tell-tale">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">"The Tell-Tale Heart"</title>
            <author>
               <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79029745">
                  <name><forename>Edgar Allan</forename><surname>Poe</surname></name>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName>
                  <name ref="editors.xml#SF">
                     <surname>Ficke</surname>
                     <forename>Sarah</forename>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup by</resp>
               <name ref="editors.xml#MUstudstaff">Students and Staff of Marymount University</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#HAS">Hawa Sheikh-Adam</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#AJB">Austin Benson.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor/>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Marymount University Department of Literature and Languages</addrLine>
               <addrLine>2807 N. Glebe Road</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Arlington, VA </addrLine>
               <addrLine>22207</addrLine>
               <addrLine>thowe@marymount.edu</addrLine>
               <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>"The Tell-Tale Heart"</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Edgar Allan Poe</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>The Pioneer</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7014406">Boston</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>J. R. Lowell and R. Carter</publisher>
                     <date when="1843">1843</date>
                     <note>Text for this digital edition drawn from <ref
                           target="http://xroads.virginia.edu/~Hyper/POE/telltale.html">The
                           University of Virginia's etext center</ref> and checked against the first
                        edition text using The Internet Archive. Page images are drawn from <ref
                           target="https://archive.org/details/pioneerliteraryc01lowe/page/28/mode/2up"
                           >The Internet Archive</ref>'s facsimile copy off <hi rend="italic">The
                           Pioneer: A Literary and Critical Magazine</hi>.</note>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">Volume I </biblScope>
                  <biblScope>pp 29-31</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <creation/>
         <textDesc n="tale">
            <channel mode="w">print</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain/>
            <factuality type="fiction"/>
            <interaction/>
            <preparedness/>
            <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
         </textDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <setting>
               <time from="1800" to="1900">19th Century</time>
            </setting>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
               sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
               the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
               and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
               </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                  indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021" who="editors.xml#HAS">Initial XML file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <pb n="29" facs="pageImages/Tell-Tale_Heart_0029.jpg"/>
            <titlePart>THE TELL-TALE HEART.</titlePart>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <docAuthor>BY EDGAR A. POE</docAuthor>
            <lb/>
            <epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Art is long and Time is fleeting,</l>
                     <l>And our hearts, though stout and brave,</l>
                     <l>Still, like muffled drums, are beating</l>
                     <l>Funeral marches to the grave.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
               <bibl><persName type="lcnaf" key="n2010037536"><hi rend="italic"
                     >Henry Wadsworth Longfellow.</hi></persName></bibl>
               <lb/>
            </epigraph>
            <docImprint/>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <p>TRUE! — nervous — very, very dreadfully nervous I had been, and am; but why <hi
                  rend="italic">will</hi> you say that I am mad? The disease had sharpened my senses
               — not destroyed — not dulled them. Above all was the sense of hearing acute. I heard
               all things in the heaven and in the earth. I heard many things in hell. How, then, am
               I mad? <ref target="hearken_" corresp="hearken">Hearken</ref> and observe how
               healthily — how calmly I can tell you the whole story.</p>
            <p>It is impossible to say how first the idea entered my brain; but, once conceived, it
               haunted me day and night. Object there was none. Passion there was none. I loved the
               old man. He had never wronged me. He had never given me insult. For his gold I had no
               desire. I think it was his eye! — yes, it was this! He had the eye of a vulture — a
               pale blue eye, with a film over it. Whenever it fell upon me, my blood ran cold; and
               so, by degrees — very gradually — I made up my mind to take the life of the old man,
               and thus rid myself of the eye forever.</p>
            <p> Now this is the point. You fancy me mad. Madmen know nothing. But you should have
               seen <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. You should have seen how wisely I proceeded — with
               what caution — with what foresight — with what <ref target="dissimulation_"
                  corresp="dissimulation">dissimulation</ref> I went to work! I was never kinder to
               the old man than during the whole week before I killed him. And every night, about
               midnight, I turned the latch of his door and opened it — oh so gently! And then, when
               I had made an opening sufficient for my head, I put in a dark lantern, all closed,
               closed, that no light shone out, and then I thrust in my head. Oh, you would have
               laughed to see how cunningly I thrust it in! I moved it slowly — very, very slowly,
               so that I might not disturb the old man's sleep. It took me an hour to place my whole
               head within the opening so far that I could see him as he lay upon his bed. Ha! —
               would a madman have been so wise as this? And then, when my head was well in the
               room, I undid the lantern cautiously — oh, so cautiously — cautiously (for the hinges
               creaked) — I undid it just so much that a single thin ray fell upon the vulture eye.
               And this I did for seven long nights — every night just at midnight — but I found the
               eye always closed; and so it <pb n="30" facs="pageImages/Tell-Tale_Heart_0030.jpg"
               />was impossible to do the work; for it was not the old man who vexed me, but his
                  <ref target="evil_eye" corresp="evil_eye">Evil Eye</ref>. And every morning, when
               the day broke, I went boldly into his chamber, and spoke courageously to him, calling
               him by name in a hearty tone, and inquiring how he has passed the night. So you see
               he would have been a very <ref target="profound_" corresp="profound">profound</ref>
               old man, indeed, to suspect that every night, just at twelve, I looked in upon him
               while he slept.</p>
            <p>Upon the eighth night I was more than usually cautious in opening the door. A watch's
               minute hand moves more quickly than did mine. Never before that night had I <hi
                  rend="italic">felt</hi> the extent of my own powers — of my <ref
                  target="sagacity_" corresp="sagacity">sagacity</ref>. I could scarcely contain my
               feelings of triumph. To think that there I was, opening the door, little by little,
               and the old man not even to dream of my secret deeds or thoughts. I fairly chuckled
               at the idea; and perhaps the old man heard me; for he moved in the bed suddenly, as
               if startled. Now you may think that I drew back — but no. His room was as black as
               pitch with the thick darkness, (for the shutters were close fastened, through fear of
               robbers,) and so I knew that he could not see the opening of the door, and I kept
               pushing it on steadily, steadily.</p>
            <p> I had got my head in, and was about to open the lantern, when my thumb slipped upon
               the tin fastening, and the old man sprang up in bed, crying out — "Who's there?"</p>
            <p> I kept quite still and said nothing. For another hour I did not move a muscle, and
               in the meantime I did not hear the old man lie down. He was still sitting up in the
               bed, listening; — just as I have done, night after night, hearkening to the
               death-watches in the wall.</p>
            <p> Presently I heard a slight groan, and I knew it was the groan of <ref
                  target="mortal_" corresp="mortal">mortal</ref> terror. It was not a groan of pain
               or of grief — oh, no! — it was the low stifled sound that arises from the bottom of
               the soul when overcharged with <hi rend="italic">awe</hi>. I knew the sound well.
               Many a night, just at midnight, when all the world slept, it has welled up from my
               own bosom, deepening, with its dreadful echo, the terrors that distracted me. I say I
               knew it well. I knew what the old man felt, and pitied him, although I chuckled at
               heart. I knew that he had been lying awake ever since the first slight noise, when he
               had turned in the bed. His fears had been, ever since, growing upon him. He had been
               trying to fancy them causeless, but could not. He had been saying to himself — "It is
               nothing but the wind in the chimney — it is only a mouse crossing the floor," or "It
               is merely a cricket which has made a single chirp." Yes, he had been trying to
               comfort himself with these <ref target="supposition_" corresp="supposition"
                  >suppositions</ref>; but he had found all in vain. <hi rend="italic">All in
                  vain:</hi> because death, in approaching the old man, had stalked with his black
               shadow before him, and enveloped the victim. And it was the mournful influence of the
               unperceived shadow that caused him to feel — although he neither saw nor heard — to
                  <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> the presence of my head within the room.</p>
            <p>When I had waited a long time, very patiently, without hearing him lie down, I
               resolved to open a little — a very, very little crevice in the lantern. So I opened
               it — you cannot imagine how stealthily, stealthily — until, at length a simple dim
               ray, like the thread of the spider, shot from out the crevice and fell full upon the
               vulture eye.</p>
            <p>It was open — wide, wide open — and I grew furious as I gazed upon it. I saw it with
               perfect distinctness — all a dull blue, with a hideous veil over it that chilled the
               very marrow in my bones; but I could see nothing else of the old man's face or
               person; for I had directed the ray as if by instinct, precisely upon the damned
               spot.</p>
            <p>And now — have I not told you that what you mistake for madness is but over-acuteness
               of the senses? — now, I say, there came to my ears <hi rend="italic">a low, dull,
                  quick sound, such as a watch makes when enveloped in cotton</hi>. I knew <hi
                  rend="italic">that</hi> sound well, too. It was the beating of the old man's
               heart. It increased my fury, as the beating of a drum stimulates the soldier into
               courage. </p>
            <p> But even yet I refrained and kept still. I scarcely breathed. I held the lantern
               motionless. I tried how steadily I could maintain the ray upon the eye. Meantime the
               hellish tattoo of the heart increased. It grew quicker, and louder and louder every
               instant. The old man's terror <hi rend="italic">must</hi> have been extreme! It grew
               louder, I say, louder every moment: — do you mark me well? I have told you that I am
               nervous: — so I am. And now, at the dead hour of the night, and amid the dreadful
               silence of that old house, so strange a noise as this excited me to uncontrollable
               wrath. Yet, for some minutes longer, I refrained and kept still. But the beating grew
               louder, <hi rend="italic">louder!</hi> I thought the heart must burst! And now a new
               anxiety seized me — the sound would be heard by a neighbor! The old man's hour had
               come! With a loud yell, I threw open the lantern and leaped into the room. He
               shrieked once — once only. In an instant I dragged him to the floor, and pulled the
               heavy bed over him. I then smiled gaily, to find the deed so far done. But, for many
               minutes, the heart beat on with a muffled sound. This, however, did not <ref
                  target="vex_" corresp="vex">vex</ref> me; it would not be heard through the walls.
               At length it ceased. The old man was dead. I removed the bed and examined the corpse.
               Yes, he was stone, stone dead. I placed my hand upon the heart and held it there many
               minutes. There was no <ref target="pulsation_" corresp="pulsation">pulsation</ref>.
               The old man was stone dead. His eye would trouble <hi rend="italic">me</hi> no
               more.</p>
            <p>If, still, you think me mad, you will think so no longer when I describe the wise
               precautions I took for the concealment of the body. The night waned, and I worked
               hastily, but in silence. First of all I dismembered the corpse. I cut off the head
               and the arms and the legs.<pb n="31" facs="pageImages/Tell-Tale_Heart_0031.jpg"/> I
               then took up three planks from the flooring of the chamber, and deposited all between
               the scantlings. I then replaced the boards so cleverly, so cunningly, that no human
               eye — not even <hi rend="italic">his</hi> — could have detected anything wrong. There
               was nothing to wash out — no stain of any kind — no blood-spot whatever. I had been
               too wary for that. A tub had caught all — ha! ha!</p>
            <p>When I had made an end of these labors, it was four o'clock — still dark as midnight.
               As the bell sounded the hour, there came a knocking at the street door. I went down
               to open it with a light heart, — for what had I <hi rend="italic">now</hi> to fear?
               There entered three men, who introduced themselves, with perfect <ref
                  target="suavity_" corresp="suavity">suavity</ref>, as officers of the police. A
               shriek had been heard by a neighbour during the night; suspicion of foul play had
               been aroused; information had been lodged at the police-office, and they (the
               officers) had been deputed to search the premises.</p>
            <p> I smiled, — for <hi rend="italic">what</hi> had I to fear? I bade the gentlemen
               welcome. The shriek, I said, was my own in a dream. The old man, I mentioned, was
               absent in the country. I took my visitors all over the house. I bade them search
               —search <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. I led them, at length, to <hi rend="italic"
                  >his</hi> chamber. I showed them his treasures, secure, undisturbed. In the
               enthusiasm of my confidence, I brought chairs into the room, and desired them <hi
                  rend="italic">here</hi>to rest from their fatigues, while I myself, in the wild
                  <ref target="audacity_" corresp="audacity">audacity</ref> of my perfect triumph,
               placed my own seat upon the very spot beneath which reposed the corpse of the
               victim.</p>
            <p>The officers were satisfied. My <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> had convinced them. I
               was singularly at ease. They sat, and while I answered cheerily, they chatted of
               familiar things. But, ere long, I felt myself getting pale and wished them gone. My
               head ached, and I fancied a ringing in my ears: but still they sat and still chatted.
               The ringing became more distinct: I talked more freely to get rid of the feeling; but
               it continued and gained definiteness — until, at length, I found that the noise was
                  <hi rend="italic">not</hi> within my ears.</p>
            <p> No doubt I now grew <hi rend="italic">very</hi> pale; — but I talked more <ref
                  target="fluently_" corresp="fluently">fluently</ref>, and with a heightened voice.
               Yet the sound increased — and what could I do? It was <hi rend="italic">a low, dull,
                  quick sound — much such a sound as a watch makes when enveloped in cotton</hi>. I
               gasped for breath — and yet the officers heard it not. I talked more quickly — more
                  <ref target="vehemently_" corresp="vehemently">vehemently</ref>; — but the noise
               steadily increased. I arose and argued about trifles, in a high key and with
                  violent <ref target="gesticulation_" corresp="gesticulation">gesticulations</ref>;
               — but the noise steadily increased. Why<hi rend="italic">would</hi> they not be gone?
               I paced the floor to and fro, with heavy strides, as if excited to fury by the
               observations of the men — but the noise steadily increased. Oh God! what <hi
                  rend="italic">could</hi> I do? I foamed — I raved — I swore! I swung the chair
               upon which I had sat, and grated it upon the boards; — but the noise arose over all
               and continually increased. It grew louder — louder — <hi rend="italic">louder!</hi>
               And still the men chatted pleasantly, and smiled. Was it possible they heard not?
               Almighty God! — no, no! They heard! — they suspected! — they<hi rend="italic"
                  >knew!</hi> — they were making a mockery of my horror! — this I thought, and this
               I think. But anything better than this agony! Anything was more tolerable than this
               derision! I could bear those hypocritical smiles no longer! I felt that I must scream
               or die! — and now — again! — hark! louder! louder! louder! <hi rend="italic"
                  >louder</hi>! —</p>
            <p>"Villains!" I shrieked, "<ref target="dissemble_" corresp="dissemble">dissemble</ref>
               no more! I admit the deed! — tear up the planks! — here, here! — it is the beating of
               his hideous heart!!!"</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <note xml:id="hearken" target="hearken_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"><p>To hear
                  with attention, give ear to; to listen to; to have regard to, heed; to understand,
                  learn by hearing. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="dissimulation" target="dissimulation_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"
                  ><p>The action of dissimulating or dissembling; concealment of what really is,
                  under a feigned semblance of something different; feigning, hypocrisy. Source:
                  Oxford English Dictionary..</p></note>
            <note xml:id="evil_eye" target="evil_eye_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> The <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/topic/evil-eye">Evil Eye</ref> is a
                  ubiquitious cultural phenomenon referring to a glance "believed to have the
                  ability to cause injury or death to those on whom it falls."</p></note>
            <note xml:id="profound" target="profound_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> Having great insight into or knowledge of something. Source: Oxford English
                  Dictionary. </p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="sagacity" target="sagacity_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"
                  ><p>Acuteness of mental discernment; aptitude for investigation or discovery;
                  keenness and soundness of judgement in the estimation of persons and conditions,
                  and in the adaptation of means to ends; penetration, shrewdness. Source: Oxford
                  English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="mortal" target="mortal_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> Of pain, grief, fear, or the like: such as might cause death; deadly in its
                  effects. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="supposition" target="supposition_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> An assumption (without reference to its truth or falsehood) used as a basis of
                  argument, or for the purpose of tracing the consequences; a premise from which a
                  conclusion is drawn. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="vex" target="vex_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"><p>To trouble,
                  afflict, or harass (a person, etc.) by aggression, encroachment, or other
                  interference with peace and quiet; to cause damage, detriment, or difficulty to.
                  Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="pulsation" target="pulsation_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"><p>The
                  beating or throbbing of the pulse; rhythmical expansion and contraction of the
                  heart, an artery, etc. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="suavity" target="suavity_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"
                  ><p>Gracious; sweet; agreeable. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="audacity" target="audacity_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> Boldness, daring, intrepidity; confidence. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="fluently" target="fluently_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> With easy and ready flow of words. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="vehemently" target="vehemently_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#AJB">
               <p> In a manner expressive of strong feeling, perturbation, or excitement; with
                  strong or forceful language. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="gesticulation" target="gesticulation_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"
                  ><p>The action or process of gesticulating; to make lively or energetic motions
                  with the limbs or body; esp. as an accompaniment or in lieu of speech. Source:
                  Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
            <note xml:id="dissemble" target="dissemble_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#HAS"><p> To
                  alter or disguise the semblance of (one's character, a feeling, design, or action)
                  so as to conceal, or deceive as to, its real nature; to give a false or feigned
                  semblance to; to cloak or disguise by a feigned appearance. Source: Oxford English
                  Dictionary.</p></note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
