<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="poe-the-cask">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Cask of Amontillado"</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79029745">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Edgar Allan</forename>
                            <surname>Poe</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
                            <forename>Tonya</forename>
                            <surname>Howe</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#UVAstudentsstaff">Students and Staff of The University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#VBS">Veronica Scott</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> 434-924-7105 </addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"The Cask of Amontillado"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName>Edgar Allan Poe</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title>"The Cask of Amontillado"</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7014406">Philadelphia</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Open Court Publishing Co</publisher>
                            <date when="1846">1846</date>
                            <note>Text for this digital edition drawn from <ref
                                target="http://xroads.virginia.edu/~Hyper/POE/cask.html">The
                                University of Virginia's etext center</ref> and checked against the first
                                edition text using <ref target="https://archive.org/details/sim_godeys-magazine_1846-11_33_5/page/216/mode/2up">
                                The Internet Archive</ref>. Page images are drawn from <ref
                                target="https://archive.org/details/sim_godeys-magazine_1846-11_33_5/page/216/mode/2up"
                                >The Internet Archive</ref>'s copy of <hi rend="italic">Godey's Magazine and Lady's Book</hi></note>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">Vol. XXXIII</biblScope>
                        <biblScope>pp 216-218</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="cask">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <time from="1700" to="1840">Early 19th Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
                    Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
                    University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-05-30" who="editors.xml#VBS">Initial XML file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb n="216"/>
                <titlePart>THE CASK OF AMONTILLADO.</titlePart>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <docAuthor>BY EDGAR A. POE</docAuthor>
                <lb/>
                <docImprint/>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>
                    THE thousand injuries of Fortunato I had borne as I best could, but when 
                    he ventured upon insult I vowed revenge. You, who so well know the nature of my soul,
                    will not suppose, however, that I gave utterance to a threat. <hi rend="italic">At length</hi> I would be avenged;
                    this was a point definitely, settled-- but the very definitiveness with which
                    it was resolved precluded the idea of risk. I must not only punish but punish with impunity.
                    A wrong is <ref target="unredressed_" corresp="unredressed">unredressed</ref> when retribution overtakes its redresser.
                    It is equally unredressed when the avenger fails to make himself felt as such to him who had done wrong.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It must be understood that neither by word nor deed had I given Fortunato cause to doubt my good will.
                    I continued, as was wont, to smile in his face, and he did not perceive that my smile <hi rend="italic">now</hi> was
                    at the thought of his immolation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    He had a weak point--this Fortunato--although in other regards he was a man to be respected and even feared.
                    He prided himself on his connoisseurship in wine. Few Italians have the virtuoso spirit.
                    For the most part their enthusiasm is adopted to suit the time and opportunity, to practice imposture upon
                    the British and Austrian <hi rend="italic">millionaires</hi>. In painting and <ref target="gemmary_" corresp="gemmary">gemmary</ref>,
                    Fortunato, like his countrymen, was a quack, but in the matter of old wines he was sincere.
                    In this respect I did not differ from him materially;--I was skilful in the Italian vintages myself,
                    and bought largely whenever I could.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It was about dusk, one evening during the supreme madness of the carnival season, that I encountered my friend.
                    He accosted me with excessive warmth, for he had been drinking much. The man wore <ref target="motley_" corresp="motley">motley</ref>.
                    He had on a tight-fitting parti-striped dress, and his head was surmounted by the conical cap and bells.
                    I was so pleased to see him that I thought I should never have done wringing his hand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I said to him--"My dear Fortunato, you are luckily met. How remarkably well you are looking to-day. But I have
                    received a pipe of what passes for Amontillado, and I have my doubts."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "How?" said he. "Amontillado? A pipe? Impossible! And in the middle of the carnival!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "I have my doubts," I replied; "and I was silly enough to pay the full Amontillado price without consulting
                    you in the matter. You were not to be found, and I was fearful of losing a bargin."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Amontillado!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "I have my doubts."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Amontillado!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "And I must satisfy them."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Amontillado!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "As you are engaged, I am on my way to Luchresi. If any one has a critical turn it is he. He will tell me--"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Luchresi cannot tell Amontillado from Sherry."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "And yet some fools will have it that his taste is a match for your own."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Come, let us go."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Whither?"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "To your vaults."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "My friend, no; I will not impose upon your good nature. I perceive you have an engagement. Luchresi--"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "I have no engagement;--come."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "My friend, no. It is not the engagement, but the severe cold with which I perceive you are afflicted.
                    The vaults are insufferably damp. They are encrusted with <ref target="nitre_" corresp="nitre">nitre</ref>."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Let us go, nevertheless. The cold is merely nothing. Amontillado! You have been imposed upon. And as for Luchresi,
                    he cannot distinguish Sherry from Amontillado."
                </p>
                <p>
                    Thus speaking, Fortunato possessed himself of my arm; and putting on a mask of black silk and drawing a
                    <ref target="roquelaire_" corresp="roquelaire"><hi rend="italic">roquelaire</hi></ref> closely around my person, I suffered him to hurry
                    me to my <ref target="palazzo_" corresp="palazzo">palazzo</ref>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There were not attendants at home; they had <ref target="absconded_" corresp="absconded">absconded</ref> to make merry
                    in honour of the time. I had told them that I should not return until the morning, and had given them explicit orders
                    not to stir from the house. The orders were sufficient, I well knew, to insure their immediate disappearance, one and all,
                    as soon as my back was turned.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I took from their sconces two <ref target="flambeaux_" corresp="flambeaux">flambeaux</ref>, and giving one to Fortunato,
                    bowed him through several suites of rooms to the archway that led into the vaults. I passed down a long and winding staircase,
                    requesting him to be cautious as he followed. We came at length to the foot of the descent,
                    and stood together upon the damp ground of the catacombs of the Montresors.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The gait of my friend was unsteady, and the bells upon his cap jingled as he strode.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "The pipe," he said.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "It is farther on," said I; "but observe the white web-work which gleams from these cavern walls."
                </p>
                <p>
                    He turned towards me, and looked into my eyes with two filmy orbs that distilled the
                    <ref target="rheum_" corresp="rheum">rheum</ref> of intoxication.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Nitre?" he asked, at length.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Nitre," I replied. "How long have you had that cough?"
                </p>
                <pb n="217"/>
                <p>
                    "Ugh! ugh! ugh!--ugh! ugh! ugh!--ugh! ugh! ugh!--ugh! ugh! ugh!--ugh! ugh! ugh!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    My poor friend found it impossible to reply for many minutes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "It is nothing," he said, at last.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Come," I said, with decision, "we will go back; your health is precious. You are rich, respected, admired, beloved; you are happy,
                    as I once was. You are a man to be missed. For me it is no matter. We will go back; you will be ill, and I cannot be responsible.
                    Besides, there is Luchresi--"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Enough," he said; "the cough is a mere nothing; it will not kill me. I shall not die of a cough."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "True--true," I replied; "and, indeed, I had no intention of alarming you unnecessarily--but you should use all proper caution.
                    A draught of this <ref target="medoc_" corresp="medoc">Medoc</ref> will defend us from the damps.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Here I knocked off the neck of a bottle which I drew from a long row of its fellows that lay upon the mould.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Drink," I said, presenting him the wine.
                </p>
                <p>
                    He raised it to his lips with a leer. He paused and nodded to me familiarly, while his bells jingled.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "I drink," he said, "to the buried that repose around us."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "And I to your long life."
                </p>
                <p>
                    He again took my arm, and we proceeded.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "These vaults," he said, "are extensive."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "The Montresors," I replied, "were a great and numerous family."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "I forget your arms."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "A huge human foot d'or, in a field azure; the foot crushes a serpent rampant whose fangs are imbedded in the heel."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "And the motto?"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "<ref target="nemo_" corresp="nemo"><hi rend="italic">Nemo me impune lacessit</hi></ref>."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Good!" he said.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The wine sparkled in his eyes and the bells jingled. My own fancy grew warm with the Medoc. We had passed through long walls
                    of piled skeletons, with casks and <ref target="puncheons_" corresp="puncheons">puncheons</ref> intermingling, into the inmost
                    recesses of the catacombs. I paused again, and this time I made bold to seize Fortunato by an arm above the elbow.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "The nitre!" I said; "see, it increases. It hangs like moss upon the vaults. We are below the river's bed. The drops of moisture trickle
                    among the bones. Come, we will go back ere it is too late. Your cough--"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "It is nothing," he said; "let us go on. But first, another draught of the Medoc."
                </p>
                <p>
                    I broke and reached him a flaçon of De Grâve. He emptied it at a breath. His eyes flashed with a fierce light. He laughed and threw the
                    bottle upwards with a gesticulation I did not understand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I looked at him in surprise. He repeated the movement--a grotesque one.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "You do not comprehend?" he said.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Not I," I replied.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Then you are not of the brotherhood."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "How?"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "You are not of the masons."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Yes, yes," I said; "yes, yes."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "You? Impossible! A mason?"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "A mason," I replied.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "A sign," he said, "a sign."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "It is this," I answered, producing from beneath the folds of my <ref target="roquelaire" corresp="roquelaire"><hi rend="italic">roquelaire</hi></ref>
                    a trowel.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "You jest," he exclaimed, recoiling a few paces. "But let us proceed to the Amontillado."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Be it so," I said, replacing the tool beneath the cloak and again offering him my arm. He leaned upon it heavily. We continued our rout in
                    search of the Amontillado. We passed through a range of low arches, descended, passed on, and descending again, arrived at a deep crypt,
                    in which the foulness of the air caused our flambeaux rather to glow than flame.
                </p>
                <p>
                    At the most remote end of the crypt there appeared another less spacious. Its walls had been lined with human remains,
                    piled to the vault overhead, in the fashion of the great catacombs of Paris. Three sides of this interior crypt were still ornamented in this manner.
                    From the fourth side the bones had been thrown down, and lay promiscuously upon the earth, forming at one point a mound of some size.
                    Within the wall thus exposed by the displacing of the bones, we perceived a still interior crypt or recess, in depth about four feet,
                    in width three, in height six or seven. It seemed to have been constructed for no especial use within itself, but formed merely the interval between
                    two of the colossal supports of the roof of the catacombs, and was backed by one of their circumscribing walls of solid granite.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It was in vain that Fortunato, uplifting his dull torch, endeavoured to pry into the depth of the recess. Its termination the feeble light did not
                    enable use to see.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Proceed," I said; "herein is the Amontillado. As for Luchresi--"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "He is an ignoramus," interrupted my friend, as he stepped unsteadily forward, while I followed immediately at his heels.
                    In an instant he had reached the extremity of the <ref target="niche_" corresp="niche">niche</ref>,
                    and finding his progress arrested by the rock, stood stupidly bewildered. A moment more and I had
                    <ref target="fettered_" corresp="fettered">fettered</ref> him to the granite. In its surface were two iron staples, distant from each other
                    about two feet, horizontally. From one of these depended a short chain, from the other a padlock. Throwing the links about his waist,
                    it was but the work of a few seconds to secure it. He was too much astounded to resit. Withdrawing the key I stepped back from the recess.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Pass your hand," I said, "over the wall; you cannot help feeling the nitre. Indeed it is <hi rend="italic">very</hi> damp.
                    Once more let me <hi rend="italic">implore</hi> you to return. No? Then I must positively leave you.
                    But I will first render you all the little attentions in my power."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "The Amontillado!" ejaculated my friend, not yet recovered from his astonishment.
                </p>
                <pb n="218"/>
                <p>
                    "True," I replied, "the Amontillado."
                </p>
                <p>
                    As I said these words I busied myself among the pile of bones of which I have before spoken. Throwing them aside, I soon uncovered
                    a quantity of building stone and mortar. With these materials and with the aid of my trowel, I began vigorously to wall up the entrance of the niche.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I had scarcely laid the first tier of the masonry when I discovered that the intoxication of Fortunato had in a great measure worn off.
                    The earliest indication I had of this was a low moaning cry from the depth of the recess. It was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the cry of a drunken man.
                    There was then a long and <ref target="obstinate_" corresp="obstinate">obstinate</ref> silence. I laid the second tier, and the third, and the fourth;
                    and then I heard the furious vibrations of the chain. The noise lasted for several minutes, duing which, that I might hearken to it with the more
                    satisfaction, I ceased my labours and sat down upon the bones. When at last the clanking subsided, I resumed the trowel, and finished without
                    interruption the fifth, the sixth, and the seventh tier. The wall was now nearly upon a level with my breast.
                    I again paused, and holding the flambeaux over the mason-work, threw a few feeble rays upon the figure within.
                </p>
                <p>
                    A succession of loud and shrill screams, bursting suddenly from the throat of the chained form, seemed to thrust me violently back. For a brief moment
                    I hesitated, I trembled. Unsheathing my rapier, I began to grope with it about the recess; but the thought of an instant reassured me.
                    I placed my hand upon the solid fabric of the catacombs, and felt satisfied. I reapproached the wall. I replied to the yells of him who clamoured.
                    I re-echoed, I aided, I surpassed them in volume and in strength. I did this, and the clamourer grew still.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It was now midnight, and my task was drawing to a close. I had completed the eight, the ninth, and the tenth tier.
                    I had finished a portion of the last and eleventh; there remained but a single stone to be fitted and plastered in.
                    I struggled with its weight; I placed it it partially in its destined position. But now there came from out the niche
                    a low laugh that erected the hairs upon my head. It was succeeded by a sad voice, which I had difficulty in recognizing as
                    that of the noble Fortunato. The voice said--
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Ha! ha! ha!--he! he! he!--a very good joke, indeed--an excellent jest. We will have many a rich laugh about it at the palazzo--he!
                    he! he--over our wine--he! he! he"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "The Amontillado!" I said.
                </p>
                <p>
                    "He! he! he!--he! he! he!--yes, the Amontillado. But is it not getting late? Will not they be awaiting us at the palazzo,
                    the Lady Fortunato and the rest? Let us be gone."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Yes," I said, "let us be gone."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "<hi rend="italic">For the love of God, Montresor!</hi>"
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Yes," I said, "for the love of God!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    But to these words I hearkened in vain for a reply. I grew impatient. I called aloud--
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Fortunato!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    No answer. I called again--
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Fortunato!"
                </p>
                <p>
                    No answer still. I thrust a torch through the remaining aperture and let it fall within. There came forth in return only a jingling of the bells.
                    My heart grew sick; it was the dampness of the catacombs that made it so. I hastened to make an end of my labour.
                    I forced the last stone into position; I plastered it up. Against the new masonry I re-erected the old rampart of bones. For the half
                    of a century no mortal has disturbed them. <ref target="requiesat_" corresp="requiesat"><hi rend="italic">In pace requiescat!</hi></ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <note xml:id="unredressed" target="unredressed_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Not redressed; not set right; uncorrected; unrecompensed.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="gemmary" target="gemmary_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Of or pertaining to gems; concerned with or skilled in gems.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="motley" target="motley_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Cloth woven from threads of two or more colours; a piece of this cloth.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="nitre" target="nitre_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Originally: †natron, native sodium carbonate (obsolete).
                    In later use: sodium or potassium nitrate; spec. potassium nitrate (saltpetre). <!-- TODO: double check -->
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="roquelaire" target="roquelaire_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A man's knee-length cloak with a cape collar,
                    fashionable during the 18th cent. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="roquelaire" target="roquelaire_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A man's knee-length cloak with a cape collar,
                    fashionable during the 18th cent. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="palazzo" target="palazzo_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A palatial mansion, esp. in Italy; (in extended use)
                    any large and imposing building or residence. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="absconded" target="absconded_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>To hide, conceal; to obscure.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="flambeaux" target="flambeaux_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A torch; esp. one made of several thick wicks dipped in wax;
                    a lighted torch. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="rheum" target="rheum_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Watery or mucous secretions,
                    esp. as collecting in or dripping from the eyes, nose, or mouth, originally believed to originate in the brain or head and to be
                    capable of causing disease; †a secretion of this nature (obsolete). In early use also: †a flow or flux (of humours) (obsolete).
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="medoc" target="medoc_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Red wine produced in Médoc; (as a count noun) a wine produced in this region.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="puncheon" target="puncheon_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Originally: a large barrel or cask,
                    esp. one of definite capacity, varying for different liquids and commodities (now historical). Now: spec. a cask used for fermenting or ageing wine.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="roquelaire" target="roquelaire_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A man's knee-length cloak with a cape collar, fashionable during the 18th cent.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="niche" target="niche_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>A shallow ornamental recess or hollow set into a wall,
                    usually for the purpose of containing a statue or other decorative object. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="fettered" target="fettered_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>To bind with or as with fetters; to chain, fasten, shackle.
                    Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="obstinate" target="obstinate_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Firmly adhering to an opinion or chosen course of action
                    despite argument, persuasion, or entreaty; inflexible, resolute, stubborn, self-willed; indicative of or characterized by inflexibility
                    or stubbornness. Usually with pejorative connotation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary.</p></note>
                <note xml:id="requiesat" target="requiesat_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Latin for "Rest in peace".</p></note>
                <note xml:id="nemo" target="nemo_" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS"><p>Latin for "No one attacks me with impunity".</p></note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>