<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wheatley-poems">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Poems on Various Subjects, Religious and Moral </title>
            <author>
               <persName type="lccn" key="n50016726">
                  <forename>Phillis</forename>
                  <surname>Wheatley</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">Tonya Howe</persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name>Students of Marymount University</name>
               <name>James West</name>
               <name>Amy Ridderhof</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <orgName>Novels in Context</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Marymount University Department of Literature and Languages</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>2807 N. Glebe Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Arlington, VA </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>22207</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>thowe@marymount.edu</email>
            </distributor>
            <authority>
               <idno>wheatley-poems</idno>
               <!-- we need to develop a plan for these identifications -->
            </authority>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
            <textDesc>
               <constitution status="incomplete"> This text is incomplete and in further need of
                  editing and annotation.</constitution>
            </textDesc>
            <date when="2018-06-18"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Wheatley, Phillis, 1753-1784</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>Poems on various subjects, Religious and Moral</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <extent>[9],124p., 18cm </extent>
                     <idno>PS886.W5 1773</idno>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="TGN" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed for A. Bell</publisher>
                     <publisher>bookseller, Aldgate</publisher>
                     <date when="1773">1773</date>
                     <note>Page images are sourced from <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiuc.5618715">the Hathi Trust digital facsimile of the first edition owned by University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</ref>.</note>
                  </imprint>
                  <imprint>
                     <extent type="online"
                        >https://quod.lib.umich.edu/a/amverse/BAP5379.0001.001?view=toc</extent>
                     <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>University of Michigan Humanities Text Initiative</publisher>
                     <date when="1999">1999</date>
                     <note>Online SGML text. SGML markup edited to conform to LiC parameters,
                        including changes to element and attribute case, ligatures, and other
                        special html characters.</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc> <p>This text is prepared as part of the <i>Literature in Context</i> project,
            which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
            relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th
            century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
            developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p></projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible
               resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
               knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If
               you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
               lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p></interpretation>
            <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has
               been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
            <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
               the word.</p></hyphenation>
            <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running
               headers have not.</p></segmentation>
            <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
               where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lccn">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece" id="div.187">
            <pb n="[frontispiece]" facs="images/WP-FP.jpg"/>
         </div>
         <pb n="[titlepage]" facs="images/WP-TP.jpg"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>POEMS <lb/>ON <lb/>VARIOUS SUBJECTS, <lb/>RELIGIOUS AND MORAL.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY</byline>
            <lb/>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="italic">PHILLIS WHEATLEY</hi>,</docAuthor>
            <lb/>
            <docAuthor><title>NEGRO SERVANT to Mr. JOHN WHEATLEY, <lb/>of BOSTON, in NEW
                  ENGLAND.</title></docAuthor>
            <lb/>
            <docImprint><pubPlace><hi rend="italic">LONDON:</hi></pubPlace><lb/>
               <publisher>Printed for A. BELL, Bookseller, Aldgate; and sold by<lb/>Messrs. COX and
                  BERRY, King-Street, <hi rend="italic">BOSTON.</hi></publisher><date>M DCC
                  LXXIII.</date>
               <pb n="[ii]" id="P445" facs="images/WP-ii.jpg"/>
               <head type="subhead"><hi rend="italic">Entered at Stationer's
               Hall.</hi></head></docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="Contents" id="div.188">
            <pb n="[125]" facs="images/WP-0125.jpg"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>To Maecenas <ref>9</ref></item>
               <item>On Virtue <ref>13</ref></item>
               <item>To the University of Cambridge, in New-England <ref>15</ref></item>
               <item>To the King's Most Excellent Majesty. 1768. <ref>17</ref></item>
               <item>On Being Brought from Africa<ref>18</ref></item>
               <item>On the Death of the Rev. Dr. Sewell. 1769.<ref>19</ref></item>
               <item>On the Rev. Mr. George Whitefield <ref>22</ref></item>
               <item>On the Death of a young Lady of five Years of Age <ref>25</ref></item>
               <item>On the Death of a young Gentleman <ref>27</ref></item>
               <item>To a Lady on the Death of her Husband <ref>29</ref></item>
               <item>Goliath of Gath <ref>31</ref></item>
               <item>Thoughts on the Works of Providence <ref>43</ref></item>
               <item>To a Lady on the Death of three Relations <ref>51</ref></item>
               <item>To a Clergyman on the Death of his Lady <ref>53</ref></item>
               <item>An Hymn to the Morning <ref>56</ref></item>
               <item>An Hymn to the Evening <ref>58</ref></item>
               <pb n="[126]" facs="images/WP-0126.jpg"/>
               <item>On Isaiah LXIII. 1-8 <ref>60</ref></item>
               <item>On Recollection <ref>62</ref></item>
               <item>On Imagination <ref>65</ref></item>
               <item>A Funeral Poem on the Death of an Infant aged twelve Months
                  <ref>69</ref></item>
               <item>To Captain H.D., of the 65th Regiment <ref>72</ref></item>
               <item>To the Rt. Hon. William, Earl of Dartmouth<ref>73</ref></item>
               <item>Ode to Neptune<ref>76</ref></item>
               <item>To a Lady on her coming to North America with her Son, for the Recovery of her
                  Health <ref>78</ref></item>
               <item>To a Lady on her remarkable Preservation in a Hurricane in North Carolina
                     <ref>80</ref></item>
               <item>To a Lady and her Children on the Death of her Son, and their Brother
                     <ref>82</ref></item>
               <item>To a Gentleman and Lady on the Death of the Lady's Brother and Sister, and a
                  Child of the Name of <hi rend="italic">Avis</hi>, aged one Year
                  <ref>84</ref></item>
               <item>On the Death of Dr. Samuel Marshall <ref>86</ref></item>
               <item>To a Gentleman on his Voyage to Great-Britain, for the Recovery of his Health
                     <ref>88</ref></item>
               <item>To the Rev. Dr. Thomas Amory on reading his Sermons on Daily Devotion, in which
                  that Duty is recommended and assisted <ref>90</ref></item>
               <pb n="[127]" facs="images/WP-0127.jpg"/>
               <item>On the Death of J. C. an Infant <ref>92</ref></item>
               <item>An Hymn to Humanity <ref>95</ref></item>
               <item>To the Hon. T. H. Esq; on the Death of his Daughter <ref>98</ref></item>
               <item>Niobe in Distress for her Children slain by Apollo, from <hi rend="italic"
                     >Ovid's</hi> Metamorphoses, Book VI. and from a View of the Painting of Mr. <hi
                     rend="italic">Richard Wilson</hi>
                  <ref>101</ref></item>
               <item>To S. M. a young African Painter, on seeing his Works <ref>114</ref></item>
               <item>To his Honour the Lieutenant-Governor, on the Death of his Lady
                  <ref>116</ref></item>
               <item>A Farewel to America <ref>119</ref></item>
               <item>A Rebus by I. B. <ref>123</ref></item>
               <item>An Answer to ditto, by <hi rend="italic">Phillis Wheatley</hi>
                  <ref>124</ref></item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication" id="div.189">
            <pb n="[iii]" id="images/WP-iii.jpg"/>
            <opener><salute>DEDICATION.<lb/>To the Right Honourable the <lb/>COUNTESS OF
                  HUNTINGDON,</salute></opener>
            <p>THE FOLLOWING <lb/>POEMS <lb/>Are most respectfully <lb/>Inscribed,</p>
            <closer><signed>By her much obliged,<lb/>Very humble,<lb/>And devoted Servant,<lb/><hi
                     rend="italic">Phillis Wheatley.</hi></signed><date><hi rend="italic">Boston,
                     June 12, 1773.</hi></date></closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface" id="div.190">
            <pb n="[iv]" id="images/WP-iv.jpg"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE following POEMS were written originally for the Amusement of the Author, as they
               were the Products of her leisure Moments. She had no Intention ever to have published
               them; nor would they now have made their Appearance, but at the Importunity of many
               of her best, and most generous Friends; to whom she considers herself, as under the
               greatest Obligations.</p>
            <p>As her Attempts in Poetry are now sent into the World, it is hoped the Critic will
               not severely censure their Defects; and we presume they have too much Merit<pb n="v"
                  id="v.jpg"/>to be cast aside with Contempt, and worthless and trifling
               Effusions.</p>
            <p>As to the Disadvantages she has laboured under, with Regard to Learning, nothing
               needs to be offered, as her Master's Letter in the following Page will sufficiently
               shew the Difficulties in the Respect she had to encounter.</p>
            <p>With all their Imperfections, the Poems are now humbly submitted to the Perusal of
               the Public.</p>
         </div>

         <div id="div.191">
            <pb n="[vi]" id="images/WP-vi.jpg"/>
            <head>The following is a Copy of a LETTER sent by the<lb/>Author's Master to the
               Publisher</head>
            <p>PHILLIS was brought from <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
                  >America</hi>, in the Year 1761, between Seven and Eight Years of Age. Without any
               Assistance from School Education, and by only what she was taught in the Family, she,
               in sixteen Months Time from her Arrival, attained the English Language, to which she
               was an utter Stranger before, the such a Degree, as to read any, the most difficult
               Parts of the Sacred Writings, to the great Astonishment of all who heard her.</p>
            <p>As to her WRITING, her own Curiosity led her to it; and this she learnt in so short a
               Time, that in the Year 1765, she wrote a Letter to the Rev. Mr. OCCOM, the <hi
                  rend="italic">Indian</hi> Minister, while in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>.</p>
            <p>She has a great Inclination to learn the Latin Tongue, and has made some Progress in
               it. This Relation is given by her Master who bought her, and with whom she now
               lives.</p>
            <closer><signed>JOHN WHEATLEY.</signed><date><hi rend="italic">Boston, Nov. 14,
                     1772.</hi></date></closer>
         </div>
         <pb n="[vii]" id="images/WP-vii.jpg"/>
         <div type="note" id="div.192">
            <head>To the PUBLICK.</head>
            <p>AS it has been repeatedly suggested to the Publisher, by Persons, who have seen the
               Manuscript, that Numbers would be ready to suspect they were not really the Writings
               of PHILLIS, he has procured the following Attestation, from the most respectable
               Characters in <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, that none might have the least Ground
               for disputing their <hi rend="italic">Original</hi>. </p>
            <p>WE whose Names are under-written, do assure the World, that the POEMS specified in
               the following Page, <note n="*" id="pvii.n1">The Words <hi rend="italic">"following
                     Page,"</hi> allude to the Contents of the Manuscript Copy, which are wrote at
                  the Back of the above Attestation.</note> were (as we verily believe) written by
               PHILLIS, a young Negro Girl, who was but a few Years since, brought an uncultivated
               Barbarian from <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi>, and has ever since been, and now is,
               under the Disadvantage of serving as a Slave in a Family in this Town. She has been
               examined by some of the best Judges, and is thought qualified to write them. <list>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">His Excellency</hi> THOMAS HUTCHINSON, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Governor,</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> ANDREW OLIVER, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lieutenant-Governor.</hi></item>
               </list><list>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> Thomas Hubbard,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> John Erving,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> James Pitts,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> Harrison Gray,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Hon.</hi> James Bowdoin,</item>
                  <item>John Hancock, <hi rend="italic">Esq;</hi></item>
                  <item>Joseph Green, <hi rend="italic">Esq;</hi></item>
                  <item>Richard Carey, <hi rend="italic">Esq;</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev.</hi> Charles Cheuney, <hi rend="italic"
                     >D.D.</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev.</hi> Mather Byles, <hi rend="italic"
                     >D.D.</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev.</hi> Ed. Pemberton, <hi rend="italic"
                     >D.D.</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev.</hi> Andrew Elliot, <hi rend="italic"
                     >D.D.</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev.</hi> Samuel Cooper, <hi rend="italic"
                     >D.D.</hi></item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev. Mr.</hi> Samuel Mather,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">The Rev. Mr.</hi> Joon Moorhead,</item>
                  <item><hi rend="italic">Mr.</hi> John Wheatley, <hi rend="italic">her
                     Master.</hi></item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> The original Attestation, signed by the above Gentlemen,
               may be seen by applying to <hi rend="italic">Archibald Bell</hi>, Bookseller, No. 8,
                  <hi rend="italic">Aldgate-Street</hi>. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <pb n="[viii]" id="images/WP-viii.jpg"/>

      <body>
         <pb n="[9]" facs="images/WP-0009.jpg"/>

         <head>POEMS<lb/> ON<lb/> VARIOUS SUBJECTS.</head>



         <div type="poem" id="div.193">
            <head>TO MAECENAS.</head>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1280">
               <l n="1">MAECENAS, you, beneath the myrtle shade,</l>
               <l n="2">Read o'er what poets sung, and shepherds play'd.</l>
               <l n="3">What felt those poets but you feel the same?</l>
               <l n="4">Does not your soul possess the sacred flame?</l>
               <l n="5">Their noble strains your equal genius shares</l>
               <l n="6">In softer language, and diviner airs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1281">
               <l rend="indent" id="7">While <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi> paints, lo!
                  circumfus'd in air,</l>
               <l n="9">Celestial Gods in mortal forms appear;</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="images/WP-0010.jpg"/>
               <l n="10">Swift as they move hear each recess rebound,</l>
               <l n="11">Heav'n quakes, earth trembles, and the shores resound.</l>
               <l n="12">Great Sire of verse, before my mortal eyes,</l>
               <l n="12">The lightnings blaze across the vaulted skies,</l>
               <l n="14">And, as the thunder shakes the heav'nly plains,</l>
               <l n="15">A deep-felt horror thrills through all my veins.</l>
               <l n="16">When gentler strains demand thy graceful song,</l>
               <l n="17">The length'ning line moves languishing along.</l>
               <l n="18">When great <hi rend="italic">Patroclus</hi> courts <hi rend="italic"
                     >Achilles'</hi> aid,</l>
               <l n="19">The grateful tribute of my tears is paid;</l>
               <l n="20">Prone on the shore he feels the pangs of love,</l>
               <l n="21">And stern <hi rend="italic">Pelides</hi> tend'rest passions move.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1282">
               <l rend="indent" id="22">Great <hi rend="italic">Maro's </hi>strain in heav'nly
                  numbers flows,</l>
               <l n="23">The <hi rend="italic">Nine</hi> inspire, and all the bosom glows.</l>
               <l n="24">O could I rival thine and <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi>'s page,</l>
               <l n="25">Or claim the <hi rend="italic">Muses</hi> with the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Mantuan</hi> Sage;</l>
               <l n="26">Soon the same beauties should my mind adorn,</l>
               <l n="27">And the same ardors in my soul should burn:</l>
               <l n="28">Then should my song in bolder notes arise,</l>
               <l n="29">And all my numbers pleasingly surprize;</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="images/WP-0011.jpg"/>
               <l n="30">But here I sit, and mourn a grov'ling mind,</l>
               <l n="31">That fain would mount, and ride upon the wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1283">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6436">Not you, my friend, these plaintive strains become,</l>
               <l n="32">Not you, whose bosom is the <hi rend="italic">Muses</hi> home;</l>
               <l n="33">When they from tow'ring <hi rend="italic">Helicon</hi> retire,</l>
               <l n="34">They fan in you the bright immortal fire,</l>
               <l n="35">But I less happy, cannot raise the song,</l>
               <l n="36">The fault'ring music dies upon my tongue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1284">
               <l rend="indent" id="37">The happier <hi rend="italic">Terence</hi>
                  <note n="*" id="p11.n1">He was an <hi rend="italic">African</hi> by birth.</note>
                  all the choir inspir'd,</l>
               <l n="38">His soul replenish'd, and his bosom fir'd;</l>
               <l n="39">But say, ye <hi rend="italic">Muses</hi>, why this partial grace,</l>
               <l n="40">To one alone of <hi rend="italic">Afric</hi>'s sable race;</l>
               <l n="41">From age to age transmitting thus his name</l>
               <l n="42">With the first glory in the rolls of fame?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1285">
               <l rend="indent" id="43">Thy virtues, great <hi rend="italic">Maecenas!</hi> shall
                  be sung</l>
               <l n="44">In praise of him, from whom those virtues sprung:</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="images/WP-0012.jpg"/>
               <l n="45">While blooming wreaths around thy temples spread,</l>
               <l n="46">I'll snatch a laurel from thine honour'd head,</l>
               <l n="47">While you indulgent smile upon the deed.</l>
            </lg>



            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1286">
               <l rend="indent" id="48">As long as <hi rend="italic">Thames</hi> in streams
                  majestic flows,</l>
               <l n="48">Or <hi rend="italic">Naiads</hi> in their oozy beds repose</l>
               <l n="50">While <hi rend="italic">Phoebus</hi> reigns above the starry train,</l>
               <l n="51">While bright <hi rend="italic">Aurora</hi> purples o'er the main,</l>
               <l n="52">So long, great Sir, the muse thy praise shall sing,</l>
               <l n="53">So long thy praise shall make <hi rend="italic">Parnassus</hi>
                  ring:</l>
               <l n="54">Then grant, <hi rend="italic">Maecenas</hi>, thy paternal rays,</l>
               <l n="55">Hear me propitious, and defend my lays.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <pb n="13" facs="images/WP-0013.jpg"/>
         <div type="poem" id="div.194">
            <head>ON VIRTUE.</head>

            <lg type="blank verse" id="LG1287">
               <l n="1">O Thou bright jewel in my aim I strive</l>
               <l n="2">To comprehend thee. Thine own words declare</l>
               <l n="3">Wisdom is higher than a fool can reach.</l>
               <l n="4">I cease to wonder, and no more attempt</l>
               <l n="5">Thine height t' explore, or fathom thy profound.</l>
               <l n="6">But, O my soul, sink not into despair,</l>
               <l n="7"><hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi> is near thee, and with gentle hand</l>
               <l n="8">Would now embrace thee, hovers o'er thine head.</l>
               <l n="9">Fain would the heav'n-born soul with her converse,</l>
               <l n="10">Then seek, then court her for her promis'd bliss.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="blank verse" id="LG1288">
               <l rend="indent" id="1">Auspicious queen, thine heav'nly pinions spread,</l>
               <l n="2">And lead celestial <hi rend="italic">Chastity</hi> along;</l>
               <l n="3">Lo! now her sacred retinue descends,</l>
               <l n="4">Array'd in glory from the orbs above.</l>
               <l n="5">Attend me, <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi>, thro' my youthful years!</l>
               <l n="6">O leave me not to the false joys of time!</l>
               <l n="7">But guide my steps to endless life and bliss.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="images/WP-0014.jpg"/>
               <l n="8"><hi rend="italic">Greatness</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Goodness</hi>,
                  say what I shall call thee,</l>
               <l n="9">To give an higher appellation still,</l>
               <l n="10">Teach me a better strain, a nobler lay,</l>
               <l n="1">O thou, enthron'd with Cherubs in the realms of day!</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <pb n="15" facs="images/WP-0015.jpg"/>
         <div type="poem" id="div.195">
            <head>TO THE UNIVERSITY OF CAMBRIDGE,<ref target="a001" corresp="n001"/> IN NEW-ENGLAND.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1289">
               <l n="1">WHILE an intrinsic ardor<ref target="a002" corresp="n002" xml:id="ardorA"/> prompts to write,</l>
               <l n="2">The muses<ref target="a003" corresp="n003" xml:id="museA"/> promise to assist my pen;</l>
               <l n="3">'Twas not long since I left my native shore</l>
               <l n="4">The land of errors, and <hi rend="italic">Egyptian</hi> gloom:<ref target="a004" corresp="n004" xml:id="egyptA"/></l>
               <l n="5">Father of mercy, 'twas thy gracious hand</l>
               <l n="6">Brought me in safety from those dark abodes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1290">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6488">Students, to you 'tis giv'n to scan the heights</l>
               <l n="7">Above, to traverse the ethereal space,</l>
               <l n="8">And mark the systems of revolving worlds.<ref target="a005" corresp="n005" xml:id="systemsA"/></l>
               <l n="9">Still more, ye sons of science ye receive</l>
               <l n="10">The blissful news by messengers from heav'n,</l>
               <l n="11">How <hi rend="italic">Jesus</hi>' blood for your redemption flows.</l>
               <l n="12">See him with hands out-stretcht upon the cross;</l>
               <l n="13">Immese compassion in his bosom glows;</l>
               <l n="14">He hears revilers, nor resents their scorn:</l>
               <l n="15">What matchless mercy in the Son of God!</l>
               <l n="16">When the whole human race by sin had fall'n,</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="WP-0016.jpg"/>
               <l n="17">He deign'd<ref target="a006" corresp="n006" xml:id="deignA"/> to die that they might rise again,</l>
               <l n="18">And share with him in the sublimest skies,</l>
               <l n="19">Life without death, and glory without end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1291">
               <l rend="indent" id="20">Improve your privileges while they stay,</l>
               <l n="21">Ye pupils, and each hour redeem, that bears</l>
               <l n="22">Or good or bad report of you to heav'n.</l>
               <l n="23">Let sin, that baneful evil to the soul,</l>
               <l n="24">By you be shunn'd, nor once remit your guard;</l>
               <l n="25">Suppress the deadly serpent in its egg.</l>
               <l n="26">Ye blooming plants of human race divine,</l>
               <l n="27">An <hi rend="italic">Ethiop</hi><ref target="a007" corresp="n007" xml:id="ethiopA"/> tells you 'tis
                  your greatest foe;</l>
               <l n="28">Its transient sweetness turns to endless pain,</l>
               <l n="29">And in immense perdition<ref target="a008" corresp="n008" xml:id="perditionA"/> sinks the soul.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.196">
            <pb n="17" facs="images/WP-0017.jpg"/>
            <head>To the KING's Most Excellent Majesty.</head>
            <opener>1768.</opener>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1292">
               <l n="1">YOUR subjects hope, dread Sire --</l>
               <l n="2">The crown upon your brows may flourish long,</l>
               <l n="3">And that your arm may in your God be strong!</l>
               <l n="4">O may your sceptre num'rous nations sway,</l>
               <l n="5">And all with love and readiness obey!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1293">
               <l rend="indent" id="6">But how shall we the <hi rend="italic">British</hi> king
                  reward!</l>
               <l n="7">Rule thou in peace, our father, and our lord!</l>
               <l n="8">Midst the remembrance of thy favours past,</l>
               <l n="9">The meanest peasants most admire the last.<note n="*" id="p17.n1">The
                     Repeal of the Stamp Act.</note></l>
               <l n="10">May <hi rend="italic">George</hi>, belov'd by all the nations
                  round,</l>
               <l n="11">Live with heav'ns choicest constant blessings crown'd!</l>
               <l n="12">Great God, direct, and guard him from on high</l>
               <l n="13">And from his head let ev'ry evil fly!</l>
               <l n="14">And may each clime with equal gladness see</l>
               <l n="15">A monarch's smile can set his subjects free!</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.197">

            <pb n="18" facs="WP-0018.jpg"/>
            <head>On being
               brought from AFRICA to AMERICA.<ref target="a009" corresp="n009" xml:id="broughtA"/></head>
            <lg type="heroic couplets"></lg>
            <l n="1">'TWAS mercy brought me from my <hi rend="italic">Pagan</hi> land,</l>
            <l n="2">Taught my benighted soul to understand</l>
            <l n="3">That there's a God, that there's a <hi rend="italic">Saviour</hi> too:</l>
            <l n="4">Once I redemption neither sought nor knew.</l>
            <l n="5">Some
               view<ref target="a010" corresp="n010" xml:id="viewA"/> our sable race with scornful eye,</l>
            <l n="6">"Their colour is a diabolic die."</l>
            <l n="7">Remember, <hi rend="italic">Christians</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
               >Negros</hi>, black
                  as <hi rend="italic">Cain</hi>,<ref target="a011" corresp="n011" xml:id="cainA"/></l>
            <l n="8">May be refin'd, and join th' angelic train.</l>


         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.198">
            <pb n="19" facs="images/WP-0019.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of the Rev. DR. SEWELL.</head>
            <opener>1769.</opener>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1294">
               <l n="1">ERE yet the morn its lovely blushes spread,</l>
               <l n="2">See <hi rend="italic">Sewell</hi> number'd with the happy dead.</l>
               <l n="3">Hail, holy man, arriv'd th' immortal shore,</l>
               <l n="4">Though we shall hear thy warning voice no more.</l>
               <l n="5">Come, let us all behold with wishful eyes</l>
               <l n="6">The saint ascending to his native skies;</l>
               <l n="7">From hence the prophet wing'd his rapt'rous way</l>
               <l n="8">To the blest mansions in eternal day.</l>
               <l n="9">Then begging for the Spirit of our God,</l>
               <l n="10">And panting eager for the same abode,</l>
               <l n="11">Come, let us all with the same vigour rise,</l>
               <l n="12">And take a prospect of the blissful skies;</l>
               <l n="13">While on our minds <hi rend="italic">Christ's</hi> image is
                  imprest,</l>
               <l n="14">And the dear Saviour glows in ev'ry breast.</l>
               <l n="15">Thrice happy saint! to find thy heav'n at last,</l>
               <l n="16">What compensation for the evils past!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="20" facs="images/WP-0020.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1295">
               <l rend="indent" id="17">Great God, incomprehensible, unknown</l>
               <l n="18">By sense, we bow at thine exalted throne.</l>
               <l n="19">O, while we beg thine excellence to feel,</l>
               <l n="20">Thy sacred Spirit to our hearts reveal,</l>
               <l n="21">And give us of that mercy to partake,</l>
               <l n="22">Which thou hast promis'd for the <hi rend="italic">Saviour</hi>'s
                  sake!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1296">
               <l rend="indent" id="23">"<hi rend="italic">Sewell</hi> is dead." Swift-pinion'd
                     <hi rend="italic">Fame</hi> thus cry'd.</l>
               <l n="24">"Is <hi rend="italic">Sewell</hi> dead," my trembling tongue
                  reply'd,</l>
               <l n="25">O what a blessing in his flight deny'd!</l>
               <l n="26">How oft for us the holy prophet pray'd!</l>
               <l n="27">How oft to us the Word of Life convey'd!</l>
               <l n="28">By duty urg'd my mournful verse to close,</l>
               <l n="29">I for his tomb this epitaph compose.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1297">
               <l rend="indent" id="30">"Lo, here a man, redeem'd by <hi rend="italic"
                  >Jesus</hi>' blood,</l>
               <l n="31">"A sinner once, but now a saint with God;</l>
               <l n="32">"Behold ye rich, ye poor, ye fools, ye wise,</l>
               <l n="33">"Nor let his monument your heart surprize;</l>
               <l n="34">"'Twill tell you what this holy man has done,</l>
               <l n="35">"Which gives him brighter lustre than the sun.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="images/WP-0012.jpg"/>
               <l n="36">"Listen, ye happy, from your seats above.</l>
               <l n="37">"I speak sincerely, while I speak and love,</l>
               <l n="38">"He sought the paths of piety and truth,</l>
               <l n="39">"By these made happy from his early youth!</l>
               <l n="40">"In blooming years that grace divine he felt,</l>
               <l n="41">"Which rescues sinners from the chains of guilt.</l>
               <l n="42">"Mourn him, ye indigent, whom he has fed,</l>
               <l n="43">"And henceforth seek, like him, for living bread;</l>
               <l n="44">"Ev'n <hi rend="italic">Christ</hi>, the bread descending from
                  above,</l>
               <l n="45">"And ask an int'rest in his saving love.</l>
               <l n="46">"Mourn him, ye youth, to whom he oft has told</l>
               <l n="47">"God's gracious wonders from the times of old.</l>
               <l n="48">"I, too have cause this mighty loss to mourn,</l>
               <l n="49">"For he my monitor will not return.</l>
               <l n="50">"O when shall we to his blest state arrive?</l>
               <l n="51">"When the same graces in our bosoms thrive."</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.199">
            <pb n="22" facs="images/WP-0022.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of the Rev. MR. GEORGE WHITEFIELD.</head>
            <opener>1770.</opener>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1298">
               <l n="1">HAIL, happy saint, on thine immortal throne,</l>
               <l n="2">Possest of glory, life, and bliss unknown;</l>
               <l n="3">We hear no more the music of thy tongue,</l>
               <l n="4">Thy wonted auditories cease to throng.</l>
               <l n="5">Thy sermons in unequall'd accents flow'd,</l>
               <l n="6">And ev'ry bosom with devotion glow'd;</l>
               <l n="7">Thou didst in strains of eloquence refin'd</l>
               <l n="8">Inflame the heart, and captivate the mind.</l>
               <l n="9">Unhappy we the setting sun deplore,</l>
               <l n="10">So glorious once, but ah! it shines no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1299">
               <l rend="indent" n="11">Behold the prophet in his tow'ring flight!</l>
               <l n="12">He leaves the earth for heav'n's unmeasur'd height,</l>
               <l n="13">And worlds unknown receive him from our sight.</l>
               <l n="14">There <hi rend="italic">Whitefield</hi> wings with rapid course his
                  way,</l>
               <l n="15">And sails to <hi rend="italic">Zion</hi> through vast seas of day.</l>
               <l n="16">Thy pray'rs, great saint, and thine incessant cries</l>
               <l n="17">Have pierc'd the bosom of thy native skies.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="images/WP-0023.jpg"/>
               <l n="18">Thou moon hast seen, and all the stars of light,</l>
               <l n="19">How he has wrestled with his God by night.</l>
               <l n="20">He pray'd that grace in ev'ry heart might dwell,</l>
               <l n="21">He long'd to see <hi rend="italic">America</hi> excel;</l>
               <l n="22">He charg'd its youth that ev'ry grace divine</l>
               <l n="23">Should with full lustre in their conduct shine;</l>
               <l n="24">That Saviour, which his soul did first receive,</l>
               <l n="25">The greatest gift that ev'n a God can give,</l>
               <l n="26">He freely offer'd to the num'rous throng,</l>
               <l n="27">That on his lips with list'ning pleasure hung.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1300">
               <l rend="indent" n="28">"Take him, ye wretched, for your only good,</l>
               <l n="29">"Take him ye starving sinners, for your food;</l>
               <l n="30">"Ye thirsty, come to this life-giving stream,</l>
               <l n="31">"Ye preachers, take him for your joyful theme;</l>
               <l n="32">"Take him my dear <hi rend="italic">Americans</hi>, he said,</l>
               <l n="33">"Be your complaints on his kind bosom laid:</l>
               <l n="34">"Take him, ye <hi rend="italic">Africans</hi>, he longs for you,</l>
               <l n="35">"<hi rend="italic">Impartial Saviour</hi> is his title due:</l>
               <l n="36">"Wash'd in the fountain of redeeming blood,</l>
               <l n="37">"You shall be sons, and kings, and priests to God."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1301">
               <pb n="24" facs="images/WP-0024.jpg"/>
               <l rend="indent" n="38">Great <hi rend="italic">Countess</hi>,<note n="*"
                     id="p24.n1">The Countess of <hi rend="italic">Huntingdon</hi>, to whom Mr. <hi
                        rend="italic">Whitefield</hi> was Chaplain.</note> we <hi rend="italic"
                     >Americans</hi> revere</l>
               <l n="39">Thy name, and mingle in thy grief sincere;</l>
               <l n="40"><hi rend="italic">New England</hi> deeply feels, the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Orphans</hi> mourn,</l>
               <l n="41">Their more than father will no more return.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1302">
               <l rend="indent" n="42">But, though arrested by the hand of death,</l>
               <l n="43"><hi rend="italic">Whitefield</hi> no more exerts his lab'ring
                  breath,</l>
               <l n="44">Yet let us view him in th' eternal skies,</l>
               <l n="45">Let ev'ry heart to this bright vision rise;</l>
               <l n="46">While the tomb safe retains its sacred trust,</l>
               <l n="47">Till life divine re-animates his dust.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.200">

            <pb n="25" facs="images/WP-0025.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of a young Lady of Five Years of Age.</head>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1303">
               <l n="1">FROM dark abodes to fair etherial light</l>
               <l n="2">Th' enraptur'd innocent has wing'd her flight;</l>
               <l n="3">On the kind bosom of eternal love</l>
               <l n="4">She finds unknown beatitude above.</l>
               <l n="5">This know, ye parents, nor her loss deplore,</l>
               <l n="6">She feels the iron hand of pain no more;</l>
               <l n="7">The dispensations of unerring grace,</l>
               <l n="8">Should turn your sorrows into grateful praise;</l>
               <l n="9">Let then no tears for her henceforward flow,</l>
               <l n="10">No more distress'd in our dark vale below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1304">
               <l rend="indent" n="11">Her morning sun, which rose divinely bright,</l>
               <l n="12">Was quickly mantled with the gloom of night;</l>
               <l n="13">But hear in heav'n's blest bow'rs your <hi rend="italic">Nancy</hi>
                  fair,</l>
               <l n="14">And learn to imitate her language there.</l>
               <l n="15">"Thou, Lord, whom I behold with glory crown'd,</l>
               <l n="16">"By what sweet name, and in what tuneful sound</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="images/WP-0026.jpg"/>
               <l n="17">"Wilt thou be prais'd? Seraphic pow'rs are faint</l>
               <l n="18">"Infinite love and majesty to paint.</l>
               <l n="19">"To thee let all their graceful voices raise,</l>
               <l n="20">"And saints and angels join their songs of praise."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1305">
               <l rend="indent" n="21">Perfect in bliss she from her heav'nly home</l>
               <l n="22">Looks down, and smiling beckons you to come;</l>
               <l n="23">Why then, fond parents, why these fruitless groans?</l>
               <l n="24">Restrain your tears, and cease your plaintive moans.</l>
               <l n="25">Freed from a world of sin, and snares, and pain,</l>
               <l n="26">Why would you wish your daughter back again?</l>
               <l n="27">No -- bow resign'd. Let hope your grief control,</l>
               <l n="28">And check the rising tumult of the soul.</l>
               <l n="29">Calm in the prosperous, and adverse day,</l>
               <l n="30">Adore the God who gives and takes away;</l>
               <l n="31">Eye him in all, his holy name revere,</l>
               <l n="32">Upright your actions, and your hearts sincere,</l>
               <l n="33">Till having sail'd through life's tempestuous sea,</l>
               <l n="34">And from its rocks, and boist'rous billows free,</l>
               <l n="35">Yourselves, safe landed on the blissful shore,</l>
               <l n="L6668">Shall join your happy babe to part no more.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.201">
            <pb n="27" facs="images/WP-0027.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of a young Gentleman.</head>

            <l n="1">WHO taught thee conflict with the pow'rs of night,</l>
            <l n="2">To vanquish Satan in the fields of fight?</l>
            <l n="3">Who strung thy feeble arms with might unknown,</l>
            <l n="4">How great thy conquest, and how bright thy crown!</l>
            <l n="5">War with each princedom, throne, and pow'r is o'er,</l>
            <l n="6">The scene is ended to return no more.</l>
            <l n="7">O could my muse thy seat on high behold,</l>
            <l n="8">How deckt with laurel, how enrich'd with gold!</l>
            <l n="9">O could she hear what praise thine harp employs,</l>
            <l n="10">How sweet thine anthems, how divine thy joys!</l>
            <l n="11">What heav'nly grandeur should exalt her strain!</l>
            <l n="12">What holy raptures in her numbers reign!</l>
            <l n="13">To sooth the troubles of the mind to peace,</l>
            <l n="14">To still the tumult of life's tossing seas,</l>
            <pb n="28" facs="images/WP-0028.jpg"/>
            <l n="15">To ease the anguish of the parents heart,</l>
            <l n="16">What shall my sympathizing verse impart?</l>
            <l n="17">Where is the balm to heal so deep a wound?</l>
            <l n="18">Where shall a sov'reign remedy be found?</l>
            <l n="19">Look, gracious Spirit, from thine heav'nly bow'r,</l>
            <l n="20">And thy full joys into their bosoms pour;</l>
            <l n="21">The raging tempest of their grief control,</l>
            <l n="22">And spread the dawn of glory through the soul,</l>
            <l n="23">To eye the path the saint departed trod,</l>
            <l n="24">And trace him to the bosom of his God.</l>


         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.202">
            <pb n="29" facs="images/WP-0029.jpg"/>
            <head>To a Lady on the Death of her Husband.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1306">
               <l n="L6693">GRIM monarch! see, depriv'd of vital breath,</l>
               <l n="L6694">A young physician in the dust of death:</l>
               <l n="L6695">Dost thou go on incessant to destroy,</l>
               <l n="L6696">Our griefs to double, and lay waste our joy?</l>
               <l n="L6697"><hi rend="italic">Enough</hi> thou never yet wast known to say,</l>
               <l n="L6698">Though millions die, the vassals of thy sway:</l>
               <l n="L6699">Nor youth, nor science, nor the ties of love,</l>
               <l n="L6700">Nor aught on earth thy flinty heart can move.</l>
               <l n="L6701">The friend, the spouse from his dire dart to save,</l>
               <l n="L6702">In vain we ask the sovereign of the grave.</l>
               <l n="L6703">Fair mourner, there see thy lov'd <hi rend="italic">Leonard</hi>
                  laid,</l>
               <l n="L6704">And o'er him spread the deep impervious shade;</l>
               <l n="L6705">Clos'd are his eyes, and heavy fetters keep</l>
               <l n="L6706">His senses bound in never-waking sleep,</l>
               <l n="L6707">Till time shall cease, till many a starry world</l>
               <l n="L6708">Shall fall from heav'n, in dire confusion hurl'd,</l>
               <l n="L6709">Till nature in her final wreck shall lie,</l>
               <l n="L6710">And her last groan shall rend the azure sky:</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="images/WP-0030.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6711">Not, not till then his active soul shall claim</l>
               <l n="L6712">His body, a divine immortal frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1307">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6713">But see the softly-stealing tears apace</l>
               <l n="L6714">Pursue each other down the mourner's face;</l>
               <l n="L6715">But cease thy tears, bid ev'ry sigh depart,</l>
               <l n="L6716">And cast the load of anguish from thine heart:</l>
               <l n="L6717">From the cold shell of his great soul arise,</l>
               <l n="L6718">And look beyond, thou native of the skies;</l>
               <l n="L6719">There fix thy view, where fleeter than the wind</l>
               <l n="L6720">Thy <hi rend="italic">Leonard</hi> mounts, and leaves the earth
                  behind.</l>
               <l n="L6721">Thyself prepare to pass the vale of night</l>
               <l n="L6722">To join for ever on the hills of light:</l>
               <l n="L6723">To thine embrace this joyful spirit moves</l>
               <l n="L6724">To thee, the partner of his earthly loves;</l>
               <l n="L6725">He welcomes thee to pleasures more refin'd,</l>
               <l n="L6726">And better suited to th' immortal mind.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.203">
            <pb n="31" facs="images/WP-0031.jpg"/>
            <head>GOLIATH OF GATH.</head>
            <opener>I SAM. Chap. xvii.</opener>



            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1308">
               <l n="L6727">YE martial pow'rs, and all ye tuneful nine,</l>
               <l n="L6728">Inspire my song, and aid my high design.</l>
               <l n="L6729">The dreadful scenes and toils of war I write,</l>
               <l n="L6730">The ardent warriors, and the fields of fight:</l>
               <l n="L6731">You best remember, and you best can sing</l>
               <l n="L6732">The acts of heroes to the vocal string:</l>
               <l n="L6733">Resume the lays with which your sacred lyre,</l>
               <l n="L6734">Did then the poet and the sage inspire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1309">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6735">Now front to front the armies were display'd,</l>
               <l n="L6736">Here <hi rend="italic">Israel</hi> rang'd, and there the foes
                  array'd;</l>
               <l n="L6737">The hosts on two opposing mountains stood,</l>
               <l n="L6738">Thick as the foliage of the waving wood;</l>
               <l n="L6739">Between them an extensive valley lay,</l>
               <l n="L6740">O'er which the gleaming armour pour'd the day,</l>
               <l n="L6741">When from the camp of the <hi rend="italic">Philistine</hi> foes,</l>
               <l n="L6742">Dreadful to view, a mighty warrior rose;</l>
               <l n="L6743">In the dire deeds of bleeding battle skill'd,</l>
               <l n="L6744">The monster stalks the terror of the field.</l>
               <pb n="32 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0032c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6745">From <hi rend="italic">Gath</hi> he sprung, <hi rend="italic"
                     >Goliath</hi> was his name,</l>
               <l n="L6746">Of fierce deportment, and gigantic frame:</l>
               <l n="L6747">A brazen helmet on his head was plac'd,</l>
               <l n="L6748">A coat of mail his form terrific grac'd,</l>
               <l n="L6749">The greaves his legs, the targe his shoulders prest:</l>
               <l n="L6750">Dreadful in arms high-tow'ring o'er the rest</l>
               <l n="L6751">A spear he proudly wav'd, whose iron head,</l>
               <l n="L6752">Strange to relate, six hundred shekels weigh'd;</l>
               <l n="L6753">He strode along, and shook the ample field,</l>
               <l n="L6754">While <hi rend="italic">Phoebus</hi> blaz'd refulgent on his
                  shield:</l>
               <l n="L6755">Through <hi rend="italic">Jacob's</hi> race a chilling horror ran,</l>
               <l n="L6756">When thus the huge, enormous chief began:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1310">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6757">"Say, what the cause that in this proud array</l>
               <l n="L6758">"You set your battle in the face of day?</l>
               <l n="L6759">"One hero find in all your vaunting train,</l>
               <l n="L6760">"Then see who loses, and who wins the plain;</l>
               <l n="L6761">"For he who wins, in triumph may demand</l>
               <l n="L6762">"Perpetual service from the vanquish'd land:</l>
               <l n="L6763">"Your armies I defy, your force despise,</l>
               <l n="L6764">"By far inferior in <hi rend="italic">Philistia's</hi> eyes:</l>
               <pb n="33 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0033c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6765">"Produce a man, and let us try the fight,</l>
               <l n="L6766">"Decide the contest, and the victor's right."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1311">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6767">Thus challeng'd he: all <hi rend="italic">Israel</hi>
                  stood amaz'd,</l>
               <l n="L6768">And ev'ry chief in consternation gaz'd;</l>
               <l n="L6769">But <hi rend="italic">Jesse's</hi> son in youthful bloom appears,</l>
               <l n="L6770">And warlike courage far beyond his years:</l>
               <l n="L6771">He left the folds, he left the flow'ry meads,</l>
               <l n="L6772">And soft recesses of the sylvan shades.</l>
               <l n="L6773">Now <hi rend="italic">Israel's</hi> monarch, and his troops arise,</l>
               <l n="L6774">With peals of shouts ascending to the skies;</l>
               <l n="L6775">In <hi rend="italic">Elah's</hi> vale the scene of combat lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1312">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6776">When the fair morning blush'd with orient red,</l>
               <l n="L6777">What <hi rend="italic">David's</hi> sire enjoin'd the son obey'd,</l>
               <l n="L6778">And swift of foot towards the trench he came,</l>
               <l n="L6779">Where glow'd each bosom with the martial flame.</l>
               <l n="L6780">He leaves his carriage to another's care,</l>
               <l n="L6781">And runs to greet his brethren of the war.</l>
               <l n="L6782">While yet they spake the giant-chief arose,</l>
               <l n="L6783">Repeats the challenge, and insults his foes:</l>
               <pb n="34 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0034c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6784">Struck with the sound, and trembling at the view,</l>
               <l n="L6785">Affrighted <hi rend="italic">Israel</hi> from its post withdrew.</l>
               <l n="L6786">"Observe ye this tremendous foe, they cry'd,</l>
               <l n="L6787">"Who in proud vaunts our armies hath defy'd:</l>
               <l n="L6788">"Whoever lays him prostrate on the plain,</l>
               <l n="L6789">"Freedom in <hi rend="italic">Israel</hi> for his house shall gain;</l>
               <l n="L6790">"And on him wealth unknown the king will pour,</l>
               <l n="L6791">"And give his royal daughter for his dow'r."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1313">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6792">Then <hi rend="italic">Jesse's</hi> youngest hope: "My
                  brethren say,</l>
               <l n="L6793">"What shall be done for him who takes away</l>
               <l n="L6794">"Reproach from <hi rend="italic">Jacob</hi>, who destroys the
                  chief,</l>
               <l n="L6795">"And puts a period to his country's grief.</l>
               <l n="L6796">"He vaunts the honours of his arms abroad,</l>
               <l n="L6797">"And scorns the armies of the living God."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1314">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6798">Thus spoke the youth, th' attentive people ey'd</l>
               <l n="L6799">The wond'rous hero, and again reply'd:</l>
               <l n="L6800">"Such the rewards our monarch will bestow,</l>
               <l n="L6801">"On him who conquers, and destroys his foe."</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="35 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0035c2.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1315">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6802"><hi rend="italic">Eliab</hi> heard, and kindled into
                  ire</l>
               <l n="L6803">To hear his shepherd-brother thus inquire,</l>
               <l n="L6804">And thus begun? "What errand brought thee? say</l>
               <l n="L6805">"Who keeps thy flock? or does it go astray?</l>
               <l n="L6806">"I know the base ambition of thine heart,</l>
               <l n="L6807">"But back in safety from the field depart."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1316">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6808"><hi rend="italic">Eliab</hi> thus to <hi rend="italic"
                     >Jesse's</hi> youngest heir,</l>
               <l n="L6809">Express'd his wrath in accents most severe.</l>
               <l n="L6810">When to his brother mildly he reply'd,</l>
               <l n="L6811">"What have I done? or what the cause to chide?"</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1317">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6812">The words were told before the king, who sent</l>
               <l n="L6813">For the young hero to his royal tent:</l>
               <l n="L6814">Before the monarch dauntless he began,</l>
               <l n="L6815">"For this <hi rend="italic">Philistine</hi> fail no heart of man:</l>
               <l n="L6816">"I'll take the vale, and with the giant fight:</l>
               <l n="L6817">"I dread not all his boasts, nor all his might."</l>
               <pb n="36 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0036c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6818">When thus the king: "Dar'st thou a stripling go,</l>
               <l n="L6819">"And venture combat with so great a foe?</l>
               <l n="L6820">"Who all his days has been inur'd to fight,</l>
               <l n="L6821">"And made its deeds his study and delight:</l>
               <l n="L6822">"Battles and bloodshed brought the monster forth,</l>
               <l n="L6823">"And clouds and whirlwinds usher'd in his birth."</l>
               <l n="L6824">When <hi rend="italic">David</hi> thus: "I kept the fleecy care,</l>
               <l n="L6825">"And out there rush'd a lion and a bear;</l>
               <l n="L6826">"A tender lamb the hungry lion took,</l>
               <l n="L6827">"And with no other weapon than my crook</l>
               <l n="L6828">"Bold I pursu'd, and chas'd him o'er the field,</l>
               <l n="L6829">"The prey deliver'd, and the felon kill'd:</l>
               <l n="L6830">"As thus the lion and the bear I slew,</l>
               <l n="L6831">"So shall <hi rend="italic">Goliath</hi> fall, and all his crew:</l>
               <l n="L6832">"The God, who sav'd me from these beasts of prey,</l>
               <l n="L6833">"By me this monster in the dust shall lay."</l>
               <l n="L6834">So <hi rend="italic">David</hi> spoke. The wond'ring king reply'd;</l>
               <l n="L6835">"Go thou with heav'n and victory on thy side:</l>
               <l n="L6836">"This coat of mail, this sword gird on," he said,</l>
               <l n="L6837">And plac'd a mighty helmet on his head:</l>
               <pb n="37 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0037c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6838">The coat, the sword, the helm he laid aside,</l>
               <l n="L6839">Nor chose to venture with those arms untry'd,</l>
               <l n="L6840">Then took his staff, and to the neighb'ring brook</l>
               <l n="L6841">Instant he ran, and thence five pebbles took.</l>
               <l n="L6842">Mean time descended to <hi rend="italic">Philistia's</hi> son</l>
               <l n="L6843">A radiant cherub, and he thus begun:</l>
               <l n="L6844">"Goliath, well thou know'st thou hast defy'd</l>
               <l n="L6845">"Yon Hebrew armies, and their God deny'd:</l>
               <l n="L6846">"Rebellious wretch! audacious worm! forbear,</l>
               <l n="L6847">"Nor tempt the vengeance of their God too far:</l>
               <l n="L6848">"Them, who with his omnipotence contend,</l>
               <l n="L6849">"No eye shall pity, and no arm defend:</l>
               <l n="L6850">"Proud as thou art, in short liv'd glory great,</l>
               <l n="L6851">"I come to tell thee thine approaching fate.</l>
               <l n="L6852">"Regard my words. The judge of all the gods,</l>
               <l n="L6853">"Beneath whose steps the tow'ring mountain nods,</l>
               <l n="L6854">"Will give thine armies to the savage brood,</l>
               <l n="L6855">"That cut the liquid air, or range the wood.</l>
               <l n="L6856">"Thee too a well-aim'd pebble shall destroy,</l>
               <l n="L6857">"And thou shalt perish by a beardless boy:</l>
               <pb n="38 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0038c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6858">"Such is the mandate from the realms above,</l>
               <l n="L6859">"And should I try the vengeance to remove,</l>
               <l n="L6860">"Myself a rebel to my king would prove.</l>
               <l n="L6861">"<hi rend="italic">Goliath</hi> say, shall grace to him be shown,</l>
               <l n="L6862">"Who dares heav'ns monarch, and insults his throne?"</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1318">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6863">"Your words are lost on me," the giant cries,</l>
               <l n="L6864">While fear and wrath contended in his eyes,</l>
               <l n="L6865">When thus the messenger from heav'n replies:</l>
               <l n="L6866">"Provoke no more <hi rend="italic">Jehovah's</hi> awful hand</l>
               <l n="L6867">"To hurl its vengeance on thy guilty land:</l>
               <l n="L6868">"He grasps the thunder, and, he wings the storm,</l>
               <l n="L6869">"Servants their sov'reign's orders to perform."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1319">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6870">The angel spoke, and turn'd his eyes away,</l>
               <l n="L6871">Adding new radiance to the rising day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1320">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6872">Now <hi rend="italic">David</hi> comes: the fatal stones
                  demand</l>
               <l n="L6873">His left, the staff engag'd his better hand</l>
               <pb n="39 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0039c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6874">The giant mov'd, and from his tow'ring height</l>
               <l n="L6875">Survey'd the stripling, and disdain'd the fight,</l>
               <l n="L6876">And thus began: "Am I a dog with thee?</l>
               <l n="L6877">"Bring'st thou no armour, but a staff to me?</l>
               <l n="L6878">"The gods on thee their vollied curses pour,</l>
               <l n="L6879">"And beasts and birds of prey thy flesh devour."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1321">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6880"><hi rend="italic">David</hi> undaunted thus, "Thy spear
                  and shield</l>
               <l n="L6881">"Shall no protection to thy body yield:</l>
               <l n="L6882">"<hi rend="italic">Jehovah's</hi> name -- no other arms I bear,</l>
               <l n="L6883">"I ask no other in this glorious war.</l>
               <l n="L6884">"To-day the Lord of Hosts to me will give</l>
               <l n="L6885">"Vict'ry, to-day thy doom thou shalt receive;</l>
               <l n="L6886">"The fate you threaten shall your own become,</l>
               <l n="L6887">"And beasts shall be your animated tomb,</l>
               <l n="L6888">"That all the earth's inhabitants may know</l>
               <l n="L6889">"That there's a God, who governs all below</l>
               <l n="L6890">"This great assembly too shall witness stand,</l>
               <l n="L6891">"That needs nor sword, nor spear, th' Almighty's hand:</l>
               <pb n="40 [copy 2]" facs="images/WP-0040c2.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6892">"The battle his, the conquest he bestows,</l>
               <l n="L6893">"And to our pow'r consigns our hated foes."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1322">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6894">Thus <hi rend="italic">David</hi> spoke; <hi
                     rend="italic">Goliath</hi> heard and came</l>
               <l n="L6895">To meet the hero in the field of fame.</l>
               <l n="L6896">Ah! fatal meeting to thy troops and thee,</l>
               <l n="L6897">But thou wast deaf to the divine decree;</l>
               <l n="L6898">Young <hi rend="italic">David</hi> meets thee, meets thee not in
                  vain;</l>
               <l n="L6899">'Tis thine to perish on th' ensanguin'd plain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1323">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6900">And now the youth the forceful pebble slung</l>
               <l n="L6901"><hi rend="italic">Philistia</hi> trembled as it whizz'd along:</l>
               <l n="L6902">In his dread forehead, where the helmet ends,</l>
               <l n="L6903">Just o'er the brows the well-aim'd stone descends,</l>
               <l n="L6904">It pierc'd the skull, and shatter'd all the brain,</l>
               <l n="L6905">Prone on his face he tumbled to the plain:</l>
               <l n="L6906"><hi rend="italic">Goliath's</hi> fall no smaller terror yields</l>
               <l n="L6907">Than riving thunders in aerial fields:</l>
               <l n="L6908">The soul still ling'red in its lov'd abode,</l>
               <l n="L6909">Till conq'ring <hi rend="italic">David</hi> o'er the giant strode:</l>
               <l n="L6910"><hi rend="italic">Goliath's</hi> sword then laid its master dead,</l>
               <l n="L6911">And from the body hew'd the ghastly head;</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="images/WP-0041.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6912">The blood in gushing torrents drench'd the plains,</l>
               <l n="L6913">The soul found passage through the spouting veins.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1324">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6914">And now aloud th' illustrious victor said,</l>
               <l n="L6915">"Where are your boastings now your champion's dead?"</l>
               <l n="L6916">Scarce had he spoke, when the <hi rend="italic">Philistines</hi>
                  fled:</l>
               <l n="L6917">But fled in vain; the conqu'ror swift pursu'd:</l>
               <l n="L6918">What scenes of slaughter! and what seas of blood!</l>
               <l n="L6919">There <hi rend="italic">Saul</hi> thy thousands grasp'd th' impurpled
                  sand</l>
               <l n="L6920">In pangs of death the conquest of thine hand;</l>
               <l n="L6921">And <hi rend="italic">David</hi> there were thy ten thousands laid:</l>
               <l n="L6922">Thus <hi rend="italic">Israel's</hi> damsels musically play'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1325">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6923">Near <hi rend="italic">Gath</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                     >Ekron</hi> many an hero lay,</l>
               <l n="L6924">Breath'd out their souls, and curs'd the light of day:</l>
               <l n="L6925">Their fury, quench'd by death, no longer burns,</l>
               <l n="L6926">And <hi rend="italic">David</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Goliath's</hi>
                  head returns,</l>
               <l n="L6927">To <hi rend="italic">Salem</hi> brought, but in his tent he plac'd</l>
               <l n="L6928">The load of armour which the giant grac'd.</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="images/WP-0042.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6929">His monarch saw him coming from the war,</l>
               <l n="L6930">And thus demanded of the son of <hi rend="italic">Ner</hi>.</l>
               <l n="L6931">"Say, who is this amazing youth?" he cry'd,</l>
               <l n="L6932">When thus the leader of the host reply'd;</l>
               <l n="L6933">"As lives thy soul I know not whence he sprung,</l>
               <l n="L6934">"So great in prowess though in years so young:"</l>
               <l n="L6935">"Inquire whose son is he," the sov'reign said,</l>
               <l n="L6936">"Before whose conq'ring arm <hi rend="italic">Philistia</hi> fled."</l>
               <l n="L6937">Before the king behold the stripling stand,</l>
               <l n="L6938"><hi rend="italic">Goliath</hi>'s head depending from his hand:</l>
               <l n="L6939">To him the king: "Say of what martial line</l>
               <l n="L6940">"Art thou, young hero, and what sire was thine?"</l>
               <l n="L6941">He humbly thus; "the son of <hi rend="italic">Jesse</hi> I:</l>
               <l n="L6942">"I came the glories of the field to try.</l>
               <l n="L6943">"Small is my tribe, but valiant in the fight;</l>
               <l n="L6944">"Small is my city, but thy royal right."</l>
               <l n="L6945">"Then take the promis'd gifts," the monarch cry'd,</l>
               <l n="L6946">Conferring riches and the royal bride:</l>
               <l n="L6947">"Knit to my soul for ever thou remain</l>
               <l n="L6948">"With me, nor quit my regal roof again."</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.204">
            <pb n="43" facs="images/WP-0043.jpg"/>
            <head>Thoughts on the WORKS of PROVIDENCE.</head>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1326">
               <l n="L6949">ARISE, my soul, on wings enraptur'd, rise</l>
               <l n="L6950">To praise the monarch of the earth and skies,</l>
               <l n="L6951">Whose goodness and beneficence appear</l>
               <l n="L6952">As round its centre moves the rolling year,</l>
               <l n="L6953">Or when the morning glows with rosy charms,</l>
               <l n="L6954">Or the sun slumbers in the ocean's arms:</l>
               <l n="L6955">Of light divine be a rich portion lent</l>
               <l n="L6956">To guide my soul, and favour my intent.</l>
               <l n="L6957">Celestial muse, my arduous flight sustain,</l>
               <l n="L6958">And raise my mind to a seraphic strain!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1327">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6959">Ador'd for ever be the God unseen,</l>
               <l n="L6960">Which round the sun revolves this vast machine,</l>
               <l n="L6961">Though to his eye its mass a point appears:</l>
               <l n="L6962">Ador'd the God that whirls surrounding spheres,</l>
               <l n="L6963">Which first ordain'd that mighty <hi rend="italic">Sol</hi> should
                  reign</l>
               <l n="L6964">The peerless monarch of th' ethereal train:</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="images/WP-0044.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6965">Of miles twice forty millions is his height,</l>
               <l n="L6966">And yet his radiance dazzles mortal sight</l>
               <l n="L6967">So far beneath -- from him th' extended earth</l>
               <l n="L6968">Vigour derives, and ev'ry flow'ry birth:</l>
               <l n="L6969">Vast through her orb she moves with easy grace</l>
               <l n="L6970">Around her <hi rend="italic">Phoebus</hi> in unbounded space;</l>
               <l n="L6971">True to her course th' impetuous storm derides,</l>
               <l n="L6972">Triumphant o'er the winds, and surging tides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1328">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6973">Almighty, in these wond'rous works of thine,</l>
               <l n="L6974">What <hi rend="italic">Pow'r</hi>, what <hi rend="italic">Wisdom</hi>,
                  and what <hi rend="italic"><CORR SIC="Goodness">Goodnes</CORR></hi> shine?</l>
               <l n="L6975">And are thy wonders, Lord, by men explor'd,</l>
               <l n="L6976">And yet creating glory unador'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1329">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6977">Creation smiles in various beauty gay,</l>
               <l n="L6978">While day to night, and night succeeds to day:</l>
               <l n="L6979">That <hi rend="italic">Wisdom</hi>, which attends <hi rend="italic"
                     >Jehovah's</hi> ways,</l>
               <l n="L6980">Shines most conspicuous in the solar rays:</l>
               <l n="L6981">Without them, destitute of heat and light,</l>
               <l n="L6982">This world would be the reign of endless night:</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="images/WP-0045.jpg"/>
               <l n="L6983">In their excess how would our race complain,</l>
               <l n="L6984">Abhorring life! how hate its length'ned chain!</l>
               <l n="L6985">From air adust what num'rous ills would rise?</l>
               <l n="L6986">What dire contagion taint the burning skies?</l>
               <l n="L6987">What pestilential vapours, fraught with death,</l>
               <l n="L6988">Would rise, and overspread the lands beneath?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1330">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6989">Hail, smiling morn, that from the orient main</l>
               <l n="L6990">Ascending dost adorn the heav'nly plain!</l>
               <l n="L6991">So rich, so various are thy beauteous dies,</l>
               <l n="L6992">That spread through all the circuit of the skies,</l>
               <l n="L6993">That, full of thee, my soul in rapture soars,</l>
               <l n="L6994">And thy great God, the cause of all adores.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1331">
               <l rend="indent" id="L6995">O'er beings infinite his love extends,</l>
               <l n="L6996">His <hi rend="italic">Wisdom</hi> rules them, and his <hi rend="italic"
                     >Pow'r</hi> defends.</l>
               <l n="L6997">When tasks diurnal tire the human frame,</l>
               <l n="L6998">The spirits faint, and dim the vital flame,</l>
               <l n="L6999">Then too that ever active bounty shines,</l>
               <l n="L7000">Which not infinity of space confines.</l>
               <l n="L7001">The sable veil, that <hi rend="italic">Night</hi> in silence draws,</l>
               <l n="L7002">Conceals effects, but shews th' <hi rend="italic">Almighty
                  Cause</hi>;</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="images/WP-0046.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7003">Night seals in sleep the wide creation fair,</l>
               <l n="L7004">And all is peaceful but the brow of care.</l>
               <l n="L7005">Again, gay <hi rend="italic">Phoebus</hi>, as the day before,</l>
               <l n="L7006">Wakes ev'ry eye, but what shall wake no more;</l>
               <l n="L7007">Again the face of nature is renew'd,</l>
               <l n="L7008">Which still appears harmonious, fair, and good.</l>
               <l n="L7009">May grateful strains salute the smiling morn,</l>
               <l n="L7010">Before its beams the eastern hills adorn!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1332">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7011">Shall day to day and night to night conspire</l>
               <l n="L7012">To show the goodness of the Almighty Sire?</l>
               <l n="L7013">This mental voice shall man regardless hear,</l>
               <l n="L7014">And never, never raise the filial pray'r?</l>
               <l n="L7015">To-day, O hearken, nor your folly mourn</l>
               <l n="L7016">For time mispent, that never will return.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1333">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7017">But see the sons of vegetation rise,</l>
               <l n="L7018">And spread their leafy banners to the skies.</l>
               <l n="L7019">All-wise Almighty Providence we trace</l>
               <l n="L7020">In trees, and plants, and all the flow'ry race;</l>
               <l n="L7021">As clear as in the nobler frame of man,</l>
               <l n="L7022">All lovely copies of the Maker's plan.</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="images/WP-0047.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7023">The pow'r the same that forms a ray of light,</l>
               <l n="L7024">That call'd creation from eternal night.</l>
               <l n="L7025">"Let there be light," he said: from his profound</l>
               <l n="L7026">Old <hi rend="italic">Chaos</hi> heard, and trembled at the sound:</l>
               <l n="L7027">Swift as the word, inspir'd by pow'r divine,</l>
               <l n="L7028">Behold the light around its maker shine,</l>
               <l n="L7029">The first fair product of th' omnific God,</l>
               <l n="L7030">And now through all his works diffus'd abroad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1334">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7031">As reason's pow'rs by day our God disclose,</l>
               <l n="L7032">So we may trace him in the night's repose:</l>
               <l n="L7033">Say what is sleep? and dreams how passing strange!</l>
               <l n="L7034">When action ceases, and ideas range</l>
               <l n="L7035">Licentious and unbounded o'er the plains,</l>
               <l n="L7036">Where <hi rend="italic">Fancy's</hi> queen in giddy triumph reigns.</l>
               <l n="L7037">Hear in soft strains the dreaming lover sigh</l>
               <l n="L7038">To a kind fair, or rave in jealousy;</l>
               <l n="L7039">On pleasure now, and now on vengeance bent,</l>
               <l n="L7040">The lab'ring passions struggle for a vent.</l>
               <l n="L7041">What pow'r, O man! thy <hi rend="italic">reason</hi> then restores,</l>
               <l n="L7042">So long suspended in nocturnal hours?</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="images/WP-0048.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7043">What secret hand returns the mental train,</l>
               <l n="L7044">And gives improv'd thine active pow'rs again?</l>
               <l n="L7045">From thee, O man, what gratitude should rise!</l>
               <l n="L7046">And, when from balmy sleep thou op'st thine eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7047">Let thy first thoughts be praises to the skies.</l>
               <l n="L7048">How merciful our God who thus imparts</l>
               <l n="L7049">O'erflowing tides of joy to human hearts,</l>
               <l n="L7050">When wants and woes might be our righteous lot,</l>
               <l n="L7051">Our God forgetting, by our God forgot!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1335">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7052">Among the mental pow'rs a question rose,</l>
               <l n="L7053">"What most the image of th' Eternal shows?"</l>
               <l n="L7054">When thus to <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> (so let <hi rend="italic"
                     >Fancy</hi> rove)</l>
               <l n="L7055">Her great companion spoke immortal <hi rend="italic">Love</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1336">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7056">"Say, mighty pow'r, how long shall strife prevail,</l>
               <l n="L7057">"And with its murmurs load the whisp'ring gale?</l>
               <l n="L7058">"Refer the cause to <hi rend="italic">Recollection's</hi> shrine,</l>
               <l n="L7059">"Who loud proclaims my origin divine,</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="images/WP-0049.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7060">"The cause whence heav'n and earth began to be,</l>
               <l n="L7061">"And is not man immortaliz'd by me?</l>
               <l n="L7062">"<hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> let this most causeless strife
                  subside."</l>
               <l n="L7063">Thus <hi rend="italic">Love</hi> pronounc'd, and <hi rend="italic"
                     >Reason</hi> thus reply'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1337">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7064">"Thy birth, celestial queen! 'tis mine to own,</l>
               <l n="L7065">"In thee resplendent is the Godhead shown;</l>
               <l n="L7066">"Thy words persuade, my soul enraptur'd feels</l>
               <l n="L7067">"Resistless beauty which thy smile reveals."</l>
               <l n="L7068">Ardent she spoke, and, kindling at her charms,</l>
               <l n="L7069">She clasp'd the blooming goddess in her arms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1338">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7070">Infinite <hi rend="italic">Love</hi> where'er we turn our
                  eyes</l>
               <l n="L7071">Appears: this ev'ry creature's wants supplies;</l>
               <l n="L7072">This most is heard in <hi rend="italic">Nature's</hi> constant
                  voice,</l>
               <l n="L7073">This makes the morn, and this the eve rejoice;</l>
               <l n="L7074">This bids the fost'ring rains and dews descend</l>
               <l n="L7075">To nourish all, to serve one gen'ral end,</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="images/WP-0050.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7076">The good of man: yet man ungrateful pays</l>
               <l n="L7077">But little homage, and but little praise.</l>
               <l n="L7078">To him, whose works array'd with mercy shine</l>
               <l n="L7079">What songs should rise, how constant, how divine!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.205">
            <pb n="51" facs="images/WP-0051.jpg"/>
            <head>To a Lady on the Death of Three Relations.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1339">
               <l n="L7080">WE trace the pow'r of Death from tomb to tomb,</l>
               <l n="L7081">And his are all the ages yet to come.</l>
               <l n="L7082">'Tis his to call the planets from on high,</l>
               <l n="L7083">To blacken <hi rend="italic">Phoebus</hi>, and dissolve the sky;</l>
               <l n="L7084">His too, when all in his dark realms are hurl'd,</l>
               <l n="L7085">From its firm base to shake the solid world;</l>
               <l n="L7086">His fatal sceptre rules the spacious whole,</l>
               <l n="L7087">And trembling nature rocks from pole to pole.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1340">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7088">Awful he moves, and wide his wings are spread:</l>
               <l n="L7089">Behold thy brother number'd with the dead!</l>
               <l n="L7090">From bondage freed, the exulting spirit flies</l>
               <l n="L7091">Beyond <hi rend="italic">Olympus</hi>, and these starry skies.</l>
               <l n="L7092">Lost in our woe for thee, blest shade, we mourn</l>
               <l n="L7093">In vain; to earth thou never must return.</l>
               <l n="L7094">Thy sisters too, fair mourner, feel the dart</l>
               <l n="L7095">Of Death, and with fresh torture rend thine heart.</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="images/WP-0052.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7096">Weep not for them, who wish thine happy mind</l>
               <l n="L7097">To rise with them, and leave the world behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1341">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7098">As a young plant by hurricanes up torn,</l>
               <l n="L7099">So near its parent lies the newly born --</l>
               <l n="L7100">But 'midst the bright ethereal train behold</l>
               <l n="L7101">It shines superior on a throne of gold:</l>
               <l n="L7102">Then, mourner, cease; let hope thy tears restrain,</l>
               <l n="L7103">Smile on the tomb, and sooth the raging pain.</l>
               <l n="L7104">On yon blest regions fix thy longing view,</l>
               <l n="L7105">Mindless of sublunary scenes below;</l>
               <l n="L7106">Ascend the sacred mount, in thought arise,</l>
               <l n="L7107">And seek substantial, and immortal joys;</l>
               <l n="L7108">Where hope receives, where faith to vision springs,</l>
               <l n="L7109">And raptur'd seraphs tune th' immortal strings</l>
               <l n="L7110">To strains extatic. Thou the chorus join,</l>
               <l n="L7111">And to thy father tune the praise divine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.206">
            <pb n="53" facs="images/WP-0053.jpg"/>
            <head>To a Clergyman on the Death of his Lady.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1342">
               <l n="L7112">WHERE contemplation finds her sacred spring,</l>
               <l n="L7113">Where heav'nly music makes the arches ring,</l>
               <l n="L7114">Where virtue reigns unsully'd and divine,</l>
               <l n="L7115">Where wisdom thron'd, and all the graces shine,</l>
               <l n="L7116">There sits thy spouse amidst the radiant throng,</l>
               <l n="L7117">While praise eternal warbles from her tongue;</l>
               <l n="L7118">There choirs angelic shout her welcome round,</l>
               <l n="L7119">With perfect bliss, and peerless glory crown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1343">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7120">While thy dear mate, to flesh no more confin'd,</l>
               <l n="L7121">Exults a blest, an heav'n-ascended mind,</l>
               <l n="L7122">Say in thy breast shall floods of sorrow rise?</l>
               <l n="L7123">Say shall its torrents overwhelm thine eyes?</l>
               <l n="L7124">Amid the seats of heav'n a place is free,</l>
               <l n="L7125">And angels ope their bright ranks for thee;</l>
               <l n="L7126">For thee they wait, and with expectant eye</l>
               <l n="L7127">Thy spouse leans downward from th' empyreal sky:</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="images/WP-0054.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7128">"O come away," her longing spirit cries,</l>
               <l n="L7129">"And share with me the raptures of the skies.</l>
               <l n="L7130">"Our bliss divine to mortals is unknown;</l>
               <l n="L7131">"Immortal life and glory are our own.</l>
               <l n="L7132">"There too may the dear pledges of our love</l>
               <l n="L7133">"Arrive, and taste with us the joys above;</l>
               <l n="L7134">"Attune the harp to more than mortal lays,</l>
               <l n="L7135">"And join with us the tribute of their praise</l>
               <l n="L7136">"To him, who dy'd stern justice to atone,</l>
               <l n="L7137">"And make eternal glory all our own.</l>
               <l n="L7138">"He in his death slew ours, and, as he rose,</l>
               <l n="L7139">"He crush'd the dire dominion of our foes;</l>
               <l n="L7140">"Vain were their hopes to put the God to flight,</l>
               <l n="L7141">"Chain us to hell, and bar the gates of light."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1344">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7142">She spoke, and turn'd from mortal scenes her eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7143">Which beam'd celestial radiance o'er the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1345">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7144">Then thou dear man, no more with grief retire,</l>
               <l n="L7145">Let grief no longer damp devotion's fire,</l>
               <l n="L7146">But rise sublime, to equal bliss aspire.</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="images/WP-0055.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7147">Thy sighs no more be wafted by the wind,</l>
               <l n="L7148">No more complain, but be to heav'n resign'd.</l>
               <l n="L7149">'Twas thine t' unfold the oracles divine,</l>
               <l n="L7150">To sooth our woes the task was also thine;</l>
               <l n="L7151">Now sorrow is incumbent on thy heart,</l>
               <l n="L7152">Permit the muse a cordial to impart;</l>
               <l n="L7153">Who can to thee their tend'rest aid refuse?</l>
               <l n="L7154">To dry thy tears how longs the heav'nly muse!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.207">
            <pb n="56" facs="images/WP-0056.jpg"/>
            <head>An HYMN to the MORNING.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1346">
               <l n="L7155">ATTEND my lays, ye ever honour'd nine,</l>
               <l n="L7156">Assist my labours, and my strains refine;</l>
               <l n="L7157">In smoothest numbers pour the notes along,</l>
               <l n="L7158">For bright <hi rend="italic">Aurora</hi> now demands my song.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1347">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7159"><hi rend="italic">Aurora</hi> hail, and all the thousands
                  dies,</l>
               <l n="L7160">Which deck thy progress through the vaulted skies:</l>
               <l n="L7161">The morn awakes, and wide extends her rays,</l>
               <l n="L7162">On ev'ry leaf the gentle zephyr plays;</l>
               <l n="L7163">Harmonious lays the feather'd race resume,</l>
               <l n="L7164">Dart the bright eye, and shake the painted plume.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1348">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7165">Ye shady groves, your verdant gloom display</l>
               <l n="L7166">To shield your poet from the burning day:</l>
               <l n="L7167"><hi rend="italic">Calliope</hi> awake the sacred lyre,</l>
               <l n="L7168">While thy fair sisters fan the pleasing fire:</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="images/WP-0057.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7169">The bow'rs, the gales, the variegated skies</l>
               <l n="L7170">In all their pleasures in my bosom rise.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1349">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7171">See in the east th' illustrious king of day!</l>
               <l n="L7172">His rising radiance drives the shades away --</l>
               <l n="L7173">But Oh! I feel his fervid beams too strong,</l>
               <l n="L7174">And scarce begun, concludes th' abortive song.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.208">
            <pb n="58" facs="images/WP-0058.jpg"/>
            <head>An HYMN to the EVENING.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1350">
               <l n="L7175">SOON as the sun forsook the eastern main</l>
               <l n="L7176">The pealing thunder shook the heav'nly plain;</l>
               <l n="L7177">Majestic grandeur! From the zephyr's wing,</l>
               <l n="L7178">Exhales the incense of the blooming spring.</l>
               <l n="L7179">Soft purl the streams, the birds renew their notes,</l>
               <l n="L7180">And through the air their mingled music floats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1351">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7181">Through all the heav'ns what beauteous dies are
                  spread!</l>
               <l n="L7182">But the west glories in the deepest red:</l>
               <l n="L7183">So may our breasts with ev'ry virtue glow,</l>
               <l n="L7184">The living temples of our God below!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1352">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7185">Fill'd with the praise of him who gives the light,</l>
               <l n="L7186">And draws the sable curtains of the night,</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="images/WP-0059.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7187">Let placid slumbers sooth each weary mind,</l>
               <l n="L7188">At morn to wake more heav'nly, more refin'd,</l>
               <l n="L7189">So shall the labours of the day begin</l>
               <l n="L7190">More pure, more guarded from the snares of sin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1353">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7191">Night's leaden sceptre seals my drowsy eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7192">Then cease, my song, till fair <hi rend="italic">Aurora</hi> rise.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.209">
            <pb n="60" facs="images/WP-0060.jpg"/>
            <head>ISAIAH lxiii. I-8.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1354">
               <l n="L7193">SAY, heav'nly muse, what king or mighty God,</l>
               <l n="L7194">That moves sublime from <hi rend="italic">Idumea's</hi> road?</l>
               <l n="L7195">In <hi rend="italic">Bozrah's</hi> dies, with martial glories
                  join'd,</l>
               <l n="L7196">His purple vesture waves upon the wind.</l>
               <l n="L7197">Why thus enrob'd delights he to appear</l>
               <l n="L7198">In the dread image of the <hi rend="italic">Pow'r</hi> of war?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1355">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7199">Compress'd in wrath the swelling wine-press groan'd,</l>
               <l n="L7200">It bled, and pour'd the gushing purple round.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1356">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7201">"Mine was the act," th' Almighty Saviour said,</l>
               <l n="L7202">And shook the dazzling glories of his head,</l>
               <l n="L7203">"When all forsook I trod the press alone,</l>
               <l n="L7204">"And conquer'd by omnipotence my own;</l>
               <l n="L7205">"For man's release sustain'd the pond'rous load,</l>
               <l n="L7206">"For man the wrath of an immortal God:</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="images/WP-0061.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7207">"To execute th' Eternal's dread command</l>
               <l n="L7208">"My soul I sacrific'd with willing hand;</l>
               <l n="L7209">"Sinless I stood before the avenging frown,</l>
               <l n="L7210">"Atoning thus for vices not my own."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1357">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7211">His eye the ample field of battle round</l>
               <l n="L7212">Survey'd, but no created succours found;</l>
               <l n="L7213">His own omnipotence sustain'd the fight,</l>
               <l n="L7214">His vengeance sunk the haughty foes in night;</l>
               <l n="L7215">Beneath his feet the prostrate troops were spread,</l>
               <l n="L7216">And round him lay the dying, and the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1358">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7217">Great God, what light'ning flashes from thine eyes?</l>
               <l n="L7218">What pow'r withstands if thou indignant rise?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1359">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7219">Against thy <hi rend="italic">Zion</hi> though her foes
                  may rage,</l>
               <l n="L7220">And all their cunning, all their strength engage,</l>
               <l n="L7221">Yet she serenely on thy bosom lies,</l>
               <l n="L7222">Smiles at their arts, and all their force defies.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.210">
            <pb n="62" facs="images/WP-0062.jpg"/>
            <head>On RECOLLECTION.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1360">
               <l n="L7223">MNEME begin. Inspire, ye sacred nine,</l>
               <l n="L7224">Your vent'rous <hi rend="italic">Afric</hi> in her great design.</l>
               <l n="L7225"><hi rend="italic">Mneme</hi>, immortal pow'r, I trace thy spring:</l>
               <l n="L7226">Assist my strains, while I thy glories sing:</l>
               <l n="L7227">The acts of long departed years, by thee</l>
               <l n="L7228">Recover'd, in due order rang'd we see:</l>
               <l n="L7229">Thy pow'r the long-forgotten calls from night,</l>
               <l n="L7230">That sweetly plays before the <hi rend="italic">fancy's</hi> sight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1361">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7231"><hi rend="italic">Mneme</hi> in our nocturnal visions
                  pours</l>
               <l n="L7232">The ample treasure of her secret stores;</l>
               <l n="L7233">Swift from above she wings her silent flight</l>
               <l n="L7234">Through <hi rend="italic">Phoebe's</hi> realms, fair regent of the
                  night;</l>
               <l n="L7235">And, in her pomp of images display'd,</l>
               <l n="L7236">To the high-raptur'd poet gives her aid,</l>
               <l n="L7237">Through the unbounded regions of the mind,</l>
               <l n="L7238">Diffusing light celestial and refin'd.</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="images/WP-0063.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7239">The heav'nly <hi rend="italic">phantom</hi> paints the actions done</l>
               <l n="L7240">By ev'ry tribe beneath the rolling sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1362">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7241"><hi rend="italic">Mneme</hi>, enthron'd within the human
                  breast,</l>
               <l n="L7242">Has vice condemn'd, and ev'ry virtue blest.</l>
               <l n="L7243">How sweet the sound when we her plaudit hear?</l>
               <l n="L7244">Sweeter than music to the ravish'd ear,</l>
               <l n="L7245">Sweeter than <hi rend="italic">Maro's</hi> entertaining strains</l>
               <l n="L7246">Resounding through the groves, and hills, and plains.</l>
               <l n="L7247">But how is <hi rend="italic">Mneme</hi> dreaded by the race,</l>
               <l n="L7248">Who scorn her warnings, and despise her grace?</l>
               <l n="L7249">By her unveil'd each horrid crime appears,</l>
               <l n="L7250">Her awful hand a cup of wormwood bears.</l>
               <l n="L7251">Days, years mispent, O what a hell of woe!</l>
               <l n="L7252">Hers the worst tortures that our souls can know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1363">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7253">Now eighteen years their destin'd course have run,</l>
               <l n="L7254">In fast succession round the central sun.</l>
               <l n="L7255">How did the follies of that period pass</l>
               <l n="L7256">Unnotic'd, but behold them writ in brass!</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="images/WP-0064.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7257">In Recollection see them fresh return,</l>
               <l n="L7258">And sure 'tis mine to be asham'd, and mourn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1364">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7259">O <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi>, smiling in immortal
                  green,</l>
               <l n="L7260">Do thou exert thy pow'r, and change the scene;</l>
               <l n="L7261">Be thine employ to guide my future days,</l>
               <l n="L7262">And mine to pay the tribute of my praise.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1365">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7263">Of <hi rend="italic">Recollection</hi> such the pow'r
                  enthron'd</l>
               <l n="L7264">In ev'ry breast, and thus her pow'r is own'd.</l>
               <l n="L7265">The wretch, who dar'd the vengeance of the skies,</l>
               <l n="L7266">At last awakes in horror and surprise,</l>
               <l n="L7267">By her alarm'd, he sees impending fate,</l>
               <l n="L7268">He howls in anguish, and repents too late.</l>
               <l n="L7269">But O! what peace, what joys are hers t' impart</l>
               <l n="L7270">To ev'ry holy, ev'ry upright heart!</l>
               <l n="L7271">Thrice blest the man, who, in her sacred shrine,</l>
               <l n="L7272">Feels himself shelter'd from the wrath divine!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.211">
            <pb n="65" facs="images/WP-0065.jpg"/>
            <head>On IMAGINATION.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1366">
               <l n="L7273">THY various works, imperial queen, we see,</l>
               <l n="L7274">How bright their forms! how deck'd with pomp by thee!</l>
               <l n="L7275">Thy wond'rous acts in beauteous order stand,</l>
               <l n="L7276">And all attest how potent is thine hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1367">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7277">From <hi rend="italic">Helicon's</hi> refulgent heights
                  attend,</l>
               <l n="L7278">Ye sacred choir, and my attempts befriend:</l>
               <l n="L7279">To tell her glories with a faithful tongue,</l>
               <l n="L7280">Ye blooming graces, triumph in my song.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1368">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7281">Now here, now there, the roving <hi rend="italic"
                     >Fancy</hi> flies,</l>
               <l n="L7282">Till some lov'd object strikes her wand'ring eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7283">Whose silken fetters all the senses bind,</l>
               <l n="L7284">And soft captivity involves the mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="66" id="P512"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1369">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7285"><hi rend="italic">Imagination!</hi> who can sing thy
                  force?</l>
               <l n="L7286">Or who describe the swiftness of thy course?</l>
               <l n="L7287">Soaring through air to find the bright abode,</l>
               <l n="L7288">Th' empyreal palace of the thund'ring God,</l>
               <l n="L7289">We on thy pinions can surpass the wind,</l>
               <l n="L7290">And leave the rolling universe behind:</l>
               <l n="L7291">From star to star the mental optics rove,</l>
               <l n="L7292">Measure the skies, and range the realms above.</l>
               <l n="L7293">There in one view we grasp the mighty whole,</l>
               <l n="L7294">Or with new worlds amaze th' unbounded soul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1370">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7295">Though <hi rend="italic">Winter</hi> frowns to <hi
                     rend="italic">Fancy's</hi> raptur'd eyes</l>
               <l n="L7296">The fields may flourish, and gay scenes arise;</l>
               <l n="L7297">The frozen deeps may break their iron bands,</l>
               <l n="L7298">And bid their waters murmur o'er the sands.</l>
               <l n="L7299">Fair <hi rend="italic">Flora</hi> may resume her fragrant reign,</l>
               <l n="L7300">And with her flow'ry riches deck the plain;</l>
               <l n="L7301"><hi rend="italic">Sylvanus</hi> may diffuse his honours round,</l>
               <l n="L7302">And all the forest may with leaves be crown'd:</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="images/WP-0067.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7303">Show'rs may descend, and dews their gems disclose,</l>
               <l n="L7304">And nectar sparkle on the blooming rose.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1371">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7305">Such is thy pow'r, nor are thine orders vain,</l>
               <l n="L7306">O thou the leader of the mental train:</l>
               <l n="L7307">In full perfection all thy works are wrought,</l>
               <l n="L7308">And thine the sceptre o'er the realms of thought.</l>
               <l n="L7309">Before thy throne the subject-passions bow,</l>
               <l n="L7310">Of subject-passions sov'reign ruler Thou;</l>
               <l n="L7311">At thy command joy rushes on the heart,</l>
               <l n="L7312">And through the glowing veins the spirits dart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1372">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7313"><hi rend="italic">Fancy</hi> might now her silken pinions
                  try</l>
               <l n="L7314">To rise from earth, and sweep th' expanse on high;</l>
               <l n="L7315">From <hi rend="italic">Tithon's</hi> bed now might <hi rend="italic"
                     >Aurora</hi> rise,</l>
               <l n="L7316">Her cheeks all glowing with celestial dies,</l>
               <l n="L7317">While a pure stream of light o'erflows the skies.</l>
               <l n="L7318">The monarch of the day I might behold,</l>
               <l n="L7319">And all the mountains tipt with radiant gold,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="images/WP-0068.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7320">But I reluctant leave the pleasing views,</l>
               <l n="L7321">Which <hi rend="italic">Fancy</hi> dresses to delight the <hi
                     rend="italic">Muse;</hi></l>
               <l n="L7322"><hi rend="italic">Winter</hi> austere forbids me to aspire,</l>
               <l n="L7323">And northern tempests damp the rising fire;</l>
               <l n="L7324">They chill the tides of <hi rend="italic">Fancy's</hi> flowing sea,</l>
               <l n="L7325">Cease then, my song, cease the unequal lay.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.212">
            <pb n="69" facs="images/WP-0069.jpg"/>
            <head>A Funeral POEM on the Death of C. E. an Infant of Twelve Months.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1373">
               <l n="L7326">THROUGH airy roads he wings his instant flight</l>
               <l n="L7327">To purer regions of celestial light;</l>
               <l n="L7328">Enlarg'd he sees unnumber'd systems roll,</l>
               <l n="L7329">Beneath him sees the universal whole,</l>
               <l n="L7330">Planets on planets run their destin'd round,</l>
               <l n="L7331">And circling wonders fill the vast profound.</l>
               <l n="L7332">Th' ethereal now, and now th' empyreal skies</l>
               <l n="L7333">With growing splendors strike his wond'ring eyes:</l>
               <l n="L7334">The angels view him with delight unknown,</l>
               <l n="L7335">Press his soft hand, and seat him on his throne;</l>
               <l n="L7336">Then smiling thus. "To this divine abode,</l>
               <l n="L7337">"The seat of saints, of seraphs, and of God,</l>
               <l n="L7338">"Thrice welcome thou." The raptur'd babe replies,</l>
               <l n="L7339">"Thanks to my God, who snatch'd me to the skies,</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="images/WP-0070.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7340">"E'er vice triumphant had possess'd my heart,</l>
               <l n="L7341">"E'er yet the tempter had beguil'd my heart,</l>
               <l n="L7342">"E'er yet on sin's base actions I was bent,</l>
               <l n="L7343">"E'er yet I knew temptation's dire intent;</l>
               <l n="L7344">"E'er yet the lash for horrid crimes I felt,</l>
               <l n="L7345">"E'er vanity had led my way to guilt,</l>
               <l n="L7346">"But, soon arriv'd at my celestial goal,</l>
               <l n="L7347">"Full glories rush on my expanding soul."</l>
               <l n="L7348">Joyful he spoke: exulting cherubs round</l>
               <l n="L7349">Clapt their glad wings, the heav'nly vaults resound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1374">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7350">Say, parents, why this unavailing moan?</l>
               <l n="L7351">Why heave your pensive bosoms with the groan?</l>
               <l n="L7352">To <hi rend="italic">Charles</hi>, the happy subject of my song,</l>
               <l n="L7353">A brighter world, and nobler strains belong.</l>
               <l n="L7354">Say would you tear him from the realms above</l>
               <l n="L7355">By thoughtless wishes, and prepost'rous love?</l>
               <l n="L7356">Doth his felicity increase your pain?</l>
               <l n="L7357">Or could you welcome to this world again</l>
               <l n="L7358">The heir of bliss? with a superior air</l>
               <l n="L7359">Methinks he answers with a smile severe,</l>
               <l n="L7360">"Thrones and dominions cannot tempt me there."</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="71" facs="images/WP-0071.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1375">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7361">But still you cry, "Can we the sigh forbear,</l>
               <l n="L7362">"And still and still must we not pour the tear?</l>
               <l n="L7363">"Our only hope, more dear than vital breath,</l>
               <l n="L7364">"Twelve moons revolv'd, becomes the prey of death;</l>
               <l n="L7365">"Delightful infant, nightly visions give</l>
               <l n="L7366">"Thee to our arms, and we with joy receive,</l>
               <l n="L7367">"We fain would clasp the <hi rend="italic">Phantom</hi> to our
                  breast,</l>
               <l n="L7368">"The <hi rend="italic">Phantom</hi> flies, and leaves the soul
                  unblest."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1376">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7369">To yon bright regions let your faith ascend,</l>
               <l n="L7370">Prepare to join your dearest infant friend</l>
               <l n="L7371">In pleasures without measure, without end.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.213">
            <pb n="72" facs="images/WP-0072.jpg"/>
            <head>To Captain H----D, of the 65th Regiment.</head>


            <l n="L7372">SAY, muse divine, can hostile scenes delight</l>
            <l n="L7373">The warrior's bosom in the fields of fight?</l>
            <l n="L7374">Lo! here the christian and the hero join</l>
            <l n="L7375">With mutual grace to form the man divine.</l>
            <l n="L7376">In H----D see with pleasure and surprize,</l>
            <l n="L7377">Where <hi rend="italic">valour</hi> kindles, and where <hi rend="italic"
                  >virtue</hi> lies:</l>
            <l n="L7378">Go, hero brave, still grace the post of fame,</l>
            <l n="L7379">And add new glories to thine honour'd name,</l>
            <l n="L7380">Still to the field, and still to virtue true:</l>
            <l n="L7381"><hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> glories in no son like you.</l>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.214">
            <pb n="73" facs="images/WP-0073.jpg"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable WILLLAM, Earl of DARTMOUTH, His Majesty's Principal
               Secretary of State for North America, &amp;c.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1377">
               <l n="L7382">HAIL, happy day, when, smiling like the morn,</l>
               <l n="L7383">Fair <hi rend="italic">Freedom</hi> rose <hi rend="italic"
                     >New-England</hi> to adorn:</l>
               <l n="L7384">The northern clime beneath her genial ray,</l>
               <l n="L7385"><hi rend="italic">Dartmouth</hi>, congratulates thy blissful sway:</l>
               <l n="L7386">Elate with hope her race no longer mourns,</l>
               <l n="L7387">Each soul expands, each grateful bosom burns,</l>
               <l n="L7388">While in thine hand with pleasure we behold</l>
               <l n="L7389">The silken reins, and <hi rend="italic">Freedom's</hi> charms
                  unfold.</l>
               <l n="L7390">Long lost to realms beneath the northern skies</l>
               <l n="L7391">She shines supreme, while hated <hi rend="italic">faction</hi>
                  dies:</l>
               <l n="L7392">Soon as appear'd the <hi rend="italic">Goddess</hi> long desir'd,</l>
               <l n="L7393">Sick at the view, she languish'd and expir'd;</l>
               <l n="L7394">Thus from the splendors of the morning light</l>
               <l n="L7395">The owl in sadness seeks the caves of night.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="74" facs="images/WP-0074.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1378">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7396">No more, <hi rend="italic">America</hi>, in mournful
                  strain</l>
               <l n="L7397">Of wrongs, and grievance unredress'd complain,</l>
               <l n="L7398">No longer shall thou dread the iron chain,</l>
               <l n="L7399">Which wanton <hi rend="italic">Tyranny</hi> with lawless hand</l>
               <l n="L7400">Had made, and with it meant t' enslave the land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1379">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7401">Should you, my lord, while you peruse my song,</l>
               <l n="L7402">Wonder from whence my love of <hi rend="italic">Freedom</hi>
                  sprung,</l>
               <l n="L7403">Whence flow these wishes for the common good,</l>
               <l n="L7404">By feeling hearts alone best understood,</l>
               <l n="L7405">I, young in life, by seeming cruel fate</l>
               <l n="L7406">Was snatch'd from <hi rend="italic">Afric's</hi> fancy'd happy
                  seat:</l>
               <l n="L7407">What pangs excruciating must molest,</l>
               <l n="L7408">What sorrows labour in my parent's breast?</l>
               <l n="L7409">Steel'd was that soul and by no misery mov'd</l>
               <l n="L7410">That from a father seiz'd his babe belov'd:</l>
               <l n="L7411">Such, such my case. And can I then but pray</l>
               <l n="L7412">Others may never feel tyrannic sway?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="75" facs="images/WP-0075.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1380">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7413">For favours past, great Sir, our thanks are due,</l>
               <l n="L7414">And thee we ask thy favours to renew,</l>
               <l n="L7415">Since in thy pow'r, as in thy will before,</l>
               <l n="L7416">To sooth the griefs, which thou did'st once deplore.</l>
               <l n="L7417">May heav'nly grace the sacred sanction give</l>
               <l n="L7418">To all thy works, and thou for ever live</l>
               <l n="L7419">Not only on the wings of fleeting <hi rend="italic">Fame</hi>,</l>
               <l n="L7420">Though praise immortal crowns the patriot's name,</l>
               <l n="L7421">But to conduct to heav'ns refulgent fane,</l>
               <l n="L7422">May fiery coursers sweep th' ethereal plain,</l>
               <l n="L7423">And bear thee upwards to that blest abode,</l>
               <l n="L7424">Where, like the prophet, thou shalt find thy God.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.215">
            <pb n="76" facs="images/WP-0076.jpg"/>
            <head>ODE TO NEPTUNE.</head>

            <opener>On Mrs. W--'s Voyage to England.</opener>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1381">
               <head type="verse">I.</head>
               <l n="L7425">WHILE raging tempests shake the shore,</l>
               <l n="L7426">While <hi rend="italic">AE'lus'</hi> thunders round us roar,</l>
               <l n="L7427">And sweep impetuous o'er the plain</l>
               <l n="L7428">Be still, O tyrant of the main;</l>
               <l n="L7429">Nor let thy brow contracted frowns betray,</l>
               <l n="L7430">While my <hi rend="italic">Susannah</hi> skims the wat'ry way.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1382">
               <head type="verse">II.</head>
               <l n="L7431">The <hi rend="italic">Pow'r</hi> propitious hears the lay,</l>
               <l n="L7432">The blue-ey'd daughters of the sea</l>
               <l n="L7433">With sweeter cadence glide along,</l>
               <l n="L7434">And <hi rend="italic">Thames</hi> responsive joins the song.</l>
               <l n="L7435">Pleas'd with their notes <hi rend="italic">Sol</hi> sheds benign his
                  ray,</l>
               <l n="L7436">And double radiance decks the face of day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="77" facs="images/WP-0077.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1383">
               <head type="verse">III.</head>
               <l n="L7437">To court thee to <hi rend="italic">Britannia's</hi> arms</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7438">Serene the climes and mild the sky,</l>
               <l n="L7439">Her region boasts unnumber'd charms,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7440">Thy welcome smiles in ev'ry eye.</l>
               <l n="L7441">Thy promise, <hi rend="italic">Neptune</hi> keep, record my pray'r,</l>
               <l n="L7442">Nor give my wishes to the empty air.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer><hi rend="italic">Boston, October</hi> 10, 1772.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.216">


            <pb n="78" facs="images/WP-0078.jpg"/>
            <head>To a LADY on her coming to North-America with her Son, for the Recovery of her
               Health.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1384">
               <l n="L7443">INdulgent muse! my grov'ling mind inspire,</l>
               <l n="L7444">And fill my bosom with celestial fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1385">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7445">See from <hi rend="italic">Jamaica's</hi> fervid shore
                  she moves,</l>
               <l n="L7446">Like the fair mother of the blooming loves,</l>
               <l n="L7447">When from above the <hi rend="italic">Goddess</hi> with her hand</l>
               <l n="L7448">Fans the soft breeze, and lights upon the land;</l>
               <l n="L7449">Thus she on <hi rend="italic">Neptune's</hi> wat'ry realm reclin'd</l>
               <l n="L7450">Appear'd, and thus invites the ling'ring wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1386">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7451">"Arise, ye winds, <hi rend="italic">America</hi>
                  explore,</l>
               <l n="L7452">"Waft me, ye gales, from this malignant shore;</l>
               <l n="L7453">"The <hi rend="italic">Northern</hi> milder climes I long to greet,</l>
               <l n="L7454">"There hope that health will my arrival meet."</l>
               <l n="L7455">Soon as she spoke in my ideal view</l>
               <l n="L7456">The winds assented, and the vessel flew.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="79" facs="images/WP-0079.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1387">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7457">Madam, your spouse bereft of wife and son,</l>
               <l n="L7458">In the grove's dark recesses pours his moan;</l>
               <l n="L7459">Each branch, wide-spreading to the ambient sky,</l>
               <l n="L7460">Forgets its verdure, and submits to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1388">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7461">From thence I turn, and leave the sultry plain,</l>
               <l n="L7462">And swift pursue thy passage o'er the main:</l>
               <l n="L7463">The ship arrives before the fav'ring wind,</l>
               <l n="L7464">And makes the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphian</hi> port assign'd,</l>
               <l n="L7465">Thence I attend you to <hi rend="italic">Bostonia's</hi> arms,</l>
               <l n="L7466">Where gen'rous friendship ev'ry bosom warms:</l>
               <l n="L7467">Thrice welcome here! may health revive again,</l>
               <l n="L7468">Bloom on thy cheek, and bound in ev'ry vein!</l>
               <l n="L7469">Then back return to gladden ev'ry heart,</l>
               <l n="L7470">And give your spouse his soul's far dearer part,</l>
               <l n="L7471">Receiv'd again with what a sweet surprize,</l>
               <l n="L7472">The tear in transport starting from his eyes!</l>
               <l n="L7473">While his attendant son with blooming grace</l>
               <l n="L7474">Springs to his father's ever dear embrace.</l>
               <l n="L7475">With shouts of joy <hi rend="italic">Jamaica's</hi> rocks resound,</l>
               <l n="L7476">With shouts of joy the country rings around.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.217">
            <pb n="80" facs="images/WP-0080.jpg"/>
            <head>To a LADY on her remarkable Preservation in an Hurricane in <hi rend="italic"
                  >North-Carolina.</hi></head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1389">
               <l n="L7477">THOUGH thou did'st hear the tempest from afar,</l>
               <l n="L7478">And felt'st the horrors of the wat'ry war,</l>
               <l n="L7479">To me unknown, yet on this peaceful shore</l>
               <l n="L7480">Methinks I hear the storm tumultuous roar,</l>
               <l n="L7481">And how stern <hi rend="italic">Boreas</hi> with impetuous hand</l>
               <l n="L7482">Compell'd the <hi rend="italic">Nereids</hi> to usurp the land.</l>
               <l n="L7483">Reluctant rose the daughters of the main,</l>
               <l n="L7484">And slow ascending glided o'er the plain,</l>
               <l n="L7485">Till <hi rend="italic">AEolus</hi> in his rapid chariot drove</l>
               <l n="L7486">In gloomy grandeur from the vault above:</l>
               <l n="L7487">Furious he comes. His winged sons obey</l>
               <l n="L7488">Their frantic sire, and madden all the sea.</l>
               <l n="L7489">The billows rave, the wind's fierce tyrant roars,</l>
               <l n="L7490">And with his thund'ring terrors shakes the shores:</l>
               <l n="L7491">Broken by waves the vessel's frame is rent,</l>
               <l n="L7492">And strows with planks the wat'ry element.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="81" facs="images/WP-0081.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1390">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7493">But thee, <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, a kind <hi
                     rend="italic">Nereid's</hi> shield</l>
               <l n="L7494">Preserv'd from sinking, and thy form upheld:</l>
               <l n="L7495">And sure some heav'nly oracle design'd</l>
               <l n="L7496">At that dread crisis to instruct thy mind</l>
               <l n="L7497">Things of eternal consequence to weigh,</l>
               <l n="L7498">And to thine heart just feelings to convey</l>
               <l n="L7499">Of things above, and of the future doom,</l>
               <l n="L7500">And what the births of the dread world to come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1391">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7501">From tossing seas I welcome thee to land.</l>
               <l n="L7502">"Resign her, <hi rend="italic">Nereid</hi>," 'twas thy God's
                  command.</l>
               <l n="L7503">Thy spouse late buried, as thy fears conceiv'd,</l>
               <l n="L7504">Again returns, thy fears are all reliev'd:</l>
               <l n="L7505">Thy daughter blooming with superior grace</l>
               <l n="L7506">Again thou see'st, again thine arms embrace;</l>
               <l n="L7507">O come, and joyful show thy spouse his heir,</l>
               <l n="L7508">And what the blessings of maternal care!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.218">

            <pb n="82" facs="images/WP-0082.jpg"/>
            <head>To a LADY and her Children, on the Death of her Son and their Brother.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1392">
               <l n="L7509">O'Erwhelming sorrow now demands my song:</l>
               <l n="L7510">From death the overwhelming sorrow sprung.</l>
               <l n="L7511">What flowing tears? What hearts with grief opprest?</l>
               <l n="L7512">What sighs on sighs heave the fond parent's breast?</l>
               <l n="L7513">The brother weeps, the hapless sisters join</l>
               <l n="L7514">Th' increasing woe, and swell the crystal brine;</l>
               <l n="L7515">The poor, who once his gen'rous bounty fed,</l>
               <l n="L7516">Droop, and bewail their benefactor dead.</l>
               <l n="L7517">In death the friend, the kind companion lies,</l>
               <l n="L7518">And in one death what various comfort dies!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1393">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7519">Th' unhappy mother sees the sanguine rill</l>
               <l n="L7520">Forget to flow, and nature's wheels stand still,</l>
               <l n="L7521">But see from earth his spirit far remov'd,</l>
               <l n="L7522">And know no grief recals your best-belov'd:</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="images/WP-0083.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7523">He, upon pinions swifter than the wind,</l>
               <l n="L7524">Has left mortality's sad scenes behind</l>
               <l n="L7525">For joys to this terrestrial state unknown,</l>
               <l n="L7526">And glories richer than the monarch's crown.</l>
               <l n="L7527">Of virtue's steady course the prize behold!</l>
               <l n="L7528">What blissful wonders to his mind unfold!</l>
               <l n="L7529">But of celestial joys I sing in vain:</l>
               <l n="L7530">Attempt not, muse, the too advent'rous strain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1394">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7531">No more in briny show'rs, ye friends around,</l>
               <l n="L7532">Or bathe his clay, or waste them on the ground:</l>
               <l n="L7533">Still do you weep, still wish for his return?</l>
               <l n="L7534">How cruel thus to wish, and thus to mourn?</l>
               <l n="L7535">No more for him the streams of sorrow pour,</l>
               <l n="L7536">But haste to join him on the heav'nly shore,</l>
               <l n="L7537">On harps of gold to tune immortal lays,</l>
               <l n="L7538">And to your God immortal anthems raise.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.219">
            <pb n="84" facs="images/WP-0084.jpg"/>
            <head>To a GENTLEMAN and LADY on the Death of the Lady's Brother and Sister, and a Child
               of the Name <hi rend="italic">Avis</hi>, aged one Year.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1395">
               <l n="L7539">ON <hi rend="italic">Death's</hi> domain intent I fix my eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7540">Where human nature in vast ruin lies,</l>
               <l n="L7541">With pensive mind I search the drear abode,</l>
               <l n="L7542">Where the great conqu'ror has his spoils bestow'd;</l>
               <l n="L7543">There there the offspring of six thousand years</l>
               <l n="L7544">In endless numbers to my view appears:</l>
               <l n="L7545">Whole kingdoms in his gloomy den are thrust,</l>
               <l n="L7546">And nations mix with their primeval dust:</l>
               <l n="L7547">Insatiate still he gluts the ample tomb;</l>
               <l n="L7548">His is the present, his the age to come</l>
               <l n="L7549">See here a brother, here a sister spread,</l>
               <l n="L7550">And a sweet daughter mingled with the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1396">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7551">But, <hi rend="italic">Madam</hi>, let your grief be laid
                  aside,</l>
               <l n="L7552">And let the fountain of your tears be dry'd,</l>
               <l n="L7553">In vain they flow to wet the dusty plain,</l>
               <l n="L7554">Your sighs are wafted to the skies in vain,</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="images/WP-0085.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7555">Your pains they witness, but they can no more,</l>
               <l n="L7556">While <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> reigns tyrant o'er this mortal
                  shore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1397">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7557">The glowing stars and silver queen of light</l>
               <l n="L7558">At last must perish in the gloom of night:</l>
               <l n="L7559">Resign thy friends to that Almighty hand,</l>
               <l n="L7560">Which gave them life, and bow to his command;</l>
               <l n="L7561">Thine <hi rend="italic">Avis</hi> give without a murm'ring heart,</l>
               <l n="L7562">Though half thy soul be fated to depart.</l>
               <l n="L7563">To shining guards consign thine infant care</l>
               <l n="L7564">To waft triumphant through the seas of air:</l>
               <l n="L7565">Her soul enlarg'd to heav'nly pleasure springs,</l>
               <l n="L7566">She feeds on truth and uncreated things.</l>
               <l n="L7567">Methinks I hear her in the realms above,</l>
               <l n="L7568">And leaning forward with a filial love,</l>
               <l n="L7569">Invite you there to share immortal bliss</l>
               <l n="L7570">Unknown, untasted in a state like this.</l>
               <l n="L7571">With tow'ring hopes, and growing grace arise,</l>
               <l n="L7572">And seek beatitude beyond the skies.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.220">

            <pb n="86" facs="images/WP-0086.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of Dr. SAMUEL MARSHALL.</head>
            <opener>1771.</opener>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1398">
               <l n="L7573">THROUGH thickest glooms look back, immortal shade,</l>
               <l n="L7574">On that confusion which thy death has made;</l>
               <l n="L7575">Or from <hi rend="italic">Olympus'</hi> height look down, and see</l>
               <l n="L7576">A <hi rend="italic">Town</hi> involv'd in grief bereft of thee.</l>
               <l n="L7577">Thy <hi rend="italic">Lucy</hi> sees thee mingle with the dead,</l>
               <l n="L7578">And rends the graceful tresses from her head,</l>
               <l n="L7579">Wild in her woe, with grief unknown opprest</l>
               <l n="L7580">Sigh follows sigh deep heaving from her breast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1399">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7581">Too quickly fled, ah! whither art thou gone?</l>
               <l n="L7582">Ah! lost for ever to thy wife and son!</l>
               <l n="L7583">The hapless child, thine only hope and heir,</l>
               <l n="L7584">Clings round his mother's neck, and weeps his sorrows there.</l>
               <l n="L7585">The loss of thee on <hi rend="italic">Tyler's</hi> soul returns,</l>
               <l n="L7586">And <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> for her dear physician mourns.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="87" facs="images/WP-0087.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1400">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7587">When sickness call'd for <hi rend="italic"
                     >Marshall's</hi> healing hand,</l>
               <l n="L7588">With what compassion did his soul expand?</l>
               <l n="L7589">In him we found the father and the friend:</l>
               <l n="L7590">In life how lov'd! how honour'd in his end!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1401">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7591">And must not then our <hi rend="italic">AEsculapius</hi>
                  stay</l>
               <l n="L7592">To bring his ling'ring infant into day?</l>
               <l n="L7593">The babe unborn in the dark womb is tost,</l>
               <l n="L7594">And seems in anguish for its father lost.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1402">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7595">Gone is <hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi> from his house of
                  earth,</l>
               <l n="L7596">But leaves the sweet memorials of his worth:</l>
               <l n="L7597">The common parent, whom we all deplore,</l>
               <l n="L7598">From yonder world unseen must come no more,</l>
               <l n="L7599">Yet 'midst our woes immortal hopes attend</l>
               <l n="L7600">The spouse, the sire, the universal friend.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.221">

            <pb n="88" facs="images/WP-0088.jpg"/>
            <head>To a GENTLEMAN on his Voyage to <hi rend="italic">Great-Britain</hi> for the
               Recovery of his Health.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1403">
               <l n="L7601">WHILE others chant of gay <hi rend="italic">Elysian</hi> scenes,</l>
               <l n="L7602">Of balmy zephyrs, and of flow'ry plains,</l>
               <l n="L7603">My song more happy speaks a greater name,</l>
               <l n="L7604">Feels higher motives and a nobler flame.</l>
               <l n="L7605">For thee, OR --, the muse attunes her strings,</l>
               <l n="L7606">And mounts sublime above inferior things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1404">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7607">I sing not now of green embow'ring woods,</l>
               <l n="L7608">I sing not now the daughters of the floods,</l>
               <l n="L7609">I sing not of the storms o'er ocean driv'n,</l>
               <l n="L7610">And how they howl'd along the waste of heav'n.</l>
               <l n="L7611">But I to R -- would paint the <hi rend="italic">British</hi> shore,</l>
               <l n="L7612">And vast <hi rend="italic">Atlantic</hi>, not untry'd before:</l>
               <l n="L7613">Thy life impair'd commands thee to arise,</l>
               <l n="L7614">Leave these bleak regions and inclement skies,</l>
               <l n="L7615">Where chilling winds return the winter past,</l>
               <l n="L7616">And nature shudders at the furious blast.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="89" facs="images/WP-0089.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1405">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7617">O thou stupendous, earth-enclosing main</l>
               <l n="L7618">Exert thy wonders to the world again!</l>
               <l n="L7619">If ere thy pow'r prolong'd the fleeting breath,</l>
               <l n="L7620">Turn'd back the shafts, and mock'd the gates of death,</l>
               <l n="L7621">If ere thine air dispens'd an healing pow'r,</l>
               <l n="L7622">Or snatch'd the victim from the fatal hour,</l>
               <l n="L7623">This equal case demands thine equal care,</l>
               <l n="L7624">And equal wonders may this patient share.</l>
               <l n="L7625">But unavailing, frantic is the dream</l>
               <l n="L7626">To hope thine aid without the aid of him</l>
               <l n="L7627">Who gave thee birth, and taught thee where to flow,</l>
               <l n="L7628">And in thy waves his various blessings show.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1406">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7629">May R-- return to view his native shore</l>
               <l n="L7630">Replete with vigour not his own before,</l>
               <l n="L7631">Then shall we see with pleasure and surprize,</l>
               <l n="L7632">And own thy work, great Ruler of the skies!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.222">
            <pb n="90" facs="images/WP-0090.jpg"/>
            <head>To the Rev. DR. THOMAS AMORY on reading his Sermons on DAILY DEVOTION, in which
               that Duty is recommended and assisted.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1407">
               <l n="L7633">TO cultivate in ev'ry noble mind</l>
               <l n="L7634">Habitual grace, and sentiments refin'd,</l>
               <l n="L7635">Thus while you strive to mend the human heart,</l>
               <l n="L7636">Thus while the heav'nly precepts you impart,</l>
               <l n="L7637">O may each bosom catch the sacred fire,</l>
               <l n="L7638">And youthful minds to <hi rend="italic">Virtue's</hi> throne
                  aspire!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1408">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7639">When God's eternal ways you set in sight,</l>
               <l n="L7640">And <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi> shines in all her native light,</l>
               <l n="L7641">In vain would <hi rend="italic">Vice</hi> her works in night
                  conceal,</l>
               <l n="L7642">For <hi rend="italic">Wisdom's</hi> eye pervades the sable veil.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1409">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7643">Artists may paint the sun's effulgent rays,</l>
               <l n="L7644">But <hi rend="italic">Amory's</hi> pen the brighter God displays:</l>
               <l n="L7645">While his great works in <hi rend="italic">Amory's</hi> pages
                  shine,</l>
               <l n="L7646">And while he proves his essence all divine,</l>
               <pb n="91" facs="images/WP-0091.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7647">The Atheist sure no more can boast aloud</l>
               <l n="L7648">Of chance, or nature, and exclude the God;</l>
               <l n="L7649">As if the clay without the potter's aid</l>
               <l n="L7650">Should rise in various forms, and shapes self-made,</l>
               <l n="L7651">Or worlds above with orb o'er orb profound</l>
               <l n="L7652">Self-mov'd could run the everlasting round.</l>
               <l n="L7653">It cannot be unerring <hi rend="italic">Wisdom</hi> guides</l>
               <l n="L7654">With eye propitious, and o'er all presides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1410">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7655">Still prosper, <hi rend="italic">Amory!</hi> still may'st
                  thou receive</l>
               <l n="L7656">The warmest blessings which a muse can give,</l>
               <l n="L7657">And when this transitory state is o'er,</l>
               <l n="L7658">When kingdoms fall, and fleeting <hi rend="italic">Fame's</hi> no
                  more,</l>
               <l n="L7659">May <hi rend="italic">Amory</hi> triumph in immortal fame,</l>
               <l n="L7660">A nobler title, and superior name!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.223">
            <pb n="92" facs="images/WP-0092.jpg"/>
            <head>On the Death of J. C. an Infant.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1411">
               <l n="L7661">NO more the flow'ry scenes of pleasure rise,</l>
               <l n="L7662">Nor charming prospects greet the mental eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7663">No more with joy we view that lovely face</l>
               <l n="L7664">Smiling, disportive, flush'd with ev'ry grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1412">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7665">The tear of sorrow flows from ev'ry eye,</l>
               <l n="L7666">Groans answer groans, and sighs to sighs reply;</l>
               <l n="L7667">What sudden pangs shot thro' each aching heart,</l>
               <l n="L7668">When, <hi rend="italic">Death</hi>, thy messenger dispatch'd his
                  dart?</l>
               <l n="L7669">Thy dread attendants, all-destroying <hi rend="italic">Pow'r</hi>,</l>
               <l n="L7670">Hurried the infant to his mortal hour.</l>
               <l n="L7671">Could'st thou unpitying close those radiant eyes?</l>
               <l n="L7672">Or fail'd his artless beauties to surprize?</l>
               <l n="L7673">Could not his innocence thy stroke controul,</l>
               <l n="L7674">Thy purpose shake, and soften all thy soul?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="93" facs="images/WP-0093.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1413">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7675">The blooming babe, with shades of <hi rend="italic"
                     >Death</hi> o'erspread,</l>
               <l n="L7676">No more shall smile, no more shall raise its head,</l>
               <l n="L7677">But, like a branch that from the tree is torn,</l>
               <l n="L7678">Falls prostrate, wither'd, languid, and forlorn.</l>
               <l n="L7679">"Where flies my <hi rend="italic">James</hi>?" 'tis thus I seem to
                  hear</l>
               <l n="L7680">The parent ask, "Some angel tell me where</l>
               <l n="L7681">"He wings his passage thro' the yielding air?"</l>
               <l n="L7682">Methinks a cherub bending from the skies</l>
               <l n="L7683">Observes the question, and serene replies,</l>
               <l n="L7684">"In heav'ns high palaces your babe appears:</l>
               <l n="L7685">"Prepare to meet him, and dismiss your tears."</l>
               <l n="L7686">Shall not th' intelligence your grief restrain,</l>
               <l n="L7687">And turn the mournful to the chearful strain?</l>
               <l n="L7688">Cease your complaints, suspend each rising sigh,</l>
               <l n="L7689">Cease to accuse the Ruler of the sky.</l>
               <l n="L7690">Parents, no more indulge the falling tear:</l>
               <l n="L7691">Let <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> to heav'n's refulgent domes
                  repair,</l>
               <l n="L7692">There see your infant, like a seraph glow:</l>
               <l n="L7693">What charms celestial in his numbers flow</l>
               <pb n="94" facs="images/WP-0094.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7694">Melodious, while the soul-enchanting strain</l>
               <l n="L7695">Dwells on his tongue, and fills th' ethereal plain?</l>
               <l n="L7696">Enough -- for ever cease your murm'ring breath;</l>
               <l n="L7697">Not as a foe, but friend converse with <hi rend="italic"
                  >Death</hi>,</l>
               <l n="L7698">Since to the port of happiness unknown</l>
               <l n="L7699">He brought that treasure which you call your own.</l>
               <l n="L7700">The gift of heav'n intrusted to your hand</l>
               <l n="L7701">Chearful resign at the divine command:</l>
               <l n="L7702">Not at your bar must sov'reign <hi rend="italic">Wisdom</hi> stand.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <pb n="95" facs="images/WP-0095.jpg"/>
         <div type="poem" id="div.224">
            <head>An HYMN to HUMANITY.</head>
            <opener>To S. P. G. Esq;</opener>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1414">
               <head type="verse">I.</head>
               <l n="L7703">LO! for this dark terrestrial ball</l>
               <l n="L7704">Forsakes his azure-paved hall</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7705">A prince of heav'nly birth!</l>
               <l n="L7706">Divine <hi rend="italic">Humanity</hi> behold.</l>
               <l n="L7707">What wonders rise, what charms unfold</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7708">At his descent to earth!</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1415">
               <head type="verse">II.</head>
               <l n="L7709">The bosoms of the great and good</l>
               <l n="L7710">With wonder and delight he view'd,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7711">And fix'd his empire there:</l>
               <l n="L7712">Him, close compressing to his breast,</l>
               <l n="L7713">The sire of gods and men address'd,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7714">"My son, my heav'nly fair!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="96" facs="images/WP-0096.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1416">
               <head type="verse">III.</head>
               <l n="L7715">"Descend to earth, there place thy throne;</l>
               <l n="L7716">"To succour man's afflicted son</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7717">"Each human heart inspire:</l>
               <l n="L7718">"To act in bounties unconfin'd</l>
               <l n="L7719">"Enlarge the close contracted mind,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7720">"And fill it with thy fire."</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1417">
               <head type="verse">IV.</head>
               <l n="L7721">Quick as the word, with swift career</l>
               <l n="L7722">He wings his course from star to star,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7723">And leaves the bright abode.</l>
               <l n="L7724">The <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi> did his charms impart;</l>
               <l n="L7725">Their G--y! then thy raptur'd heart</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7726">Perceiv'd the rushing God:</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1418">
               <head type="verse">V.</head>
               <l n="L7727">For when thy pitying eye did see</l>
               <l n="L7728">The languid muse in low degree,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7729">Then, then at thy desire</l>
               <l n="L7730">Descended the celestial nine;</l>
               <l n="L7731">O'er me methought they deign'd to shine,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7732">And deign'd to string my lyre.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="97" facs="images/WP-0097.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1419">
               <head type="verse">VI.</head>
               <l n="L7733">Can <hi rend="italic">Afric's</hi> muse forgetful prove?</l>
               <l n="L7734">Or can such friendship fail to move</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7735">A tender human heart?</l>
               <l n="L7736">Immortal <hi rend="italic">Friendship</hi> laurel-crown'd</l>
               <l n="L7737">The smiling <hi rend="italic">Graces</hi> all surround</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L7738">With ev'ry heav'nly <hi rend="italic">Art</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.225">
            <pb n="98" facs="images/WP-0098.jpg"/>
            <head>To the Honourable T. H. Esq; on the Deathof his Daughter.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1420">
               <l n="L7739">WHILE deep you mourn beneath the cypress-shade</l>
               <l n="L7740">The hand of Death, and your dear daughter laid</l>
               <l n="L7741">In dust, whose absence gives your tears to flow,</l>
               <l n="L7742">And racks your bosom with incessant woe,</l>
               <l n="L7743">Let <hi rend="italic">Recollection</hi> take a tender part,</l>
               <l n="L7744">Assuage the raging tortures of your heart,</l>
               <l n="L7745">Still the wild tempest of tumultuous grief,</l>
               <l n="L7746">And pour the heav'nly nectar of relief:</l>
               <l n="L7747">Suspend the sigh, dear Sir, and check the groan,</l>
               <l n="L7748">Divinely bright your daughter's <hi rend="italic">Virtues</hi>
                  shone:</l>
               <l n="L7749">How free from scornful pride her gentle mind,</l>
               <l n="L7750">Which ne'er its aid to indigence declin'd!</l>
               <l n="L7751">Expanding free, it sought the means to prove</l>
               <l n="L7752">Unfailing charity, unbounded love!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1421">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7753">She unreluctant flies to see no more</l>
               <l n="L7754">Her dear-lov'd parents on earth's dusky shore:</l>
               <pb n="99" facs="images/WP-0099.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7755">Impatient heav'n's resplendent goal to gain,</l>
               <l n="L7756">She with swift progress cuts the azure plain,</l>
               <l n="L7757">Where grief subsides, where changes are no more,</l>
               <l n="L7758">And life's tumultuous billows cease to roar;</l>
               <l n="L7759">She leaves her earthly mansion for the skies,</l>
               <l n="L7760">Where new creations feast her wond'ring eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1422">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7761">To heav'n's high mandate chearfully resign'd</l>
               <l n="L7762">She mounts, and leaves the rolling globe behind;</l>
               <l n="L7763">She, who late wish'd that <hi rend="italic">Leonard</hi> might
                  return,</l>
               <l n="L7764">Has ceas'd to languish, and forgot to mourn;</l>
               <l n="L7765">To the same high empyreal mansions come,</l>
               <l n="L7766">She joins her spouse, and smiles upon the tomb:</l>
               <l n="L7767">And thus I hear her from the realms above:</l>
               <l n="L7768">"Lo! this the kingdom of celestial love!</l>
               <l n="L7769">"Could ye, fond parents, see our present bliss,</l>
               <l n="L7770">"How soon would you each sigh, each fear dismiss?</l>
               <l n="L7771">"Amidst unutter'd pleasures whilst I play</l>
               <l n="L7772">"In the fair sunshine of celestial day,</l>
               <l n="L7773">"As far as grief affects an happy soul</l>
               <l n="L7774">"So far doth grief my better mind controul,</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="images/WP-0100.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7775">"To see on earth my aged parents mourn,</l>
               <l n="L7776">"And secret wish for T--l to return:</l>
               <l n="L7777">"Let brighter scenes your ev'ning-hours employ:</l>
               <l n="L7778">"Converse with heav'n, and taste the promis'd joy."</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.226">
            <pb n="101" facs="images/WP-0101.jpg"/>
            <head>NIOBE in Distress for her Children slain by APOLLO, from <hi rend="italic"
                  >Ovid's</hi> Metamorphoses, Book VI. and from a view of the Painting of Mr. <hi
                  rend="italic">Richard Wilson.</hi></head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1423">
               <l n="L7779">APOLLO's wrath to man the dreadful spring</l>
               <l n="L7780">Of ills innum'rous, tuneful goddess, sing!</l>
               <l n="L7781">Thou who did'st first th' ideal pencil give,</l>
               <l n="L7782">And taught'st the painter in his works to live,</l>
               <l n="L7783">Inspire with glowing energy of thought,</l>
               <l n="L7784">What <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi> painted, and what <hi rend="italic"
                     >Ovid</hi> wrote.</l>
               <l n="L7785">Muse! lend thy aid, nor let me sue in vain,</l>
               <l n="L7786">Tho' last and meanest of the rhyming train!</l>
               <l n="L7787">O guide my pen in lofty strains to show</l>
               <l n="L7788">The <hi rend="italic">Phrygian</hi> queen, all beautiful in woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1424">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7789">'Twas where <hi rend="italic">Maeonia</hi> spreads her
                  wide domain</l>
               <l n="L7790"><hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi> dwelt, and held her potent reign:</l>
               <l n="L7791">See in her hand the regal sceptre shine,</l>
               <l n="L7792">The wealthy heir of <hi rend="italic">Tantalus</hi> divine,</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="images/WP-0102.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7793">He most distinguish'd by <hi rend="italic">Dodonean Jove</hi>,</l>
               <l n="L7794">To approach the tables of the gods above:</l>
               <l n="L7795">Her grandsire <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, who with mighty pains</l>
               <l n="L7796">Th' ethereal axis on his neck sustains:</l>
               <l n="L7797">Her other <CORR REND="grandsire">gran sire</CORR> on the throne on
                  high</l>
               <l n="L7798">Rolls the loud-pealing thunder thro' the sky.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1425">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7799">Her spouse, <hi rend="italic">Amphion</hi>, who from <hi
                     rend="italic">Jove</hi> too springs,</l>
               <l n="L7800">Divinely taught to sweep the sounding strings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1426">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7801">Seven sprightly sons the royal bed adorn,</l>
               <l n="L7802">Seven daughters beauteous as the op'ning morn,</l>
               <l n="L7803">As when <hi rend="italic">Aurora</hi> fills the ravish'd sight,</l>
               <l n="L7804">And decks the orient realms with rosy light</l>
               <l n="L7805">From their bright eyes the living splendors play,</l>
               <l n="L7806">Nor can beholders bear the flashing ray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1427">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7807">Wherever, <hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi>, thou turn'st
                  thine eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7808">New beauties kindle, and new joys arise!</l>
               <l n="L7809">But thou had'st far the happier mother prov'd,</l>
               <l n="L7810">If this fair offspring had been less belov'd:</l>
               <pb n="103" facs="images/WP-0103.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7811">What if their charms exceed <hi rend="italic">Aurora's</hi> teint,</l>
               <l n="L7812">No words could tell them, and no pencil paint,</l>
               <l n="L7813">Thy love too vehement hastens to destroy</l>
               <l n="L7814">Each blooming maid, and each celestial boy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1428">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7815">Now <hi rend="italic">Manto</hi> comes, endu'd with
                  mighty skill,</l>
               <l n="L7816">The past to explore, the future to reveal.</l>
               <l n="L7817">Thro' <hi rend="italic">Thebes'</hi> wide streets <hi rend="italic"
                     >Tiresia's</hi> daughter came,</l>
               <l n="L7818">Divine <hi rend="italic">Latona's</hi> mandate to proclaim:</l>
               <l n="L7819">The Theban maids to hear the orders ran,</l>
               <l n="L7820">When thus <hi rend="italic">Maeonia's</hi> prophetess began:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1429">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7821">"Go, <hi rend="italic">Thebans!</hi> great <hi
                     rend="italic">Latona's</hi> will obey,</l>
               <l n="L7822">"And pious tribute at her altars pay:</l>
               <l n="L7823">"With rights divine, the goddess be implor'd,</l>
               <l n="L7824">"Nor be her sacred offspring unador'd."</l>
               <l n="L7825">Thus <hi rend="italic">Manto</hi> spoke. The <hi rend="italic"
                     >Theban</hi> maids obey,</l>
               <l n="L7826">And pious tribute to the goddess pay.</l>
               <l n="L7827">The rich perfumes ascend in waving spires,</l>
               <l n="L7828">And altars blaze with consecrated fires;</l>
               <l n="L7829">The fair assembly moves with graceful air,</l>
               <l n="L7830">And leaves of laurel bind the flowing hair.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="104" facs="images/WP-0104.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1430">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7831"><hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi> comes with all her royal
                  race,</l>
               <l n="L7832">With charms unnumber'd, and superior grace:</l>
               <l n="L7833">Her <hi rend="italic">Phrygian</hi> garments of delightful hue,</l>
               <l n="L7834">Inwove with gold, refulgent to the view,</l>
               <l n="L7835">Beyond description beautiful she moves</l>
               <l n="L7836">Like heav'nly Venus, 'midst her smiles and loves:</l>
               <l n="L7837">She views around the supplicating train,</l>
               <l n="L7838">And shakes her graceful head with stern disdain,</l>
               <l n="L7839">Proudly she turns around her lofty eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7840">And thus reviles celestial deities:</l>
               <l n="L7841">"What madness drives the <hi rend="italic">Theban</hi> ladies fair</l>
               <l n="L7842">"To give their incense to surrounding air?</l>
               <l n="L7843">"Say why this new sprung deity preferr'd?</l>
               <l n="L7844">"Why vainly fancy your petitions heard?</l>
               <l n="L7845">"Or say why <hi rend="italic">Coeus'</hi> offspring is obey'd,</l>
               <l n="L7846">"While to my goddesship no tribute's paid?</l>
               <l n="L7847">"For me no altars blaze with living fires,</l>
               <l n="L7848">"No bullock bleeds, no frankincense transpires,</l>
               <l n="L7849">"Tho' <hi rend="italic">Cadmus'</hi> palace, not unknown to fame,</l>
               <l n="L7850">"And <hi rend="italic">Phrygian</hi> nations all revere my name.</l>
               <pb n="105" facs="images/WP-0105.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7851">"Where'er I turn my eyes vast wealth I find.</l>
               <l n="L7852">"Lo! here an empress with a goddess join'd.</l>
               <l n="L7853">"What, shall a <hi rend="italic">Titaness</hi> be deify'd,</l>
               <l n="L7854">"To whom the spacious earth a couch deny'd?</l>
               <l n="L7855">"Nor heav'n, nor earth, nor sea receiv'd your queen,</l>
               <l n="L7856">"Till pitying <hi rend="italic">Delos</hi> took the wand'rer in.</l>
               <l n="L7857">"Round me what a large progeny is spread!</l>
               <l n="L7858">"No frowns of fortune has my soul to dread.</l>
               <l n="L7859">"What if indignant she decrease my train</l>
               <l n="L7860">"More than <hi rend="italic">Latona's</hi> number will remain?</l>
               <l n="L7861">"Then hence, ye <hi rend="italic">Theban</hi> dames, hence haste
                  away,</l>
               <l n="L7862">"Nor longer off'rings to <hi rend="italic">Latona</hi> pay?</l>
               <l n="L7863">"Regard the orders of <hi rend="italic">Amphion's</hi> spouse,</l>
               <l n="L7864">"And take the leaves of laurel from your brows."</l>
               <l n="L7865"><hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi> spoke. The <hi rend="italic">Theban</hi>
                  maids obey'd,</l>
               <l n="L7866">Their brows unbound, and left the rights unpaid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1431">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7867">The angry goddess heard, then silence broke</l>
               <l n="L7868">On <hi rend="italic">Cynthus'</hi> summit, and indignant spoke;</l>
               <pb n="106" facs="images/WP-0106.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7869">"<hi rend="italic">Phoebus!</hi> behold, thy mother in disgrace,</l>
               <l n="L7870">"Who to no goddess yields the prior place</l>
               <l n="L7871">"Except to <hi rend="italic">Juno's</hi> self, who reigns above,</l>
               <l n="L7872">"The spouse and sister of the thund'ring <hi rend="italic"
                  >Jove</hi>.</l>
               <l n="L7873">"<hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi>, sprung from <hi rend="italic"
                     >Tantalus</hi>, inspires</l>
               <l n="L7874">"Each <hi rend="italic">Theban</hi> bosom with rebellious fires;</l>
               <l n="L7875">"No reason her imperious temper quells,</l>
               <l n="L7876">"But all her father in her tongue rebels;</l>
               <l n="L7877">"Wrap her own sons for her blaspheming breath,</l>
               <l n="L7878">"<hi rend="italic">Apollo!</hi> wrap them in the shades of death."</l>
               <l n="L7879"><hi rend="italic">Latona</hi> ceas'd, and ardent thus replies</l>
               <l n="L7880">The God, whose glory decks th' expanded skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1432">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7881">"Cease thy complaints, mine be the task assign'd</l>
               <l n="L7882">"To punish pride, and scourge the rebel mind."</l>
               <l n="L7883">This <hi rend="italic">Phoebe</hi> join'd. -- They wing their instant
                  flight;</l>
               <l n="L7884"><hi rend="italic">Thebes</hi> trembled as th' immortal pow'rs
                  alight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1433">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7885">With clouds incompass'd glorious <hi rend="italic"
                     >Phoebus</hi> stands;</l>
               <l n="L7886">The feather'd vengeance quiv'ring in his hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="107" facs="images/WP-0107.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1434">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7887">Near <hi rend="italic">Cadmus'</hi> walls a plain
                  extended lay,</l>
               <l n="L7888">Where <hi rend="italic">Thebes'</hi> young princes pass'd in sport the
                  day:</l>
               <l n="L7889">There the bold coursers bounded o'er the plains,</l>
               <l n="L7890">While their great masters held the golden reins.</l>
               <l n="L7891"><hi rend="italic">Ismenus</hi> first the racing pastime led,</l>
               <l n="L7892">And rul'd the fury of his flying steed.</l>
               <l n="L7893">"Ah me," he sudden cries, with shrieking breath,</l>
               <l n="L7894">While in his breast he feels the shaft of death;</l>
               <l n="L7895">He drops the bridle on his courser's mane,</l>
               <l n="L7896">Before his eyes in shadows swims the plain,</l>
               <l n="L7897">He, the first-born of great <hi rend="italic">Amphion's</hi> bed,</l>
               <l n="L7898">Was struck the first, first mingled with the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1435">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7899">Then didst thou, <hi rend="italic">Sipylus</hi>, the
                  language hear</l>
               <l n="L7900">Of fate portentous whistling in the air:</l>
               <l n="L7901">As when th' impending storm the sailor sees</l>
               <l n="L7902">He spreads his canvas to the fav'ring breeze,</l>
               <pb n="108" facs="images/WP-0108.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7903">So to thine horse thou gav'st the golden reins,</l>
               <l n="L7904">Gav'st him to rush impetuous o'er the plains:</l>
               <l n="L7905">But ah! a fatal shaft from <hi rend="italic">Phoebus'</hi> hand</l>
               <l n="L7906">Smites through thy neck, and sinks thee on the sand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1436">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7907">Two other brothers were at <hi rend="italic"
                     >wrestling</hi> found,</l>
               <l n="L7908">And in their pastime claspt each other round:</l>
               <l n="L7909">A shaft that instant from <hi rend="italic">Apollo's</hi> hand</l>
               <l n="L7910">Transfixt them both, and stretcht them on the sand:</l>
               <l n="L7911">Together they their cruel fate bemoan'd,</l>
               <l n="L7912">Together languish'd, and together groan'd:</l>
               <l n="L7913">Together too th' unbodied spirits fled,</l>
               <l n="L7914">And sought the gloomy mansions of the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1437">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7915"><hi rend="italic">Alphenor</hi> saw, and trembling at the
                  view,</l>
               <l n="L7916">Beat his torn breast, that chang'd its snowy hue.</l>
               <l n="L7917">He flies to raise them in a kind embrace;</l>
               <l n="L7918">A brother's fondness triumphs in his face:</l>
               <l n="L7919"><hi rend="italic">Alphenor</hi> fails in this fraternal deed,</l>
               <l n="L7920">A dart dispatch'd him (so the fates decreed:)</l>
               <pb n="109" facs="images/WP-0109.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7921">Soon as the arrow left the deadly wound,</l>
               <l n="L7922">His issuing entrails smoak'd upon the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1438">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7923">What woes on blooming <hi rend="italic">Damasichon</hi>
                  wait!</l>
               <l n="L7924">His sighs portend his near impending fate.</l>
               <l n="L7925">Just where the well-made leg begins to be,</l>
               <l n="L7926">And the soft sinews form the supple knee,</l>
               <l n="L7927">The youth sore wounded by the <hi rend="italic">Delian</hi> god</l>
               <l n="L7928">Attempts t' extract the crime-avenging rod,</l>
               <l n="L7929">But, whilst he strives the will of fate t' avert,</l>
               <l n="L7930">Divine <hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi> sends a second dart;</l>
               <l n="L7931">Swift thro' his throat the feather'd mischief flies,</l>
               <l n="L7932">Bereft of sense, he drops his head, and dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1439">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7933">Young <hi rend="italic">Ilioneus</hi>, the last, directs
                  his pray'r,</l>
               <l n="L7934">And cries, "My life, ye gods celestial! spare."</l>
               <l n="L7935"><hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi> heard, and pity touch'd his heart,</l>
               <l n="L7936">But ah! too late, for he had sent the dart:</l>
               <l n="L7937">Thou too, O <hi rend="italic">Ilioneus</hi>, art doom'd to fall,</l>
               <l n="L7938">The fates refuse that arrow to recal.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="110" facs="images/WP-0110.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1440">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7939">On the swift wings of ever-flying <hi rend="italic"
                     >Fame</hi></l>
               <l n="L7940">To <hi rend="italic">Cadmus'</hi> palace soon the tidings came:</l>
               <l n="L7941"><hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi> heard, and with indignant eyes</l>
               <l n="L7942">She thus express'd her anger and surprize:</l>
               <l n="L7943">"Why is such privilege to them allow'd?</l>
               <l n="L7944">"Why thus insulted by the <hi rend="italic">Delian</hi> god?</l>
               <l n="L7945">"Dwells there such mischief in the pow'rs above?</l>
               <l n="L7946">"Why sleeps the vengeance of immortal <hi rend="italic">Jove?</hi>"</l>
               <l n="L7947">For now <hi rend="italic">Amphion</hi> too, with grief oppress'd,</l>
               <l n="L7948">Had plung'd the deadly dagger in his breast.</l>
               <l n="L7949"><hi rend="italic">Niobe</hi> now, less haughty than before,</l>
               <l n="L7950">With lofty head directs her steps no more.</l>
               <l n="L7951">She, who late told her pedigree divine,</l>
               <l n="L7952">And drove the <hi rend="italic">Thebans</hi> from <hi rend="italic"
                     >Latona's</hi> shrine,</l>
               <l n="L7953">How strangely chang'd! -- yet beautiful in woe,</l>
               <l n="L7954">She weeps, nor weeps unpity'd by the foe.</l>
               <l n="L7955">On each pale corse the wretched mother spread</l>
               <l n="L7956">Lay overwhelm'd with grief, and kiss'd her dead,</l>
               <l n="L7957">Then rais'd her arms, and thus, in accents slow,</l>
               <l n="L7958">"Be sated cruel <hi rend="italic">Goddess!</hi> with my woe;</l>
               <pb n="111" facs="images/WP-0111.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7959">"If I've offended, let these streaming eyes,</l>
               <l n="L7960">"And let this sev'nfold funeral suffice:</l>
               <l n="L7961">"Ah! take this wretched life you deign'd to save,</l>
               <l n="L7962">"With them I too am carried to the grave.</l>
               <l n="L7963">"Rejoice triumphant, my victorious foe,</l>
               <l n="L7964">"But show the cause from whence your triumphs flow?</l>
               <l n="L7965">"Tho' I unhappy mourn these children slain,</l>
               <l n="L7966">"Yet greater numbers to my lot remain."</l>
               <l n="L7967">She ceas'd, the bow-string twang'd with awful sound,</l>
               <l n="L7968">Which struck with terror all th' assembly round,</l>
               <l n="L7969">Except the queen, who stood unmov'd alone,</l>
               <l n="L7970">By her distresses more presumptuous grown.</l>
               <l n="L7971">Near the pale corses stood their sisters fair</l>
               <l n="L7972">In sable vestures and dishevell'd hair;</l>
               <l n="L7973">One, while she draws the fatal shaft away,</l>
               <l n="L7974">Faints, falls, and sickens at the light of day.</l>
               <l n="L7975">To sooth her mother, lo! another flies,</l>
               <l n="L7976">And blames the fury of inclement skies,</l>
               <l n="L7977">And, while her words a filial pity show,</l>
               <l n="L7978">Struck dumb -- indignant seeks the shades below.</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="images/WP-0112.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7979">Now from the fatal place another flies,</l>
               <l n="L7980">Falls in her flight, and languishes, and dies.</l>
               <l n="L7981">Another on her sister drops in death;</l>
               <l n="L7982">A fifth in trembling terrors yields her breath;</l>
               <l n="L7983">While the sixth seeks some gloomy cave in vain,</l>
               <l n="L7984">Struck with the rest, and mingl'd with the slain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1441">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7985">One only daughter lives, and she the least;</l>
               <l n="L7986">The queen close clasp'd the daughter to her breast:</l>
               <l n="L7987">"Ye heav'nly pow'rs, ah spare me one," she cry'd,</l>
               <l n="L7988">"Ah! spare me one," the vocal hills reply'd:</l>
               <l n="L7989">In vain she begs, the <hi rend="italic">Fates</hi> her suit deny,</l>
               <l n="L7990">In her embrace she sees her daughter die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1442">
               <l rend="indent" id="L7991"><note n="*" id="p112.n1">This Verse to the End is ther
                     Work of another Hand.</note> "The queen of all her family bereft,</l>
               <l n="L7992">"Without or husband, son, or daughter left,</l>
               <l n="L7993">"Grew stupid at the shock. The passing air</l>
               <l n="L7994">"Made no impression on her stiff'ning hair.</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="images/WP-0113.jpg"/>
               <l n="L7995">"The blood forsook her face: amidst the flood</l>
               <l n="L7996">"Pour'd from her cheeks, quite fix'd her eye-balls stood.</l>
               <l n="L7997">"Her tongue, her palate both obdurate grew,</l>
               <l n="L7998">"Her curdled veins no longer motion knew;</l>
               <l n="L7999">"The use of neck, and arms, and feet was gone,</l>
               <l n="L8000">"And ev'n her bowels hard'ned into stone:</l>
               <l n="L8001">"A marble statue now the queen appears,</l>
               <l n="L8002">"But from the marble steal the silent tears."</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.227">
            <pb n="114" facs="images/WP-0114.jpg"/>
            <head>To S. M. a young <hi rend="italic">African</hi> Painter, on seeing his
               Works.</head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1443">
               <l n="L8003">TO show the lab'ring bosom's deep intent,</l>
               <l n="L8004">And thought in living characters to paint,</l>
               <l n="L8005">When first thy pencil did those beauties give,</l>
               <l n="L8006">And breathing figures learnt from thee to live,</l>
               <l n="L8007">How did those prospects give my soul delight,</l>
               <l n="L8008">A new creation rushing on my sight?</l>
               <l n="L8009">Still, wond'rous youth! each noble path pursue,</l>
               <l n="L8010">On deathless glories fix thine ardent view:</l>
               <l n="L8011">Still may the painter's and the poet's fire</l>
               <l n="L8012">To aid thy pencil, and thy verse conspire!</l>
               <l n="L8013">And may the charms of each seraphic theme</l>
               <l n="L8014">Conduct thy footsteps to immortal fame!</l>
               <l n="L8015">High to the blissful wonders of the skies</l>
               <l n="L8016">Elate thy soul, and raise thy wishful eyes.</l>
               <l n="L8017">Thrice happy, when exalted to survey</l>
               <l n="L8018">That splendid city, crown'd with endless day,</l>
               <l n="L8019">Whose twice six gates on radiant hinges ring:</l>
               <l n="L8020">Celestial <hi rend="italic">Salem</hi> blooms in endless spring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="115" facs="images/WP-0115.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1444">
               <l rend="indent" id="L8021">Calm and serene thy moments glide along,</l>
               <l n="L8022">And may the muse inspire each future song!</l>
               <l n="L8023">Still, with the sweets of contemplation bless'd,</l>
               <l n="L8024">May peace with balmy wings your soul invest!</l>
               <l n="L8025">But when these shades of time are chas'd away,</l>
               <l n="L8026">And darkness ends in everlasting day,</l>
               <l n="L8027">On what seraphic pinions shall we move,</l>
               <l n="L8028">And view the landscapes in the realms above?</l>
               <l n="L8029">There shall thy tongue in heav'nly murmurs flow,</l>
               <l n="L8030">And there my muse with heav'nly transport glow:</l>
               <l n="L8031">No more to tell of <hi rend="italic">Damon's</hi> tender sighs,</l>
               <l n="L8032">Or rising radiance of <hi rend="italic">Aurora's</hi> eyes,</l>
               <l n="L8033">For nobler themes demand a nobler strain,</l>
               <l n="L8034">And purer language on th' ethereal plain.</l>
               <l n="L8035">Cease, gentle muse! the solemn gloom of night</l>
               <l n="L8036">Now seals the fair creation from my sight.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.228">
            <pb n="116" facs="images/WP-0116.jpg"/>
            <head>To His Honour the Lieutenant-Governor, on the Death of his Lady.</head>
            <opener><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 24, 1773.</opener>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1445">
               <l n="L8037">ALL-conquering Death! by thy resistless pow'r,</l>
               <l n="L8038">Hope's tow'ring plumage falls to rise no more!</l>
               <l n="L8039">Of scenes terrestrial how the glories fly,</l>
               <l n="L8040">Forget their splendors, and submit to die!</l>
               <l n="L8041">Who ere escap'd thee, but the saint <note n="*" id="p116.n1"
                     >Enoch.</note> of old</l>
               <l n="L8042">Beyond the flood in sacred annals told,</l>
               <l n="L8043">And the great sage, <note n="+" id="p116.n2">Elijah.</note> whom fiery
                  courses drew</l>
               <l n="L8044">To heav'n's bright portals from <hi rend="italic">Elisha's</hi>
                  view;</l>
               <l n="L8045">Wond'ring he gaz'd at the refulgent car,</l>
               <l n="L8046">Then snatch'd the mantle floating on the air.</l>
               <l n="L8047">From <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> these only could exemption boast,</l>
               <l n="L8048">And without dying gain'd th' immortal coast.</l>
               <l n="L8049">Not falling millions sate the tyrant's mind,</l>
               <l n="L8050">Nor can the victor's progress be confin'd.</l>
               <l n="L8051">But cease thy strife with <hi rend="italic">Death</hi>, fond <hi
                     rend="italic">Nature,</hi> cease:</l>
               <l n="L8052">He leads the <hi rend="italic">virtuous</hi> to the realms of
                  peace;</l>
               <pb n="117" facs="images/WP-0117.jpg"/>
               <l n="L8053">His to conduct to the immortal plains,</l>
               <l n="L8054">Where heav'n's Supreme in bliss and glory reigns.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1446">
               <l rend="indent" id="L8055">There sits, illustrious Sir, thy beauteous spouse;</l>
               <l n="L8056">A gem-blaz'd circle beaming on her brows.</l>
               <l n="L8057">Hail'd with acclaim among the heav'nly choirs,</l>
               <l n="L8058">Her soul new-kindling with seraphic fires,</l>
               <l n="L8059">To notes divine she tunes the vocal strings,</l>
               <l n="L8060">While heav'n's high concave with the music rings.</l>
               <l n="L8061"><hi rend="italic">Virtue's</hi> rewards can mortal pencil paint?</l>
               <l n="L8062">No -- all descriptive arts, and eloquence are faint;</l>
               <l n="L8063">Nor canst thou, <hi rend="italic">Oliver</hi>, assent refuse</l>
               <l n="L8064">To heav'nly tidings from the <hi rend="italic">Afric</hi> muse.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1447">
               <l rend="indent" id="L8065">As soon may change thy laws, eternal <hi rend="italic"
                     >fate</hi>,</l>
               <l n="L8066">As the saint miss the glories I relate;</l>
               <l n="L8067">Or her <hi rend="italic">Benevolence</hi> forgotten lie,</l>
               <l n="L8068">Which wip'd the trick'ling tear from <hi rend="italic">Mis'ry's</hi>
                  eye.</l>
               <l n="L8069">Whene'er the adverse winds were known to blow,</l>
               <l n="L8070">When loss to loss <note n="*" id="p117.n1">Three amiable Daughters who
                     died when just arrived to Womens Estate.</note> ensu'd, and woe to woe,</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="images/WP-0118.jpg"/>
               <l n="L8071">Calm and serene beneath her father's hand</l>
               <l n="L8072">She sat resign'd to the divine command.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1448">
               <l rend="indent" id="L8073">No longer then, great Sir, her death deplore,</l>
               <l n="L8074">And let us hear the mournful sigh no more,</l>
               <l n="L8075">Restrain the sorrow streaming from thine eye,</l>
               <l n="L8076">Be all thy future moments crown'd with joy!</l>
               <l n="L8077">Nor let thy wishes be to earth confin'd,</l>
               <l n="L8078">But soaring high pursue th' unbodied mind.</l>
               <l n="L8079">Forgive the muse, forgive th' advent'rous lays,</l>
               <l n="L8080">That fain thy soul to heav'nly scenes would raise.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.229">
            <pb n="119" facs="images/WP-0119.jpg"/>
            <head>A Farewel to AMERICA.</head>
            <opener>To Mrs. S. W.</opener>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1449">
               <head type="verse">I.</head>
               <l n="L8081">ADIEU, <hi rend="italic">New-England's</hi> smiling meads,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8082">Adieu, the flow'ry plain:</l>
               <l n="L8083">I leave thine op'ning charms, O spring,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8084">And tempt the roaring main.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1450">
               <head type="verse">II.</head>
               <l n="L8085">In vain for me the flow'rets rise,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8086">And boast their gaudy pride,</l>
               <l n="L8087">While here beneath the northern skies</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8088">I mourn for <hi rend="italic">health</hi> deny'd.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1451">
               <head type="verse">III.</head>
               <l n="L8089">Celestial maid of rosy hue,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8090">O let me feel thy reign!</l>
               <l n="L8091">I languish till thy face I view,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8092">Thy vanish'd joys regain.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="120" facs="images/WP-0120.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1452">
               <head type="verse">IV.</head>
               <l n="L8093"><hi rend="italic">Susannah</hi> mourns, nor can I bear</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8094">To see the crystal show'r,</l>
               <l n="L8095">Or mark the tender falling tear</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8096">At sad departure's hour;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1453">
               <head type="verse">V.</head>
               <l n="L8097">Not unregarding can I see</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8098">Her soul with grief opprest:</l>
               <l n="L8099">But let no sighs, no groans for me,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8100">Steal from her pensive breast.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1454">
               <head type="verse">VI.</head>
               <l n="L8101">In vain the feather'd warblers sing,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8102">In vain the garden blooms,</l>
               <l n="L8103">And on the bosom of the spring</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8104">Breathes out her sweet perfumes</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1455">
               <head type="verse">VII.</head>
               <l n="L8105">While for <hi rend="italic">Britannia's</hi> distant shore</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8106">We sweep the liquid plain,</l>
               <l n="L8107">And with astonish'd eyes explore</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8108">The wide-extended main.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="121" facs="images/WP-0121.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1456">
               <head type="verse">VIII.</head>
               <l n="L8109">Lo! <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> appears! celestial dame!</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8110">Complacent and serene,</l>
               <l n="L8111">With <hi rend="italic">Hebe's</hi> mantle o'er her Frame,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8112">With soul-delighting mein.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1457">
               <head type="verse">IX.</head>
               <l n="L8113">To mark the vale where <hi rend="italic">London</hi> lies</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8114">With misty vapours crown'd,</l>
               <l n="L8115">Which cloud <hi rend="italic">Aurora's</hi> thousand dyes,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8116">And veil her charms around,</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1458">
               <head type="verse">X.</head>
               <l n="L8117">Why, Phoebus, moves thy car so slow?</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8118">So slow thy rising ray?</l>
               <l n="L8119">Give us the famous town to view,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8120">Thou glorious king of day!</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1459">
               <head type="verse">XI.</head>
               <l n="L8121">For thee, <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi>, I resign</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8122"><hi rend="italic">New-England's</hi> smiling fields;</l>
               <l n="L8123">To view again her charms divine,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8124">What joy the prospect yields!</l>
            </lg>

            <pb n="122" facs="images/WP-0122.jpg"/>
            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1460">
               <head type="verse">XII.</head>
               <l n="L8125">But thou! Temptation hence away,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8126">With all thy fatal train</l>
               <l n="L8127">Nor once seduce my soul away,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8128">By thine enchanting strain.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1461">
               <head type="verse">XIII.</head>
               <l n="L8129">Thrice happy they, whose heav'nly shield</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8130">Secures their souls from harms,</l>
               <l n="L8131">And fell <hi rend="italic">Temptation</hi> on the field</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8132">Of all its pow'r disarms!</l>
            </lg>
            <closer><hi rend="italic">Boston, May </hi>7, 1773.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.230">

            <pb n="123" facs="images/WP-0123.jpg"/>
            <head> A REBUS, by <hi rend="italic">I. B.</hi></head>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1462">
               <head type="verse">I.</head>
               <l n="L8133">A BIRD delicious to the taste,</l>
               <l n="L8134">On which an army once did feast,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8135">Sent by an hand unseen;</l>
               <l n="L8136">A creature of the horned race,</l>
               <l n="L8137">Which <hi rend="italic">Britain's</hi> royal standards grace;</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8138">A gem of vivid green;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1463">
               <head type="verse">II.</head>
               <l n="L8139">A town of gaiety and sport,</l>
               <l n="L8140">Where beaux and beauteous nymphs resort,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8141">And gallantry doth reign;</l>
               <l n="L8142">A <hi rend="italic">Dardan</hi> hero fam'd of old</l>
               <l n="L8143">For youth and beauty, as we're told,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8144">And by a monarch slain;</l>
            </lg>

            <lg type="heroic couplets" id="LG1464">
               <head type="verse">III.</head>
               <l n="L8145">A peer of popular applause,</l>
               <l n="L8146">Who doth our violated laws,</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8147">And grievances proclaim.</l>
               <l n="L8148">Th' initials show a vanquish'd town,</l>
               <l n="L8149">That adds fresh glory and renown</l>
               <l rend="indent" id="L8150">To old <hi rend="italic">Britannia's</hi> fame.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" id="div.231">
            <pb n="124" facs="images/WP-0124.jpg"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER to the <hi rend="italic">Rebus</hi>, by the Author of these
               POEMS,</head>


            <l n="1">THE poet asks, and <hi rend="italic">Phillis</hi> can't refuse</l>
            <l n="2">To shew th'obedience of the Infant muse.</l>
            <l n="3">She knows the <hi rend="italic">Quail</hi> of most inviting taste</l>
            <l n="4">Fed <hi rend="italic">Israel's</hi> army in the dreary waste;</l>
            <l n="5">And what's on <hi rend="italic">Britain's</hi> royal standard borne,</l>
            <l n="6">But the tall, graceful, rampant <hi rend="italic">Unicorn</hi>?</l>
            <l n="7">The <hi rend="italic">Emerald</hi> with a vivid verdure glows</l>
            <l n="8">Among the gems which regal crowns compose;</l>
            <l n="9"><hi rend="italic">Boston's</hi> a town, polite and debonair,</l>
            <l n="10">To which the beaux and beauteous nymphs repair,</l>
            <l n="11">Each <hi rend="italic">Helen</hi> strikes the mind with sweet
               surprise,</l>
            <l n="12">While living lightning flashes from her eyes,</l>
            <l n="13">See young <hi rend="italic">Euphorbus</hi> of the <hi rend="italic"
                  >Dardan</hi> line</l>
            <l n="14">By <hi rend="italic">Menelaus'</hi> hand to death resign:</l>
            <l n="15">The well known peer of popular applause</l>
            <l n="16">Is <hi rend="italic">C--m</hi> zealous to support our laws.</l>
            <l rend="indent" id="17"><hi rend="italic">Quebec</hi> now vanquish'd must obey,</l>
            <l rend="indent" id="18">She too must annual tribute pay</l>
            <l rend="indent" id="19">To <hi rend="italic">Britain</hi> of immortal fame,</l>
            <l rend="indent" id="20">And add new glory to her name.</l>



         </div>
         <closer>FINIS.</closer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <head>Editorial Annotations</head>
            <div>
               <head>"TO THE UNIVERSITY OF CAMBRIDGE, IN NEW-ENGLAND"</head>
               <note xml:id="n001" target="a001" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><graphic url="http://www.courses.fas.harvard.edu/~hsb41/slides/revere_harvard_engraving.jpg" width="300" style="float:right"/>After describing her own
                     educational journey, Wheatley advises students at the University of Cambridge
                     in New England to appreciate and "[i]mprove" (21) the privilege of their
                     education by "shunn[ing]" (25) the "transient sweetness" (29) of sin using a
                     variety of religious images. The University of Cambridge in New England is now
                     known as <ref
                        target="https://www.harvard.edu/about-harvard/harvard-glance/history/historical-facts"
                        >Harvard University</ref>. <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pyf-VckC5PgC">According to
                        Katherine Clay Bassard</ref>, Wheatley wrote this poem when she was about
                  fourteen years old (41). The engraving included here is by Paul Revere and shows "A Westerly View of The Colledges in Cambridge New England" (1767), <ref target="http://sites.fas.harvard.edu/%7Ehsb41/Inventing_Harvard/colonial_harvard.html">via the President and Fellows of Harvard College</ref>.<ptr target="#cambridgeA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n002" target="a002" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>Wheatley works from the premise,
                     commonly used among early women writers and the enslaved who were restricted
                     from intellectual pursuits like writing, that her desire to write is
                     "intrinsic" (1) or God-given, and therefore appropriate. The word "ardor" also
                     connotes physical desire and flame-like passion, according to the OED (n.3).
                        <ptr target="#ardorA"/>
                  </p></note>
               <note xml:id="n003" target="a003" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>According to <ref
                        target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0104%3Aalphabetic+letter%3DM%3Aentry+group%3D31%3Aentry%3Dmusae-bio-1"
                           ><hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and
                           Mythology</hi></ref>, the Muses are inspiring goddesses of song" who
                     presid[e] over the different kinds of poetry, and over the arts and sciences."
                     The invocation of the muse to aid the poet's work is often used by
                     neoclassical authors like those whom Wheatley has clearly read and was
                     influenced by, including <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/685428">Milton</ref> and <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCBgqF1yFXYC">Pope</ref>. However, Hilene Flanzbaum suggests
                     that Wheatleys notably frequent invocation of the muse is more significant
                     than formulaic or imitative--it is the very means by which she usurps power
                     for herself and claims a berth for her own thoughts, emotions and desires. And
                     while some may claim that these functions accompany any appearance of the muse,
                     when the muses bestow their power on a black female slave, they transport
                     Wheatley to a domain surprisingly free of restriction and previously forbidden
                        (<ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/468067">Unprecedented Liberties 75</ref>). <ptr target="#museA"
                     /></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n004" target="a004" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>Wheatley here alludes to <ref
                        target="https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Exodus-Chapter-10/">Exodus 10:21-22</ref>, wherein the ninth plague of darkness is
                     visited upon Egypt. This reference is also in line with contemporary
                     Orientalist notions about Egypt and Egyptian religiosity, which was believed to
                     be full of occult practices. Early nineteenth-century British historian and
                     scholar Thomas Maurice explores these ideas of idolatry and superstition in
                        <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=aItPAAAAYAAJ">Observations on
                        the Remains of Ancient Egyptian Grandeur and Superstition</ref>. A detailed
                     focus on the Egyptian religious practices can be found in the chapter
                     "Strictures on the superstitious rites of the Egyptians, particularly on the
                     Nefarious Worship paid to Beasts, Esteemed Sacred, and called in Scripture the
                     Abominations of Egypt" (74-83). <ptr target="#egyptA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n005" target="a005" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><graphic url="http://s3.amazonaws.com/ourheritagemedia%2Foriginal%2F2bab3e89ed86399fa4795f0459931566.jpg" width="300" style="float:right"/>The sixteenth- and
                     seventeenth-century development of the microscope and the telescope had made
                     great scientific advancements possible, especially in astronomy; in the title page and pull-out image represented here, you can see an eighteenth-century orrery--a scientific clockwork instrument used to dramatize the motion of the planets in the solar system (via the University of Otago). Possibly an
                     allusion to Alexander Pope's 1733-34 <ref
                        target="https://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poems/essay-man-epistle-i"><hi
                           rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> (I.23-28)</ref>, Wheatley here may also be referencing 
                     contemporary scientific thought about the <ref target="https://www.wwnorton.com/college/english/nael/18century/topic_3/welcome.htm">plurality of worlds</ref>.<ptr
                        target="#systemsA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n006" target="a006" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p> According to the Oxford English
                     Dictionary <ref target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/49189">deign</ref> means
                     "to think it worthy of oneself" or "to think fit" (n.1a). Today, it typically
                     has a negative connotation, though it does not here. <ptr target="#deignA"
                     /></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n007" trget="a007" type="editorial" resp="JW">
                  <p><graphic url="https://stacks.stanford.edu/image/iiif/hj384dy5623%2FAM_0241/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg" width="300" style="float:right"/>According to the OED, the word <ref target="http://www.oed.com">Ethiop</ref>
                     would have been used during Wheatley's time most often to refer to "[a] black
                     or dark-skinned person; a black African," and only occasionally to the country
                     of Ethiopia, specifically (n.A). Included here, <ref target="https://exhibits.stanford.edu/maps-of-africa/catalog/hj384dy5623">via the Norwich Collection at Stanford University</ref>, is a 1666 map of Africa and the surrounding oceans, embellished with a variety of images. <ptr target="#ethiopA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n008" target="a008" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>In theological discussion, the
                     word <ref target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/140642">perdition</ref> means
                     "the state of final spiritual ruin or damnation; the consignment of the
                     unredeemed or wicked and impenitent soul to hell; the fate of those in hell;
                     eternal death" (OED, "perdition" n.2a). In more general terms, it suggests ruin or degradation (n.1a). <ptr target="#perditionA"/></p></note>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>"On being brought from AFRICA to AMERICA"</head>
               <note xml:id="n009" target="a009" type="editorial" resp="TH"><p>Wheatley's description of those who
                     "view our sable race with scornful eye" (5) is a clear rejection of what <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">Lena Hill describes
                        as "ignorant" interpretations of "visual blackness" (37-38)</ref>, as is her
                     attribution of speech in direct discourse: "'Their color is a diabolic die'"
                     (6). Henry Louis Gates argues that Wheatley's very presence as an author
                     complicated assumptions of "natural" inferiority. For more about this topic,
                     see Gates' <hi rend="italic"><ref
                           target="https://books.google.com/books?id=vzXnCwAAQBAJ">Figures in
                           Black</ref></hi> and Walt Nott's discussion of Wheatley's public persona
                     in <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/468063">"From 'Uncultivated
                        Barbarian' to 'Poetical Genius': The Public Presence of Phillis
                        Wheatley."</ref>
                     <ptr target="#viewA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n010" target="a010" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><graphic url="http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/external/brooksslaveship-tl.jpg" width="300" style="float:right"/>The title of one Wheatley's most
                     (in)famous poems, "On being brought from AFRICA to AMERICA" alludes to the
                     experiences of many Africans who became subject to the <ref
                        target="http://www.unesco.org/new/en/social-and-human-sciences/themes/slave-route/transatlantic-slave-trade/"
                        >transatlantic slave trade</ref>. Wheatley uses biblical references and
                     direct address to appeal to a Christian audience, while also defending the
                     ability of her "sable race" to become "refin'd" through Christian theology.
                     Henry Louis Gates, who in <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=vzXnCwAAQBAJ"><hi rend="italic">Figures in Black:
                           Words, Signs, and the "Racial" Self</hi></ref> (1989) situates Wheatley
                     as an important voice in the eighteenth-century debate about natural human
                     rights, summarizes the "recurrent suggestion that Wheatley has remained aloof
                     from matters that were in any sense racial, or more correctly, 'positively'
                     racial," as a "misreading" (74-75). Notable for the complexity of its brief
                     discussion of blackness in the Christian slaveholding American republic, this
                     poem in particular is frequently criticized for its apparent rejection of
                     Africa and African-ness. However, Wheatley was working within a non-free
                     context, and her critique of slavery is mediated by Christianity acquired as
                     part of her enslavement. For a fuller exploration of Wheatleys poem, see <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/books?id=xjBRKDHdMmsC"><hi rend="italic">Authority and Female Authorship in Colonial
                           America</hi>, by William Scheick (especially chapter 4)</ref>. The image included here, <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/item106661.html">via the British Library</ref>, shows a diagram of the Brookes' slave ship (c.1801).<ptr
                        target="#broughtA"/></p></note>
               <note xml:id="n011" target="a011" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>The phrase "black as Cain" is a
                     distortion of the biblical idea of the mark of Cain <ref
                        target="https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Genesis-4-15/">(Genesis
                        4:15)</ref> and was used as justification for the enslavement of people of
                     color. Many scholars point out that this was Wheatley's "most maligned poem,"
                        <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">(Hill 37)</ref>
                     which is ultimately about the inclusion of Africans in the "Christian family"
                     and her critique of "ignorant" interpretations of "visual blackness" <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">(37-38)</ref>. For
                     an interesting contemporary read of the mark of Cain in anti-abolitionist
                     discourse, see Josiah Priest's <ref
                        target="https://books.google.com/books?id=nLgJAAAAIAAJ"><hi rend="italic"
                           >Slavery as it Relates to the Negro</hi> (1843)</ref>, where he rejects
                     the possibility that dark-skinned peoples could be related to Adam by blood
                        <ref target="https://archive.org/details/slaveryasitrela00priegoog"
                        >(134-136)</ref>. For a larger reading of Wheatley's use of blackness and
                     the role of blackness in the early American imagination, see Lena Hill's
                     chapter "Witnessing Moral Authority in Pre-Abolition Literature," from <hi
                        rend="italic"><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=nLgJAAAAIAAJ"
                           >Visualizing Blackness and the Creation of the African American Literary
                           Tradition</ref></hi> (2014)<ptr target="#cainA"/></p>
               </note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
      <tooltip_notes>
         <div class="tooltip_templates">
            
           
            <span id="cambridge" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><img src="http://www.courses.fas.harvard.edu/~hsb41/slides/revere_harvard_engraving.jpg" width="100%"/>After describing her own
                  educational journey, Wheatley advises students at the University of Cambridge
                  in New England to appreciate and "[i]mprove" (21) the privilege of their
                  education by "shunn[ing]" (25) the "transient sweetness" (29) of sin using a
                  variety of religious images. The University of Cambridge in New England is now
                  known as <a href="https://www.harvard.edu/about-harvard/harvard-glance/history/historical-facts"
                     >Harvard University</a>. <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=pyf-VckC5PgC">According to
                        Katherine Clay Bassard</a>, Wheatley wrote this poem when she was about
                  fourteen years old (41). For more information on women's writing in the early
                  . The engraving included here is by Paul Revere and shows "A Westerly View of The Colledges in Cambridge New England" (1767), <a href="http://sites.fas.harvard.edu/%7Ehsb41/Inventing_Harvard/colonial_harvard.html">via the President and Fellows of Harvard College</a>.</p></span>
               <span id="ardor" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>Wheatley works from the premise,
                  commonly used among early women writers and the enslaved who were restricted
                  from intellectual pursuits like writing, that her desire to write is
                  "intrinsic" (1) or God-given, and therefore appropriate. The word "ardor" also
                  connotes physical desire and flame-like passion, according to the OED (n.3).
                 
               </p></span>
               <span id="muse" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>According to <a href="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0104%3Aalphabetic+letter%3DM%3Aentry+group%3D31%3Aentry%3Dmusae-bio-1"
                  ><hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and
                     Mythology</hi></a>, the Muses are inspiring goddesses of song" who
                  presid[e] over the different kinds of poetry, and over the arts and sciences."
                  The invocation of the muse to aid the poet's work is often used by
                  neoclassical authors like those whom Wheatley has clearly read and was
                  influenced by, including <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/685428">Milton</a> and <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCBgqF1yFXYC">Pope</a>. However, Hilene Flanzbaum suggests
                  that Wheatleys notably frequent invocation of the muse is more significant
                  than formulaic or imitative--it is the very means by which she usurps power
                  for herself and claims a berth for her own thoughts, emotions and desires. And
                  while some may claim that these functions accompany any appearance of the muse,
                  when the muses bestow their power on a black female slave, they transport
                  Wheatley to a domain surprisingly free of restriction and previously forbidden
                  (<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/468067">Unprecedented Liberties 75</a>). 
                  </p></span>
               <span id="egyptian" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>Wheatley here alludes to <a
                  href="https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Exodus-Chapter-10/">Exodus 10:21-22</a>, wherein the ninth plague of darkness is
                  visited upon Egypt. This reference is also in line with contemporary
                  Orientalist notions about Egypt and Egyptian religiosity, which was believed to
                  be full of occult practices. Early nineteenth-century British historian and
                  scholar Thomas Maurice explores these ideas of idolatry and superstition in
                  <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=aItPAAAAYAAJ">Observations on
                     the Remains of Ancient Egyptian Grandeur and Superstition</a>. A detailed
                  focus on the Egyptian religious practices can be found in the chapter
                  "Strictures on the superstitious rites of the Egyptians, particularly on the
                  Nefarious Worship paid to Beasts, Esteemed Sacred, and called in Scripture the
                  Abominations of Egypt" (74-83).</p></span>
               <span id="systems" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><img src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/ourheritagemedia%2Foriginal%2F2bab3e89ed86399fa4795f0459931566.jpg" width="100%"/>The sixteenth- and
                  seventeenth-century development of the microscope and the telescope had made
                  great scientific advancements possible, especially in astronomy; in the title page and pull-out image represented here, you can see an eighteenth-century orrery--a scientific clockwork instrument used to dramatize the motion of the planets in the solar system (via the University of Otago). Possibly an
                  allusion to Alexander Pope's 1733-34 <a
                     href="https://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poems/essay-man-epistle-i"><hi
                        rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> (I.23-28)</a>, Wheatley here may also be referencing 
                  contemporary scientific thought about the <a href="https://www.wwnorton.com/college/english/nael/18century/topic_3/welcome.htm">plurality of worlds</a>.
                     </p></span>
               <span id="deign" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p> According to the Oxford English
                  Dictionary <a href="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/49189">deign</a> means
                  "to think it worthy of oneself" or "to think fit" (n.1a). Today, it typically
                  has a negative connotation, though it does not here. </p></span>
               <span id="ethiop" type="editorial" resp="JW">
                  <p><img src="https://stacks.stanford.edu/image/iiif/hj384dy5623%2FAM_0241/full/!1000,1000/0/default.jpg" width="100%"/>According to the OED, the word <a href="http://www.oed.com">Ethiop</a>
                     would have been used during Wheatley's time most often to refer to "[a] black
                     or dark-skinned person; a black African," and only occasionally to the country
                     of Ethiopia, specifically (n.A). Included here, <a href="https://exhibits.stanford.edu/maps-of-africa/catalog/hj384dy5623">via the Norwich Collection at Stanford University</a>, is a 1666 map of Africa and the surrounding oceans, embellished with a variety of images. <ptr href="#ethiopA"/></p></span>
               <span id="perdition" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>In theological discussion, the
                  word <a href="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/140642">perdition</a> means
                  "the state of final spiritual ruin or damnation; the consignment of the
                  unredeemed or wicked and impenitent soul to hell; the fate of those in hell;
                  eternal death" (OED, "perdition" n.2a). In more general terms, it suggests ruin or degradation (n.1a). </p></span>
            
            
               <span id="view" type="editorial" resp="TH"><p>Wheatley's description of those who
                  "view our sable race with scornful eye" (5) is a clear rejection of what <a
                     href="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">Lena Hill describes
                     as "ignorant" interpretations of "visual blackness" (37-38)</a>, as is her
                  attribution of speech in direct discourse: "'Their color is a diabolic die'"
                  (6). Henry Louis Gates argues that Wheatley's very presence as an author
                  complicated assumptions of "natural" inferiority. For more about this topic,
                  see Gates' <hi rend="italic"><a
                     href="https://books.google.com/books?id=vzXnCwAAQBAJ">Figures in
                     Black</a></hi> and Walt Nott's discussion of Wheatley's public persona
                  in <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/468063">"From 'Uncultivated
                     Barbarian' to 'Poetical Genius': The Public Presence of Phillis
                     Wheatley."</a>
                  </p></span>
               <span id="brought" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p><img src="http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/external/brooksslaveship-tl.jpg" width="100%"/>The title of one Wheatley's most
                  (in)famous poems, "On being brought from AFRICA to AMERICA" alludes to the
                  experiences of many Africans who became subject to the <a
                     href="http://www.unesco.org/new/en/social-and-human-sciences/themes/slave-route/transatlantic-slave-trade/"
                     >transatlantic slave trade</a>. Wheatley uses biblical references and
                  direct address to appeal to a Christian audience, while also defending the
                  ability of her "sable race" to become "refin'd" through Christian theology.
                  Henry Louis Gates, who in <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=vzXnCwAAQBAJ"><hi rend="italic">Figures in Black:
                     Words, Signs, and the "Racial" Self</hi></a> (1989) situates Wheatley
                  as an important voice in the eighteenth-century debate about natural human
                  rights, summarizes the "recurrent suggestion that Wheatley has remained aloof
                  from matters that were in any sense racial, or more correctly, 'positively'
                  racial," as a "misreading" (74-75). Notable for the complexity of its brief
                  discussion of blackness in the Christian slaveholding American republic, this
                  poem in particular is frequently criticized for its apparent rejection of
                  Africa and African-ness. However, Wheatley was working within a non-free
                  context, and her critique of slavery is mediated by Christianity acquired as
                  part of her enslavement. For a fuller exploration of Wheatleys poem, see <a
                     href="https://books.google.com/books?id=xjBRKDHdMmsC"><hi rend="italic">Authority and Female Authorship in Colonial
                        America</hi>, by William Scheick (especially chapter 4)</a>. The image included here, <a href="http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/item106661.html">via the British Library</a>, shows a diagram of the Brookes' slave ship (c.1801).</p></span>
               <span id="cain" type="editorial" resp="JW"><p>The phrase "black as Cain" is a
                  distortion of the biblical idea of the mark of Cain <a
                     href="https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Genesis-4-15/">(Genesis
                     4:15)</a> and was used as justification for the enslavement of people of
                  color. Many scholars point out that this was Wheatley's "most maligned poem,"
                  <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">(Hill 37)</a>
                  which is ultimately about the inclusion of Africans in the "Christian family"
                  and her critique of "ignorant" interpretations of "visual blackness" <a
                     href="https://books.google.com/books?id=pxaTAgAAQBAJ">(37-38)</a>. For
                  an interesting contemporary read of the mark of Cain in anti-abolitionist
                  discourse, see Josiah Priest's <a
                     href="https://books.google.com/books?id=nLgJAAAAIAAJ"><hi rend="italic"
                        >Slavery as it Relates to the Negro</hi> (1843)</a>, where he rejects
                  the possibility that dark-skinned peoples could be related to Adam by blood
                  <a href="https://archive.org/details/slaveryasitrela00priegoog"
                     >(134-136)</a>. For a larger reading of Wheatley's use of blackness and
                  the role of blackness in the early American imagination, see Lena Hill's
                  chapter "Witnessing Moral Authority in Pre-Abolition Literature," from <hi
                     rend="italic"><a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=nLgJAAAAIAAJ"
                        >Visualizing Blackness and the Creation of the African American Literary
                        Tradition</a></hi> (2014)</p>
               </span>
            
         </div>
      </tooltip_notes>
   </text>



</TEI>
