<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="burney-letter-march-22-1812">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter to Esther Burney, Dated 22 March 1812]</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80075853">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Frances</forename>
                            <surname>Burney</surname>
                            <!-- <addName>D'Arblay</addName> -->
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="000">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
                            <forename>Tonya</forename>
                            <surname>Howe</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>

                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>

                    <name>Tonya Howe</name>

                </respStmt>

                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>

                    <analytic>

                        <title>[Letter to Esther Burney, Dated 22 March 1812]</title>

                    </analytic>

                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80075853">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Frances</forename>
                                    <surname>Burney</surname>
                                    <!-- <addName>D'Arblay</addName> -->
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>

                        <title>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American
                            Literature, The New York Public Library</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace> Online </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>The New York Public Library Digital Collections</publisher>
                            <date when="1812">1803-1812</date>
                            <note>In 1810, Burney became alarmed by a pain in her breast, diagnosed
                                as cancer. In September of the following year, she underwent a
                                radical double mastectomy, without anesthetic. This letter, a copy
                                Burney recorded in her journals, is notable for a variety of
                                reasons, not least of which is that it is a rare example of a
                                first-person account of such an operation. It is also an excellent
                                representative of the genre of letter-writing during the period,
                                when of course there were no other methods of long-distance
                                communication; it was used for conducting business, communicating
                                news, reaching out to friends and family, and more. Many manuals
                                teaching letter-writing to the new "middling sort" were available
                                during the eighteenth century; these manuals taught conventions and
                                even offered sample letters for different purposes. Samuel
                                Richardson, whose epistolary novel <hi rend="italic">Pamela</hi>
                                (1740)--an "epistolary" novel was written in the form of letters
                                sent between the different characters--was a bestseller, a testament
                                to the compelling nature of the personal letter during the period.
                                Richardson's <hi rend="italic">Letters Written to and for Particular
                                    Friends</hi>, a letter-writing manual with examples, was
                                calibrated to the close, personal relationship, while Daniel Defoe's
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Complete English Tradesman</hi> (1725) was
                                geared toward those needing to correspond on business matters.
                                Writing conventions differed by gender, age, class, and according to
                                the relationship between author and addressee. Among the many rules
                                for letter-writers, manuals encouraged writers to compose with the
                                same voice they would use to converse directly with that person.
                                Burney's letter to her sister vividly captures that voice and their
                                relationship. Young writers were also taught to cultivate their
                                "hand" or handwriting; in this letter, you can see that Burney's
                                hand is not as neat as you might expect. This is because the letter
                                was transcribed or copied down in her journal--a common way to keep
                                records--before the actual letter was sent off to her sister.</note>
                            <note>This digital edition of Frances Burney's harrowing letter to
                                Esther is drawn from the facsimile of the original housed in the
                                Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American
                                Literature at The New York Public Library, made possible through the
                                Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations. Readers can explore the
                                document, identifiable as "Burney, Esther Burney, her sister. 1 ALS
                                and 4 AL to", online, at <ref
                                    target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/13e47ec0-d47e-0135-f4b9-11359cd62681"
                                    >https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/13e47ec0-d47e-0135-f4b9-11359cd62681</ref>.
                                Our transcription draws on a handout from Kimberly Cox (Chadron
                                State College) available at <ref
                                    target="https://britlit-middleagestoeighteenthcentury.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/2/8/44283759/burney_a_mastectomy.pdf"
                                    >https://britlit-middleagestoeighteenthcentury.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/2/8/44283759/burney_a_mastectomy.pdf</ref>
                                and has been updated to reflect the facsimile. We especially thank
                                The New York Public Library for making this material freely
                                available. </note>
                            <note>For more information on letter writing during the long eighteenth century, see 
                                Louise Curran's <ref target="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Samuel_Richardson_and_the_Art_of_Letter/imWSCwAAQBAJ"><hi rend="italic">Samuel Richardson and the Art of Letter-Writing</hi> (2016)</ref> 
                                and Susan Whyman's <ref target="https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Pen_and_the_People/xN-lKMF3MogC"><hi rend="italic">The Pen and the People: English Letter Writers 1660-1800</hi> (2009)</ref>.</note>
                        </imprint>



                    </monogr>

                </biblStruct>

            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letters">
                <channel mode="w">manuscript</channel>
                <constitution type="single">journal entry</constitution>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="applicable"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="mew"/>
                <purpose type="express" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>

            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>

                <setting>

                    <time from="1800" to="1815">Early 19th Century</time>

                </setting>

            </settingDesc>

        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>

            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up
                    selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British
                    and American literature. This project is was initially funded by the National
                    Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of
                    Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-05-25" who="editors.xml#TH">First pass xml.</change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[1]" facs="pageImages/00.jpeg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart>[Letter to Esther Burney, Dated 22 March 1812]</titlePart>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div type="letter">
                <dateline>
                    <date>March 22<lb/>1812<lb/></date>
                </dateline>

                <p>P. S. I have promised my dearest Esther a Volume– &amp; here it is: I am at this
                    moment quite well– so are my Alexanders. Read, therefore, this narrative at your
                    leisure, &amp; without emotion--for all has ended happily. I will send the rest
                    by the very first opportunity: I seize this present with eagerness– oh let none–
                    none pass by that may bring me a return!– I have no more yet written.</p>
                <dateline>March 22<lb/>1812</dateline>
                <p>Separated as I have now so long—long been from my dearest
                    Father—Brothers—Sisters— Nieces, and Native Friends, I would spare, at least,
                    their kind hearts any grief for me but what they must inevitably feel in
                    reflecting upon the sorrow of such absence to one so tenderly attached to all
                    her first and for-ever so dear and regretted ties—nevertheless, if they should
                    hear that I have been dangerously ill from any hand but my own, they might have
                    doubts of my perfect recovery which my own alone can obviate. And how can I hope
                    they will escape hearing what has reached Seville to the South, and
                    Constantinople to the East? from both I have had messages—yet nothing could urge
                    me to this communication till I heard that M. de Boinville had written it to his
                    Wife, without any precaution, because in ignorance of my plan of silence. Still
                    I must hope it may never travel to my dearest Father—But to You, my beloved
                    Esther, who, living more in the World, will surely hear it ere long, to you I
                    will write the whole history, certain that, from the moment you know any evil
                    has befallen me your kind kind heart will be constantly anxious to learn its
                    extent and its circumstances, as well as its termination.</p>
                <p>About August, in the year 1810, I began to by annoyed by a small pain in my
                    breast, which went on augmenting from week to week, yet, being rather heavy than
                    acute, without causing me any uneasiness with respect to consequences: Alas,
                    “what was ignorance?” The most sympathising of Partners, however, was more
                    disturbed: not a start, not a wry face, not a movement that indicated pain was
                    unobserved, and he early conceived apprehensions to which I was a stranger. He
                    pressed me to see some Surgeon; I revolted from the idea, and hoped, by care and
                    warmth, to make all succour unnecessary. Thus passed some months, during which
                    Madame de Maisonneuve, my particularly intimate friend, joined with M. d’Arblay
                    to press me to consent to an examination. I thought their fears groundless, and
                    could not make so great a conquest over my repugnance. I relate this false
                    confidence, now, as a warning to my dear Esther—my Sisters and Nieces, should
                    any similar sensations excite similar alarm.</p>
                <p>M. d’Arblay now revealed his uneasiness to another of our kind friends, Mme de
                    Tracy, who wrote to me a long and eloquent Letter upon the subject, that began
                    to awaken very unpleasant surmizes: and a conference with her ensued, in which
                    her urgency and representations, aided by her long experience of disease, and
                    most miserable existence by art, subdued me, and, most painfully and
                    reluctantly, I ceased to object, and M. d’Arblay summoned a physician—M.
                    Bourdois? Maria will cry;—No, my dear Maria, I would not give your beau frere
                    that trouble; not him, but Dr Jouart, the physician of Miss. Potts. Thinking but
                    slightly of my statement, he gave me <pb n="[2]" facs="pageImages/01.jpeg"/>some
                    directions that produced no fruit—on the contrary, I grew worse, and M. d’Arblay
                    now would take no denial to my consulting M. Dubois, who had already attended
                    and cured me in an abscess of which Maria, my dearest Esther, can give you the
                    history.</p>
                <p>M. Dubois, the most celebrated surgeon of France, was then appointed accoucheur
                    (obstetrician) to the Empress, and already lodged in the Tuilleries, and in
                    constant attendance: but nothing could slacken the ardour of M. d’Arblay to
                    obtain the first advice. Fortunately for his kind wishes, M. Dubois had retained
                    a partial regard for me from the time of his former attendance, and, when
                    applied to through a third person, he took the first moment of liberty, granted
                    by a promenade taken by the Empress, to come to me. It was now I began to
                    perceive my real danger, M. Dubois gave me a prescription to be pursued for a
                    month, during which time he could not undertake to see me again, an pronounced
                    nothing—but uttered so many charges to me to be tranquil, and to suffer no
                    uneasiness, that I could not but suspect there was room for terrible
                    inquietude.</p>
                <p>My alarm was encreased by the non-appearance of M. d’Arblay after his departure.
                    They had remained together some time in the Book room, and M. d’Arblay did not
                    return—till, unable to bear the suspence, I begged him to come back. He, also,
                    sought then to tranquilize me—but in words only; his looks were shocking! his
                    features, his whole face displayed the bitterest woe. I had not, therefore, much
                    difficulty in telling myself what he endeavoured not to tell me—that a small
                    operation would be necessary to avert evil consequences!—Ah, my dearest Esther,
                    for this I felt no courage—my dread and repugnance, from a thousand reasons
                    besides the pain, almost shook my faculties, and, for some time, I was rather
                    confounded and stupefied than affrighted.— Direful, however was the effect of
                    this interview; the pains became quicker and more violent, and the hardness of
                    the spot affected encreased. I took, but vainly, my proscription, and every
                    symtom grew more serious.</p>
                <p>At that time, M. de Narbonne spoke to M. d’Arblay of a Surgeon of great eminence,
                    M. Larrey, who had cured a polonoise lady of his acquaintance of a similar
                    malady; and, as my horror of an operation was insuperable, M. de Narbonne
                    strongly recommended that I should have recourse to M. Larrey. I thankfully
                    caught at any hope; and another friend of M. d’Arblay gave the same counsel
                    instant, which other, M. Barbier Neuville, has an influence irresistible over
                    this M. Larrey, to whom he wrote the most earnest injunction that he would use
                    every exertion to rescue me from what I so much dreaded. M. Larrey came, though
                    very unwillingly, and full of scruples concerning M. Dubois; nor would he give
                    me his services till I wrote myself to state my affright at the delay of
                    attendance occasioned by the present high office and royal confinement of M.
                    Dubois, and requesting that I might be made over to M. Larrey. An answer such as
                    might be expected arrived, and I was <pb n="[3]" facs="pageImages/02.jpeg"/>now
                    put upon a new regime, and animated by fairest hopes.—</p>
                <p>M. Larrey has proved one of the worthiest, most disinterested, and singularly
                    excellent of men, endowed with real Genius in his profession, though with an
                    ignorance of the World and its usages that induces a naiveté that leads those
                    who do not see him thoroughly to think him not alone simple, but weak. They are
                    mistaken; but his attention and thoughts having exclusively turned one way, he
                    is hardly awake any other. His directions seemed all to succeed, for though I
                    had still cruel seizures of terrible pain, the fits were shorter and more rare,
                    and my spirits revived, and I went out almost daily, and quite daily received to
                    my Apartment some friend or intimate acquaintance, contrarily to my usual mode
                    of sauvagerie (unsociability)—and what friends I have found! what kind,
                    consoling, zealous friends during all this painful period! In fine, I was much
                    better, and every symptom of alarm abated. My good M. Larrey was enchanted, yet
                    so anxious, that he forced me to see le Docteur Ribe, the first anatomist, he
                    said, in France, from his own fear lest he was under any delusion, from the
                    excess of his desire to save me. I was as rebellious to the first visit of this
                    famous anatomist as Maria will tell you I had been to that of M. Dubois, so
                    odious to me was this sort of process: however, I was obliged to submit: and M.
                    Ribe confirmed our best hopes—</p>
                <p>Here, my dearest Esther, I must grow brief, for my theme becomes less
                    pleasant—Sundry circumstances, too long to detail, combined to counter-act all
                    my flattering expectations, and all the skill, and all the cares of my assiduous
                    and excellent Surgeon. The principal of these evils were—the death, broke to me
                    by a newspaper! of the lovely and loved Princess Amelia (at age 27) —the illness
                    of her venerated father (King George III) —and the sudden loss of my nearly
                    adored—my Susan’s nearly worshipped Mr Lock—which terrible calamity reached me
                    in a few lines from Fanny Waddington, when I knew not of any illness or fear!—Oh
                    my Esther, I must indeed be brief, for I am not yet strong enough for
                    sorrow.—The good M. Larrey, when he came to me next after the last of these
                    trials, was quite thrown into a consternation, so changed he found all for the
                    worse—“Et qu’est il donc arrive?” (“And so, what is going on?”) he cried, and
                    presently, sadly, announced his hope of dissolving the hardness were nearly
                    extinguished. M. Ribe was now again called in—but he only corroborated the
                    terrible judgement; yet they allowed me to my pleadings some further essays, and
                    the more easily as the weather was not propitious to any operation. My Exercise,
                    at this time, though always useful and chearing, occasioned me great suffering
                    in its conclusion, from mounting up three pair of stairs: my tenderest Partner,
                    therefore, removed me to La Rue Mirmenil, where I began my Paris residence
                    nearly 10 Years ago!—quite 10 next Month! Here we are <pb n="[4]"
                        facs="pageImages/03.jpeg"/>au premier—but alas—to no effect! once only have
                    I yet descended the short flight of steps from which I had entertained new
                    hopes.</p>
                <p>A Physician was now called in, Dr Moreau, to hear if he could suggest any new
                    means: but Dr Larrey had left him no resources untried. A formal consultation
                    now was held, of Larrey, Ribe, and Moreau—and, in fine, I was formally condemned
                    to an operation by all Three. I was as much astonished as disappointed—for the
                    poor breast was no where discoloured, and not much larger than its healthy
                    neighbour. Yet I felt the evil to be deep, so deep, that I often thought if it
                    could not be dissolved, it could only with life be extirpated. I called up,
                    however, all the reason I possessed, or could assume, and told them that—if they
                    saw no other alternative, I would not resist their opinion and experience—the
                    good Dr Larrey, who, during his long attendance had conceived for me the warmest
                    friendship, had now tears in his Eyes; from my dread he had expected resistance.
                    He proposed again calling in M. Dubois. No, I told him, if I could not by
                    himself be saved, I had no sort of hope elsewhere, and, if it must be, what I
                    wanted in courage should be supplied by Confidence. The good man was now
                    dissatisfied with himself, and declared that I ought to have the First and most
                    eminent advice his Country could afford; “Vous êtes si considerée,” Madame, said
                    he, “ici, que le public même sera mecontent si vous n’avez pas tout le secour
                    que nous avons à vous offrir.—” Yet this modest man is premier chirugien de la
                    Garde Imperiale, and had been lately created a Baron for his eminent
                    services!—M. Dubois, he added, from his super-skill and experience, might yet,
                    perhaps, suggest some cure. This conquered me quickly, ah—Send for him! Send for
                    him! I cried—and Dr Moreau received the commission to consult with him.—</p>
                <p>What an interval was this! Yet my poor M. d’Arblay was more to be pitied than
                    myself, though he knew not the terrible idea I had internally annexed to the
                    trial—but Oh what he suffered!—and with what exquisite tenderness he solaced all
                    that I had to bear! My poor Alex I kept as much as possible, and as long,
                    ignorant of my situation.—M. Dubois behaved extremely well, no pique intervened
                    with the interest he had professed in my well-doing, and his conduct was manly
                    and generous. It was difficult still to see him, but he appointed the earliest
                    day in his power for a general and final consultation. I was informed of it only
                    on the Same day, to avoid any useless agitation. He met here Drs Larrey, Ribe,
                    and Moreau. The case, I saw, offered uncommon difficulties, or presented eminent
                    danger, but the examination over, they desired to consult together. I left
                    them—what an half hour I passed alone!—M. d’Arblay was at his office. Dr Larrey
                    then came to summon me. He did not speak, but looked very like my dear Brother
                    James, to whom he has a personal resemblance that has struck M. d’Arblay as well
                    as myself. I came back, and took my seat, with what calmness I was able. All
                    were silent, and Dr Larrey, I saw, hid himself nearly behind my Sofa. My heart
                    beat fast: I saw all hope was over. I called upon them to speak. M. Dubois then,
                    after a long and unintelligible harangue, from his own disturbance, pronounced
                    my doom. I now saw it was inevitable, and abstained from any further effort.
                    They received my formal consent, and retired to fix a day.</p>
                <pb n="[5]" facs="pageImages/04.jpeg"/>
                <p>All hope of escaping this evil now at an end, I could only console or employ my
                    Mind in considering how to render it less dreadful to M. d’Arblay. M. Dubois had
                    pronounced “il faut s’attendre à souffrir, Je ne veux pas vous tromper—Vous
                    Souffrirez—vous souffrirez beaucoup!—” (“You must expect to suffer, I do not
                    want to deceive you—you will suffer—you will suffer very much!—”) M. Ribe had
                    charged me to cry! to withhold or restrain myself might have seriously bad
                    consequences, he said. M. Moreau, in echoing this injunction, enquired whether I
                    had cried or screamed at the birth of Alexander—Alas, I told him, it had not
                    been possible to do otherwise; Oh then, he answered, there is no fear!—What
                    terrible inferences were here to be drawn! I desired, therefore, that M.
                    d’Arblay might be kept in ignorance of the day might be kept in ignorance of the
                    day till the operation should be over. To this they agreed, except M. Larrey,
                    with high approbation: M. Larrey looked dissentient, but was silent. M. Dubois
                    protested he would not undertake to act, after what he had seen of the agitated
                    spirits of M. d’Arblay if he were present: nor would he suffer me to know the
                    time myself over night; I obtained with difficulty a promise of 4 hours warning,
                    which were essential to me for sundry regulations.</p>
                <p> From this time, I assumed the best spirits in my power, to meet the coming
                    blow;—and support my too sympathising Partner. They would let me make no
                    preparations, refusing to inform me what would be necessary; I have known,
                    since, that Mme de Tessé, an admirable old friend of M. d’Arblay, now mine,
                    equally, and one of the first of her sex, in any country, for uncommon
                    abilities, and nearly universal knowledge, had insisted upon sending me all that
                    might be necessary, and of keeping me in ignorance. M. d’Arblay filled a Closet
                    with Charpie, compresses, and bandages—All that to me was owned, as wanting, was
                    an arm Chair and some Towels.—Many things, however, joined to the depth of my
                    pains, assured me the business was not without danger. I therefore made my
                    Will—unknown, to this moment, to M. d’Arblay, and entrusted it privately to M.
                    La Tour Maubourg, without even letting my friend his Sister, Mme de Maisonneuve,
                    share the secret. M. de Maubourg conveyed it for me to Maria’s excellent M.
                    Gillet, from whom M. de Maubourg brought me directions. As soon as I am able to
                    go out I shall reveal this clandestine affair to M. d’Arblay—till then, if might
                    still affect him. Mme de Maisonneuve desired to be present at the operation;—but
                    I would not inflict such pain. Mme de Chastel belle soeur de Mme de Boinville,
                    would also have sustained the shock; but I secured two Guards, one of whom is
                    known to my two dear Charlottes, Mme Soubiren, portiere de l’Hotel Marengo: a
                    very good Creature, who often amuses me by repeating “ver. vell, Mawm;” which
                    she tells me she learnt of Charlotte the younger, whom she never names but with
                    rapture, The other is a workman whom I have often employed. The kindnesses I
                    received at this period would have made me for-ever love France, had I hitherto
                    been hard enough of heart to hate it—but Mme d’Henin—the tenderness she shewed
                    me surpasses all description. Twice she came to Paris from the Country, to see,
                    watch and sit with me; there is nothing that can be suggested of use or comfort
                    that she omitted. She loves me not only from her kind heart, but also from her
                    love of Mrs. Lock, often, often, exclaiming “Ah! si votre Angelique amie étoit
                    ici!—” (“Ah! if your angelic friend were here!—”) But I must force myself from
                    these episodes, though my dearest Esther will not think them de trop.</p>
                <pb n="[6]" facs="pageImages/05.jpeg"/>
                <p>After sentence thus passed, I was in hourly expectation of a summons to
                    execution; judge, then to my surprise to be suffered to on full 3 Weeks in the
                    same state! M. Larrey from time to time visited me, but pronounced nothing, and
                    was always melancholy. At length, M d’Arblay was told that he waited himself for
                    a Summons! and that, a formal one, and in writing! I could not give one. A
                    consent was my utmost effort. But poor M. d’Arblay wrote a desire that the
                    operation, if necessary, might take place without further delay. In my own mind,
                    I had all this time been persuaded there were hopes of a cure: why else, I
                    thought, let me know my doom thus long? But here I must account for this
                    apparently useless, and therefore cruel measure, though I only learnt it myself
                    2 months afterwards. M. Dubois had given his opinion that the evil was too far
                    advanced for any remedy; that the cancer was already internally declared; that I
                    was inevitably destined to that most frightful of deaths, and that an operation
                    would but accellerate my dissolution. Poor M. Larrey was so deeply affected by
                    this sentence, that—as he has lately told me, he regretted to his Soul ever
                    having known me, and was upon the point of demanding a commission to the
                    furthest end of France in order to force me into other hands. I had said,
                    however, he remembered, once, that I would far rather suffer a quick end
                    without, than a lingering life with this dreadfullest of maladies: he finally,
                    therefore, considered it might be possible to save me by the trial, but that
                    without it my case was desperate, and resolved to make the attempt.
                    Nevertheless, the responsibility was too great to rest upon his own head
                    entirely; and therefore he waited the formal summons.—</p>
                <p>In fine, One morning—the last of September, 1811, while I was in Bed, and M.
                    d’Arblay was arranging some papers for his office, I received a Letter written
                    by M. de Lally to a Journalist, in vindication of the honoured memory of his
                    Father against the assertions of Mme du Deffand. I read it aloud to My
                    Alexanders, with tears of admiration and sympathy, and then sent it by Alex. to
                    its excellent Author, as I had promised the preceding evening.</p>
                <p>I then then dressed, aided, as usual for many months, by my maid, my right arm
                    being condemned to total inaction; but not yet was the grand business over, when
                    another Letter was delivered to me—another, indeed!—’twas from M. Larrey, to
                    acquaint me that at 10 o’clock he should be with me, properly accompanied, and
                    to exhort me to rely as much upon his sensibility &amp; his prudence, as upon
                    his dexterity and his experience; he charged to secure the absence of M.
                    d’Arblay—and told me that the young Physician who would deliver me this announce
                    would prepare for the operation, in which he must lend his aid: and also that it
                    had been the decision of the consultation to allow me but two hours’
                    notice.—judge, my Esther, if I read this unmoved!— yet I had to disguise my
                    sensations and intentions from M. d’Arblay!</p>
                <p>Dr Aumont, the Messenger and terrible Herald, was in waiting; M. d’Arblay stood
                    by my bedside; I affected to be long reading the Note, to gain time for forming
                    some plan, and such was my terror of involving M. d’Arblay in the unavailing
                    wretchedness of witnessing what I must go through, that it conquered every
                    other, and gave me the force to act as if I were directing some third person.
                    The detail would be too Wordy, as James<pb n="[7]" facs="pageImages/06.jpeg"/>
                    says, but the wholesale is—I called Alex to my Bedside, and sent him to inform
                    M. Barbier Neuville, chef du division du Bureau de M. d’Arblay that the moment
                    was come, and I entreated him to write a summons upon urgent business for M.
                    d’Arblay and to detain him till all should be over. Speechless and appalled, off
                    went Alex, and, as I have since heard, was forced to sit down and sob in
                    executing his commission.</p>
                <p>I then, by the maid, sent word to the young Dr Aumont that I could not be ready
                    till one o’clock: and I finished my breakfast, and—not with much appetite, you
                    will believe! forced down a crust of bread, and hurried off, under various
                    pretences, M. d’Arblay. He was scarcely gone, when M Du Bois arrived: I renewed
                    my request for one o’clock: the rest came; all were fain to consent to the
                    delay, for I had an apartment to prepare for my banished Mate. This arrangement,
                    and those for myself, occupied me completely. Two engaged nurses were out of the
                    way—I had a bed, Curtains, and heaven knows what to prepare—but business was
                    good for my nerves. I was obliged to quit my room to have it put in order—Dr
                    Aumont would not leave the house; he remained in the Salon, folding linen!—He
                    had demanded 4 or 5 old and fine left off under Garments—I glided to our Book
                    Cabinet: sundry necessary works and orders filled up my time entirely till One
                    O’clock, When all was ready—but Dr Moreau then arrived, with news that M. Dubois
                    could not attend till three. Dr Aumont went away—and the Coast was clear. This,
                    indeed, was a dreadful interval. I had no longer anything to do—I had only to
                    think—Two Hours thus spent seemed never-ending.</p>
                <p> I would fain have written to my dearest Father—to You, my Esther—to Charlotte
                    James— Charles—Amelia Lock—but my arm prohibited me: I strolled to the Sallon—I
                    saw it fitted with preparations, and I recoiled—But I soon returned; to what
                    effect disguise from myself what I must so soon know?—yet the sight of the
                    immense quantity of bandages, compresses, sponges, Lint—made me a little sick:—I
                    walked backwards and forwards till I quieted all emotion, and became, by
                    degrees, nearly stupid - torpid, without sentiment or consciousness;—and thus I
                    remained till the Clock struck three.</p>
                <p>A sudden spirit of exertion then returned,—I defied my poor arm, no longer worth
                    sparing, and took my long banished pen to write a few words to M. d’Arblay— and
                    a few more for Alex, in case of a fatal result. These short billets I could only
                    deposit safely, when the Cabriolets— one—two—three—four—succeeded rapidly to
                    each other in stopping at the door. Dr Moreau instantly entered my room, to see
                    if I were alive. He gave me a wine cordial, and went to the Sallon. I rang for
                    my Maid and Nurses,—but before I could speak to them, my room, without previous
                    message, was entered by 7 Men in black, Dr Larry, M. Dubois, Dr Moreau, Dr
                    Aumont, Dr Ribe, and a pupil of Dr Larry, and another of M. Dubois. I was now
                    awakened <pb n="[8]" facs="pageImages/07.jpeg"/>from my stupor—and by a sort of
                    indignation—Why so many? and without leave?—But I could not utter a
                    syllable.</p>
                <p>M. Dubois acted as Commander in Chief. Dr Larry kept out of sight; M. Dubois
                    ordered a Bed stead into the middle of the room. Astonished, I turned to Dr
                    Larry, who had promised that an Arm Chair would suffice; but he hung his head,
                    &amp; would not look at me. Two old mattrasses M. Dubois then demanded, and an
                    old Sheet. I now began to tremble violently, more with distaste and horror of
                    the preparations even than of the pain. These arranged to his liking, he desired
                    me to mount the Bed stead. I stood suspended, for a moment, whether I should not
                    abruptly escape—I looked at the door, the windows—I felt desperate—but it was
                    only for a moment, my reason then took the command, and my fears and feelings
                    struggled vainly against it. I called to my maid—she was crying, and the two
                    Nurses stood, transfixed, at the door. “Let those women all go!” cried M.
                    Dubois. This order recovered me my Voice—“No,” I cried, “let them stay! qu’elles
                    restent!” (“Let them stay!”)</p>
                <p>This occasioned a little dispute, that re-animated me—The Maid, however, and one
                    of the nurses ran off—I charged the other to approach, and she obeyed. M. Dubois
                    now tried to issue his commands en militaire, but I resisted all that were
                    resistable—I was compelled, however, to submit to taking off my long robe de
                    Chambre, which I had meant to retain—Ah, then, how did I think of My
                    Sisters!—not one, at so dreadful an instant, at hand, to protect—adjust—guard
                    me— I regretted that I had refused Mme de Maisonneuve—Mme Chastel—no one upon
                    whom I could rely—my departed Angel!—how did I think of her!—how did I long—long
                    for my Esther—my Charlotte!—</p>
                <p>My distress was, I suppose, apparent, though not my Wishes, for M. Dubois himself
                    now softened, and spoke soothingly. “Can You,” I cried, “feel for an operation
                    that, to You, must seem so trivial?”—“Trivial?” he repeated—taking up a bit of
                    paper, which he tore, unconsciously, into a million of pieces, “oui—c’est peu de
                    chose—mais”—(“Yes—it’s a small thing—but”—) he stammered, and could not go on.
                    No one else attempted to speak, but I was softened myself, when I saw even M.
                    Dubois grow agitated, while Dr Larry kept always aloof, yet a glance shewed me
                    he was pale as ashes. I knew not, positively, then, the immediate danger, but
                    every thing convinced me danger was hovering about me, and that this experiment
                    could alone save me from its laws. I mounted, therefore, unbidden, the Bed
                    stead—and M. Dubois placed me upon the mattrass, and spread a cambric
                    handkerchief upon my face.</p>
                <p>It was transparent, however, and I saw, through it, that the Bedstead was
                    instantly surrounded by the 7 men and my nurse. I refused to be held; but when,
                    Bright through the cambric, I saw the glitter of polished Steel—I closed my
                    Eyes. I would not trust to convulsive fear the sight of the terrible <pb n="[9]"
                        facs="pageImages/08.jpeg"/>incision. A silence the most profound ensued,
                    which lasted for some minutes, during which, I imagine, they took their orders
                    by signs, and made their examination— Oh what a horrible suspension!—I did not
                    breathe—and M. Dubois tried vainly to find any pulse. This pause, at length, was
                    broken by Dr Larry, who, in a voice of solemn melancholy, said “Qui me tiendra
                    ce sein?—” (“Who will hold this breast for me?—”)</p>
                <p>No one answered; at least not verbally; but this aroused me from my passively
                    submissive state, for I feared they imagined the whole breast infected—feared it
                    too justly,—for, again through the Cambric, I saw the hand of M. Dubois held up,
                    while his forefinger first described a straight line from top to bottom of the
                    breast, secondly a Cross, and thirdly a circle; intimating that the Whole was to
                    be taken off. Excited by this idea, I started up, threw off my veil, and, in
                    answer to the demand “Qui me tiendra ce sein?” cried “C’est moi, Monsieur!” (“I
                    will, Sir!”) and I held My hand under it, and explained the nature of my
                    sufferings, which all sprang from one point, though they darted into every part.
                    I was heard attentively, but in utter silence, and M. Dubois then re-placed me
                    as before, and, as before, spread my veil over my face. How vain, alas, my
                    representation! immediately again I saw the fatal finger describe the Cross—and
                    the circle— Hopeless, then, desperate, and self-given up, I closed once more my
                    Eyes, relinquishing all watching, all resistance, all interference, and sadly
                    resolute to be wholly resigned.</p>
                <p>My dearest Esther,—and all my dears to whom she communicates this doleful ditty,
                    will rejoice to hear that this resolution once taken, was firmly adhered to, in
                    defiance of a terror that surpasses all description, and the most torturing
                    pain. Yet—when the dreadful steel was plunged into the breast—cutting through
                    veins—arteries—flesh—nerves—I needed no injunctions not to restrain my cries. I
                    began a scream that lasted unintermittingly during the whole time of the
                    incision—and I almost marvel that it rings not in my Ears still! so excruciating
                    was the agony. When the wound was made, and the instrument was withdrawn, the
                    pain seemed undiminished, for the air that suddenly rushed into those delicate
                    parts felt like a mass of minute but sharp and forked poniards, that were
                    tearing the edges of the wound—but when again I felt the instrument—describing a
                    curve—cutting against the grain, if I may so say, while the flesh resisted in a
                    manner so forcible <pb n="[10]" facs="pageImages/09.jpeg"/>as to oppose and tire
                    the hand of the operator, who was forced to change from the right to the
                    left—then, indeed, I thought I must have expired.</p>
                <p> I attempted no more to open my Eyes,—they felt as if hermetically shut, and so
                    firmly closed, that the Eyelids seemed indented into the Cheeks. The instrument
                    this second time withdrawn, I concluded the operation over—Oh no! presently the
                    terrible cutting was renewed— and worse than ever, to separate the bottom, the
                    foundation of this dreadful gland from the parts to which it adhered—Again all
                    description would be baffled—yet again all was not over,—Dr Larry rested but his
                    own hand, and—Oh Heaven!—I then felt the Knife rackling against the breast
                    bone—scraping it!—This performed, while I yet remained in utterly speechless
                    torture, I heard the Voice of Mr Larry,—(all others guarded a dead silence) in a
                    tone nearly tragic, desire everyone present to pronounce if anything more
                    remained to be done; The general voice was Yes,—but the finger of Mr
                    Dubois—which I literally felt elevated over the wound, though I saw nothing, and
                    though he touched nothing, so indescribably sensitive was the spot—pointed to
                    some further requisition—and again began the scraping!—and, after this, Dr
                    Moreau thought he discerned a peccant attom (fragments of diseased [peccant]
                    breast tissue)—and still, and still, M. Dubois demanded attom after attom.—</p>
                <p>My dearest Esther, not for days, not for Weeks, but for Months I could not speak
                    of this terrible business without nearly again going through it! I could not
                    think of it with impunity! I was sick, I was disordered by a single
                    question—even now, 9 months after it is over, I have a headache from going on
                    with the account! and this miserable account, which I began 3 Months ago, at
                    least, I dare not revise, nor read, the recollection is still so painful.</p>
                <pb n="[11]" facs="pageImages/10.jpeg"/>
                <p>To conclude, the evil was so profound, the case so delicate, and the precautions
                    necessary for preventing a return so numerous, that the operation, including the
                    treatment and the dressing, lasted 20 minutes! a time, for sufferings so acute,
                    that was hardly supportable—However, I bore it with all the courage I could
                    exert, and never moved, nor stopt them, nor resisted, nor remonstrated, nor
                    spoke - except once or twice, during the dressings, to say “Ah Messieurs! que je
                    vous plains!—” (“Ah Sirs! how I pity you!—”) for indeed I was sensible to the
                    feeling concern with which they all saw what I endured, though my speech was
                    principally—very principally meant for Dr Larry. Except this, I uttered not a
                    syllable, save, when so often they recommenced, calling out “Avertissez moi,
                    Messieurs! Avertissez moi!—” (“Warn me, Sirs! warn me!”) Twice, I believe, I
                    fainted; at least, I have two total chasms in my memory of this transaction,
                    that impede my tying together what passed.</p>
                <p>When all was done, and they lifted me up that I might be put to bed, my strength
                    was so totally annihilated, that I was obliged to be carried, and could not even
                    sustain my hands and arms, which hung as if I had been lifeless; while my face,
                    as the Nurse has told me, was utterly colourless. This removal made me open my
                    Eyes—and I then saw my good Dr Larry, pale nearly as myself, his face streaked
                    with blood, its expression depicting grief, apprehension, and almost
                    horrour.</p>
                <p>When I was in bed,—my poor M. d’Arblay—who ought to write you himself his own
                    history of this Morning—was called to me—and afterwards our Alex.—</p>

            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
