<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="marlowe-faustus">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Tragicall History of Doctor Faustus</title>
            <author>
               <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78088956">    
                  <name ref="xxx.xml">           
                     <forename>Christopher</forename> 
                     <surname>Marlowe</surname>             
                  </name>              
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                  <name ref="editors.#JOB">
                     <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                     <forename>John</forename>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
              
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name ref="editors.xml#StudStaffUVA">Text Creation Partnership and Students and Staff at the University of Virginia</name>

            </respStmt>
            
            <sponsor/>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
     
         </titleStmt>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>University of Virginia</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA</addrLine>
               <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
               <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
              <monogr>
               <author>
                        <forename>Christopher</forename> 
                        <surname>Marlowe</surname>             
               </author>
                  <title>The Tragicall history of Doctor Faustus</title>
                  
               <imprint>
                  <pubPlace>
                     <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                  </pubPlace>
                  
                  <publisher>Printed by V. S[immes] for Thomas Bushell</publisher>
                  <date when="1604">1604.</date>
                  <note>The texts we have of Christopher Marlowe's play <hi rend="italic">The Tragicall History of Doctor Faustus</hi> were printed years after the play's first production somewhere between 1589 and 1594, and probably only approximate the play as Marlowe wrote it. For one thing, Marlowe died in 1593, so not only did he have no opportunity to guarantee that the printed texts were reliable (and most authors in this period did not worry too much about that anyway), but the intervening years probably meant that the play had gotten altered at least somewhat in the course of years of performance in ways that we cannot retrace. Two distinct versions of the play exist: an edition published in 1604, usually referred to as the "A" text, and another, longer edition, published in 1616, known as the "B" text. Scholars have gone back and forth over the decades arguing about which one better reflects Marlowe's original version. But we'll never really know  for sure. It is also possible, even likely, for example, that some of the additional material that appears in the B text (mostly adding more comedy and slapstick humor), was added by other writers. It's also possible that the A text, which is short by the standard of most plays of the period, is a cut down version of the play. Our edition follows the A text, which was digitized by the Text Creation Partnership. The printed text that the TCP was working from is printed in gothic-style black letter, which was getting a little old fashioned even in 1604. For this Literature in Context edition, we've left the original spelling largely intact, since it helps guide pronunciation, which is slightly different from modern English, but not hard to figure out, particularly if the reader says the words out loud. The spelling is inconsistent throughout the play, which is typical of this period, when people did not care all that much about consistent spelling. We have brought the letters "u" and "v" to conform to modern usage; the black letter most frequently reverses them. Finally, we have spelled out the names of speakers in full, to make the text more reader-friendly.</note>
               </imprint>
               <extent>[46] pp.</extent>
              </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         
         
         
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
         
     
     
      
      <textDesc n="play">
         
         <channel mode="w">print</channel>
         
         <constitution type="single">single play</constitution>
         <derivation type="original"/>
         <domain/>
         <factuality type="fiction"/>
         <interaction/>
         <preparedness type="original"/>
         <purpose type="express"/>
         <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
         <!-- interpretation in the textDesc will be necessary -->
      </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
               
               <setting>
                  <name type="tgn" key="7078537">Wittenberg, Germany</name>
               
                  <time from="1550" to="1600">Late sixteeenth century</time>
                 
               </setting>
               
            </settingDesc>
            
      
         </profileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
    
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
               primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
               literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
               Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
               University.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                  lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2002-06-01" who="TCP"> Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change when="2002-07-01" who="Aptara">Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change when="2002-08-01" who="Mona Logarbo"> Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change when="2002-11-01" who="Aptara">Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change when="2002-12-01" who="Jennifer Kietzman">Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change when="2003-05-01" who="Aptara"> Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change when="2004-09-01" who="Ben Griffin"> Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change when="2004-09-01" who="Ben Griffin"> Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change when="2004-10-01" who="pfs"> Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change when="2024-02-01" who="John O'Brien"> Proofread and corrected for Literature in Context Edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
      
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <pb />
            <titlePart>THE<lb/>
               TRAGICALL<lb/>
               History of D. Faustus.</titlePart><lb/>
            <titlePart><hi rend="italic">As it hath bene Acted by the Right<lb/>
               Honorable the Earle of Nottingham his servants.</hi></titlePart><lb/>
            <titlePart>Written by Ch. Marl.</titlePart>
            <docImprint>LONDON<lb/>
Printed by V. S. for Thomas Bushell. 1604.</docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
  
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb />
            <pb />
            <head>The tragicall Historie of Doctor Faustus.</head>
            <stage>Enter</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>Not marching now in fields of <hi rend="italic">Thracimene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi rend="italic">Mars</hi> did mate the Carthaginians,</l>
               <l>Nor sporting in the dalliance of love,</l>
               <l>In courts of Kings where state is overturnd,</l>
               <l>Nor in the pompe of prowd audacious deedes,</l>
               <l>Intends our Muse to daunt his heavenly verse:</l>
               <l>Onely this (Gentlemen) we must performe,</l>
               <l>The forme of <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> fortunes good or bad.</l>
               <l>To patient Judgements we appeale our plaude,</l>
               <l>And speake for <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> in his infancie:</l>
               <l>Now is he borne, his parents base of stocke,</l>
               <l>In <hi rend="italic">Germany,</hi> within a towne calld <hi rend="italic">Rhodes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of riper yéeres to <hi rend="italic">Wertenberg</hi> he went,</l>
               <l>Whereas his kinsmen chiefly brought him up,</l>
               <l>So soone hée profites in Divinitie,</l>
               <l>The fruitfull plot of Scholerisme grac't,</l>
               <l>That shortly he was grac't with Doctors name,</l>
               <l>Excelling all, whose swéete delight disputes</l>
               <l>In heauenly matters of <hi rend="italic">Theologie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till swolne with cunning of a selfe conceit,</l>
               <l>His waxen wings did mount above his reach,</l>
               <l>And melting heavens conspirde his overthrow.</l>
               <l>For falling to a divelish exercise,</l>
               <l>And glutted more with learnings golden gifts,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb/>
He surffets upon cursed Negromancy,
               </l>
               <l>Nothing so sweete as magicke is to him</l>
               <l>Which he preferres before his chiefest blisse,</l>
               <l>And this the man that in his study sits.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Faustus in his Study.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Settle thy studies <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> and beginne</l>
               <l>To sound the deapth of that thou wilt professe:</l>
               <l>Having commencde, be a Divine in shew,</l>
               <l>Yet levell at the end of every Art,</l>
               <l>And live and die in <hi rend="italic">Aristotles</hi> workes:</l>
               <l>Sweete <hi rend="italic">Anulatikes</hi> tis thou hast ravisht me,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Bene disserere est finis logicis.
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is, to dispute well, Logickes chiefest end</l>
               <l>Affoords this Art no greater myracle:</l>
               <l>Then reade no more, thou hast attaind the end:</l>
               <l>A greater subject fitteth <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> wit,</l>
               <l>Bid <hi rend="italic">Oncaymaeon</hi> farewell, <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi> come:</l>
               <l>Séeing, <hi rend="italic">vbi desinit philosophus, ibi incipit medicus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be a physition <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> heape up golde,</l>
               <l>And be eternizde for some wondrous cure,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Summum bonum medicinae sanitas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The end of physicke is our bodies health:</l>
               <l>Why <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> hast thou not attaind that end?</l>
               <l>Is not thy common talke sound Aphorismes?</l>
               <l>Are not thy billes hung up as monuments,</l>
               <l>Whereby whole Citties have escapt the plague,</l>
               <l>And thousand desprate maladies béene easde,</l>
               <l>Yet art thou still but <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> and a man.</l>
               <l>Wouldst thou make man to liVe eternally?</l>
               <l>Or being dead, raise them to life againe?</l>
               <l>Then this profession were to be estéemd.</l>
               <l>Physicke farewell, where is Justinian?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Si une eademqu res legatus duobus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Aiter rem alter valorem rei,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>A pretty case of paltry legacies:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Ex heriditari filiu nisi poest pater nisi:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such is the subiect of the institute</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
And universall body of the Church:</l>
               <l>
                This study fittes a mercenary drudge,</l>
               <l>Who aimes at nothing but externall trash,</l>
               <l>The devill and illiberall for me:</l>
               <l>When all is done, Divinitie is best.</l>
               <l>
                  Jeromes Bible, Faustus, view it well.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Stipendium peccati mors est:</hi> ha, <hi>Stipendium, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The reward of sinne is death: thats hard.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Si peccasse negamus, fallimur, &amp; nulla est in nobis veritas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If we say that we haVe no sinne,</l>
               <l>We deceive our selves, and theres no truth in us.</l>
               <l>Why then belike we must sinne,</l>
               <l>And so consequently die.</l>
               <l>I, we must die an everlasting death:</l>
               <l>What doctrine call you this, <hi rend="italic">Che sera, sera,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What wil be, shall be? Divinitie, adieu,</l>
               <l>These Metaphisickes of Magicians,</l>
               <l>And Negromantike bookes are heavenly</l>
               <l>Lines, circles, sceanes, letters and characters:</l>
               <l>I, these are those that <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> most desires.</l>
               <l>O what a world of profit and delight,</l>
               <l>Of power, of honor, of omnipotence</l>
               <l>Is promised to the studious Artizan?</l>
               <l>All things that moove betweene the quiet poles</l>
               <l>Shalbe at my commaund, Emperours and Kings,</l>
               <l>Are but obeyd in their severall provinces:</l>
               <l>Nor can they raise the winde, or rend the cloudes:</l>
               <l>But his dominion that excéedes in this,</l>
               <l>Stretcheth as farre as doth the minde of man.</l>
               <l>A sound Magician is a mighty god:</l>
               <l>Héere <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> trie thy braines to gaine a deitie.</l>
               <stage>Enter Wagner.</stage>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wagner,</hi> commend me to my deerest friends,</l>
               <l>The Germaine <hi rend="italic">Valde,</hi> and <hi>Corneliu,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Request them earnestly to visite me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>I wil sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Their conference will be a greater help to me,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Than all my labours, plodde I nere so fast.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the good Angell and the evill Angell.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good Angell</speaker>
               <l>O <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> lay that damned booke aside,</l>
               <l>And gaze not on it, lest it tempt thy soule,</l>
               <l>And heape Gods heauy wrath vpon thy head,</l>
               <l>Reade, reade the scriptures, that is blasphemy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Evill Angell</speaker>
               <l>Go forward <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> in that famous art,</l>
               <l>Wherein all natures treasury is containd:</l>
               <l>Be thou on earth as <hi rend="italic">Ioue</hi> is in the skie,</l>
               <l>Lord and commaunder of these Elements.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>How am I glutted with conceit of this?</l>
               <l>Shall I make spirits fetch me what I please,</l>
               <l>Resolve me of all ambiguities,</l>
               <l>Performe what desperate enterprise I will?</l>
               <l>Ile have them flye to <hi rend="italic">India</hi> for gold,</l>
               <l>Ransacke the Ocean for orient pearle,</l>
               <l>And search all corners of the new found world</l>
               <l>For pleasant fruites and princely delicates:</l>
               <l>Ile have them reade mée straunge philosophie,</l>
               <l>And tell the secrets of all forraine kings,</l>
               <l>Ile have them wall all <hi rend="italic">Iermany</hi> with brasse,</l>
               <l>And make swift <hi rend="italic">Rhine</hi> circle faire <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile have them fill the publike schooles with skill.</l>
               <l>Wherewith the students shalbe bravely clad:</l>
               <l>Ile levy souldiers with the coyne they bring,</l>
               <l>And chase the Prince of <hi rend="italic">Parma</hi> from our land,</l>
               <l>And raigne sole king of all our provinces:</l>
               <l>Yea stranger engines for the brunt of warre,</l>
               <l>Then was the fiery kéele at <hi rend="italic">Antwarpes</hi> bridge,</l>
               <l>Ile make my servile spirits to invent:</l>
               <l>Come <hi rend="italic">Germaine Valdes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cornelius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And make me blest with your sage conference,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Valdes,</hi> swéete <hi rend="italic">Valdes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cornelius,</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Enter Valdes and Cornelius.</stage>
               <l>Know that your words have woon me at the last,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
To practise Magicke and concealed arts:</l>
               <l>Yet not your words onely, but mine owne fantasie,</l>
               <l>That will receive no obiect for my head,</l>
               <l>But ruminates on Negremantique skill,</l>
               <l>Philosophy is odious and obscure,</l>
               <l>Both Law and Phisicke are for pettie wits,</l>
               <l>Divinitie is basest of the thrée,</l>
               <l>Unpleasant, harsh, contemptible and vilde,</l>
               <l>Tis Magicke, Magicke that hath ravisht mée,</l>
               <l>Then gentle friends ayde me in this attempt,</l>
               <l>And I that have with Consissylogismes</l>
               <l>Graveld the Pastors of the Germaine Church,</l>
               <l>And made the flowring pride of <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swarme to my Problemes as the infernall spirits</l>
               <l>On swéet <hi rend="italic">Musaeus</hi> when he came to hell,</l>
               <l>Will be as cunning as <hi rend="italic">Agrippa</hi> was,</l>
               <l>Whose shadowes made all <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> honor him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Valdes</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faustus</hi> these bookes thy wit and our experience</l>
               <l>Shall make all nations to canonize vs,</l>
               <l>As Indian Moores obey their Spanish Lords,</l>
               <l>So shall the subiects of every element</l>
               <l>Be alwaies serviceable to us thrée,</l>
               <l>Like Lyons shall they guard us when we please,</l>
               <l>Like <hi rend="italic">Almaine</hi> Rutters with their horsemens staues,</l>
               <l>Or Lapland Gyants trotting by our sides,</l>
               <l>Sometimes like women, or unwedded maides,</l>
               <l>Shadowing more beautie in their ayrie browes,</l>
               <l>Then in their white breasts of the queene of Love:</l>
               <l>For <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> shall they dregge huge Argoces,</l>
               <l>And from <hi rend="italic">America</hi> the golden fléece,</l>
               <l>That yearely stuffes olde <hi rend="italic">Philips</hi> treasury</l>
               <l>If learned <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> will be resolute.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Valdes</hi> as resolute am I in this</l>
               <l>As thou to live, therefore obiect it not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cornelius</speaker>
               <l>The myracles that Magicke will performe,</l>
               <l>Will make thée vow to studie nothing else,</l>
               <l>He that is grounded in Astrologie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Inricht with tongues well séene minerals,</l>
               <l>Hath all the principles Magicke doth require,</l>
               <l>Then doubt not <hi rend="italic">(Faustus)</hi> but to be renownd,</l>
               <l>And more frequented for this mystery,</l>
               <l>Then heretofore the Dolphian Oracle.</l>
               <l>The spirits tell me they can drie the sea,</l>
               <l>And fetch the treasure of all forraine wrackes,</l>
               <l>I, all the wealth that our forefathers hid</l>
               <l>Within the massie entrails of the earth.</l>
               <l>Then tell me <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> what shal we three want?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Nothing <hi rend="italic">Cornelius,</hi> O this cheares my soule,</l>
               <l>Come shewe me some demonstrations magicall,</l>
               <l>That I may coniure in some lustie grove,</l>
               <l>And have these ioyes in full possession.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Valdes</speaker>
               <l>Then haste thée to some solitary grove,</l>
               <l>And beare wise <hi rend="italic">Bacons</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Albanus</hi> workes,</l>
               <l>The Hebrew Psalter, and new Testament,</l>
               <l>And whatsoever else is requisit</l>
               <l>Wee will enforme thée ere our conference cease.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cornelius</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Valdes,</hi> first let him know the words of art,</l>
               <l>And then all other ceremonies learnd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> may trie his cunning by himselfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Valdes</speaker>
               <l>First Ile instruct thee in the rudiments,</l>
               <l>And then wilt thou be perfecter then I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Then come and dyne with me, and after meate</l>
               <l>Wéele canvas euery quidditie thereof:</l>
               <l>For ere I sleepe Ile trie what I can do,</l>
               <l>This night Ile coniure though I die therefore.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter two Schollers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 Sch.</speaker>
               <l>I wonder whats become of <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> that was
wont to make our schooles ring with, <hi rend="italic">sic probo.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 Sch.</speaker>
               <l>That shall we know, for see here comes his boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Wagner.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Sch.</speaker>
               <l>How now sirra, wheres thy maister?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>God in heauen knowes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2.</speaker>
               <l>Why, dost not thou know?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>Yes I know, but that followes not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1.</speaker>
               <l>Go too sirra, leaue your ieasting, and tell vs where
hée is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>That follows not necessary by force of argument,
that you being licentiate should stand vpon't, therefore acknowledge
your error, and be attentive.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2.</speaker>
               <l>Why, didst thou not say thou knewst?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>Haue you any witnesse on't?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1.</speaker>
               <l>Yes sirra, I heard you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>Aske my fellow if I be a thiefe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2.</speaker>
               <l>Well, you will not tell vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <l>Yes sir, I will tell you, yet if you were not dunces
you would never aske me such a question, for is not he corpus <hi rend="italic">
naturale,</hi> and is not that <hi rend="italic">mobile,</hi> then wherefore should
you aske me such a question: but that I am by nature flegmaticke,
slowe to wrath, and prone to leachery, (to love I
would say) it were not for you to come within fortie foote of
the place of execution, although I do not doubt to sée you
both hang'd the next Sessions. Thus having triumpht over
you, I will set my countnance like a precisian, and begin to
speake thus: truly my deare brethren, my maister is within
at dinner with <hi rend="italic">Valdes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cornelius,</hi> as this wine if it could
speake, it would enforme your worships, and so the Lord
blesse you, preserve you, and kéepe you my deare brethren,
my deare brethren.</l>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1.</speaker>
               <l>Nay then I feare he is falne into that damned art, for
which they two are infamous through the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2.</speaker>
               <l>Were he a stranger, and not alied to me, yet should
I grieve for him: but come let us go and informe the Rector,
and sée if hée by his grave counsaile can reclaime him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1.</speaker>
               <l>O but I feare me nothing can reclaime him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2.</speaker>
               <l>Yet let vs trie what we can do.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Faustus to coniure.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Now that the gloomy shadow of the earth,</l>
               <l>Longing to view <hi rend="italic">Orions</hi> drisling looke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Leapes from th'antartike world vnto the skie,</l>
               <l>And dimmes the welkin with her pitchy breath:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> begin thine incantations,</l>
               <l>And trie if divels will obey thy hest,</l>
               <l>Séeing thou hast prayde and sacrific'd to them.</l>
               <l>Within this circle is <hi rend="italic">Jehovah's</hi> name,</l>
               <l>Forward and backward, and Agramithist,</l>
               <l>Th'abbreviated names of holy Saints,</l>
               <l>Figures of euery adjunct to the heavens,</l>
               <l>And characters of signes and erring starres.</l>
               <l>By which the spirits are inforst to rise,</l>
               <l>Then feare not <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> but be resolute.</l>
               <l>And trie the vttermost Magicke can performe.</l>
               <l><hi rend="italic">Sint mihi dei acherontis propitij, valeat numen triplex Iehouae, ignei,aerij, Aquatani spiritus saluete, Orientis princeps Belsibub, inferni
ardentis monarcha &amp; demigorgon, propitiamus vos, vt apariat &amp;
surgat Mephastophilis, quòd tumeraris, per Ichouam gehennam &amp;
consecratam aquam quam nunc spargo, signúmque crucis quodnunc
facio, &amp; per vota nostra ipse nunc surgat nobis dicitis Mephastophilis.</hi></l>
               <stage>Enter a Divell.</stage>
               <l>I charge thée to returne and change thy shape,</l>
               <l>Thou art too ugly to attend on me,</l>
               <l>Goe and returne an old Franciscan Frier,</l>
               <l>That holy shape becomes a divell best.</l>
               <stage>Exit diuell.</stage>
               <l>I see theres vertue in my heauenly words,</l>
               <l>Who would not be proficient in this art?</l>
               <l>How pliant is this <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Full of obedience and humilitie,</l>
               <l>Such is the force of Magicke and my spels,</l>
               <l>No <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> thou art Coniurer laureate</l>
               <l>That canst commaund great <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l> <hi rend="italic">Quin regis Mephastophilis fratris imagine.</hi></l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mephostophilis.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephostophilis</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> what wouldst thou have me do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>I charge thée wait upon me whilst I liue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
To do what ever <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> shall commaund,</l>
               <l>Be it to make the Moone drop from her spheare,</l>
               <l>Or the Ocean to ouerwhelme the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephostophilis</speaker>
               <l>I am a servant to great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And may not follow thée without his leave,</l>
               <l>No more then he commaunds must we performe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Did not he charge thée to appeare to me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>No, I came now hither of mine owne accord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Did not my coniuring spéeches raise thee? speake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>That was the cause, but yet per accident,</l>
               <l>For when we heare one racke the name of God,</l>
               <l>Abiure the scriptures, and his Saviour Christ,</l>
               <l>Wée flye, in hope to get his glorious soule,</l>
               <l>Nor will we come, unlesse he use such meanes</l>
               <l>Whereby he is in danger to be damnd:</l>
               <l>Therefore the shortest cut for coniuring</l>
               <l>Is stoutly to abiure the Trinitie,</l>
               <l>And pray devoutly to the prince of hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>So <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> hath already done, &amp; holds this principle</l>
               <l>There is no chiefe but onely <hi rend="italic">Belsibub,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To whom <hi rend="italic">Faustus
                  </hi> doth dedicate himselfe,</l>
               <l>This word damnation terrifies not him,</l>
               <l>For he confounds hell in <hi rend="italic">Elizium,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His ghost be with the olde Philosophers,</l>
               <l>But leaving these vaine trifles of mens soules,</l>
               <l>Tell me what is that <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi></l></sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Arch-regent and commaunder of all spirits.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Was not that <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> an Angell once?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Yes <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> and most dearely lov'd of God.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>How comes it then that he is prince of divels?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>O by aspiring pride and insolence,</l>
               <l>For which God threw him from the face of heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>and what are you that liue with <hi rend="italic">Lucifer?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Unhappy spirits that fell with <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conspir'd against our God with <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And are for everdamnd with <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Where are you damn'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>In hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>How comes it then that thou art out of hel?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MMephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Why this is hel, nor am I out of it:</l>
               <l>Thinkst thou that I who saw the face of God,</l>
               <l>And tasted the eternal ioyes of heaven,</l>
               <l>Am not tormented with ten thousand hels,</l>
               <l>In being depriv'd of euerlasting blisse:</l>
               <l>O <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> leave these frivolous demaunds,</l>
               <l>which strike a terror to my fainting soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>What, is great <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis</hi> so passionate,</l>
               <l>For being deprivd of the ioyes of heaven?</l>
               <l>Learne thou of <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> manly fortitude,</l>
               <l>And scorne those ioyes thou never shalt possesse.</l>
               <l>Go beare those tidings to great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Séeing <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> hath incurrd eternall death,</l>
               <l>By desprate thoughts against <hi rend="italic">Ioues</hi> deitie:</l>
               <l>Say, he surrenders up to him his soule,</l>
               <l>So he will spare him 24. yéeres,</l>
               <l>Letting him live in al voluptuousnesse,</l>
               <l>Having thee ever to attend on me,</l>
               <l>To giue me whatsoever I shal aske,</l>
               <l>To tel me whatsoever I demaund,</l>
               <l>To slay mine enemies, and ayde my friends,</l>
               <l>And alwayes be obedient to my wil:</l>
               <l>Goe and returne to mighty <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And méete mée in my study at midnight,</l>
               <l>And then resolue me of thy maisters minde.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>I will <hi rend="italic">Faustus.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Had I as many soules as there be starres,</l>
               <l>Ide giue them al for <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By him Ile be great Emprour of the world,</l>
               <l>And make a bridge through the moouing ayre,</l>
               <l>To passe the <hi rend="italic">Ocean</hi> with a band of men,</l>
               <l>Ile ioyne the hils that binde the <hi rend="italic">Affricke</hi> shore,</l>
               <l>And make that land continent to <hi rend="italic">Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And both contributory to my crowne:</l>
               <l>The Emprour shal bot live but by my leave,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Nor any Potentate of <hi rend="italic">Germany:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now that I haue obtaind what I desire,</l>
               <l>Ile live in speculation of this Art,</l>
               <l>Til <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis</hi> returne againe.</l>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Wagner and the Clowne.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>Sirra boy, come hither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>How, boy? swowns boy, I hope you haue séene many
boyes with such pickadevaunts as I haue. Boy quotha?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Tel me sirra, hast thou any commings in?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
               <l>I, and goings out too, you may sée else.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Alas poore slaue, sée how pouerty iesteth in his nakednesse,
the vilaine is bare, and out of seruice, and so hungry,
that I know he would giue his soule to the Divel for a
shoulder of mutton, though it were blood rawe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>How, my soule to the Divel for a shoulder of mutton
though twere blood rawe? not so good friend, burladie I
had néede haue it wel roasted, and good sawce to it, if I pay so
déere.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Wel, wilt thou serve me, and Ile make thée go like
<hi rend="italic">Qui mihi discipulus?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>How, in verse?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <l>No sirra, in beaten silke and staues acre.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Wow, how, knaves acre? I, I thought that was al
the land his father left him: Doe yee heare, I would be sorie
to robbe you of your living.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Sirra, I say in staues acre.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Oho, oho, staves acre, why then belike, if I were
your man, I should be ful of vermine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner</speaker>
               <l>So thou shalt, whether thou bée it with me, or no:
but sirra, leaue your iesting, and binde your selfe presently
unto me for seaven yéeres, or Ile turne al the lice about thée
into familiars, and they shal teare thée in péeces.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Doe you heare sir? you may save that labour, they
are too familiar with me already, swowns they are as bolde
with my flesh, as if they had payd for my meate and drinke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Wel, do you heare sirra? holde, take these gilders.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Gridyrons, what be they?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Why french crownes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne</speaker>
               <l>Mas but for the name of french crownes a man
were as good haue as many english counters, and what
should I do with these?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Why now sirra thou art at an houres warning
whensoever or wheresoever the divell shall fetch thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>No, no, here take your gridirons againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Truly Ile none of them.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Truly but you shall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Beare witnesse I gave them him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Beare witnesse I give them you againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Well, I will cause two divels presently to fetch
thée away <hi rend="italic">Baliol</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Belcher.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>Let your <hi rend="italic">Baliol
                  </hi> and your <hi rend="italic">Belcher</hi> come here, and Ile
knocke them, they were neuer so knockt since they were divels,
say I should kill one of them. What would folkes say? do
ye see yonder tall fellow in the round flop, hee has kild the divell,
so I should be cald kill divell all the parish over.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter two diuells, and the clowne runnes vp
and downe crying.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Baliol
                  </hi> and <hi rend="italic">Belcher,</hi> spirits away.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>What, are they gone? a vengeance on them, they
haue vilde long nailes, there was a hee diuell and a shée divell,
Ile tell you how you shall know them, all hee divels has hornes, and all shée diuels had clifts and clouen feete.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Well sirra follow me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>But do you hear? if I should serve you, would you teach me to raise up <hi rend="italic">Banios</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Belcheos?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>I will teach thee to turne thy self to anything, to a dogge, or a catte, or a mouse or a ratte, or any thing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>How? a Christian fellow to a dogge or a catte, a mouse, or a ratte: no, no sir, if you turne me into any thing, let it be the likeness of a little pretie frisking flea, that I
might be here and there and every where, O Ile tickle the pretty wenches plackets! Ill be amongst them i'faith.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Wel sirra, come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>But doe you heare <hi rend="italic">Wagner?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>How <hi rend="italic">Balioll</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Belcher.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne.</speaker>
               <l>O Lord I pray sir, let <hi rend="italic">Banio</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Belcher</hi> go sléepe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Villain, call me Master Wagner, and let thy left eye be diametrically fixt upon my right heele, with <hi rend="italic">Quasi vestigias nostras insistere.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clowne</speaker>
               <l>God forgive me, he speakes Dutch fustian: well,
Ile folow him, Ile serve him, thats flat.</l>
               <stage>exit</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Faustus in his Study.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Now Faustus must thou néedes be damnd,</l>
               <l>And canst thou not be saved?</l>
               <l>What bootes it then to thinke of God or heaven?</l>
               <l>Away with such vaine fancies and despaire,</l>
               <l>Despaire in God, and trust in Belsabub:</l>
               <l>Now go not backeward: no Faustus, be resolute,</l>
               <l>Why wacverest thou? O something soundeth in mine eares:</l>
               <l>Abjure this Magicke, turne to God againe,</l>
               <l>I and Faustus wil turne to God againe.</l>
               <l>To God? he loves thee not,</l>
               <l>The god thou servest is thine owne appetite,</l>
               <l>Wherein is fixt the love of Belsabub,</l>
               <l>To him Ile build an altare and a church,</l>
               <l>And offer luke warme blood of new borne babes.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter good Angell, and Evill.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good Angel</speaker>
               <l>Swéet Faustus, leave that execrable art.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Contrition, prayer, repentance: what of them?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good Angel</speaker>
               <l>O they are meanes to bring thée unto heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Evill Angel</speaker>
               <l>Rather illusions fruites of lunacy,</l>
               <l>That makes men foolish that do trust them most.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good Angel</speaker>
               <l>Swéet Faustus thinke of heaven, and heauenly
things.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euill Angel</speaker>
               <l>No Faustus, thinke of honor and wealth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Of wealth,</l>
               <stage>exeunt.</stage>
               <l>Why the signory of Emden shalbe mine,</l>
               <l>when <hi rend="italic">Mephatophilus</hi> shal stand by me,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
What God can hurt thée Faustus? thou art safe,</l>
               <l>Cast no more doubts, come <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And bring glad tidings from great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ist not midnight? come <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Veni veni Mephastophile</l>
               <stage>enter Mephistophilis</stage>
               <l>Now tel, what sayes <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> thy Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>That I shal waite on Faustus whilst I live,</l>
               <l>So he wil buy my service with his soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Already Faustus hath hazarded that for thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>But Faustus, thou must bequeathe it solemnely,</l>
               <l>And write a déede of gift with thine owne blood,</l>
               <l>For that security craves great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou deny it, I wil backe to hel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Stay <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi> and tel me, what good wil
my soule do thy Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Inlarge his kingdome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Is that the reason he tempts us thus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Solamen miseris socios habuisse doloris.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Haue you any paine that tortures others?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>As great as have the humane soules of men:</l>
               <l>But tel me Faustus, shal I have thy soule,</l>
               <l>And I wil be thy slave, and waite on thée,</l>
               <l>And giue thée more than thou hast wit to aske.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>I <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi> I give it thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Then stabbe thine arme couragiously,</l>
               <l>And binde thy soule, that at some certaine day</l>
               <l>Great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> may claime it as his owne,</l>
               <l>And then be thou as great as <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Loe <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi> for love of thée,</l>
               <l>I cut mine arme, and with my proper blood</l>
               <l>Assure my soule to be great <hi rend="italic">Lucifers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chiefe Lord and regent of perpetual night,</l>
               <l>Vuew heere the blood that trickles from mine arme,</l>
               <l>And let it be propitious for my wish.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>But Faustus, thou must write it in manner of a
déede of gift.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I so I will, but <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis</hi> my bloud conieales
<pb />
and I can write no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Ile fetch thée fier to dissolve it straight.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>What might the staying of my bloud portend?</l>
               <l>Is it unwilling I should write this bill?</l>
               <l>Why streames it not, that I may write afresh?</l>
               <l>Faustus gives to thee his soule: ah there it stayde,</l>
               <l>Why shouldst thou not? is not thy soule thine owne?</l>
               <l>Then write againe, Faustus gives to thée his soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mephastophilis with a chafer of coles.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Heres fier, come Faustus, set it on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>So now the bloud begins to cleare againe,</l>
               <l>Now will I make an ende immediately.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>O what will not I do to obtaine his soule?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Consummatum est,</hi> this Bill is ended,</l>
               <l>And Faustus hath bequeath'd his soule to <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what is this inscription on mine arme?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Homo fuge,</hi> whither should I flie?</l>
               <l>If vnto God hée'le throwe thée downe to hell,</l>
               <l>My sences are deceiu'd, here's nothing writ,</l>
               <l>I sée it plaine, here in this place is writ,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Homo fuge,</hi> yet shall not <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> flye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Ile fetch him somewhat to delight his minde.</l>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter with divels, giving crownes and rich apparell to
Faustus, and daunce, and then depart.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Speake Mephastophilis, what meanes this shewe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Nothing Faustus, but to delight thy minde withall,</l>
               <l>And to shewe thee what Magicke can performe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>But may I raise up spirits when I please?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>I Faustus, and do greater things then these.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Then theres inough for a thousand soules,</l>
               <l>Here Mephastophilis receive this scrowle,</l>
               <l>A déede of gift of body and of soule:</l>
               <l>But yet conditionally, that thou performe</l>
               <l>All articles prescrib'd betwéene vs both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Faustus, I sweare by hel and <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To effect all promises betweene vs made.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Then heare me reade them: on these conditions following.</l>
               <l>First, that Faustus may be a spirit in forme and substance.</l>
               <l>Secondly, that Mephastophilis shall be his servant, and at
his commaund.</l>
               <l>Thirdly, that Mephastophilis shall do for him, and bring
him whatsoever.</l>
               <l>Fourthly, that hee shall be in his chamber or house invisible.</l>
               <l>Lastly, that hee shall appeare to the said <hi rend="italic">Iohn Faustus</hi> at all times, in what forme or shape soever he please.</l>
               <l>I <hi rend="italic">Iohn Faustus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge,</hi> Doctor, by these presents, do
give both body and soule to <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> prince of the East, and his
minister <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi> and furthermore graunt vnto them,
that 24. yeares being expired, the articles aboue written inviolate,
full power to fetch or carry the said <hi rend="italic">Iohn Faustus</hi> body
and soule, flesh, bloud, or goods, into their habitation wheresoever.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>By me Iohn Faustus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Speake <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> do you deliver this as your déede?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>I, take it, and the divell giue thee good on 't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephisophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Now Faustus aske what thou wilt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>First will I question with thée about hell,</l>
               <l>Tel me, where is the place that men call hell?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Under the heavens.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I, but where about?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Within the bowels of these elements,</l>
               <l>Where we are tortur'd and remaine for euer,</l>
               <l>Hell hath no limits, nor is circumscrib'd</l>
               <l>In one selfe place, for where we are is hell,</l>
               <l>And where hell is, must we ever be:</l>
               <l>And to conclude, when all the world dissolves,</l>
               <l>And euery creature shalbe purified,</l>
               <l>All places shall be hell that is not heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Come, I thinke hell's a fable.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>I, thinke so still, till experience change thy minde.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Why? thinkst thou then that Faustus shall bée
damn'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>I of necessitie, for here's the scrowle,</l>
               <l>Wherein thou hast giuen thy soule to <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I, and body too, but what of that?</l>
               <l>Thinkst thou that Faustus is so sond,</l>
               <l>To imagine, that after this life there is any paine?</l>
               <l>Tush these are trifles and méere olde wives tales.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>But Faustus I am an instance to prove the contrary
For I am damnd, and am now in hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>How? now in hell? nay and this be hell, Ile willingly
be damnd here: what walking, disputing, &amp;c. But
leauing off this, let me haue a wife, the fairest maid in <hi rend="italic">Germany,</hi>
for I am wanton and lascivious, and can not live
without a wife.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>How, a wife? I prithée <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> talke not of a wife.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Nay sweete <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis</hi> fetch me one, for I will
haue one.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Well thou wilt haue one, sit there till I come, Ile
fetch thée a wife in the divels name.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter with a divell drest like a woman,
with fier workes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Tel Faustus, how dost thou like thy wife?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>A plague on her for a hote whore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Tut Faustus, marriage is but a ceremoniall toy, if
thou lovest me, thinke more of it.</l>
               <l>Ile cull thée out the fairest curtezans,</l>
               <l>And bring them eu'ry morning to thy bed,</l>
               <l>She whome thine eie shall like, thy heart shal have,</l>
               <l>Be she as chaste as was <hi rend="italic">Penelope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As wise as <hi rend="italic">Saba,</hi> or as beautiful</l>
               <l>As was bright <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> before his fall.</l>
               <l>Hold, take this booke, peruse it thorowly,</l>
               <l>The iterating of these lines brings golde,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
The framing of this circle on the ground,</l>
               <l>Brings whirlewindes, tempests, thunder and lightning.</l>
               <l>Pronounce this thrice deuoutly to thy selfe,</l>
               <l>And men in armour shal appeare to thee,</l>
               <l>Ready to execute what thou desirst.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Thankes <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi> yet faine would I have
a booke wherein I might beholde al spels and incantations,
that I might raise up spirits when I please.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Here they are in this booke.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>There turne to them</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Now would I haue a booke where I might sée al
characters and planets of the heavens, that I might knowe
their motions and dispositions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Héere they are too. <hi rend="italic">Turne to them</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Nay let me have one booke more, and then I haue
done, wherein I might sée al plants, hearbes and trées that
grow upon the earth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Here they be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>O thou art deceived.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Tut I warrant thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Turne to them</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>When I behold the heavens, then I repent,</l>
               <l>And curse thée wicked <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Because thou hast depriv'd me of those ioyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Why Faustus,</l>
               <l>Thinkst thou heaven is such a glorious thing?</l>
               <l>I tel thée tis not halfe so faire as thou,</l>
               <l>Or any man that breathes on earth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>How proovest thou that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>It was made for man, therefore is man more excellent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>If it were made for man, twas made for me:</l>
               <l>I wil renounce this magicke, and repent.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter good Angel, and evill Angel.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good Angell.</speaker>
               <l>Faustus, repent yet, God wil pitty thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>evill Angell.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art a spirite, God cannot pitty thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Who buzzeth in mine eares I am a spirite?</l>
               <l>Be I a divel, yet God may pitty me,</l>
               <l>I God wil pitty me, if I repent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>euill Angell</speaker>
               <l>I but Faustus neuver shal repent.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>My hearts so hardned I cannot repent,</l>
               <l>Scarse can I name saluation, faith, or heaven,</l>
               <l>But feareful ecchoes thunders in mine eares,</l>
               <l>Faustus, thou art damn'd, then swordes and knives,</l>
               <l>Poyson, gunnes, halters, and invenomd stéele</l>
               <l>Are layde before me to dispatch my selfe,</l>
               <l>And long ere this I should have slaine my selfe,</l>
               <l>Had not swéete pleasure conquerd déepe dispaire.</l>
               <l>Have not I made blinde <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi> sing to me,</l>
               <l>Of <hi rend="italic">Alexanders</hi> love, and <hi rend="italic">Enons</hi> death,</l>
               <l>And hath not he that built the walles of <hi rend="italic">Thebes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With ravishing sound of his melodious harp</l>
               <l>Made musicke with my <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why should I dye then, or basely dispaire?</l>
               <l>I am resolv'd <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> shal nere repent,</l>
               <l>Come Mephastophilis, let vs dispute againe,</l>
               <l>And argue of divine <hi rend="italic">Astrologie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tel me, are there many heavens above the Moone?</l>
               <l>Are all celestiall bodies but one globe,</l>
               <l>As is the substance of this centricke earth?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>As are the elements, such are the spheares,</l>
               <l>Mutually folded in each others orbe,</l>
               <l>And <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> all iointly move upon one axletrée,</l>
               <l>Whose terminine is tearmd the worlds wide pole,</l>
               <l>Nor are the names of <hi rend="italic">Saturne, Mars,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Iupiter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faind, but are erring starres.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>But tell me, have they all one motion? both <hi rend="italic"> situ &amp;
tempore.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>All ioyntly moue from East to West in 24. houres
upon the poles of the world, but differ in their motion upon
the poles of the Zodiake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Tush, these slender trifles <hi rend="italic">Wagner</hi> can decide,</l>
               <l>Hath <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilus</hi> no greater skill?</l>
               <l>Who knowes not the double motion of the plannets?</l>
               <l>The first is straight in a naturall day,</l>
               <l>The second thus, as <hi rend="italic">Saturne</hi> in 30. yeares, <hi rend="italic">Iupiter</hi> in 12.
<pb />
                  <hi rend="italic">Mars</hi> in 4. the Sunne, <hi rend="italic">Venus,</hi> and Mercury in a yeare: the Moone in 28. dayes. Tush these are fresh mens suppositions,
but tell me, hath every spheare a dominion or <hi rend="italic">Intelligentia?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>How many heavens or spheares are there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>Nine, the seven planets, the firmament, and the imperiall
hea\ven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Well, resolve me in this question, why have wée
not coniunctions, oppositions, aspects, eclipsis, all at one
time, but in some yeares we have more, in some lesse?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>Per inaequalem motum respectu totius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Well, I am answered, tell me who made the world?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>I will not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Sweete Mephastophilus tell me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus</speaker>
               <l>Moue me not, for I will not tell thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Villaine, haue I not bound thée to tel me any thing?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MMephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>I, that is not against our kingdome, but this is,</l>
               <l>Thinke thou on hell <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> for thou art damnd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus</speaker>
               <l>Thinke Faustus upon God that made the world.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus</speaker>
               <l>Remember this.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I, goe accursed spirit to ugly hell,</l>
               <l>Tis thou hast damned distressed <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> soule:</l>
               <l>Ist not too late?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter good Angell and evill.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>evill Anegll.</speaker>
               <l>Too late.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>good Angell.</speaker>
               <l>Never too late, if Faustus can repent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>evill Angell.</speaker>
               <l>If thou repent diuels shall teare thee in péeces.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>good Agell.</speaker>
               <l>Repent, &amp; they shal neuer race thy skin.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustuss.</speaker>
               <l>Ah Christ my Sauiour, seeke to save distressed Faustus
soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lucifer, Belsabub, and Mephastophilus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer.</speaker>
               <l>Christ cannot save thy soule, for he is iust,</l>
               <l>Theres none but I have intrest in the same.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus:</speaker>
               <l>O who art thou that lookst so terrible?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer.</speaker>
               <l>I am <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi> and this is my companion Prince in
hel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>O Faustus, they are come to fetch away thy soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Lucifer</speaker>
               <l>we come to tell thée thou dost iniure vs,</l>
               <l>Thou talkst of Christ, contrary to thy promise</l>
               <l>Thou shouldst not thinke of God, thinke of the devil,</l>
               <l>And of his dam too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Nor will I henceforth: pardon me in this,</l>
               <l>And Faustus vowes never to looke so heauen,</l>
               <l>Never to name God, or to pray to him,</l>
               <l>To burne his Scriptures, slay his Ministers,</l>
               <l>And make my spirites pull his churches downe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer</speaker>
               <l>Do so, and we will highly gratifie thee:</l>
               <l>Faustus, we are come from hel to shew thée some pastime:
sit downe, and thou shalt see al the seaven deadly sinnes appeare
in their proper shapes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>That sight will be as pleasing unto me, as paradise
was to <hi rend="italic">Adam,</hi> the first day of his creation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer</speaker>
               <l>Talke not of paradise, nor creation, but marke this
shew, talke of the divel, and nothing else: come away.</l>
               <stage>Enter the seaven deadly sinnes.</stage>
               <l>Now Faustus, examine them of their several names and
dispositions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>What art thou? the first.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pride</speaker>
               <l>I am Pride, I disdaine to have any parents, I am
like to <hi rend="italic">Ovids</hi> flea, I can créepe into every corner of a wench,
sometimes like a periwig, I sit upon her brow, or like a fan
of feathers, I kisse her lippes, indéede I doe, what doe I not?
but fie, what a scent is here? Ile not speake an other worde,
except the ground were perfumde and couered with cloth of
arras.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>What art thou? the second.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Covetousness.</speaker>
               <l>I am <hi rend="italic">Covetousnes,</hi> begotten of an olde churle, in
an olde leatherne bag: and might I haue my wish, I would
desire, that this house, and all the people in it were turnd to
golde, that I might locke you uppe in my good chest, O my
sweete golde</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>What art thou? the third.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wrath</speaker>
               <l>I am <hi rend="italic">Wrath,</hi> I had neither father nor mother, I
leapt out of a lions mouth, when I was scarce half an houre
<pb />
olde, and ever since I haue runne up and downe the worlde,
with this case of rapiers wounding my selfe, when I had no
body to fight withal: I was borne in hel, and looke to it, for
some of you shalbe my father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>what art thou? the fourth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Envy</speaker>
               <l>I am <hi rend="italic">Envy,</hi> begotten of a Chimney-swéeper, and
an Oyster wife, I cannot reade, and therefore wish al bookes
were burnt: I am leane with séeing others eate, O that
there would come a famine through all the worlde, that all
might die, and I liue alone, then thou shouldst see how fatt I
would be: but must thou sit and I stand? come downe with
a vengeance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Away envious rascall: what art thou? the fift.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gluttony.</speaker>
               <l>who I sir, I am <hi rend="italic">Gluttony,</hi> my parents are al dead,
and the divel a peny they have left me, but a bare pention,
and that is 30. meales a day, and tenne beavers, a small
triflle to suffice nature, O I come of a royall parentage, my
grandfather was a gammon of bacon, my grandmother a
hogs head of Claret-wine: My godfathers were these, Peter
Pickle-herring, and Martin-Martlemas biefe, O but
my godmother she was a iolly gentlewoman, and welbeloved
in euery good towne and Citie, her name was mistresse
Margery March-béere: now <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> thou hast heard all my
Progeny, wilt thou bid me to supper?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>No, Ile sée thée hanged, thou wilt eate up all my
victualls.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gluttony.</speaker>
               <l>Then the divell choake thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Choake thy selfe glutton: what art thou? the sixt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sloath.</speaker>
               <l>I am sloath, I was begotten on a sunny banke,
where I haue laine ever since, and you have done me great
iniury to bring me from thence, let me be carried thither againe
by Gluttony and Leachery, Ile not speake an other
word for a Kings ransome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>What are you mistresse minkes? the seaventh
and last.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lechery</speaker>
               <l>Who I sir? I am one that loves an inch of raw
Mutton better then an ell of frid stock-fish, and the first
<pb />
letter of my name beginnes with leachery.</l>
               <l>Away, to hel, to hel.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt the sinnes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer.</speaker>
               <l>Now Faustus, how dost thou like this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>O this feedes my soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer.</speaker>
               <l>But Faustus, in hel is al manner of delight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>O might I sée hel, and returne againe, how happy
were I then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucifer</speaker>
               <l>Thou shalt, I wil send for thée at midnight, in mean
time take this booke, peruse it throwly, and thou shalt turne
thy selfe into what shape thou wilt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Great thankes mighty Lucifer, this wil I kéepe as
chary as my life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
               <l>Farewel Faustus, and thinke on the divel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Farewel great <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi> come <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>enter Wagner solus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Learned Faustus,</l>
               <l>To know the secrets of <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Graven in the booke of <hi rend="italic">Iouves</hi> hie firmament,</l>
               <l>Did mount himselfe to scale <hi rend="italic">Olympus</hi> top,</l>
               <l>Being seated in a chariot burning bright,</l>
               <l>Drawne by the strength of yoky dragons neckes,</l>
               <l>He now is gone to proove <hi rend="italic">Cosmography,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as I guesse, wil first arive at <hi rend="italic">Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To see the Pope, and manner of his court,</l>
               <l>And take some part of holy <hi rend="italic">Peters</hi> feast,</l>
               <l>That to this day is highly solemnizd.</l>
               <stage>exit Wagner</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Faustus and Mephastophilus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Having now, my good Mephastophilus,</l>
               <l>Past with delight the stately towne of <hi rend="italic">Trier,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Invirond round with ayrie mountaine tops,</l>
               <l>With walles of flint, and déepe intrenched lakes,</l>
               <l>Not to be wonne by any conquering prince,</l>
               <l>From <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> next coasting the Realme of France,</l>
               <l>Wée sawe the river <hi rend="italic">Maine</hi> fall into <hi rend="italic">Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose bankes are set with groves of fruitful vines.</l>
               <l>Then up to <hi rend="italic">Naples,</hi> rich <hi rend="italic">Campania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Whose buildings faire and gorgeous to the eye,</l>
               <l>The stréetes straight forth, and pau'd with finest bricke,</l>
               <l>Quarters the towne in foure equivolence.</l>
               <l>There sawe we learned <hi rend="italic">Maroes</hi> golden tombe,</l>
               <l>The way he cut an English mile in length,</l>
               <l>Thorough a rocke of stone in one nights space.</l>
               <l>From thence to <hi rend="italic">Venice, Padua,
                  </hi> and the rest,</l>
               <l>In midst of which a sumptuous Temple stands,</l>
               <l>That threats the starres with her aspiring toppe.</l>
               <l>Thus hitherto hath Faustus spent his time,</l>
               <l>But tell me now, what resting place is this?</l>
               <l>Hast thou as erst I did commaund,</l>
               <l>Conducted me within the walles of <hi rend="italic">Rome?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>Faustus I haue, and because we wil not be unprouided,
I haue taken up his holinesse privy chamber for
our use.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I hope his holinesse will bid us welcome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus</speaker>
               <l>Tut, tis no matter man, wéele be bold with his good cheare,</l>
               <l>And now my Faustus, that thou maist perceive</l>
               <l>What <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> containeth to delight thée with,</l>
               <l>Know that this Citie stands upon seven hilles</l>
               <l>That underprops the groundworke of the same,</l>
               <l>Ouer the which foure stately bridges leane,</l>
               <l>That makes safe passage to each part of <hi rend="italic">Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Upon the bridge call'd <hi rend="italic">Ponto Angelo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Erected is a Castle passing strong,</l>
               <l>Within whose walles such store of ordonance are,</l>
               <l>And double Canons, fram'd of carved brasse,</l>
               <l>As match the dayes within one compleate yeare,</l>
               <l>Besides the gates and high piramides,</l>
               <l>Which <hi rend="italic">Iulius Caesar</hi> brought from <hi rend="italic">Affrica.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Now by the kingdomes of infernall rule,</l>
               <l>Of <hi rend="italic">Styx, Acheron,
                  </hi> and the fiery lake</l>
               <l>Of ever burning <hi rend="italic">Phelegethon</hi> I sweare,</l>
               <l>That I do long to sée the monuments</l>
               <l>And scituation of bright splendant <hi rend="italic">Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come therefore lets away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>Nay Faustus stay, I know youd faine sée the Pope,</l>
               <l>And take some part of holy <hi rend="italic">Peters</hi> feast,</l>
               <l>Where thou shalt see a troupe of bald-pate Friers,</l>
               <l>Whose <hi rend="italic">summum bonum</hi> is in belly-cheare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Well, I am content, to compasse then some sport,</l>
               <l>And by their folly make vs merriment,</l>
               <l>Then charme me that I may be invisible, to do what I
please unseene of any whilst I stay in Rome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>So Faustus, now do what thou wilt, thou shalt not
be discerned.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Sound a Sonnet, enter the Pope and the Cardinall of Lorraine
to the banket, with Friers attending.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope</speaker>
               <l>My Lord of <hi rend="italic">Lorraine,</hi> wilt please you draw neare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Fall too, and the divel choake you and you spare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope</speaker>
               <l>How now, whose that which spake? Friers looke
about.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friers.</speaker>
               <l>Héere's no body, if it like your Holynesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, here is a daintie dish was sent me from
the Bishop of <hi rend="italic">Mallaine.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I thanke you sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Snatch it.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>How now, whose that which snatcht the meate
from me? will no man looke?</l>
               <l>My Lord, this dish was sent me from the Cardinall of Florence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>You say true, Ile hate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>What againe? my Lord Ile drinke to your grace</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Ile pledge your grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lorraine.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, it may be some ghost newly crept out of
Purgatory come to begge a pardon of your holinesse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope</speaker>
               <l>It may be so, Friers prepare a dirge to lay the fury
of this ghost, once againe my Lord fall too.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>The Pope crosseth himselfe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>What, are you crossing of your selfe?</l>
               <l>Well vse that tricke no more, I would advise you.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Crosse againe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Well, theres the second time, aware the third,</l>
               <l>I give you faire warning.</l>
            </sp>   <pb />
            <stage>Crosse againe, and Faustus hits him a boxe of the eare,
and they all runne away.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Come on Mephastophilis, what shall we do?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker> Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Nay I know not, we shalbe curst with bell, booke,
                  and candle.</l> 
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>How? bell, booke, and candle, candle, booke, and bell,</l>
               <l>Forward and backward, to curse <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> to hell.</l>
               <l>Anon you shal heare a hogge grunt, a calfe bleate, and an
asse braye,</l>
               <l>because it is S. <hi rend="italic">Peters</hi> holy day.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter all the Friers to sing the Dirge.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frier.</speaker>
               <l>Come brethren, lets about our businesse with good
deuotion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Sing this.</stage>
               <l>Cursed be hee that stole away his holinesse meate
from the table. <hi rend="italic">maledicat dominus.</hi></l>
                  <l>Cursed be hee that strooke his holinesse a blowe on the face. 
                  <hi rend="italic">maledicat dominus.</hi></l>
                  <l>Cursed be he that tooke Frier <hi rend="italic">Sandelo</hi> a blow on the pate.
                  <hi rend="italic">male, &amp;c.</hi></l>
                  <l>Cursed be he that disturbeth our holy Dirge. <hi rend="italic">male, &amp;c.</hi></l>
                  <l>Cursed be he that tooke away his holinesse wine.
                  <hi rend="italic">maledicat dominus.</hi></l>
                  <l><hi rend="italic">Et omnes sancti. Amen.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Beate the Friers, and fling fier-workes among
them, and so Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>When Faustus had with pleasure tane the view</l>
               <l>Of rarest things, and royal courts of kings,</l>
               <l>Hée stayde his course, and so returned home,</l>
               <l>Where such as beare his absence, but with griefe,</l>
               <l>I meane his friends and nearest companions,</l>
               <l>Did gratulate his safetie with kinde words,</l>
               <l>And in their conference of what befell,</l>
               <l>Touching his iourney through the world and ayre,</l>
               <l>They put forth questions of Astrologie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />Which <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> answerd with such learned skill,</l>
               <l>As they admirde and wondered at his wit.</l>
               <l>Now is his fame spread forth in every land,</l>
               <l>Amongst the rest the Emperour is one,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Carolus</hi> the fift, at whose pallace now</l>
               <l>Faustus is feasted mongst his noble men.</l>
               <l>What there he did in triall of his art,</l>
               <l>I leave untold, your eyes shall see performd.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Robin the Ostler with a booke in his hand</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>O this is admirable! here I ha stolne one of doctor
Faustus coniuring books, and i'faith I meane to search some
circles for my owne use: now wil I make al the maidens in
our parish dance at my pleasure starke naked before me, and
so by that meanes I shal see more then ere I shall see more than ere I felt or saw yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Rafe calling Robin.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> prethee come away, theres a Gentleman
tarries to haue his horse, and he would have his things rubd
and made cleane: he keepes such a chafing with my mistris
about it, and she has sent me to looke thée out, prethée come
away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>Keepe out, kéep out, or else you are blowne up, you
are dismembred <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> kéepe out, for I am about a roaring
peece of worke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>Come, what doest thou with that same booke thou
canst not reade?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>Yes, my maister and mistris shal finde that I can
reade, he for his forehead, she for her private study, shée's
borne to beare with me, or else my Art failes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>Why <hi rend="italic">Robin</hi> what booke is that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>What booke? why the most intollerable booke for
coniuring that ere was invented by any brimstone diuel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>Canst thou coniure with it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>I can do al these things easily with it: first, I can
make thée druncke with ippocrase at any taberne in Europe
for nothing, thats one of my coniuring workes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>Our maister Parson sayes thats nothing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>True <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> and more <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> if thou hast any mind
<pb />
to <hi rend="italic">Nan Spit</hi> our kitchin maide, then turne her and wind hir
to thy owne use, as often as thou wilt, and at midnight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>O brave <hi rend="italic">Robin;</hi> shal I have <hi rend="italic">Nan Spit,</hi> and to mine owne vse? On that condition Ile feede thy diuel with horsebread
as long as he lives, of frée cost.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>No more swéete <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> letts goe and make cleane
our bootes which lie foule vpon our handes, and then to our
coniuring in the divels name.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Robin and Rafe with a silver Goblet.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>Come <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> did not I tell thee, we were for euer
made by this doctor Faustus booke? <hi rend="italic">ecce signum,</hi> héeres a simple
purchase for horse-kéepers, our horses shal eate no hay as
long as this lasts.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>enter the Vintner.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>But <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> here comes the vintner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>Hush, Ile gul him supernaturally: Drawer, I
hope al is payd, God be with you, come <hi rend="italic">Rafe.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vintner.</speaker>
               <l>Soft sir, a word with you, I must yet haue a goblet
payde from you ere you goe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>I a goblet <hi rend="italic">Rafe,</hi> I a goblet? I scorne you: and you
are but a &amp;c. I a goblet? search me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vintner.</speaker>
               <l>I meane so sir with your fauor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>How say you now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vintner</speaker>
               <l>I must say somewhat to your felow, you sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>Me sir, me sir, search your fill: now sir, you may be
ashamed to burden honest men with a matter of truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vintner</speaker>
               <l>Wel, tone of you hath this goblet about you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>
               <l>You lie Drawer, tis afore me: sirra you, Ile teach ye
to impeach honest men: stand by, Ile scowre you for a goblet,
stand aside you had best, I charge you in the name of Belzabub:
looke to the goblet <hi rend="italic">Rafe.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vintner</speaker>
               <l>What meane you sirra?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>Ile tel you what I meane.</l>
               <stage>He reades.</stage>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sanctobulorum Periphrasticon:</hi> nay Ile tickle you Uintner,
looke to the goblet <hi rend="italic">Rafe, Polypragmos Belebeborams framanto pacostiphos
tostu Mephastophilis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mephostophilis: sets squibs at their backes:
they runne about.</stage>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Vintner</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">O nomine Domine,</hi> what meanest thou <hi rend="italic">Robin</hi> thou hast no goblet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Peccatum peccatorum,</hi> heeres thy goblet, good Uintner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Misericordia pro nobis
                  </hi> what shal I doe? good divel
forgive me now, and Ile never rob thy Library more.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter to them Mephistophilus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus.</speaker>
               <l>Vanish vilaines, th one like an Ape, an other like
a Beare, the third an Asse, for doing this enterprise.</l>
               <l>Monarch of hel, under whose blacke survey</l>
               <l>Great Potentates do kneele with awful feare,</l>
               <l>Upon whose altars thousand soules do lie</l>
               <l>How am I vexed with these vilaines charmes?</l>
               <l>From <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi> am I hither come,</l>
               <l>Onely for pleasure of these damned slaves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>How, from <hi rend="italic">Constantinople?</hi> you have had a great
iourney, wil you take sixe pence in your purse to pay for your
supper, and be gone?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilus</speaker>
               <l>wel villaines, for your presumption, I transforme
thée into an Ape, and thée into a Dog, and so be gone.</l>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>
               <l>How, into an Ape? thats brave, Ile have fine sport
with the boyes, Ile get nuts and apples enow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rafe</speaker>
               <l>And I must be a Dogge.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin</speaker>
               <l>I faith thy head wil never be out of the potage pot.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Emperour, Faustus, and a Knight,
with Attendants.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Maister doctor Faustus, I haue heard strange report
of thy knowledge in the blacke Arte, how that none in
my Empire, nor in the whole world can compare with thée,
for the rare effects of Magicke: they say thou hast a familiar
spirit, by whome thou canst accomplish what thou list, this
therefore is my request that thou let me sée some proofe of thy
skil, that mine eies may be witnesses to confirme what mine
eares have heard reported, and here I sweare to thée, by the
honor of mine Imperial crowne, that what ever thou doest,
thou shalt be no wayes preiudiced or indamaged.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight</speaker>
               <l>I faith he lookes much like a coniurer.</l>
               <stage>aside.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>My gratious Soveraigne, though I must confesse
my selfe farre inferior to the report men have published, and
nothing answerable to the honor of your Imperial maiesty,
yet for that love and duety bindes me thereunto, I am content
to do whatsoever your maiesty shall command me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Then doctor Faustus, marke what I shall say, As
I was sometime solitary set, within my Closet, sundry
thoughts arose, about the honour of mine auncestors, howe
they had wonne by prowesse such exploits, gote such riches,
subdued so many kingdomes, as we that do succéede, or they
that shal hereafter possesse our throne, shal (I feare me) neuer
attaine to that degrée of high renowne and great authoritie,
amongest which kings is <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi> the great, chiefe
spectacle of the worldes preheminence,</l>
               <l>The bright shining of whose glorious actes</l>
               <l>Lightens the world with his reflecting beames,</l>
               <l>As when I heare but motion made of him,</l>
               <l>It grieves my soule I neuer saw the man:</l>
               <l>If therefore thou, by cunning of thine Art,</l>
               <l>Canst raise this man from hollow vaults below,</l>
               <l>Where lies intombde this famous Conquerour,</l>
               <l>And bring with him his beauteous Paramour,</l>
               <l>Both in their right shapes, gesture, and attire</l>
               <l>They used to weare during their time of life,</l>
               <l>Thou shalt both satisfie my iust desire,</l>
               <l>And give me cause to praise thée whilst I live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>My gratious Lord, I am ready to accomplish your
request, so farre forth as by art and power of my spirit I am
able to performe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight</speaker>
               <l>Faith thats iust nothing at all.</l>
               <stage>aside.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>But if it like your Grace, it is not in my abilitie to
present before your eyes, the true substantiall bodies of those
two deceased princes which long since are consumed to dust.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
               <l>I mary master doctor, now theres a signe of grace
in you, when you wil confesse the trueth.</l>
               <stage>aside.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>But such spirites as can lively resemble <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi>
and his Paramour, shal appeare before your Grace, in that
<pb />
manner that they best liv'd in, in their most florishing estate,
which I doubt not shal sufficiently content your Imperiall
maiesty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Go to maister Doctor, let me sée them presently.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
               <l>Do you heare maister Doctor? you bring <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi>
and his paramour before the emperor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustis.</speaker>
               <l>How then sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
               <l>I faith thats as true as <hi rend="italic">Diana</hi> turnd me to a stag.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus:</speaker>
               <l>No sir but when <hi rend="italic">Acteon</hi> died, he left the hornes for
you: <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis</hi> be gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exit Mephistophilis.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, and you go to coniuring, Ile be gone.</l>
               <stage>exit Knight.
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Ile méete with you anone for interrupting me so:
héere they are my gratious Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mephhistophiles with Alexander and his paramour.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour</speaker>
               <l>Maister Doctor, I heard this Lady while she liv'd
had a wart or moale in her necke, how shal I know whether
it be so or no?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Your highnes may boldly go and sée.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exit Alexander</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>Sure these are no spirites, but the true substantiall
bodies of those two deceased princes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Wilt please your highnes now to send for the knight
that was so pleasant with me here of late?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour</speaker>
               <l>One of you call him foorth.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the Knight with a paire of hornes on his head.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour.</speaker>
               <l>How now sir Knight? why I had thought thou
hadst beene a batcheler, but now I sée thou hast a wife, that
not only gives thee hornes, but makes thée weare them, feele
on thy head.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knight</speaker>
               <l>Thou damned wretch, and execrable dogge,</l>
               <l>Bred in the concave of some monstrous rocke:</l>
               <l>How darst thou thus abuse a Gentleman?</l>
               <l>Uilaine I say, undo what thou hast done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>O not so fast sir, theres no haste but good, are you
remembred how you crossed me in my conference with the
emperour? I thinke I have met with you for it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>emp:</speaker>
               <l>Good Maister Doctor, at my intreaty release him,
he hath done penance sufficient.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>My Gratious Lord, not so much for the iniury hée
offred me héere in your presence, as to delight you with some
mirth, hath <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> worthily requited this iniurious knight,
which being all I desire, I am content to release him of his
hornes: and sir knight, hereafter speake well of Scholers:
<hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi> transforme him strait. Now my good Lord
hauing done my duety, I humbly take my leave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emperour</speaker>
               <l>Farewel maister Doctor, yet ere you goe, expect
from me a bounteous reward.</l>
               <stage>exit Emperour.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Now Mephastophilis, the restlesse course that time
doth runne with calme and silent foote,</l>
               <l>Shortning my dayes and thred of vitall life,</l>
               <l>Calls for the payment of my latest yeares,</l>
               <l>Therefore swéet Mephastophilis, let vs make haste to <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>What, wil you goe on horse backe, or on foote?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Nay, til I am past this faire and pleasant gréene, ile
walke on foote.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>enter a Horse-courser</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>I haue béene al this day séeking one maister Fustian:
masse sée where he is, God saue you maister doctor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>What horse-courser, you are wel met.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Do you heare sir? I have brought you forty dollers
for your horse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>I cannot sel him so: if thou likst him for fifty, take
him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Alas sir, I have no more, I pray you speake for
me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephilistophilis</speaker>
               <l>I pray you let him have him, he is an honest felow,
and he has a great charge, neither wife nor childe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Wel, come give me your money, my boy wil delvuer
him to you: but I must tel you one thing before you have
<pb />
him, ride him not into the water at any hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Why sir, wil he not drinke of all waters?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>O yes, he wil drinke of al waters, but ride him not
into the water, ride him over hedge or ditch, or where thou
wilt, but not into the water.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Wel sir, Now am I made man for ever, Ile not
leave my horse for fortie: if he had but the qualitie of hey
ding, ding, hey, ding, ding, Ide make a brave liuing on him;
hée has a buttocke as slicke as an Ele: wel god buy sir, your
boy wil deliuer him me: but hark ye sir, if my horse he sick, or
ill at ease, if I bring his water to you youle tel me what it is?</l>
               <stage>Exit Horsecourser.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Away you villaine: what, doost thinke I am a horse-doctor?
what art thou Faustus but a man condemnd to die?</l>
               <l>Thy fatall time doth drawe to finall ende</l>
               <l>Dispaire doth drive distrust unto my thoughts,</l>
               <l>Confound these passions with a quiet sléepe:</l>
               <l>Tush, Christ did call the thiefe upon the Crosse,</l>
               <l>Then rest thée Faustus quiet in conceit.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Sleepe in his chaire.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Horsecourser all wet, crying.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Alas, alas, Doctor Fustian quoth a, mas Doctor
<hi rend="italic">Lopus</hi> was neuer such a Doctor, has giuen me a purgation,
has purg'd me of fortie Dollers, I shall never sée them more:
but yet like an asse as I was, I would not be ruled by him,
for he bade me I should ride him into no water; now, I thinking
my horse had had some rare qualitie that he would not
haue had me knowne of, I like a ventrous youth, rid him into
the deepe pond at the townes ende, I was no sooner in the
middle of the pond, but my horse vanisht away, and I sat vpon
a bottle of hey, neuer so neare drowning in my life: but
Ile séeke out my Doctor, and haue my fortie dollers againe,
or Ile make it the dearest horse: O yonder is his snipper
snapper, do you heare? you, hey, passe, where's your
maister?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>why sir, what would you? you cannot speake
with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>But I wil speake with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephilstophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Why hée's fast asléepe, come some other time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>Ile speake with him now, or Ile breake his glasse-windowes
about his eares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>I tell thee he has not slept this eight nights.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hors-courser.</speaker>
               <l>And he have not slept this eight wéekes Ile speake
with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Sée where he is fast asléepe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>I, this is he, God save ye maister doctor, maister
doctor, maister doctor Fustian, fortie dollers, fortie dollers
for a bottle of hey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Why, thou seest he heares thée not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>So, ho, ho: so, ho, ho.</l>
               <stage>Hallow in his eare.</stage>
               <l>No, will you not wake? Ile make you wake ere I goe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Pull him by the legge, and pull it away.</stage>
            <l>Alas, I am undone, what shall I do:</l>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>O my legge, my legge, helpe <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi> call the
Officers, my legge, my legge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Come villaine to the Constable.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>O Lord sir, let me goe, and Ile give you fortie dollers
more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Where be they?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse-courser.</speaker>
               <l>I have none about me, come to my Oastrie and Ile
give them you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis.</speaker>
               <l>Be gone quickly.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Horsecourser runnes away.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>What is he gone? farwel he, Faustus has his legge
againe, and the Horsecourser I take it, a bottle of hey for his
labour; wel, this tricke shal cost him fortie dollers more.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Wagner.</stage>
            <l>How now <hi rend="italic">Wagner,</hi> what's the newes with thée?</l>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, the Duke of <hi rend="italic">Vanholt</hi> doth earnestly entreate
your company.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>The Duke of <hi rend="italic">Vanholt!</hi> an honourable gentleman,
to whom I must be no niggard of my cunning, come <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi>
let's away to him.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter to them the Duke, and the Dutches,
the Duke speakes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke</speaker>
               <l>Beléeve me maister Doctor, this merriment hath
much pleased me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>My gratious Lord, I am glad if contents you so
wel: but it may be Madame, you take no delight in this, I
have heard that great bellied women do long for some dainties
or other, what is it Madame? tell me, and you shal have
it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dutchess.</speaker>
               <l>Thankes, good maister doctor,
And for I sée your curteous intent to pleasure me, I wil not
hide from you the thing my heart desires, and were it nowe
summer, as it is Ianuary, and the dead time of the winter, I
would desire no better meate then a dish of ripe grapes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Alas Madame, thats nothing, <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi> be
gone: <stage>exit Mephistophilis.</stage> were it a greater thing then this, so
it would content you, you should haue it <stage>enter Mephistophilis: with the grapes.</stage>
here they be madam, wilt please you taste
on them.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke</speaker>
               <l>Beléeue me master Doctor, this makes me wonder
aboue the rest, that being in the dead time of winter, and in
the month of Ianuary, how you shuld come by these grapes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau:</speaker>
               <l>If it like your grace, the yéere is divided into twoo
circles ouer the whole worlde, that when it is héere winter
with vs, in the contrary circle it is summer with them, as in
<hi rend="italic">India>, Saba,</hi> and farther countries in the East, and by means
of a swift spirit that I have, I had them brought hither, as ye
see, how do you like them Madame, be they good?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dutchess.</speaker>
               <l>Beléeue me Maister doctor, they be the best grapes
<pb />
that ere I tasted in my life before.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I am glad they content you so Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke</speaker>
               <l>Come Madame, let us in, where you must wel reward
this learned man for the great kindnes he hath shewd
to you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dutchess</speaker>
               <l>And so I wil my Lord, and whilst I live,</l>
               <l>Rest beholding for this curtesie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>I humbly thanke your Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duchess</speaker>
               <l>Come, maister Doctor follow vs, and receive your
reward.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>enter Wagner solus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wagner.</speaker>
               <l>I thinke my maister meanes to die shortly,</l>
               <l>For he hath given to me al his goodes,</l>
               <l>And yet me thinkes, if that death were néere,</l>
               <l>He would not banquet, and carowse, and swill</l>
               <l>Amongst the Students, as even now he doth,</l>
               <l>who are at supper with such belly-cheere,</l>
               <l>As <hi rend="italic">Wagner</hi> nere beheld in all his life.</l>
               <l>Sée where they come: belike the least is ended.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Faustus with two or three Schollers</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Sch.</speaker>
               <l>Maister Doctor <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> since our conference about
faire Ladies, which was the beutifulst in all the world,
we have determined with our selves, that <hi rend="italic">Helen</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Greece</hi>
was the admirablest Lady that euer lived: therefore master
Doctor, if you wil do vs that fauor, as to let vs sée that péerelesse
Dame of <hi rend="italic">Greece,</hi> whome al the world admires for maiesty,
wée should thinke our selves much beholding vnto
you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustis.</speaker>
               <l>Gentlemen, for that I know your friendship is vnfained,
and Faustus custome is not to denie the iust requests
of those that wish him well, you shall behold that pearelesse
dame of <hi rend="italic">Greece,</hi> no otherwaies for pompe and maiestie, then
when sir <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> crost the seas with her, and brought the spoiles
to rich <hi rend="italic">Dardama.</hi> Be silent then, for danger is in words.</l>
            </sp>
           
               <pb />
            <stage>
Musicke sounds, and Helen passeth ouer the Stage.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Too simple is my wit to tell her praise,</l>
               <l>Whom all the world admires for maiestie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>3. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>No marvel tho the angry Greekes pursude</l>
               <l>With tenne yeares warre the rape of such a quéene,</l>
               <l>Whose heavenly beauty passeth all compare.</l>
            </sp>
            <l>1. Since we have séene the pride of natures workes,</l>
            <l>And onely Paragon of excellence,</l>
            <stage>Enter an old man.</stage>
            <l>Let us depart, and for this glorious déed</l>
            <l>Happy and blest be Faustus evermore.</l>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Gentlemen farwel, the same I wish to you.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Schollers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <l>Ah Doctor Faustus, that I might prevaile,</l>
               <l>To guide thy steps vnto the way of life,</l>
               <l>By which swéete path thou maist attaine the gole</l>
               <l>That shall conduct thée to celestial rest.</l>
               <l>Breake heart, drop bloud, and mingle it with teares,</l>
               <l>Teares falling from repentant heavinesse</l>
               <l>Of thy most vilde and loathsome filthinesse,</l>
               <l>The stench whereof corrupts the inward soule</l>
               <l>With such flagitious crimes of hainous sinnes,</l>
               <l>As no commiseration may expel,</l>
               <l>But mercie Faustus of thy Saviour swéete,</l>
               <l>Whose bloud alone must wash away thy guilt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Where art thou Faustus? wretch what hast thou done?</l>
               <l>Damnd art thou Faustus, damnd, dispaire and die,</l>
               <l>Hell calls for right, and with a roaring voyce</l>
               <l>Sayes, Faustus come, thine houre is come,</l>
               <stage>Mephastophalis. gives him a dagger.</stage>
               <l>And Faustus will come to do thée right.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old man.</speaker>
               <l>Ah stay good Faustus, stay thy desperate steps,</l>
               <l>I sée an Angell houers ore thy head,</l>
               <l>And with a violl full of precious grace,</l>
               <l>Offers to powre the same into thy soule,</l>
               <l>Then call for mercie and avoyd dispaire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Ah my swéete friend, I féele thy words</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
To comfort my distressed soule,</l>
               <l>Leave me a while to ponder on my sinnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old man.</speaker>
               <l>I goe swéete Faustus, but with heavy cheare,
fearing the ruine of thy hopelesse soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Accursed Faustus, where is mercie now?</l>
               <l>I do repent, and yet I do dispaire:</l>
               <l>Hell strives with grace for conquest in my breast,</l>
               <l>What shal I do to shun the snares of death?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Thou traitor Faustus, I arrest thy soule</l>
               <l>For disobedience to my soveraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>Revolt, or Ile in peece-meale teare thy flesh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Sweete <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis,</hi> intreate thy Lord</l>
               <l>To pardon my uniust presumption,</l>
               <l>And with my blood againe I wil confirme</l>
               <l>My former vow I made to <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>Do it then quickely, with unfained heart,</l>
               <l>Lest greater danger do attend thy drift.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustis</speaker>
               <l>Torment sweete friend, that base and crooked age,</l>
               <l>That durst disswade me from thy <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With greatest torments that our hel affoords.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>His faith is great, I cannot touch his soule,</l>
               <l>But what I may afflict his body with,</l>
               <l>I wil attempt, which is but little worth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>One thing, good servant, let me crave of thée</l>
               <l>To glut the longing of my hearts desire,</l>
               <l>That I might haue unto my paramour,</l>
               <l>That heavenly <hi rend="italic">Helen</hi> which I saw of late,</l>
               <l>Whose swéete imbracings may extinguish cleane</l>
               <l>These thoughts that do disswade me from my vow,</l>
               <l>And kéepe mine oath I made to <hi rend="italic">Lucifer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mephistophilis</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> this, or what else thou shalt desire,</l>
               <l>Shalbe performde in twinckling of an eie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>enter Helen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Was this the face that launcht a thousand shippes?</l>
               <l>And burnt the toplesse Towres of <hi rend="italic">Ilium?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swéete <hi rend="italic">Helen,</hi> make me immortall with a kisse:</l>
               <l>Her lips suckes forth my soule, see where it flies:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Come <hi rend="italic">Helen,</hi> come give mée my soule againe.</l>
               <l>Here wil I dwel, for heaven be in these lips,</l>
               <l>And all is drosse that is not <hi rend="italic">Helena:</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>enter old man</stage>
               <l>I wil be <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> and for love of thée,</l>
               <l>Instéede of <hi rend="italic">Troy</hi> shal <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge</hi> be sackt,</l>
               <l>And I wil combate with weake <hi rend="italic">Menelaus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And weare thy colours on my plumed Crest:</l>
               <l>Yea I wil wound <hi rend="italic">Achillis</hi> in the héele,</l>
               <l>And then returne to <hi rend="italic">Helen</hi> for a kisse.</l>
               <l>O thou art fairer then the evening aire,</l>
               <l>Clad in the beauty of a thousand starres,</l>
               <l>Brighter art thou then flaming <hi rend="italic">Iupiter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When he appeard to haplesse <hi rend="italic">Semele,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More lovely then the monarke of the skie</l>
               <l>And wanton Arethuses azure arms</l>
               <l>And none but thou shalt be my paramour.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old man.</speaker>
               <l>Accursed <hi rend="italic">Faustus,</hi> miserable man,</l>
               <l>That from thy soule excludst the grace of heaven,</l>
               <l>And fliest the throne of his tribunall seate,</l>
               <stage>Enter the Devils.</stage>
               <l>Satan begins to sift me with his pride,</l>
               <l>As in this furnace God shal try my faith,</l>
               <l>My faith, vile hel, shal triumph over thée,</l>
               <l>Ambitious friends, sée how the heavens smile
               </l>
               <l>At your repulse, and laughs your state to scorn,</l>
               <l>Hence hel, for hence I flie unto my God.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Faustus with the Schollers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Ah Gentlemen!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Scholar
               </speaker>
               <l>What ailes Faustus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Ah my swéete chamber-fellow! had I lived with
thée, then had I liued stil, but now I die eternally: looke,
comes he not? comes he not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Scholar</speaker>
               <l>What meanes Faustus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>3. Scholar</speaker>
               <l>Belike he is growne into some sickenesse, by
<pb />
being ever solitary.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Scholar:</speaker>
               <l>If it be so, wéele have Physitians to cure him,
tis but a surffit, never feare man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus:</speaker>
               <l>A surffet of deadly sinne that hath damnd both body
and soule.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Yet Faustus looke up to heauen, remember gods
mercies are infinite.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>But Faustus offence can nere be pardoned,
               The Serpent that tempted <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi> may be saved,
               But not Faustus: Ah Gentlemen, hear with patience,
and tremble not at my spéeches, though my heart pants and
quivers to remember that I haue beene a student here these
thirty yéeres, O would I had never séene <hi rend="italic">Wertenberge,</hi> never
read booke: and what wonders I have done, al Germany
can witnes, yea all the world, for which Faustus hath lost
both <hi rend="italic">Germany,</hi> and the world, yea heaven it selfe, the
seate of God, the throne of the blessed, the kingdome of ioy,
and must remaine in hel for ever, hel ah hel for ever. Sweet
friends, what shall become of Faustus, being in hel for ever?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>3rd. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Yet Faustus call on God.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>On god whom Faustus hath abjured, on God, whome Faustus hath blasphemed, ah my God, I would weepe, but the divel draws in my tears. Gush forth blood instead of tears, yea, life and soule. Oh, he stayes my tongue, I would lift up my ands, theuy hold them, they hold them.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All</speaker>
               <l>Who Faustus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Lucifer and Mephastophilis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ah Gentlemen! I gaue them my soule for my cunning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All</speaker>
               <l>God forbid.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>God forbade it indéede, but Faustus hath done it:
for vaine pleasure of 24 yeares, hath Faustus lost eternall
ioy and felicitie, I writ them a bill with mine owne bloud,
the date is expired, the time will come, and he wil fetch mee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  1 Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Why did not Faustus tel us of this before, that
Diuines might haue prayed for thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb />
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Oft have I thought to have done so, but the divell
threatned to teare mée in péeces, if I namde God, to fetch
both body and soule, if I once gaue eare to diuinitie: and
now tis too late: Gentlemen away, lest you perish with me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>O what shal we do to Faustus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus</speaker>
               <l>Talke not of me, but saue your selues, and depart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>3. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>God wil strengthen me, I wil stay with Faustus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Tempt not God, swéete friend, but let us into the
next roome, and there pray for him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>I pray for me, pray for me, and what noyse soever
yée heare, come not unto me, for nothing can rescue me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Scholar.</speaker>
               <l>Pray thou, and we wil pray that God may have
mercy vpon thée.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Gentlemen farewel, if I live til morning, Ile visite
you: if not, Faustus is gone to hel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All</speaker>
               <l>Faustus, farewel.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Schollars.</stage>
            <stage>The clocke strikes eleauen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faustus.</speaker>
               <l>Ah Faustus,</l>
               <l>Now hast thou but one bare hower to liue,</l>
               <l>And then thou must be damnd perpetually:</l>
               <l>Stand stil you ever mooving spheres of heauen,</l>
               <l>That time may cease, and midnight never come:</l>
               <l>Faire Natures eie, rise rise, againe, and make</l>
               <l>Perpetuall day, or let this houre be but a yeere,</l>
               <l>A moneth, a wéeke, a naturall day,</l>
               <l>That Faustus may repent and save his soule,</l>
               <l>O lente lente curite noctis equi:</l>
               <l>The starres mooue stil, time runs, the clocke wil strike,</l>
               <l>The divel wil come, and Faustus must be damnd.</l>
               <l>O Ile leape up to my God: who pulles me downe?</l>
               <l>See see where Christs blood streames in the firmament,</l>
               <l>One drop would save my soule, halfe a drop, ah my Christ,</l>
               <l>Ah rend not my heart for naming of my Christ,</l>
               <l>Yet wil I call on him, oh spare me <hi rend="italic">Lucifer!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Where is it now? tis gone:</l>
               <l>And see where God stretcheth out his arme,</l>
               <l>And bends his irefull browes:</l>
               <l>Mountaines and hilles, come come, and fall on me,</l>
               <l>And hide me from the heavy wrath of God.</l>
               <l>No no, then wil I headlong runne into the earth:</l>
               <l>Earth gape, O no, it wil not harbour me:</l>
               <l>You starres that raignd at my nativitie,</l>
               <l>Whose influence hath alotted death and hel,</l>
               <l>Now draw up Faustus like a foggy mist,</l>
               <l>Into the intrailes of yon labring cloude,</l>
               <l>That when you vomite foorth into the ayre,</l>
               <l>My limbes may issue from your smoaky mouthes,</l>
               <l>So that my soule may but ascend to heauen:</l>
               <l>Ah, halfe the houre is past:</l>
               <stage>The watch strikes.</stage>
               <l>Twil all be past anone:</l>
               <l>Oh God, if thou wilt not have mercy on my soule,</l>
               <l>Yet for Christs sake, whose bloud hath ransomd me,</l>
               <l>Impose some end to my incessant paine,</l>
               <l>Let Faustus live in hel a thousand yeeres,</l>
               <l>A hundred thousand, and at last be saved.</l>
               <l>O no end is limited to damned soules,</l>
               <l>Why wert thou not a creature wanting soule?</l>
               <l>Or, why is this immortall that thou hast?</l>
               <l>Ah Pythagoras <hi rend="italic">metem su cossis</hi>
                   were that true,</l>
               <l>This soule should flie from me, and I be changde</l>
               <l>Unto some brutish beast: al beasts are happy, for when they die,</l>
               <l>Their soules are soone dissolvd in elements,</l>
               <l>But mine must liue still to be plagde in hel:</l>
               <l>Curst be the parents that ingendred me:</l>
               <l>No Faustus, curse thy selfe, curse <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That hath depriude thée of the ioyes of heauen:</l>
               <stage>The clooke striketh twelve.</stage>
               <l>O it strikes, it strikes, now body turne to ayre,</l>
               <l>Or <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> wil beare thée quicke to hel:</l>
               <stage>Thunder and lightning.</stage>
               <l>
                  <pb />
Oh soule, be changde into little water drops,</l>
               <l>And fal into the <hi rend="italic">Ocean,</hi> nere be found:</l>
               <l>My God, my God, looke not so fierce on me:</l>
               <stage>Enter divels.</stage>
               <l>Adders, and Serpents, let me breathe a while:</l>
               <l>Ugly hell gape not, come not <hi rend="italic">Lucifer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile burne my bookes, ah <hi rend="italic">Mephastophilis.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi rend="italic">exeunt</hi> with him</stage>
            <stage>Enter</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>Cut is the branch that might have growne ful straight,</l>
               <l>And burned is <hi rend="italic">Apolloes</hi> Laurel bough,</l>
               <l>That sometime grew within this learned man:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Faustus</hi> is gone, regard his hellish fall,</l>
               <l>Whose fiendful fortune may exhort the wise,</l>
               <l>Onely to wonder at unlawful things,</l>
               <l>whose deepenesse doth intise such forward wits,</l>
               <l>To practise more than heavenly power permits.</l>
            </sp>
            <closer>Terminat hora diem, Terminat Author opus.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
