<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eliot-tradition">
 
 
 <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Tradition and the Individual Talent</title>
    <author>
     <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79006870">
      <name><forename>T.S.</forename><surname>Eliot</surname></name>
     </persName>
     
    </author>
    
    
    <editor>
     <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">
      <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
       <forename>Tonya</forename>
       <surname>Howe</surname>
      </name>
     </persName>
    </editor>
    
    <respStmt>
     <!-- edit this content to reflect this digital edition -->
     <resp>Markup</resp>
     <name ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</name>
     <!-- More names can be added as needed. Be sure to add a unique identifier pointing to further information about contributors in editors.xml.  -->
    </respStmt>
    
    <sponsor/>
    <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
    <address>
     
     <addrLine>thowe@marymount.edu</addrLine>
     <!-- Add your email address.  -->
     <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
     <!-- Do not alter. -->
    </address>
    <availability status="free">
     <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
      Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
      License </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   
   <sourceDesc>
    
    <biblStruct>
     
     <analytic>
      <title>"Tradition and the Individual Talent</title>
     </analytic>
     <monogr>
      <author>
       <name><forename>T. S. </forename>
        <surname>Eliot</surname></name>
       
      </author>
      
      <title>The Sacred Wood</title>
      
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>
        <placeName type="tgn" key="7013596">London</placeName>
       </pubPlace>
       <publisher>Methuen &amp; Co</publisher>
       <date when="1920">1920</date>
       
       <note>"Tradition and the Individual Talent" was first published in the journal <hi rend="italic">The Egoist</hi> in 1919. It was republished in 1920 in Eliot's essay collection <hi rend="italic">The Sacred.</hi>This edition is based on the Hathi Trust copy of the first edition of that volume. Page images are taken from that copy.</note>
      </imprint>
      
      <extent></extent>
      
      
      
     </monogr>
     
    </biblStruct>
    
   </sourceDesc>
   
  </fileDesc>
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="en">English</language>
    
   </langUsage>
   
   <creation/>
   
   <textDesc n="essay">
    
    <channel mode="w">print</channel>
    
    <constitution type="single">single essay</constitution>
    <derivation type="original"/>
    <domain/>
    <factuality type="inapplicable"/>
    <interaction/>
    <preparedness type="revised"/>
    <purpose type="express"/>
    <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
    
   </textDesc>
   
   <settingDesc>
    
    <setting>
     
     <time from="1910" to="1925">Early 20th Century</time>
     
    </setting>
    
   </settingDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   
   <projectDesc>
    <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
     project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
     primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
     literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
     Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
     University.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <interpretation>
     <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
      links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
      defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
      notice an error in these annotations, please contact
      lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
    </interpretation>
    <normalization>
     <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
      silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
    </normalization>
    <hyphenation>
     <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
      word.</p>
    </hyphenation>
    <segmentation>
     <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
      not.</p>
    </segmentation>
    <correction>
     <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
      possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
    </correction>
   </editorialDecl>
   <tagsDecl>
    <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
     <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
    </namespace>
   </tagsDecl>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
     <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
    <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
     <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
    <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
     <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
    <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
     <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-10-19" who="editors.xml#TH">Initial markup</change>
   
  </revisionDesc>
  
 </teiHeader>
 
 
 
 <text>
  

<body>




<head>Tradition and the Individual Talent </head> 
 
<head> I </head>

<pb n="42" facs="pageImages/p.42.jpg"/>
 <p>IN English writing we seldom speak of tradition, 
 though we occasionally apply its name in deplor- 
 ing its absence. We cannot refer to " the tradition " 
 or to "a tradition"; at most, we employ the ad- 
 jective in saying that the poetry of So-and-so is 
 " traditional " or even " too traditional." Seldom, 
 perhaps, does the word appear except in a phrase of 
 censure. If otherwise, it is vaguely approbative, with 
 the implication, as to the work approved, of some 
 pleasing archaeological reconstruction. You can 
 hardly make the word agreeable to English ears 
 without this comfortable reference to the reassuring 
 science of archaeology.</p>
 
 <p>Certainly the word is not likely to appear in our 
 appreciations of living or dead writers. Every nation, 
 every race, has not only its own creative, but its own 
 critical turn of mind ; and is even more oblivious of 
 the shortcomings and limitations of its critical habits 
 than of those of its creative genius. We know, or 
 think we know, from the enormous mass of critical 
 writing that has appeared in the French language the 
 critical method or habit of the French ; we only con- 
 clude (we are such unconscious people) that the 
 French are " more critical " than we, and sometimes </p>
 



<pb n="43" facs="pageImages/P.43.jpg"/>
<p>Tradition and the Individual Talent </p>
 
<p>even plume ourselves a little with the fact, as if the 
 French were the less spontaneous. Perhaps they are ; 
 but we might remind ourselves that criticism is as 
 inevitable as breathing, and that we should be none 
 the worse for articulating what passes in our minds 
 when we read a book and feel an emotion about it, 
 for criticizing our own minds in their work of criticism. 
 One of the facts that might come to light in this 
 process is our tendency to insist, when we praise a 
 poet, upon those aspects of his work in which he 
 least resembles anyone else. In these aspects or 
 parts of his work we pretend to find what is indi- 
 vidual, what is the peculiar essence of the man. 
 We dwell with satisfaction upon the poet's difference 
 from his predecessors, especially his immediate pre- 
 decessors ; we endeavour to find something that can 
 be isolated in order to be enjoyed. Whereas if we 
 approach a poet without his prejudice we shall often 
 find that not only the best, but the most individual 
 parts of his work may be those in which the dead 
 poets, his ancestors, assert their immortality most 
 vigorously. And I do not mean the impressionable 
 period of adolescence, but the period of full maturity. </p>
 <p>Yet if the only form of tradition, of handing down, 
 consisted in following the ways of the immediate 
 generation before us in a blind or timid adherence to 
 its successes, "tradition" should positively be dis- 
 couraged. We have seen many such simple currents 
 soon lost in the sand ; and novelty is better than 
 repetition. Tradition is a matter of much wider 
 significance. It cannot be inherited, and if you want 
 it you must obtain it by great labour. It involves, in 
 the first place, the historical sense, which we may </p>
 
 
 
<pb n="44" facs="pageImages/p.44.jpg"/>

 
<p>call nearly indispensable to anyone who would con- 
 tinue to be a poet beyond his twenty-fifth year ; and 
 the historical sense involves a perception, not only of 
 the pastness of the past, but of its presence ; the his- 
 torical sense compels a man to write not merely with 
 his own generation in his bones, but with a feeling 
 that the whole of the literature of Europe from 
 Homer and within it the whole of the literature of 
 his own country has a simultaneous existence and 
 composes a simultaneous order. This historical sense, 
 which is a sense of the timeless as well as of the 
 temporal and of the timeless and of the temporal 
 together, is what makes a writer traditional. And it 
 is at the same time what makes a writer most acutely 
 conscious of his place in time, of his contempo- 
 raneity. </p>
 
<p>No poet, no artist of any art, has his complete 
 meaning alone. His significance, his appreciation is 
 the appreciation of his relation to the dead poets and 
 artists. You cannot value him alone ; you must set 
 him, for contrast and comparison, among the dead. 
 I mean this as a principle of aesthetic, not merely 
 historical, criticism. The necessity that he shall con- 
 form, that he shall cohere, is not one-sided ; what 
 happens when a new work of art is created is some- 
 thing that happens simultaneously to all the works 
 of art which preceded it. The existing monuments 
 form an ideal order among themselves, which is 
 modified by the introduction of the new (the really 
 new) work of art among them. The existing order is 
 complete before the new work arrives; for order to 
 persist after the supervention of novelty, the whole 
 existing order must be, if ever so slightly, altered; </p>
 



<pb n="45" facs="pageImages/p.45.jpg"/>

 
<p>and so the relations, proportions, values of each work 
 of art toward the whole are readjusted; and this is 
 conformity between the old and the new. Whoever 
 has approved this idea of order, of the form of 
 European, of English literature, will not find it pre- 
 posterous that the past should be altered by the 
 present as much as the present is directed by the 
 past. And the poet who is aware of this will be 
 aware of great difficulties and responsibilities.</p> 
 
<p>In a peculiar sense he will be aware also that he 
 must inevitably be judged by the standards of the 
 past. I say judged, not amputated, by them; not 
 judged to be as good as, or worse or better than, 
 the dead; and certainly not judged by the canons 
 of dead critics. It is a judgment, a comparison, in 
 which two things are measured by each other. To 
 conform merely would be for the new work not really 
 to conform at all ; it would not be new, and would 
 therefore not be a work of art. And we do not quite 
 say that the new is more valuable because it fits in ; 
 but its fitting in is a test of its value a test, it is 
 true, which can only be slowly and cautiously applied, 
 for we are none of us infallible judges of conformity. 
 We say : it appears to conform, and is perhaps indi- 
 vidual, or it appears individual, and may conform ; 
 but we are hardly likely to find that it is one and not 
 the other</p>
 
<p>To proceed to a more, intelligible exposition of the 
 relation of the poet to the past : he can neither take 
 the past as a lump, an indiscriminate bolus, nor 
 can he form himself wholly on one or two private 
 admirations, nor can he form himself wholly upon 
 one preferred period. The first course is inadmissible, </p>

<pb n="46" facs="pageImages/p.46.jpg"/>

 
<p>the second is an important experience of youth, and 
 the third is a pleasant and highly desirable supple- 
 ment. The poet must be very conscious of the main 
 current, which does not at all flow invariably through 
 the most distinguished reputations. He must be 
 quite aware of the obvious fact that art never improves, 
 but that the material of art is never quite the same. 
 He must be aware that the mind of Europe the 
 mind of his own country a mind which he learns 
 in time to be much more important than his own 
 private mind is a mind which changes, and that 
 this change is a development which abandons nothing 
 en route, which does not superannuate either Shake- 
 speare, or Homer, or the rock drawing of the Mag- 
 dalenian draughtsmen. That this development, 
 refinement perhaps, complication certainly, is not, 
 from the point of view of the artist, any improvement. 
 Perhaps not even an improvement from the point of 
 view of the psychologist or not to the extent which 
 we imagine ; perhaps only in the end based upon a 
 complication in economics and machinery. But the 
 difference between the present and the past is that the 
 conscious present is an awareness of the past in a 
 way and to an extent which the past's awareness of 
 itself cannot show. </p>
 
<p>Some one said : " The dead writers are remote from 
 us because we know so much more than they did." 
 Precisely, and they are that which we know. </p> 
 
<p>I am alive to a usual objection to what is clearly 
 part of my programme for the métier of poetry. The 
 objection is that the doctrine requires a ridiculous 
 amount of erudition (pedantry), a claim which can be 
 rejected by appeal to the lives of poets in any pan-</p> 
 


<pb n="47" facs="pageImages/p.47.jpg"/>

 
<p>theon. It will even be affirmed that much learning 
 deadens or perverts poetic sensibility. While, how- 
 ever, we persist in believing that a poet ought to 
 know as much as will not encroach upon his necessary 
 receptivity and necessary laziness, it is not desirable 
 to confine knowledge to whatever can be put into a 
 useful shape for examinations, drawing-rooms, or the 
 still more pretentious modes of publicity. Some can 
 absorb knowledge, the more tardy must sweat for it. 
 Shakespeare acquired more essential history from Plu- 
 tarch than most men could from the whole British 
 Museum. What is to be insisted upon is that the 
 poet must develop or procure the consciousness of 
 the past and that he should continue to develop this 
 consciousness throughout his career. </p>
 
<p>What happens is a continual surrender of himself 
 as he is at the moment to something which is more 
 valuable. The progress of an artist is a continual self- 
 sacrifice, a continual extinction of personality. </p>
 
<p>There remains to define this process of deperson- 
 alization and its relation to the sense of tradition. It 
 is in this depersonalization that art may be said to 
 approach the condition of science. I shall, therefore, 
 invite you to consider, as a suggestive analogy, the 
 action which takes place when a bit of finely filiated 
 platinum is introduced into a chamber containing 
 oxygen and sulphur dioxide. </p>
 
 <head>II</head>
 
<p>Honest criticism and sensitive appreciation is 
 directed not upon the poet but upon the poetry. If 
 we attend to the confused cries of the newspaper </p>


<pb n="48" facs="pageImages/p.48.jpg"/>

 
<p>critics and the susurrus of popular repetition that 
 follows, we shall hear the names of poets in great 
 numbers; if we seek not Blue-book knowledge but 
 the enjoyment of poetry, and ask for a poem, we shall 
 seldom find it. In the last article I tried to point 
 out the importance of the relation of the poem to 
 other poems by other authors, and suggested the 
 conception of poetry as a living whole of all the 
 poetry that has ever been written. The other aspect of 
 this Impersonal theory of poetry is the relation of the 
 poem to its author. And I hinted, by an analogy, that 
 the mind of the mature poet differs from that of the 
 immature one not precisely in any valuation of 
 " personality," not being necessarily more interesting, 
 or having " more to say," but rather by being a more 
 finely perfected medium in which special, or very 
 varied, feelings are at liberty to enter into new com- 
 binations. </p>
 
<p>The analogy was that of the catalyst. When the 
 two gases previously mentioned are mixed in the 
 presence of a filament of platinum, they form sul- 
 phurous acid. This combination takes place only 
 if the platinum is present; nevertheless the newly 
 formed acid contains no trace of platinum, and the 
 platinum itself is apparently unaffected ; has remained 
 inert, neutral, and unchanged. The mind of the poet 
 is the shred of platinum. It may partly or exclusively 
 operate upon the experience of the man himself; but, 
 the more perfect the artist, the more completely 
 separate in him will be the man who suffers and the 
 mind which creates; the more perfectly will the 
 mind digest and transmute the passions which are its 
 material. </p>
 

<pb n="49" facs="pageImages/p.49.jpg"/>

 
<p>The experience, you will notice, the elements 
 which enter the presence of the transforming catalyst, 
 are of two kinds : emotions and feelings. The effect 
 of a work of art upon the person who enjoys it is an 
 experience different in kind from any experience not 
 of art. It may be formed out of one emotion, or 
 may be a combination of several ; and various feel- 
 ings, inhering for the writer in particular words or 
 phrases or images, may be added to compose the 
 final result. Or great poetry may be made without 
 the direct use of any emotion whatever : composed 
 out of feelings solely. Canto XV of the Inferno 
 (Brunetto Latini) is a working up of the emotion 
 evident in the situation ; but the effect, though single 
 as that of any work of art, is obtained by consider- 
 able complexity of detail. The last quatrain gives 
 an image, a feeling attaching to an image, which 
 " came," which did not develop simply out of what 
 precedes, but which was probably in suspension in 
 the poet's mind until the proper combination arrived 
 for it to add itself to. The poet's mind is in fact a 
 receptacle for seizing and storing up numberless feel- 
 ings, phrases, images, which remain there until all 
 the particles which can unite to form a new com- 
 pound are present together. </p>
 
<p>If you compare several representative passages of 
 the greatest poetry you see how great is the variety 
 of types of combination, and also how completely any 
 semi-ethical criterion of " sublimity " misses the mark. 
 For it is not the "greatness," the intensity, of the 
 emotions, the components, but the intensity of the 
 artistic process, the pressure, so to speak, under 
 which the fusion takes place, that counts. The </p>


<pb n="50" facs="pageImages/p.50.jpg"/>

 
<p>episode of Paolo and Francesca employs a definite 
 emotion, but the intensity of the poetry is something 
 quite different from whatever intensity in the supposed 
 experience it may give the impression of. It is no 
 more intense, furthermore, than Canto XXVI, the 
 voyage of Ulysses, which has not the direct depend- 
 ence upon an emotion. Great variety is possible in 
 the process of transmution of emotion : the murder 
 of Agamemnon, or the agony of Othello, gives an 
 artistic effect apparently closer to a possible original 
 than the scenes from Dante. In the Agamemnon, 
 the artistic emotion approximates to the emotion of 
 an actual spectator; in Othello to the emotion of 
 the protagonist himself. But the difference between 
 art and the event is always absolute ; the combina- 
 tion which is the murder of Agamemnon is probably 
 as complex as that which is the voyage of Ulysses. 
 In either case there has been a fusion ef elements. 
 The ode of Keats contains a number of feelings 
 which have nothing particular to do with the night- 
 ingale, but which the nightingale, partly, perhaps, 
 because of its attractive name, and partly because of 
 its reputation, served to bring together.</p> 
 
<p>The point of view which I am struggling to attack 
 is perhaps related to the metaphysical theory of the 
 substantial unity of the soul : for my meaning is, that 
 the poet has, not a "personality" to express, but a 
 particular medium, which is only a medium and not 
 a personality, in which impressions and experiences 
 combine in peculiar and unexpected ways. Im- 
 pressions and experiences which are important 
 for the man may take no place in the poetry, 
 and those which become important in the poetry </p>


<pb n="51" facs="pageImages/p.51.jpg"/>

 
<p>may play quite a negligible part in the man, the 
 personality. </p>
 
<p>I will quote a passage which is unfamiliar enough 
 to be regarded with fresh attention in the light or 
 darkness of these observations: </p>
 
<p>And now methinks I could e'en chide myself 
 For doating on her beauty, though her death 
 Shall be revenged after no common action. 
 Does the silkworm expend her yellow labours 
 For thee? For thee does she undo herself? 
 Are lordships sold to maintain ladyships 
 For the poor benefit of a bewildering minute? 
 Why does yon fellow falsify highways, 
 And put his life between the judge's lips, 
 To refine such a thing keeps horse and men 
 To beat their valours for her? . . . </p>
 
<p>In this passage (as is evident if it is taken in its con- 
 text) there is a combination of positive and negative 
 emotions: an intensely strong attraction toward 
 beauty and an equally intense fascination by the 
 ugliness which is contrasted with it and which 
 destroys it. This balance of contrasted emotion is 
 in the dramatic situation to which the speech is 
 pertinent, but that situation alone is inadequate to 
 it. This is, so to speak, the structural emotion, pro- 
 vided by the drama. But the whole effect, the 
 dominant tone, is due to the fact that a number of 
 floating feelings, having an affinity to this emotion by 
 no means superficially evident, have combined with it 
 to give us a new art emotion. </p>
 
<p>It is not in his personal emotions, the emotions 
 provoked by particular events in his life, that the 
 poet is in any way remarkable or interesting. His </p>



<pb n="52" facs="pageImages/p.52.jpg"/>

 
<p>particular emotions may be simple, or crude, or flat. 
 The emotion in his poetry will be a very complex 
 thing, but not with the complexity of the emotions 
 of people who have very complex or unusual 
 emotions in life. One error, in fact, of eccentricity in 
 poetry is to seek for new human emotions to express : 
 and in this search for novelty in the wrong place it 
 discovers the perverse. The business of the poet is 
 not to find new emotions, but to use the ordinary 
 onqs and, in working them up into poetry, to express 
 feelings which are not in actual emotions at all. 
 And emotions which he has never experienced will 
 serve his turn as well as those familiar to him. Con- 
 sequently, we must believe that " emotion recollected 
 in tranquillity" is an inexact formula. For it is 
 neither emotion, nor recollection, nor, without dis- 
 tortion of meaning, tranquillity. It is a concentra- 
 tion, and a new thing resulting from the concentration, 
 of a very great number of experiences which to the 
 practical and active person would not seem to be 
 experiences at all ; it is a concentration which does 
 not happen consciously or of deliberation. These 
 experiences are not "recollected," and they finally 
 unite in an atmosphere which is "tranquil" only in 
 that it is a passive attending upon the event. Of 
 course this is not quite the whole story. There is a 
 great deal, in the writing of poetry, which must be 
 conscious and deliberate. In fact, the bad poet is 
 usually unconscious where he ought to be con- 
 scious, and conscious where he ought to be uncon- 
 scious. Both errors end to make him "personal." 
 Poetry is not a turning loose of emotion, but an 
 escape from emotion; it is not the expression of </p>


<pb n="53" facs="pageImages/p.53.jpg"/>

 
<p>personality, but an escape from personality. But, 
 of course, only those who have personality and 
 emotions know what it means to want to escape from 
 these things. </p>
 
<head> III</head>
 
<p>ὁ δὲ νοῦς ἴσως θειότερον τι καὶ ἀπαθές ἐστιν</p>

 
<p>This essay proposes to halt at the frontier of meta- 
 physics or mysticism, and confine itself to such 
 practical conclusions as can be applied by the re- 
 sponsible person interested in poetry. To divert 
 interest from the poet to the poetry is a laudable aim : 
 for it would conduce to a juster estimation of actual 
 poetry, good and bad. There are many people who 
 appreciate the expression of sincere emotion in verse, 
 and there is a smaller number of people who can 
 appreciate technical excellence. But very few know 
 when there is expression of significant emotion, 
 emotion which has its life in the poem and not in 
 the history of the poet. The emotion of art is 
 impersonal. And the poet cannot reach this im- 
 personality without surrendering himself wholly to 
 the work to be done. And he is not likely to know 
 what is to be done unless he lives in what is not 
 merely the present, but the present moment of the 
 past, unless he is conscious, not of what is dead, but 
 of what is already living. </p>
</body>
 </text>
</TEI>
 
 

