<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
    Extent Still needs to be worked out with the proper sizing dimensionso`8j
    ClassDecl/Taxonomy stuff needs to be inserted and properly done.
!-->         
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Swift">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Travels into Several Remote Nations of the World</title>

                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n97925119">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Jonathan</forename>
                            <surname>Swift</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Students of The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>Samuel Nicol</name>
                    <name>Millicent Wise</name>
                    <name>Jianna Torre</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                    <name>Spencer Suddarth</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>

                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>

                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>This edition has been prepared from the edition undertaken by the University
                    of Virginia Library, which reproduces the copy of the first edition in the
                    University of Virginia Special Collections Library, Charlottesville, Virginia.
                    <extent/>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n97925119">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Jonathan </forename>
                                    <surname>Swift</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Travels into Several Remote Nations of the World</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="city" key="ld">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Benjamin Motte</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="England">United Kingdom</placeName>
                                <placeName type="city" key="lon">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <date when="1726">1726</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> The publication history of <hi
                                    rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi> is complicated, and so too
                                is the publication history of this digital edition. Swift's first
                                publisher, Benjamin Motte, altered the text a bit to disguise some
                                of the harshest and most obvious episodes of satire against the
                                government. Most of these changes occur in Book I, where the
                                Lilliputian court was enough like the court culture of London in
                                1726 that readers would be quick to make obvious connections. Swift
                                does not seem to have been happy about the changes, and when the
                                opportunity came to revise the text back to what he intended in
                                1735, Swift took it, and restored some of the original jokes. This
                                is the edition that has most frequently been reprinted since the
                                1730s. Our digital edition is based on the version encoded for the
                                University of Virginia's E-Text Center in the 1990s and early 2000s.
                                It in turn is a transcription of the 1784 edition of Swift's
                                collected works as edited by Thomas Sheridan. Why this particular
                                edition was chosen by the E-Text Center is at this point beyond
                                reconstruction; one suspects that the facts that the edition was in
                                the public domain and close at hand played a significant part. But
                                the choice of base text explains why there are a few points where
                                the reading text produced here differs from the page images, which
                                are taken from a copy of the first, 1726 edition in the University
                                of Michigan Library, digitized by Google and accessed through the
                                HathiTrust.</note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="satire">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <time when="1726">1726</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in
                        Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up
                    selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British
                    and American literature of the 18th century. This project is funded by the
                    National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University
                    of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb n="[Title Page]"
                    facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-title-page.jpg"/>

                <titlePart type="main"><ref target="a000" corresp="n000">TRAVELS</ref>
                    <lb/> INTO SEVERAL <lb/> Remote NATIONS <lb/> OF THE <lb/> WORLD. <milestone
                        unit="part" rend="line"/>
                    <lb/> IN FOUR PARTS</titlePart>
                <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                <lb/>
                <titlePart type="subtitle">By <hi rend="italic">LEMUEL GULLIVER,</hi>
                    <lb/> first a Surgeon, and then a Captain <lb/> of several SHIPS</titlePart>
                <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                <lb/>
                <titlePart type="desc">VOL. I.</titlePart>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781"><hi rend="italic"
                            >LONDON:</hi></placeName></pubPlace>
                    <publisher><hi rend="italic">Printed for</hi> BENJ. MOTTE, <hi rend="italic">at
                            the Middle</hi> Temple-Gate <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
                        Fleet-street</publisher>
                    <docDate>M, DCC, XXVI</docDate></docImprint>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>
                <note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n000" target="a000">When it was first published in 1726, the book that
                    we have come to call <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi> appeared, without
                    any advance notice or fanfare, on the shelves of London booksellers under the
                    title <hi rend="italic">Travels into Several Remote Nations of the World</hi>.
                    The book identified its author as “Lemuel Gulliver, first a Surgeon, and then a
                    Captain of Several Ships." The name Jonathan Swift appeared nowhere on or in the
                    the book. Rather, a man named “Lemuel Gulliver" was was said to be the author,
                    his seeming authenticity proven by the fact that he was portrayed in a
                    frontispiece portrait that identified him as being fifty-eight years old and a
                    resident of Redriff, a village on the Thames river to the south east of London,
                    a logical place for a retired seaman to be living. <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic
                            url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/notes/1726-Frontispiece.jpg"
                            style="float:right" width="300px"/>
                    </figure>
                    <caption><hi rend="center">"Lemuel Gulliver," from a copy printed for the second
                            state of the first, 1726 edition. The Latin caption, from the Roman
                            satirist Persius, translates as something like "justice, uprightness,
                            and nobility of soul, in the sacred places of the mind, with a heart
                            filled with generous honor." University of Virginia
                        Library</hi></caption>
                    <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/> There was of course no Lemuel Gulliver, and the travels depicted in the
                    book that follows his portrait are fictions as well. What Swift had discovered
                    in a way that no one else had before him was the ability of a new medium, here
                    the printed travel narrative, to create the impression of a reality that did not
                    exist. Part-satire, part-hoax, <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi> is
                    everywhere an exercise on understanding the relationship between reading and
                    knowing, an attack on the thoughtlessness of colonialist ideology, and a
                    profound contemplation on what it means to be a human being. <lb/> If there was
                    never a Lemuel Gulliver, there was no one else quite like Jonathan Swift,
                    either. He was born in Ireland in 1667 to a family that was a part of the wave
                    of English people who went there in that period, English Protestants who were
                    encouraged to emigrate and take positions in Irish institutions in order to bind
                    that island ever more tightly to English domination. Almost all biographical
                    accounts state that his father, also named Jonathan Swift, died seven months
                    before he was born. But there is no documentary evidence for that, or for his
                    parents’ marriage, the date of his father’s death, or even for Swift’s baptism.
                    Swift’s most recent biographer, Leo Damrosch, suggests that his real father may
                    have been Sir John Temple, a wealthy English nobleman who was living in Ireland
                    at the time and who knew Swift’s mother and her family. There is no way of
                    proving this, but it would explain some things, such as how Swift would become
                    the private secretary to William Temple, Sir John Temple’s son. Swift, without a
                    living father who could arrange such a post for him and having had an
                    undistinguished career as a student at Trinity College in Dublin, would not have
                    been an obvious choice, and he seems not to have met William Temple before he
                    began working for him. We will probably never be certain of the truth here. It
                    does not help that Swift cultivated a certain amount of mystery about his
                    private life. Although we know, for example, that he had intimate friendships
                    with several women, notably Esther Johnson (to whom he gave the name “Stella")
                    and Esther Vanhomrigh (who he referred to as Vanessa, a name that he invented),
                    the full nature of these relationships eluded, even mystified people who knew
                    both of them then, and frustrates us now. (Some people believed that Swift and
                    Esther Johnson had been secretly married; others thought that idea was
                    ridiculous.) Friends often found Swift to be witty and generous, but he could
                    also be demanding and moody. He suffered for much of his life from Meniere’s
                    disease, a disorder where fluid builds up in the inner ear. The condition
                    sometimes left him bedridden for days as he dealt with intense vertigo and
                    nausea; he eventually went deaf. Satirists are often outsiders, and it is not
                    hard to imagine how Swift might have felt himself to be an outsider to his
                    society, set apart by his birth and his health to be an ironic observer as often
                    as a full participant. <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi> was immediately a hit with readers,
                    and it did not take long for its real author to be identified, even though Swift
                    publicly stayed silent about his role for several years. The book was translated
                    into French and other European languages very early on; theatrical versions,
                    some with children playing the Lilliputians, were on the stage in London within
                    a few years. Gulliver's adventures, particularly his experiences with the small
                    but ruthless Lilliputians and the large but gentle Brobdignagians, have become
                    myths of the modern world, stories that everyone knows the general outlines of
                    even if they have never opened the book. But fully grasping what Swift was up to
                    has proven to be a challenge. Swift provided no gloss on his own work, and the
                    book defies an easy moral or satisfying conclusion. What, exactly, are we to
                    make of the Houyhnhnms, the intelligent horses of book IV who seem to have come
                    up with the kind of minimal, direct mode of governance that Swift seems
                    elsewhere to favor, but who are also able to contemplete genocide in casually
                    thinking of exterminating all the Yahoos? What do all of the encounters of Book
                    III, where Gulliver visits a series of miserable projectors of various kinds,
                    add up to, if anything? Who is this Gulliver, anyway, and what kind of character
                    are we dealing with? Swift plays with, defies, and undercuts our expectations
                    for what either a truthful travel narrative or a fictional story should be. <hi
                        rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi> is one of the greatest books in
                    English from the eighteenth century. <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic
                            url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/notes/Jonathan-Swift_Binden.jpg"
                            style="float:right" width="300px"/>
                    </figure>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                    <caption><hi rend="center">Jonathan Swift, as painted by Francis Binden in about
                            1735. Swift holds a copy of the manuscript of part IV, the voyage to the
                            Houyhnhnms, in his hand; in the field outside can be seen horses,
                            referring to the theme of the book.</hi></caption></note>
                <milestone unit="part" rend="line"/>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
            </head>

            <div type="frontispiece">
                <pb n="Frontispiece"
                    facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/notes/1726-Frontispiece.jpg"/>
                <figure>
                    <graphic
                        url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/notes/1726-Frontispiece.jpg"
                        style="float:center" width="500px"/>
                </figure>
            </div>

            <div type="Contents" n="iii">
                <pb n="[Contents]"
                    facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-p.III.jpg"/>
                <list type="Contents">

                    <item>PART I.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>A Voyage to <hi rend="italic">Lilliput.</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>PART II.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>A Voyage to <hi rend="italic">Brobdingnag.</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>PART III.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>A Voyage to <hi rend="italic">Laputa</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Balnibarbi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Luggnug</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Japan.</hi></item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>PART IV.</item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>A Voyage to the Country of the <hi rend="italic">Houyhnhnms.</hi></item>
                </list>
            </div>

            <div type="Preface">
                <pb n="IV"
                    facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-pIV.jpg"/>
                <p>THE</p>
                <p>PUBLISHER</p>
                <p>TO THE</p>
                <p>READER.</p>
                <lb/>
                <p>The Author of of these Travels, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Lemuel Gulliver</hi>, is my
                    antient and intimate Friend; there is likewise some Relation between us by the
                    Mother's Side. About three Years ago, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gulliver</hi>
                    growing weary of the Concourse of curious <pb n="V"
                        facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-pV.jpg"
                    /> People coming to him at his House in <hi rend="italic">Redriff</hi>, made a
                    small Purchase of Land, with a convenient House, near <hi rend="italic"
                        >Newark</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Nottinghamshire</hi>, his Native Country;
                    where he now lives retired, yet in good Esteem among his Neighbours.</p>

                <p>Although Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gulliver</hi> was born in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nottinghamshire</hi>, where his Father dwelt, yet I have heard him say, his
                    Family came from <hi rend="italic">Oxfordshire</hi>; to confirm which, I have
                    observed in the Church-Yard at <hi rend="italic">Banbury</hi>, in that County,
                    several Tombs and Monuments of the <hi rend="italic">Gullivers.</hi></p>

                <p>Before he quitted <hi rend="italic">Redriff</hi>, he left the custody of the
                    following Papers in my Hands, with the liberty to <pb n="VI"
                        facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-pVI.jpg"
                    /> dispose of them as I should think fit. I have carefully perused them three
                    Times: The Style is very plain and simple; and the only Fault I find is, that
                    the Author, after the Manner of Travellers, is a little too circumstantial.
                    There is an Air of Truth apparent through the Whole; and indeed, the Author was
                    so distinguished for his Veracity, that it became a sort of Proverb among his
                    Neighbours at <hi rend="italic">Redriff</hi>, when any one affirm'd a Thing, to
                    say, it was as true as if Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gulliver</hi> had spoke it.</p>

                <p>By the Advice of several worthy Persons, to whom, with the Author's Permission, I
                    communicated these Papers, I now venture to send them <pb n="VII"
                        facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-pVII.jpg"
                    /> into the World, hoping they may be at least, for some time, a better
                    Entertainment to our young Noblemen, than the common Scribbles of Politicks and
                    Party.</p>

                <p>This Volume would have been at least twice as large, if I had not made bold to
                    strike out innumerable Passages relating to the Winds and Tides, as well as to
                    the Variations and Bearings in the several Voyages; together with the minute
                    Descriptions of the Management of the Ship in Storms, in the Style of Sailors:
                    Likewise the Account of the Longitudes and Latitudes; wherein I have Reason to
                    apprehend that Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gulliver</hi> may be a little dissatisfied:
                    But I was resolved to fit the Work <pb n="VIII"
                        facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-pVIII.jpg"
                    /> as much as possible to the general Capacity of Readers. However, if my own
                    Ignorance in Sea-Affairs shall have led me to commit some Mistakes, I alone am
                    answerable for them: And if any Traveller hath a Curiosity to see the whole Work
                    at large, as it came from the Hand of the Author, I shall be ready to gratify
                    him.</p>

                <p>As for any further Particulars relating to the Author, the Reader will receive
                    Satisfaction from the first Pages of the Book.</p>
                <lb/>

                <p><ref target="a001a" corresp="n001a">RICHARD SYMPSON</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n001a"
                        target="a001a">"Richard Sympson" is, like Lemuel Gulliver, a fictional
                        person. But he is in some senses more "real" than Gulliver. Richard Sympson
                        was the pseudonym that Swift used when he was negotiating for the
                        publication of this book with the London publisher Benjamin Motte; Swift
                        wanted to keep his identity secret, very likely out of concern that there
                        might be repercussions for the harshness of the satire against the
                        government. There had once been a real Richard Sympson; he worked with Swift
                        on a 1698 edition of the works of Sir Wiliam Temple, Swift's patron and (in
                        the belief of some), possibly his father. The fictionality of the man who
                        attests to the veracity of the fictional protagonist of the book, and who
                        goes so far as to claim that he has a manuscript of the book available for
                        skeptical readers to view, only deepens the reader's challenge in sorting
                        out what is real from what is fake.</note></p>

                <pb n="[Map]"
                    facs="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/lilliput-map.jpg"/>

                <div type="chapter" n="1">
                    <p>PART I </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>A VOYAGE TO LILLIPUT</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic width="300px" style="float:center"
                            url="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/lilliput-map.jpg"
                        />
                    </figure>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>

                    <pb n="1"
                        facs="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/Swift/pageImages/Gulliver-1-p1.jpg"/>
                    <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>CHAPTER I<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Author gives some account of himself and family.
                                His first <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">inducements</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                    xml:id="n001" target="a001">Reasons which persuade or lead
                                    someone to action. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English
                                        Dictionary.</hi></note> to travel. He is shipwrecked, and
                                swims for his life; gets safe on Shore in the country of
                                </hi>Lilliput;<hi rend="italic"> is made a prisoner, and carried up
                                the country.</hi></head>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>My father had a small estate in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="a002"
                                    corresp="n002">Nottinghamshire</ref></hi><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n002"
                                target="a002">A county in the east Midlands of England. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note>; I was the third of five sons. He
                            sent me to Emanuel College in Cambridge at fourteen years old, where I
                            resided three years, and applied myself <pb n="2"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p2.jpg"/> close to my studies: but the
                            charge of maintaining me (although I had a very scanty allowance) being
                            too great for a narrow fortune, I was bound apprentice to Mr. James
                            Bates, an eminent surgeon in London, with whom I continued <ref
                                target="a003" corresp="n003">four years</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n003"
                                target="a003">Apprenticeships in the 16th and 17th century generally
                                lasted five to nine years. The implication is that Gulliver quit or
                                was dismissed before his apprenticeship was complete. Gulliver does
                                not explain what happened, but contemporary readers might well have
                                noticed the problem. It is also worth pointing out that there is a
                                sense in which "eminent surgeon" is a contradiction in terms in this
                                period. Surgery was considered to be a low-ranking medical
                                profession, akin to barbering, since both involved using sharp
                                instruments to cut parts of the body away; surgeons and barbers were
                                united in the same guild, for example.</note>; and my father now and
                            then sending me small sums of money, I laid them out in learning
                            navigation, and other parts of the mathematics, useful to those who
                            intend to travel, as I always believed it would be some time or other my
                            fortune to do. When I left Mr. Bates, I went down to my father; where,
                            by the assistance of him and my uncle John, and some other relations, I
                            got <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">forty pounds, and a promise of
                                thirty pounds a year</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n004" target="a004">Forty
                                pounds would be worth 5600 pounds today (2018) or 8000 USD. He was
                                given just thirty pounds to live on each year, so thus roughly just
                                enough to live off of each year. Source:
                                https://www.measuringworth.com/calculators/ukcompare/relativevalue.php</note>
                            to maintain me at <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Leyden</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"                                xml:id="n005" target="a005">Leyden, also known as Leiden in the
                                Netherlands, is a college that at the time was renowned for teaching
                                medicine. Source: https://www.universiteitleiden.nl/en</note>: there
                            I studied physic <ref target="a455" corresp="n455">two years and seven
                                months</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n455" target="a455">Similar to his
                                apprenticeship, Gulliver seems to have not finished his schooling
                                either, instead opting to drop out part way through. "Physic" was
                                the eighteenth-century term for internal medicine, a more
                                respectable field than surgery. Source: Wikipedia</note>, knowing it
                            would be useful in long voyages.</p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Soon after my return from Leyden, I was recommended, by my good master
                            Mr. Bates, to be surgeon to the Swal- <pb n="3"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p3.jpg"/> low, Captain Abraham Pannell
                            commander; with whom I continued three years and a half, making a voyage
                            or two into the <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Levant</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n006" target="a006">The Levant, depicted here, <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Levant.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure> is composed of the countries on the Eastern Mediterranean
                                Sea spanning from approximately Greece to Egypt. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note>, and some other parts. When I came back, I
                            resolved to settle in London, to which Mr. Bates, my master, encouraged
                            me, and by him I was recommended to several patients. I took part of a
                            small house in the <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Old Jury</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n007" target="a007">The Old Jury, or the Old Jewry, is a
                                street in London that historically is a main financial and
                                commercial district in England. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>; and being advised to alter my condition, I
                            married Mrs. Mary Burton, second daughter to Mr. Edmund Burton, <ref
                                target="a008" corresp="n008">hosier</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n008"
                                target="a008">A maker of women's panty hose, stockings, or tights.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, in Newgate-street, with
                            whom I received four hundred pounds for a <ref target="a009"
                                corresp="n009">portion</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n009" target="a009"
                                >Portion refers to his dowry he received during their marriage. A
                                dowry is gifts or money given to the husband from the wife's family
                                when they marry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>But, my good <ref target="a456" corresp="n456">master Bates</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n456" target="a456">\Here, Swift lands the punchline of his
                                play on words by aligning the words just so to sound like
                                "masturbates."</note> dying in two years after, and I having few
                            friends, my business began to fail; for my conscience would not suffer
                            me to imitate the bad practice of too many among my brethren. Having
                            therefore consulted with my wife, and some of my acquaintance, I
                            determined to go again to sea. I was <ref target="a010" corresp="n010"
                                >surgeon successively in two ships</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n010"
                                target="a010">While Swift does not outright say it, most likely this
                                is a slave ship, and as a surgeon on a slave-trade, he was mainly
                                there to make sure the the slaves stayed alive during the voyage so
                                they could be traded. Slaves were dying at a nearly one in five
                                rate, so companies begain hiring surgeons to keep their stock alive.
                                Source:
                                http://www.liverpoolmuseums.org.uk/ism/slavery/middle_passage/ and
                                http://www.liverpoolmuseums.org.uk/ism/slavery/archaeology/caribbean/</note>,
                            and made several voyages, for six years, <pb n="4"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p4.jpg"/> to the <ref target="a013"
                                corresp="n013">East</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n013" target="a013">The East
                                Indies refers to India and the neighboring areas of southeast Asia.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="http://www.sil.si.edu/expeditions/1926/map/MapImages/Indonesia.png"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note> and <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">West</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n014" target="a014">The West Indies refers to the area of
                                North America first found by Christopher Columbus and the
                                surrounding area, including the Caribbean Islands. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c4/Caribbean_Sea_and_West_Indies.png"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note> Indies, by which I got some addition to my fortune. My hours of
                            leisure I spent in reading the best authors, ancient and modern, being
                            always provided with a good number of books; and when I was ashore, in
                            observing the manners and dispositions of the people, well as learning
                            their language, wherein I had a great facility by the strength of my
                            memory.</p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The last of these voyages not proving very fortunate, I grew weary of the
                            sea, and intended to stay at home with my wife and family. I removed
                            from the Old Jury to <ref target="a457" corresp="n457"
                                >Fetter-Lane</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n457" target="a457"
                                >(DRAFT-DC)Fetter-Lane is a street in London, whose name originally
                                came from the Old French for lawyer: 'faitor.' However, over the
                                years, the name of the street became synonymous with beggars and
                                vagrants who were seen around the area. Later, the street was known
                                for its gibbet, a structure used for public executions, that stood
                                at the junction of Fleet and Fetter street. While there is no
                                evidence of it, it's been rumoured that English Poet John Dryden
                                once lived on Fetter-Lane. Source: Wikipedia</note>, and from thence
                            to <ref target="a460" corresp="n460">Wapping</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n460"
                                target="a460">(DRAFT-DC)Wapping is a district in East London that is
                                located on the North bank of the River Thames. Due to its proximity
                                to the River, the Wapping district has been strongly characterized
                                by a maritime and nautical character. In addition to that, the
                                Wapping district is well known for its trade, victuallers (liquor
                                salesmen), and Execution Dock. The Execution Dock was a common place
                                for pirates and criminals to be killed, most often by hanging from
                                gibbets. Those executed on the gibbets were hung during low tide,
                                and were then left to hang until they'd been submerged three times
                                by the comings and goings of the tide. Source: Wikipedia</note>
                            hoping to get business among the sailors; but <ref target="a015"
                                corresp="n015">it would not turn to account</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n015"
                                target="a015">'To turn [something] to account' is defined as turning
                                something into an advantage. In this case, most likely Swift is
                                using the phrase to imply that he did not profit from his endeavors.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. After three years
                            expectation that things would mend, I accepted an advantageous offer
                            from Captain William Prichard, master of the Antelope, who was making a
                            voyage to the <ref target="a458" corresp="n458">South-Sea</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n458" target="a458">(DRAFT-DC)At the beginning of the
                                eighteenth century, the South Sea referred to all of the South
                                Pacific Ocean. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. We set sail
                            from Bristol May 4, 1699, and our voyage at first was very prosperous. </p>
                        <pb n="5" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p5.jpg"/>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>It would not be proper, for some reasons, to trouble the reader with the
                            particulars of our adventures in those seas: let it suffice to inform
                            him, that in our passage from thence to the East Indies, we were driven
                            by a violent storm to the northwest of <ref target="a016" corresp="n016"
                                >Van Diemen's Land</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n016" target="a016">Van
                                Diemen's Land was the Dutch name used for what is now the Australian
                                island of Tasmania. Source:
                                https://www.britannica.com/place/Van-Diemens-Land</note>. By an
                            observation, we found ourselves in the latitude of 30 degrees 2 minutes
                            south. Twelve of our crew were dead by immoderate labor and ill food,
                            the rest were in a very weak condition. On the fifth of November, which
                            was the beginning of summer in those parts, the weather being very hazy,
                            the seamen spied a rock, <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">within half a
                                cable's length of the ship</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n017" target="a017">A
                                cable's length is a nautical measurement that is roughly 608 feet.
                                So the rock was spied within approximately 304 feet off the ship.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; but the wind was so
                            strong, that we were driven directly upon it, and immediately split. Six
                            of the crew, of whom I was one, having let down the boat into the sea,
                            made a shift to get clear of the ship, and the rock. We rowed by my
                            computation about <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">three
                                leagues</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n018" target="a018">A league is a unit of
                                measurement equal to approximately 2.4 - 4.6 miles. Thus three
                                leagues is 7.2 - 13.8 miles. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, till we were able to work no <pb n="6"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p6.jpg"/> longer, being already spent
                            with labor while we were in the ship. We therefore trusted ourselves to
                            the mercy of the waves, and in about half an hour the boat was overset
                            by a sudden flurry from the north. What became of my companions in the
                            boat, as well as of those who escaped on the rock, or were left in the
                            vessel, I cannot tell; but conclude they were all lost. For my own part,
                            I swam as fortune directed me, and was pushed forward by wind and tide.
                            I often let my legs drop, and could feel no bottom: but when I was
                            almost gone, and able to struggle no longer, I found myself within my
                            depth; and by this time the storm was much abated. The <ref
                                target="a019" corresp="n019">declivity</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n019"
                                target="a019">(DRAFT-DC)A descending incline, here being used to
                                reference the walkable slope of the ocean's continental shelf.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> was so small, that I walked
                            near a mile before I got to the shore, which I conjectured was about
                            eight o'clock in the evening. I then advanced forward near half a mile,
                            but could not discover any sign of houses or inhabitants; at least I was
                            in so weak a condition, that I did not observe them. I was extremely <pb
                                n="7" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p7.jpg"/> tired, and with that,
                            and the heat of the weather, and about half a pint of brandy that I
                            drank as I left the ship, I found myself much inclined to sleep. I lay
                            down on the grass, which was very short and soft, where I slept sounder
                            than ever I remember to have done in my life, and, as I reckoned, above
                            nine hours; for when I awakened, it was just daylight. I attempted to
                            rise, but was not able to stir for, as I happened to lie on my back, I
                            found my arms and legs were strongly fastened on each side to the
                            ground; and my hair, which was long and thick, tied down in the same
                            manner. I likewise felt several slender <ref target="a459"
                                corresp="n459">ligatures</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n459" target="a459"
                                >Bindings such as rope, thread, or bandages. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> across my body, from my armpits to my thighs. I
                            could only look upwards; the sun began to grow hot, and the light
                            offended my eyes. I heard a confused noise about me, but in the posture
                            I lay, could see nothing except the sky. In a little time I felt
                            something alive moving on my left leg, which advancing gently forward
                            over my breast, <pb n="8" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p8.jpg"/> came
                            almost up to my chin; when bending my eyes downwards as much as I could,
                            I perceived it to be a human creature not six inches high, with a bow
                            and arrow in his hands, and a quiver at his back. In the meantime, I
                            felt at least forty more of the same kind (as I conjectured) following
                            the first. I was in the utmost astonishment, and roared so loud, that
                            they all ran back in a fright; and some of them, as I was afterwards
                            told, were hurt with the falls they got by leaping from my sides upon
                            the ground. However, they soon returned, and one of them, who ventured
                            so far as to get a full sight of my face, lifting up his hands and eyes
                            by way of admiration, cried out in a shrill but distinct voice, <hi
                                rend="italics">Hekinah degul</hi>: the others repeated the same
                            words several times, but I then knew not what they meant. I lay all this
                            while, as the reader may believe, in great uneasiness: at length,
                            struggling to get loose, I had the fortune to break the strings, and
                            wrench out the pegs that fastened my <pb n="9"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p9.jpg"/> left arm to the ground; for,
                            by lifting it up to my face, I discovered the methods they had taken to
                            bind me, and at the same time, with a violent pull, which gave me
                            excessive pain, I a little loosened the strings that tied down my hair
                            on the left side, so that I was just able to turn my head about two
                            inches. But the creatures ran off a second time, before I could seize
                            them; whereupon there was a great shout in a very shrill accent, and
                            after it ceased, I heard one of them cry aloud, <hi rend="italics">tolgo
                                phonac</hi>; when in an instant I felt above a hundred arrows
                            discharged on my left hand, which pricked me like so many needles; and
                            besides they shot another flight into the air, as we do bombs in Europe,
                            whereof many, I suppose, fell on my body (though I felt them not) and
                            some on my face, which I immediately covered with my left hand. When
                            this shower of arrows was over, I fell a groaning with grief and pain,
                            and then striving again to get loose, they discharged an- <pb n="10"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p10.jpg"/> other volley larger than the
                            first, and some of them attempted with spears to stick me in the sides;
                            but, by good luck, I had on me <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">a buff
                                jerkin</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n020" target="a020">A vest or jacket made
                                from ox or buffalo hide. The jerkin was often worn by soldiers to
                                help protect against cuts and slashes, as well as, to help prevent
                                chafing under plate armour. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and
                                Wikipedia <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a5/Picture_of_jerkin.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, which they could not pierce. I thought it the most prudent
                            method to lie still, and my design was to continue so till night, when,
                            my left hand being already loose, I could easily free myself: and as for
                            the inhabitants, I had reason to believe I might be a match for the
                            greatest armies they could bring against me, if they were all of the
                            same size with him that I saw. But fortune disposed otherwise of me.
                            When the people observed I was quiet, they discharged no more arrows;
                            but, by the noise I heard, I knew their numbers increased; and about
                            four yards from me, over against my right ear, I heard a knocking for
                            above an hour, like that of people at work; when turning my head that
                            way, as well as the pegs and strings would permit me, I saw a stage
                            erected, about a foot and a half from the ground, capable of hold- <pb
                                n="11" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p11.jpg"/> ing four of the
                            inhabitants, with two or three ladders to mount it: from whence one of
                            them, who seemed to be a person of quality, made me a long speech,
                            whereof I understood not one syllable. But I should have mentioned, that
                            before the principal person began his oration, he cried out three times
                                <hi rend="italics">langro dehul san</hi>: (these words and the
                            former were afterwards repeated and explained to me). Whereupon
                            immediately about fifty of the inhabitants came, and cut the strings
                            that fastened the left side of my head, which gave me the liberty of
                            turning it to the right, and of observing the person and gesture of him
                            that was to speak. He appeared to be of a middle age, and taller than
                            any of the other three who attended him, whereof one was a <ref
                                target="a021" corresp="n021">page</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n021"
                                target="a021">A servant. Often this position is held by a child or
                                young adult. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> that held up
                            his <ref target="a022" corresp="n022">train</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n022"
                                target="a022">A train is the bottom of a robe, dress, or coat. If a
                                train is long enough it will drag on the ground, and thus a royal's
                                train would be carried by servants. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, and seemed to be somewhat longer than my middle
                            finger; the other two stood one on each side to support him. He acted
                            every part of an orator, and I could observe many periods of
                            threatenings, <pb n="12" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p12.jpg"/> and
                            others of promises, pity, and kindness. I answered in a few words, but
                            in the most submissive manner, lifting up my left hand and both my eyes
                            to the sun, as calling him for a witness; and being almost famished with
                            hunger, having not eaten a morsel for some hours before I left the ship,
                            I found the demands of nature so strong upon me, that I could not <ref
                                target="a023" corresp="n023">forbear</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n023"
                                target="a023">Bear or endure. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> showing my impatience (perhaps against the strict
                            rules of decency) by putting my finger frequently on my mouth, to
                            signify that I wanted food. The Hurgo (for so they call a great lord, as
                            I afterwards learned) understood me very well. He descended from the
                            stage, and commanded that several ladders should be applied to my sides,
                            on which above a hundred of the inhabitants mounted, and walked towards
                            my mouth, laden with baskets full of meat, which had been provided, and
                            sent thither by the King's orders, upon the first intelligence he
                            received of me. I observed there was the flesh of several animals, <pb
                                n="13" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p13.jpg"/> but could not
                            distinguish them by the taste. There were shoulders, legs, and loins,
                            shaped like those of mutton, and very well dressed, but smaller than the
                            wings of a <ref target="a024" corresp="n024">lark</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n024" target="a024">A type of small brown songbird. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note> bigness of <ref target="a025"
                                corresp="n025">musket bullets</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n025" target="a025"
                                >The diameter of a musket ball was about half an inch on average.
                                Source: Wikipedia</note>. They supplied me as they could, showing a
                            thousand marks of wonder and astonishment at my bulk and appetite. I
                            then made another sign that I wanted drink. They found by my eating that
                            a small quantity would not suffice me, and being a most ingenious
                            people, they slung up with great dexterity one of their largest <ref
                                target="a026" corresp="n026">hogsheads</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n026"
                                target="a026">A hogshead is a large cask or barrel that is often
                                used to hold liquids, such as alcohol. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, then rolled it toward my hand, and beat out the
                            top; I drank it off at a <ref target="a027" corresp="n027"
                                >draught</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n027" target="a027">All in one pull,
                                swallow, or drink. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, which I
                            might well do, for it did not hold half a pint, and tasted like a small
                            wine of Burgundy, but much more delicious. They brought me a second
                            hogshead, which I drank in the same manner, and made signs for more, but
                            they had none to give me. When I had performed these <pb n="14"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p14.jpg"/> wonders, they shouted for
                            joy, and danced upon my breast, repeating several times as they did at
                            first, <hi rend="italics">hekinah degul</hi>. They made me a sign that I
                            should throw down the two hogsheads, but first warning the people below
                            to stand out of the way, crying aloud, <hi rend="italics">borach
                                mivola</hi>, and when they saw the vessels in the air, there was a
                            universal shout of <hi rend="italics">hekinah degul</hi>. I confess I
                            was often tempted, while they were passing backwards and forwards on my
                            body, to seize forty or fifty of the first that came in my reach, and
                            dash them against the ground. But the remembrance of what I had felt,
                            which probably might not be the worst they could do, and the promise of
                            honor I made them, for so I interpreted my submissive behavior, soon
                            drove out these imaginations. Besides, I now considered myself as bound
                            by the laws of hospitality to a people who had treated me with so much
                            expense and magnificence. However, in my thoughts I could not
                            sufficiently wonder at the in- <pb n="15"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p15.jpg"/> trepidity of these diminutive
                            mortals, who dare venture to mount and walk upon my body, while one of
                            my hands was at liberty, without trembling at the very sight of so <ref
                                target="a028" corresp="n028">prodigious</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n028"
                                target="a028">Amazing or extraordinary. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> a creature as I must appear to them. After some
                            time, when they observed that I made no more demands for meat, there
                            appeared before me a person of high rank from his Imperial Majesty. His
                            Excellency, having mounted on the small of my right leg,advanced
                            forwards up to my face, with about a dozen of his <ref target="a029"
                                corresp="n029">retinue</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n029" target="a029">A
                                group of the King's attendants and closest servants. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note>. And producing his credentials under the
                                <ref target="a461" corresp="n461">Signet Royal</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n461" target="a461">A signet is a formal seal most commonaly
                                found on documents that serves as authentication of one's position.
                                Here the signet serves as proof of his royal position. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note>, which he applied close to my eyes,
                            spoke about ten minutes, without any signs of anger, but with a kind of
                            determinate resolution; often pointing forwards, which, as I afterwards
                            found, was towards the capital city, about half a mile distant, whither
                            it was agreed by his Majesty in council that I must be conveyed. I
                            answered in few words, but to no purpose, and made a sign with my hand
                            that was loose, putting it to the <pb n="16"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p16.jpg"/> other (but over his
                            Excellency's head, for fear of hurting him or his train) and then to my
                            own head and body, to signify that I desired my liberty. It appeared
                            that he understood me well enough, for he shook his head by way of <ref
                                target="a030" corresp="n030">disapprobation</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n030"
                                target="a030">Disapproval. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,
                            and held his hand in a posture to show that I must be carried as a
                            prisoner. However, he made other signs to let me understand that I
                            should have meat and drink enough, and very good treatment. Whereupon I
                            once more thought of attempting to break my bonds, but again, when I
                            felt the <ref target="a031" corresp="n031">smart</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n031" target="a031">Sharp pain inflicted by some outside
                                source. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of their arrows
                            upon my face and hands, which were all in blisters, and many of the
                            darts still sticking in them, and observing likewise that the number of
                            my enemies increased, I gave tokens to let them know that they might do
                            with me what they pleased. Upon this the Hurgo and his train withdrew
                            with much civility and cheerful countenances. Soon after I heard a
                            general shout, with frequent repetitions of the words, <hi
                                rend="italics">peplom selan</hi>, and <pb n="17"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p17.jpg"/> I felt great numbers of the
                            people on my left side relaxing the cords to such a degree, that I was
                            able to turn upon my right, and to ease myself with <ref target="a032"
                                corresp="n032">making water</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n032" target="a032"
                                >Urinating. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; which I very
                            plentifully did, to the great astonishment of the people, who
                            conjecturing by my motions what I was going to do, immediately opened to
                            the right and left on that side, to avoid the torrent which fell with
                            such noise and violence from me. But before this, they had <ref
                                target="a033" corresp="n033">daubed</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n033"
                                target="a033">To cover or put on. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> my face and both my hands with a sort of ointment
                            very pleasant to the smell, which in a few minutes removed all the smart
                            of their arrows. These circumstances, added to the refreshment I had
                            received by their <ref target="a034" corresp="n034">victuals</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n034" target="a034">Food. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> and drink, which were very nourishing, disposed me
                            to sleep. I slept about eight hours, as I was afterwards assured; and it
                            was no wonder, for the physicians, by the Emperor's order, had mingled a
                            sleepy potion in the hogsheads of wine. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="18" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p18.jpg"/>

                        <p>It seems that upon the first moment I was discovered sleeping on the
                            ground after my landing, the Emperor had early notice of it by an
                            express; and determined in council that I should be tied in the manner I
                            have related (which was done in the night while I slept), that plenty of
                            meat and drink should be sent me, and a machine prepared to carry me to
                            the capital city. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This resolution perhaps may appear very bold and dangerous, and I am
                            confident would not be imitated by any prince in Europe on the like
                            occasion; however, in my opinion, it was extremely prudent, as well as
                            generous. For supposing these people had endeavored to kill me with
                            their spears and arrows while I was asleep, I should certainly have
                            awakened with the first sense of smart, which might so far have roused
                            my rage and strength, as to have enabled me to break the strings
                            wherewith I was tied; after which, as <pb n="19"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p19.jpg"/> they were not able to make
                            resistance, so they could expect no mercy. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>These people are most excellent mathematicians, and arrived to great
                            perfection in mechanics by the countenance and encouragement of the
                            Emperor, who is a renowned patron of learning. This prince has several
                            machines fixed on wheels for the carriage of trees and other great
                            weights. He often builds his largest men of war, whereof some are nine
                            feet long, in the woods where the timber grows, and has them carried on
                            these engines three or four hundred yards to the sea. Five hundred
                            carpenters and engineers were immediately set at work to prepare the
                            greatest engine they had. It was a frame of wood raised three inches
                            from the ground, about seven feet long and four wide, moving upon
                            twenty-two wheels. The shout I heard was upon the arrival of this
                            engine, which it seems set out in four hours after my landing. It was
                            brought <pb n="20" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p20.jpg"/> parallel to me
                            as I lay. But the principal difficulty was to raise and place me in this
                            vehicle. Eighty poles, each of one foot high, were erected for this
                            purpose, and very strong cords of the bigness of <ref target="a035"
                                corresp="n035">packthread</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n035" target="a035"
                                >Small twine or thread used to sew or close up bags. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note> were fastened by hooks to many bandages,
                            which the workmen had <ref target="a036" corresp="n036">girt</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n036" target="a036">Girt is the past tense of gird meaning
                                to bind or to secure something. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> round my neck, my hands, my body, and my legs.
                            Nine hundred of the strongest men were employed to draw up these cords
                            by many pulleys fastened on the poles, and thus, in less than three
                            hours, I was raised and slung into the engine, and there tied fast. All
                            this I was told, for while the whole operation was performing, I lay in
                            a profound sleep, by the force of that <ref target="a037" corresp="n037"
                                >soporiferous</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n037" target="a037">To cause
                                someone to fall asleep. Thus, the medicine will cause him to sleep
                                or pass out. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> medicine
                            infused into my liquor. Fifteen hundred of the Emperor's largest horses,
                            each about four inches and a half high, were employed to draw me towards
                            the metropolis, which, as I said, was half a mile distant. <pb n="21"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p21.jpg"/>
                        </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>About four hours after we began our journey, I awaked by a very
                            ridiculous accident; for the carriage being stopped a while to adjust
                            something that was out of order, two or three of the young natives had
                            the curiosity to see how I looked when I was asleep; they climbed up
                            into the engine, and advancing very softly to my face, one of them, an
                            officer in the Guards, put the sharp end of his half-pike a good way up
                            into my left nostril, which tickled my nose like a straw, and made me
                            sneeze violently: whereupon they stole off unperceived, and it was three
                            weeks before I knew the cause of my awaking so suddenly. We made a long
                            march the remaining part of that day, and rested at night with five
                            hundred guards on each side of me, half with torches, and half with bows
                            and arrows, ready to shoot me if I should offer to stir. The next
                            morning at sunrise we continued our march, and arrived within two
                            hundred yards of the <pb n="22" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p22.jpg"/>
                            city gates about noon. The Emperor, and all his court, came out to meet
                            us; but his great officers would by no means suffer his Majesty to
                            endanger his person by mounting on my body. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>At the place where the carriage stopped, there stood an ancient temple,
                            esteemed to be the largest in the whole kingdom, which having been
                            polluted some years before by <ref target="a038" corresp="n038">an
                                unnatural murder</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n038" target="a038">This seems
                                to be an allusion to the beheading of King Charles I that occurred
                                at the Banqueting-House at White-Hall. Pictured below is an unknown
                                artist's rendering of the scene of Charles I's Execution. Source:
                                https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/king-charles-i-executed-for-treason <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://www.nationalgalleries.org/sites/default/files/styles/postcard/public/externals/42119.jpg?itok=xJVGplgj"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, was, according to the zeal of those people, looked on as
                            profane, and therefore had been applied to common uses, and all the
                            ornaments and furniture carried away. In this edifice it was determined
                            I should lodge. The great gate fronting to the north was about four feet
                            high, and almost two feet wide, through which I could easily creep. On
                            each side of the gate was a small window not above six inches from the
                            ground: into that on the left side, the King's smiths conveyed <ref
                                target="a039" corresp="n039">fourscore and eleven chains</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n039" target="a039">Fourscore is four times twenty or
                                eighty. So thus there were ninety-one chains. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, like those that hang to a lady's watch in Europe,
                                <pb n="23" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p23.jpg"/> and almost as
                            large, which were locked to my left leg with six and thirty padlocks.
                            Over against this temple, on the other side of the great highway, at
                            twenty feet distance, there was a turret at least five feet high. Here
                            the Emperor ascended with many principal lords of his court, to have an
                            opportunity of viewing me, as I was told, for I could not see them. It
                            was reckoned that above a hundred thousand inhabitants came out of the
                            town upon the same errand; and in spite of my guards, I believe there
                            could not be fewer than ten thousand, at several times, who mounted upon
                            my body by the help of ladders. But a proclamation was soon issued to
                            forbid it upon pain of death. When the workmen found it was impossible
                            for me to break loose, they cut all the strings that bound me; whereupon
                            I rose up with as melancholy a disposition as ever I had in my life. But
                            the noise and astonishment of the people at seeing me rise and walk, are
                            not to be expressed. The chains that held my <pb n="24"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p24.jpg"/> left leg were about two yards
                            long, and gave me not only the liberty of walking backwards and forwards
                            in a semi-circle; but, being fixed within four inches of the gate,
                            allowed me to creep in, and lie at my full length in the temple. </p>
                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="2">
                        <pb n="25" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p25.jpg"/>
                        <head>CHAPTER II</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">The Emperor of </hi>Lilliput, <hi rend="italics"
                                    >attended by several of the nobility, come to see the Author in
                                    his confinement. The emperor's person and habit described.
                                    Learned men appointed to teach the Author their language. He
                                    gains favour by his mild disposition. His pockets are searched,
                                    and his sword and pistols taken from him.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>When I found myself on my feet, I looked about me, and must confess I
                            never beheld a more entertaining prospect. The country round appeared
                            like a continued garden, and the inclosed fields, which were generally
                            forty feet square, resembled so many beds of flowers. These fields were
                            intermingled with <pb n="26" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p26.jpg"/>
                            woods of <ref target="a040" corresp="n040">half a stang</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n040" target="a040">A stang is a measurement of land equal
                                to a Rood, a unit of land that is equal to approximately a quarter
                                of an acre, 10890 square feet. Thus, half a stang is equal to about
                                5445 square feet, which is about two tennis courts worth. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and the tallest trees, as I could
                            judge, appeared to be seven feet high. I viewed the town on my left
                            hand, which looked like the painted scene of a city in a theatre. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I had been for some hours extremely pressed by the necessities of nature;
                            which was no wonder, it being almost two days since I had last
                            unburdened myself. I was under great difficulties between urgency and
                            shame. The best <ref target="a041" corresp="n041">expedient</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n041" target="a041">An expedient is something done so one
                                can quickly achieve something. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> I could think of, was to creep into my house,
                            which I accordingly did; and shutting the gate after me, I went as far
                            as the length of my chain would suffer, and discharged my body of that
                            uneasy load. But this was the only time I was ever guilty of so
                            uncleanly an action; for which I cannot but hope the candid reader will
                            give some allowance, after he has maturely and impartially considered my
                            case, and the distress I was in. From this time my constant practice
                            was, as soon as I rose, to perform that busi- <pb n="27"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p27.jpg"/> ness in open air, at the full
                            extent of my chain, and due care was taken every morning before company
                            came, that the offensive matter should be carried off in wheelbarrows,
                            by two servants appointed for that purpose. I would not have dwelt so
                            long upon a circumstance, that perhaps at first sight may appear not
                            very momentous, if I had not thought it necessary to justify my
                            character in point of cleanliness to the world; which I am told some of
                            my <ref target="a042" corresp="n042">maligners</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n042"
                                target="a042">Maligners refers to the people who have "maligned" him
                                or attacked him publically. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
                            have been pleased, upon this and other occasions, to call in question. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>When this adventure was at an end, I came back out of my house, having
                            occasion for fresh air. The Emperor was already descended from the
                            tower, and advancing on horseback towards me, which had like to have
                            cost him dear; for the beast, though very well trained, yet wholly
                            unused to such a sight, which appeared as if a mountain moved before
                            him, he reared up on his hinder feet: but <pb n="28"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p28.jpg"/> that prince, who is an
                            excellent horseman, kept his seat, till his attendants ran in, and held
                            the bridle, while his Majesty had time to dismount. When he <ref
                                target="a043" corresp="n043">alighted</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n043"
                                target="a043"> Alighted is to come down or get down from something
                                like a bus or a horse. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, he
                            surveyed me round with great admiration, but kept without the length of
                            my chain. He ordered his cooks and butlers, who were already prepared,
                            to give me victuals and drink, which they pushed forward in a sort of
                            vehicle upon wheels till I could reach them. I took these vehicles, and
                            soon emptied them all; twenty of them were filled with meat, and ten
                            with liquor; each of the former afforded me two or three good mouthfuls,
                            and I emptied the liquor of ten vessels, which was contained in earthen
                            vials, into one vehicle, drinking it off at a draught; and so I did with
                            the rest. The Empress, and young Princes of the blood, of both sexes,
                            attended by many ladies, sat at some distance in their chairs; but upon
                            the accident that happened to the Emperor's horse, they alighted, and
                            came near his <pb n="29" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p29.jpg"/> person,
                            which I am now going to describe. He is taller by almost the breadth of
                            my nail than any of his court, which alone is enough to strike an awe
                            into the beholders. His features are strong and masculine, with an
                            Austrian lip and <ref target="a044" corresp="n044">arched
                                nose</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n044" target="a044">The arched nose is most
                                likely a reference to William III who also had that defining
                                feature. Below is a portrait painting done by Willem Wissing in the
                                late 1600's that truly shows the prominent nose Swift alludes to. <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://collectionimages.npg.org.uk/large/mw06796/King-William-III.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, his complexion olive, his countenance erect, his body and limbs
                            well proportioned, all his motions graceful, and his <ref target="a045"
                                corresp="n045">deportment</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n045" target="a045"
                                >Deportment is the manner with which one conducts oneself. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionaries</note> majestic. He was then past his
                                <ref target="a046" corresp="n046">prime</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n046"
                                target="a046">This is most likely a reference to George I who was 66
                                when he ruled. Source:
                                https://www.britannica.com/biography/George-I-king-of-Great-Britain</note>,
                            being twenty-eight years and three quarters old, of which he had reigned
                            about <ref target="a047" corresp="n047">seven</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n047"
                                target="a047">This is an allusion to George I who had reigned seven
                                years when Gulliver's Travels was published. <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://collectionimages.npg.org.uk/large/mw06796/King-William-III.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, in great <ref target="a048" corresp="n048">felicity</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n048" target="a048">Felicity is the quality or state of
                                being happy. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and generally
                            victorious. For the better convenience of beholding him, I lay on my
                            side, so that my face was parallel to his, and he stood but three yards
                            off: however, I have had him since many times in my hand, and therefore
                            cannot be deceived in the description. His dress was very plain and
                            simple, and the fashion of it <ref target="a049" corresp="n049">between
                                the Asiatic and the European</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n049" target="a049"
                                >This is a nod to George I who had Turkish servants and thus was
                                often depicted in Turkish dress. Source:
                                https://www.bsecs.org.uk/news-and-events/turkish-servants-to-the-kin <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://collectionimages.npg.org.uk/std/mw02444/King-George-I.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>; but he had on his head a light helmet of gold, adorned with
                            jewels, and a plume on the crest. <pb n="30"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p30.jpg"/> He held his sword drawn in
                            his hand, to defend himself, if I should happen to break loose; it was
                            almost three inches long, the hilt and <ref target="c049" corresp="n999"
                                >scabbard</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n999" target="c049">A sheath for a
                                sword. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> were gold enriched
                            with diamonds. His voice was shrill, but very clear and articulate, and
                            I could distinctly hear it when I stood up. The ladies and courtiers
                            were all most magnificently clad, so that the spot they stood upon
                            seemed to resemble a petticoat spread on the ground, embroidered with
                            figures of gold and silver. His Imperial Majesty spoke often to me, and
                            I returned answers, but neither of us could understand a syllable. There
                            were several of his priests and lawyers present (as I conjectured by
                            their habits) who were commanded to address themselves to me, and I
                            spoke to them in as many languages as I had the least smattering of,
                            which were <ref target="a050" corresp="n050">High </ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n050" target="a050">Language from the highlands in Southern
                                Germany, now the German Language. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> and <ref target="a051" corresp="n051">Low Dutch
                                </ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n051" target="a051">The Dutch Language. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note>, Latin, French, Spanish, Italian,
                            and <ref target="a052" corresp="n052">Lingua Franca </ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n052" target="a052">A mix of the southern Romance languages.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; but all to no purpose.
                            After about two hours the court retired, and I was left with a strong
                            guard, to prevent the im- <pb n="31"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p31.jpg"/> pertinence, and probably the
                            malice of the rabble, who were very impatient to crowd about me as near
                            as they dare, and some of them had the impudence to shoot their arrows
                            at me as I sat on the ground by the door of my house, whereof one very
                            narrowly missed my left eye. But the colonel ordered six of the
                            ringleaders to be seized, and thought no punishment so proper as to
                            deliver them bound into my hands, which some of his soldiers accordingly
                            did, pushing them forwards with the butt-ends of their pikes into my
                            reach; I took them all in my right hand, put five of them into my coat
                            pocket, and as to the sixth, I made a countenance as if I would eat him
                            alive. The poor man squalled terribly, and the colonel and his officers
                            were in much pain, especially when they saw me take out my penknife: but
                            I soon put them out of fear; for, looking mildly, and immediately
                            cutting the strings he was bound with, I set him gently on the ground,
                            and away he ran. I treated the <pb n="32"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p32.jpg"/> rest in the same manner,
                            taking them one by one out of my pocket, and I observed both the
                            soldiers and people were highly obliged at this mark of my clemency,
                            which was represented very much to my advantage at court. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Towards night I with some difficulty got into my house, where I lay on
                            the ground, and continued to do so about a fortnight; during which time
                            the Emperor gave orders to have a bed prepared for me. Six hundred beds
                            of the common measure were brought in carriages, and worked up in my
                            house; a hundred and fifty of their beds sewn together made up the
                            breadth and length, and these were four double, which however kept me
                            but very indifferently from the hardness of the floor, that was of
                            smooth stone. By the same computation they provided me with sheets,
                            blankets, and coverlets, tolerable enough for one who had been so long
                            inured to hardships as I. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="33" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p33.jpg"/>

                        <p>As the news of my arrival spread through the kingdom, it brought
                            prodigious numbers of rich, idle, and curious people to see me; so that
                            the villages were almost emptied, and great neglect of tillage and
                            household affairs must have ensued, if his Imperial Majesty had not
                            provided, by several proclamations and orders of state, against this
                            inconveniency. He directed that those who had already beheld me should
                            return home, and not presume to come within fifty yards of my house
                            without license from court; whereby the secretaries of state got
                            considerable fees. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In the meantime, the Emperor held frequent councils to debate what course
                            should be taken with me; and I was afterwards assured by a particular
                            friend, a person of great quality, who was looked upon to be as much in
                            the secret as any, that the court was under many difficulties concerning
                            me. They ap- <pb n="34" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p34.jpg"/> prehended
                            my breaking loose, that my diet would be very expensive, and might cause
                            a famine. Sometimes they determined to starve me, or at least to shoot
                            me in the face and hands with poisoned arrows, which would soon dispatch
                            me: but again they considered, that the stench of so large a carcass
                            might produce a plague in the metropolis, and probably spread through
                            the whole kingdom. In the midst of these consultations, several officers
                            of the army went to the door of the great council chamber; and two of
                            them being admitted, gave an account of my behavior to the six criminals
                            above mentioned, which made so favorable an impression in the breast of
                            his Majesty and the whole board in my behalf, that an Imperial
                            Commission was issued out, obliging all the villages nine hundred yards
                            round the city, to deliver in every morning six <ref target="a053"
                                corresp="n053">Beeves</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n053" target="a053">Oxen or
                                cattle. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, forty sheep, and
                            other victuals for my sustenance; together with a proportionable
                            quantity of bread, and wine, and other liquors <pb n="35"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p35.jpg"/> for the due payment of which
                            his Majesty gave assignments upon his treasury. For this prince lives
                            chiefly upon his own <ref target="a054" corresp="n054"
                                >demesnes</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n054" target="a054">Land held by the
                                state. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, seldom, except upon
                            great occasions, raising any subsidies upon his subjects, who are bound
                            to attend him in his wars at their own expense. An establishment
                            was-also made of six hundred persons to be my domestics, who had
                            board-wages allowed for their maintenance, and tents built for them very
                            conveniently on each side of my door. It was likewise ordered, that
                            three hundred tailors should make me a suit of clothes after the fashion
                            of the country: that six of his Majesty's greatest scholars should be
                            employed to instruct me in their language: and, lastly, that the
                            Emperor's horses, and those of the nobility, and troops of guards,
                            should be frequently exercised in my sight, to accustom themselves to
                            me. All these orders were duly put in execution, and in about three
                            weeks I made a great progress in learning their language; during <pb
                                n="36" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p36.jpg"/> which time the Emperor
                            frequently honored me with his visits, and was pleased to assist my
                            masters in teaching me. We began already to converse together in some
                            sort; and the first words I learned were to express my desire that he
                            would please give me my liberty, which I every day repeated on my knees.
                            His answer, as I could apprehend it, was, that this must be a work of
                            time, not to be thought on without the advice of his council, and that
                            first I must <hi rend="italics">lumos kelmin pesso desmar lon
                                emposo</hi>; that is, swear a peace with him and his kingdom.
                            However, that I should be used with all kindness; and he advised me to
                            acquire, by my patience and discreet behavior, the good opinion of
                            himself and his subjects. He desired I would not take it ill, if he gave
                            orders to certain proper officers to search me; for probably I might
                            carry about me several weapons, which must needs be dangerous things, if
                            they answered the bulk of so prodigious a person. I said, his Majesty
                                <pb n="37" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p37.jpg"/> should be
                            satisfied, for I was ready to strip myself, and turn out my pockets
                            before him. This I delivered part in words, and part in signs. He
                            replied, that by the laws of the kingdom I must be searched by two of
                            his officers; that he knew this could not be done without my consent and
                            assistance; that he had so good an opinion of my generosity and justice,
                            as to trust their persons in my hands: that whatever they took from me
                            should be returned when I left the country, or paid for at the rate
                            which I would set upon them. I took up the two officers in my hands, put
                            them first into my coat-pockets, and then into every other pocket about
                            me, except my two <ref target="a055" corresp="n055">fobs</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n055" target="a055">A small pocket, usually for watches,
                                money, or small valuables. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,
                            and another secret pocket I had no mind should be searched, wherein I
                            had some little necessaries that were of no consequence to any but
                            myself. In one of my fobs there was a silver watch, and in the other a
                            small quantity of gold in a purse. These gentlemen, having pen, ink, and
                                <pb n="38" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p38.jpg"/> paper about them,
                            made an exact inventory of everything they saw; and when they were
                            through, desired I would set them down, that they might deliver it to
                            the Emperor. This inventory I afterwards translated that into English,
                            and is word for word as follows. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p><ref target="a056" corresp="n056"><hi rend="italics"
                                >Imprimis</hi></ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n056" target="a056">Legal term
                                denoting a list of items. Placed at the top of many legal documents
                                of the time, from wills to inventories. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, In the right coat pocket of the Great Man
                            Mountain (for so I interpret the words <hi rend="italics">quinbus
                                flestrin</hi>) after the strictest search, we found only one great
                            piece of coarse cloth, large enough to be a foot cloth for your
                            Majesty's chief room of state. In the left pocket we saw a huge silver
                            chest, with a cover of the same metal, which we the searchers were not
                            able to lift. We desired it should be opened, and one of us stepping
                            into it, found himself up to the mid leg in a sort of dust, some part
                            whereof flying up to our faces, set us both sneezing for several times
                            together. In his right waistcoat pocket we found a prodigious bundle of
                            white thin sub- <pb n="39" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p39.jpg"/>
                            stances, folded one over another, about the bigness of three men, tied
                            with a strong cable, and marked with black figures; which we humbly
                            conceive to be writings, every letter almost half as large as the palm
                            of our hands. In the left there was a sort of engine, from the back of
                            which were extended twenty long poles, resembling the palisades before
                            your Majesty's court; wherewith we conjecture the Man-Mountain combs his
                            head, for we did not always trouble him with questions, because we found
                            it a great difficulty to make him understand us. In the large pocket on
                            the right side of his middle cover (so I translate the word <hi
                                rend="italics">ranfu-lo</hi>, by which they meant my breeches) we
                            saw a hollow pillar of iron, about the length of a man, fastened to a
                            strong piece of timber, larger than the pillar; and upon one side of the
                            pillar were huge pieces of iron sticking out, cut into strange figures,
                            which we know not what to make of. In the left pocket, another engine
                                <pb n="40" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p40.jpg"/> of the same kind.
                            In the smaller pocket on the right side, were several round flat pieces
                            of white and red metal, of different bulk; some of the white, which
                            seemed to be silver, were so large and heavy, that my comrade and I
                            could hardly lift them. In the left pocket were two black pillars
                            irregularly shaped: we could not, without difficulty, reach the top of
                            them as we stood at the bottom of his pocket. One of them was covered,
                            and seemed all of a piece: but at the upper end of the other, there
                            appeared a white round substance, about twice the bigness of our heads.
                            Within each of these was enclosed a prodigious plate of steel; which, by
                            our orders, we obliged him to show us, because we apprehended they might
                            be dangerous engines. He took them out of their cases, and told us, that
                            in his own country his practice was to shave his beard with one of
                            these, and to cut his meat with the other. There were two pockets which
                            we could not enter: these he <pb n="41"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p41.jpg"/> called his fobs; they were
                            two large slits cut into the top of his middle cover, but squeezed close
                            by the pressure of his belly. Out of the right fob hung a great silver
                            chain, with a wonderful kind of engine at the bottom. We directed him to
                            draw out whatever was fastened to that chain; which appeared to be a
                            globe, half silver, and half of some transparent metal: for on the
                            transparent side we saw certain strange figures circularly drawn, and
                            thought we could touch them, till we found our fingers stopped by that
                            lucid substance. He put this engine to our ears, which made an incessant
                            noise like that of a water-mill: and we conjecture it is either some
                            unknown animal, or the god that he worships; but we are more inclined to
                            the latter opinion, because he assured us (if we understood him right,
                            for he expressed himself very imperfectly) that he seldom did anything
                            without consulting it: he called it his oracle, and said it pointed out
                            the time for every ac- <pb n="42" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p42.jpg"/>
                            tion of his life. From the left fob he took out a net almost large
                            enough for a fisherman, but contrived to open and shut like a purse, and
                            serve him for the same use: we found therein several massy pieces of
                            yellow metal, which, if they be real gold, must be of immense value. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Having thus, in obedience to your Majesty's commands, diligently searched
                            all his pockets, we observed a girdle about his waist made of the hide
                            of some prodigious animal; from which, on the left side, hung a sword of
                            the length of five men; and on the right, a bag or pouch divided into
                            two cells, each cell capable of holding three of your Majesty's
                            subjects. In one of these cells were several globes or balls of a most
                            ponderous metal, about the bigness of our heads, and requiring a strong
                            hand to lift them: the other cell contained a heap of certain black
                            grains, but of no great bulk <pb n="43"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p43.jpg"/> or weight, for we could hold
                            above fifty of them in the palms of our hands. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This is an exact inventory of what we found about the body of the
                            Man-Mountain, who used us with great civility, and due respect to your
                            Majesty's commission. Signed and sealed on the fourth day of the
                            eighty-ninth moon of your Majesty's auspicious reign. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p> Clefren Frelock, Marsi Frelock. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>When this inventory was read over to the Emperor, he directed me,
                            although in very gentle terms, to deliver up the several particulars. He
                            first called for my scimitar, which I took out, scabbard and all. In the
                            meantime he ordered three thousand of his choicest troops (who then
                            attended him) to surround me at a distance, with their bows and arrows
                            just ready to discharge: but I did not observe it, for my eyes were
                            wholly fixed upon his Majesty. He then desired me to draw my scimitar,
                            which, <pb n="44" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p44.jpg"/> although it had
                            got some rust by the sea water, was in most parts exceeding bright. I
                            did so, and immediately all the troops gave a shout between terror and
                            surprise; for the sun shone clear, and the reflection dazzled their eyes
                            as I waved the scimitar to and fro in my hand. His Majesty, who is a
                            most magnanimous prince, was less daunted than I could expect; he
                            ordered me to return it into the scabbard, and cast it on the ground as
                            gently as I could, about six foot from the end of my chain. The next
                            thing he demanded was one of the hollow iron pillars, by which he meant
                            my pocket-pistols. I drew it out, and at his desire, as well as I could,
                            expressed to him the use of it; and charging it only with powder, which
                            by the closeness of my pouch happened to escape wetting in the sea (an
                            inconvenience against which all prudent mariners take special care to
                            provide) I first cautioned the Emperor not to be afraid, and then I let
                            it off in the air. The astonishment here was much greater <pb n="45"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p45.jpg"/> than at the sight of my
                            scimitar. Hundreds fell down as if they had been struck dead; and even
                            the Emperor, although he stood his ground, could not recover himself in
                            some time. I delivered up both my pistols in the same manner as I had
                            done my scimitar, and then my pouch of powder and bullets; begging him
                            that the former might be kept from the fire, for it would kindle with
                            the smallest spark, and blow up his imperial palace into the air. I
                            likewise delivered up my watch, which the Emperor was very curious to
                            see, and commanded two of his tallest yeomen of the guards to bear it on
                            a pole upon their shoulders, as draymen in England do a barrel of ale.
                            He was amazed at the continual noise it made, and the motion of the
                            minute-hand, which he could easily discern; for their sight is much more
                            acute than ours; and asked the opinions of his learned men about him,
                            which were various and remote, as the reader may well imagine without my
                            repeating; although indeed <pb n="46"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p46.jpg"/> I could not very perfectly
                            understand them. I then gave up my silver and copper money, my purse
                            with nine large pieces of gold, and some smaller ones; my knife and
                            razor, my comb and silver snuff-box, my handkerchief and journal-book.
                            My scimitar, pistols, and pouch, were conveyed in carriages to his
                            Majesty's stores; but the rest of my goods were returned me. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I had, as I before observed, one private pocket which escaped their
                            search, wherein there was a pair of spectacles (which I sometimes use
                            for the weakness of my eyes), a pocket <ref target="a057" corresp="n057"
                                >perspective</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n057" target="a057">Telescope.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/64/Monocular_telescope-Lord-Nelson.JPG"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, and several other little conveniences; which, being of no
                            consequence to the Emperor, I did not think myself bound in honor to
                            discover, and I apprehended they might be lost or spoiled if I ventured
                            them out of my possession. </p>
                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="3">
                        <pb n="47" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p47.jpg"/>
                        <head>CHAPTER III</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">The Author diverts the emperor and his nobility of
                                    both sexes in a very uncommon manner. The diversions of the
                                    court of</hi> Lilliput <hi rend="italics">described. The Author
                                    hath his liberty granted him upon certain conditions.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <p>My gentleness and good behavior had gained so far on the Emperor and his
                            court, and indeed upon the army and people in general, that I began to
                            conceive hopes of getting my liberty in a short time. I took all
                            possible methods to cultivate this favorable disposition. The natives
                            came by degrees to be less apprehensive of any danger from me. I would
                            sometimes lie down, and let five or <pb n="48"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p48.jpg"/> six of them dance on my hand.
                            And last the boys and girls would venture to come and play at hide and
                            seek in my hair. I had now made good progress in understanding and
                            speaking their language. The Emperor had a mind one day to entertain me
                            with several of the country shows, wherein they exceeded all nations I
                            have known, both for dexterity and magnificence. I was diverted with
                            none so much as that of the <ref target="a058" corresp="n058"
                                >Rope-dancers</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n058" target="a058">A
                                tightrope-esque performance using a slackline suspended above the
                                ground, usually involving acrobatics. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, performed upon a slender white thread, extended
                            about two feet, and twelve inches from the ground. Upon which I shall
                            desire liberty, with the reader's patience, to enlarge a little. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This diversion is only practiced by those persons who are candidates for
                            great employments and high favors at court. They are trained in this art
                            from their youth, and are not always of noble birth, or liberal
                            education. When a great office is vacant either by death or disgrace
                            (which often happens) five <pb n="49"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p49.jpg"/> or six of those candidates
                            petition the Emperor to entertain his Majesty and the court with a dance
                            on the rope, and whoever jumps the highest without falling, succeeds in
                            the office. Very often the chief ministers themselves are commanded to
                            show their skill, and to convince the Emperor that they have not lost
                            their faculty. <ref target="a059" corresp="n059">Flimnap</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n059" target="a059">Flimnap was believed to be an allegory
                                of Sir Robert Walpole, especially with his perceived ability to
                                twist and turn to fit the political clime. Political enemy of Swift.
                                Source:
                                http://ecti.english.illinois.edu/volume-53-2012-supplement/jonathan-swifts-political-biography/
                                and
                                http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/walpole_robert.shtml</note>,
                            the Treasurer, is allowed to cut a caper on the straight rope, at least
                            an inch higher than any other lord in the whole empire. I have seen him
                            do the <ref target="a060" corresp="n060">summerset</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n060" target="a060">Somersault. Souce: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>several times together upon a trencher fixed on the
                            rope, which is no thicker than a common packthread in England. My friend
                                <ref target="a061" corresp="n061">Reldresal</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n061"
                                target="a061">Allegory to signify moderate Whigs who had some
                                proclivity for Tories.</note>, principal Secretary for Private
                            Affairs, is, in my opinion, if I am not partial, the second after the
                            Treasurer; the rest of the great officers are much upon a par. (need
                            Sam's source) </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>These diversions are often attended with fatal accidents, whereof great
                            numbers are on record. I myself have seen two or three candidates break
                            a limb. <pb n="50" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p50.jpg"/> But the danger
                            is much greater when the ministers themselves are commanded to show
                            their dexterity; for by contending to excell themselves and their
                            fellows, they strain so far, that there is hardly one of them who has
                            not received a fall, and some of them two or three. I was assured that a
                            year or two before my arrival, Flimnap would have infallibly broken his
                            neck, if one of the King's cushions, that accidentally lay on the
                            ground, had not weakened the force of his fall. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>There is likewise another diversion, which is only shown before the
                            Emperor and Empress, and first minister, upon particular occasions. The
                            Emperor lays on the table <ref target="a062" corresp="n062">three fine
                                silken threads</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n062" target="a062"
                                >(DRAFT-Sidebar?)The silken threads are the same colors as the Order
                                of the Garter, Order of Bath, and Order of the Thistle. These were
                                military and civilian order conferred based on merit. Swift was
                                satirizing the focus on what he saw as arbitrary distinctions and
                                awards. In the first edition, Swift's publisher changed the colors
                                to purple, yellow, and white to avoid possible political
                                retribution. Swift was upset and wrote a note decrying this change
                                in subsequent editions.</note> of six inches long. One is blue, the
                            other red, and the third green. These threads are proposed as prizes for
                            those persons whom the Emperor has a mind to distinguish by a peculiar
                            mark of his favor. The ceremony is performed in his Majesty's great
                            chamber of state, <pb n="51" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p51.jpg"/>
                            where the candidates are to undergo a trial of dexterity very different
                            from the former, and such as I have not observed the least resemblance
                            of in any other country of the old or the new world. The Emperor holds a
                            stick in his hands, both ends parallel to the horizon, while the
                            candidates, advancing one by one, sometimes leap over the stick,
                            sometimes creep under it backwards and forwards several times, according
                            as the stick is advanced or depressed. Sometimes the Emperor holds one
                            end of the stick, and his first minister the other; sometimes the
                            minister has it entirely to himself. Whoever performs his part with most
                            agility, and holds out the longest in leaping and creeping, is rewarded
                            with the blue-colored silk; the red is given to the next, and the green
                            to the third, which they all wear girt twice round about the middle; and
                            you see few great persons about this court who are not adorned with one
                            of these girdles. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="52" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p52.jpg"/>

                        <p>The horses of the army, and those of the royal stables, having been daily
                            led before me, were no longer shy, but would come up to my very feet
                            without starting. The riders would leap them over my hand as I held it
                            on the ground, and one of the Emperor's huntsmen, upon a large courser,
                            took my foot, shoe and all; which was indeed a prodigious leap. I had
                            the good fortune to divert the Emperor one day after a very
                            extraordinary manner. I desired he would order several sticks two feet
                            high, and the thickness of an ordinary cane, to be brought me; whereupon
                            his Majesty commanded the master of his woods to give directions
                            accordingly; and the next morning six woodmen arrived with as many
                            carriages, drawn by eight horses to each. I took nine of these sticks,
                            and fixing them firmly in the ground in a quadrangular figure, two feet
                            and a half square, I took four other sticks, and tied them parallel at
                            each corner, about <pb n="53" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p53.jpg"/> two
                            feet from the ground; then I fastened my handkerchief to the nine sticks
                            that stood erect, and extended it on all sides till it was as tight as
                            the top of a drum; and the four parallel sticks rising about five inches
                            higher than the handkerchief served as ledges on each side. When I had
                            finished my work, I desired the Emperor to let a troop of his best
                            horse, twentyfour in number, come and exercise upon this plain. His
                            Majesty approved of the proposal, and I took them up one by one in my
                            hands, ready mounted and armed, with the proper officers to exercise
                            them. As soon as they got into order, they divided into two parties,
                            performed mock skirmishes, discharged blunt arrows, drew their swords,
                            fled and pursued, attacked and retired, and in Short <ref target="a063"
                                corresp="n063">discovered</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n063" target="a063"
                                >Revealed. Souce: Oxford English Dictionary</note> the best military
                            discipline I ever beheld. The parallel sticks secured them and their
                            horses from falling over the stage; and the Emperor was so much
                            delighted, that he ordered this entertainment to be re- <pb n="54"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p54.jpg"/> peated several days, and once
                            was pleased to be lifted up and give the word of command; and, with
                            great difficulty, persuaded even the Empress herself to let me hold her
                            in her close chair within two yards of the stage, from whence she was
                            able to take a full view of the whole performance. It was my good
                            fortune that no ill accident happened in these entertainments, only once
                            a fiery horse that belonged to one of the captains pawing with his hoof
                            struck a hole in my handkerchief, and his foot slipping, he overthrew
                            his rider and himself; but I immediately relieved them both, and
                            covering the hole with one hand, I set down the troop with the other, in
                            the same manner as I took them up. The horse that fell was strained in
                            the left shoulder, but the rider got no hurt, and I repaired my
                            handkerchief as well as I could: however I would not trust to the
                            strength of it any more in such dangerous enterprises. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="55" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p55.jpg"/>

                        <p>About two or three days before I was set at liberty, as I was
                            entertaining the court with these kind of feats, there arrived an
                            express to inform his Majesty that some of his subjects riding near the
                            place where I was first taken up, had seen a great black substance lying
                            on the ground, very oddly shaped, extending its edges round as wide as
                            his Majesty's bedchamber, and rising up in the middle as high as a man;
                            that it was no living creature, as they at first apprehended, for it lay
                            on the grass without motion, and some of them had walked round it
                            several tunes: that by mounting upon each other's shoulders, they had
                            got to the top, which was flat and even, and stamping upon it they found
                            it was hollow within; that they humbly conceived it might be something
                            belonging to the Man-Mountain, and if his Majesty pleased, they would
                            undertake to bring it with only five horses. I presently knew what they
                            meant, and was glad at heart to re- <pb n="56"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p56.jpg"/> ceive this intelligence. It
                            seems upon my first reaching the shore after our shipwreck, I was in
                            such confusion, that before I came to the place where I went to sleep,
                            my hat, which I had fastened with a string to my head while I was
                            rowing, and had stuck on all the time I was swimming, fell off after I
                            came to land; the string, as I conjecture, breaking by some accident
                            which I never observed, but thought my hat had been lost at sea. I
                            entreated his Imperial Majesty to give orders it might be brought to me
                            as soon as possible, describing to him the use and the nature of it: and
                            the next day the wagoners arrived with it, but not in a very good
                            condition; they had bored two holes in the brim, within an inch and a
                            half of the edge, and fastened two hooks in the holes; these hooks were
                            tied by a long cord to the harness, and thus my hat was dragged along
                            for above half an English mile: but the ground in that country being
                            extremely smooth and level, it received less damage than I expected. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="57" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p57.jpg"/>

                        <p>Two days after this adventure, the Emperor having ordered that part of
                            his army which quarters in and about his metropolis to be in a
                            readiness, took a fancy of diverting himself in a very singular manner.
                            He desired I would stand like a Colossus, with my legs as far asunder as
                            I conveniently could. He then commanded his General (who was an old
                            experienced leader, and a great patron of mine) to draw up the troops in
                            close order, and march them under me, the foot by twentyfour <ref
                                target="a064" corresp="n064">in a breast</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n064"
                                target="a064">Abreast. Souce: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and
                            the horse by sixteen, with drums beating, colors flying, and pikes
                            advanced. This body consisted of three thousand foot, and a thousand
                            horse. His Majesty gave orders, upon pain of death, that every soldier
                            in his march should observe the strictest decency with regard to my
                            person; which, however, could not prevent some of the younger officers
                            from turning up their eyes as they passed under me. And, to confess the
                            truth, <pb n="58" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p58.jpg"/> my breeches
                            were at that time in so ill a condition, that they afforded some
                            opportunities for laughter and admiration. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I had sent so many memorials and petitions for my liberty, that his
                            Majesty at length mentioned the matter, first in the cabinet, and then
                            in a full council; where it was opposed by none, except <ref
                                target="a065" corresp="n065">Skyresh Bolgolam</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n065" target="a065">Believed to be a reference to the Second
                                Earl of Nottingham. Source: Lock, F. P. The Politics of Gulliver's
                                Travels. Clarendon Press, 1980. (pg. 114)</note>, who was pleased,
                            without any provocation, to be my mortal enemy. But it was carried
                            against him by the whole board, and confirmed by the Emperor. That
                            minister was Galbet, or Admiral of the Realm, very much in his master's
                            confidence, and a person well versed in affairs, but of a morose and
                            sour complexion. However, he was at length persuaded to comply; but
                            prevailed that the articles and conditions upon which I should be set
                            free, and to which I must swear, should be drawn up by himself. These
                            articles were brought to me by Skyresh Bolgolam in person, attended by
                            two under-secre- <pb n="59" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p59.jpg"/>
                            taries, and several persons of distinction. After they were read, I was
                            demanded to swear to the performance of them; first in the manner of my
                            own country, and afterwards in the method prescribed by their laws;
                            which was to hold my right foot in my left hand, to place the middle
                            finger of my right hand on the crown of my head, and my thumb on the tip
                            of my right ear. But because the reader may perhaps be curious to have
                            some idea of the style and manner of expression peculiar to that people,
                            as well as to know the articles upon which I recovered my liberty, I
                            have made a translation of the whole instrument word for word, as near
                            as I was able, which I here offer to the public. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Golbasto Momaren Evlame Gurdilo Shefin Mully Ully Gue, most mighty
                            Emperor of Lilliput, delight and terror of the universe, whose dominions
                            extend five thousand blustrugs (about twelve miles in circumference) to
                                <pb n="60" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p60.jpg"/> the extremities of
                            the globe; monarch of all monarchs, taller than the sons of men; whose
                            feet press down to the <ref target="a066" corresp="n066">Center
                                </ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n066" target="a066">Of the Earth. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note>, and whose head strikes against the sun;
                            at whose nod the princes of the earth shake their knees; pleasant as the
                            spring, comfortable as the summer, fruitful as autumn, dreadful as
                            winter. His most sublime Majesty proposes to the Man-Mountain, lately
                            arrived to our celestial dominions, the following articles, which by a
                            solemn oath he shall be obliged to perform. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>First, The Man-Mountain shall not depart from our dominions, without our
                            license under our great seal. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>2nd, He shall not presume to come into our metropolis, without our
                            express order; at which time the inhabitants shall have two hours
                            warning to keep within their doors. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="61" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p61.jpg"/>

                        <p>3rd, The said Man-Mountain shall confine his walks to our principal high
                            roads, and not offer to walk or lie down in a meadow or field of corn. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>4th, As he walks the said roads, he shall take the utmost care not to
                            trample upon the bodies of any of our loving subjects, their horses, or
                            carriages, nor take any of our said subjects into his hands, without
                            their own consent. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>5th, If an express requires extraordinary dispatch, the Man-Mountain
                            shall be obliged to carry in his pocket the messenger and horse a six
                            days journey once in every moon, and return the said messenger back (if
                            so required) safe to our Imperial Presence. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>6th, He shall be our ally against our enemies in the Island of Blefuscu,
                            and do his utmost to destroy their fleet, which is now preparing to
                            invade us. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="62" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p62.jpg"/>

                        <p>7th, That the said Man-Mountain shall, at his times of leisure, be aiding
                            and assisting to our workmen, in helping to raise certain great stones,
                            towards covering the wall of the principal park, and other of our royal
                            buildings. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>8th, That the said Man-Mountain shall, in two moons' time, deliver in an
                            exact survey of the circumference of our dominions by a computation of
                            his own paces round the coast. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p> Lastly, That upon his solemn oath to observe all the above articles, the
                            said Man-Mountain shall have a daily allowance of meat and drink
                            sufficient for the support of 1,728 of our subjects, with free access to
                            our Royal Person, and other marks of our favor. Given at our Palace at
                            Belfaborac the twelfth day of the <ref target="c001" corresp="n0001"
                                >ninety-first moon of our reign</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0001"
                                target="c001">Given that there is a full moon every twenty-ninedays,
                                "the ninety-first moon of our reign" is a little over seven years.
                                Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_phase</note>. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="63" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p63.jpg"/>

                        <p>I swore and subscribed to these articles with great cheerfulness and
                            content, although some of them were not so honorable as I could have
                            wished; which proceeded wholly from the malice of Skyresh Bolgolam the
                            High Admiral: whereupon my chains were immediately unlocked, and I was
                            at full liberty; the Emperor himself in person did me the honor to be by
                            at the whole ceremony. I made my acknowledgments by <ref target="c0002"
                                corresp="n0002">prostrating</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0002" target="c0002"
                                >The act of prostration is similar to kneeling or bowing, and is
                                meant to show submission to a higher power. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/49/Different_kinds_of_bows_in_eo.gif"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note> myself at his Majesty's feet: but he commanded me to rise; and
                            after many gracious expressions, which, to avoid the <ref target="c0003"
                                corresp="n0003">censure</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0003" target="c0003">A
                                formal disapproval, criticism, or judgement. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> of vanity, I shall not repeat, he added, that he
                            hoped I should prove a useful servant, and well deserve all the favors
                            he had already conferred upon me, or might do for the future. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The reader may please to observe, that in the last article for the
                            recovery of my liberty the Emperor stipulates <pb n="64"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p64.jpg"/> to allow me a quantity of
                            meat and drink sufficient for the support of 1,728 Lilliputians. Some
                            time after, asking a friend at court how they came to fix on that
                            determinate number, he told me that his Majesty's mathematicians, having
                            taken the height of my body by the help of a <ref target="c0004"
                                corresp="n0004">quadrant</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0004" target="c0004">A
                                measuring instrument similar to an astrolabe. The picture shows
                                Ptolemy, its creator, using the quadrant. <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/59/Ptolemy_Astrology_1564.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, and finding it to exceed theirs in the proportion of twelve to
                            one, they concluded from the similarity of their bodies, that mine must
                            contain at least 1,728 of theirs, and consequently would require as much
                            food as was necessary to support that number of Lilliputians. By which
                            the reader may conceive an idea of the ingenuity of that people, as well
                            as the prudent and exact economy of so great a prince. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="4">

                        <pb n="65" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p65.jpg"/>

                        <head>CHAPTER IV</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p>Mildendo <hi rend="italics">the metropolis of</hi> Lilliput, <hi
                                    rend="italics">described, together with the emperor's palace. A
                                    conversation between the Author and a principal secretary,
                                    concerning the affairs of that empire. The Author's offers to
                                    serve the emperor in his wars.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The first request I made after I had obtained my liberty, was, that I
                            might have license to see Mildendo, the metropolis, which the Emperor
                            easily granted me, but with a special charge to do no hurt either to the
                            inhabitants or their houses. The people had notice by proclamation of my
                            design to visit the town. The wall which encompassed it is two feet and
                            a half <pb n="66" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p66.jpg"/> high, and at
                            least eleven inches broad, so that a coach and horses may be driven very
                            safely round it; and it is flanked with strong towers at ten feet
                            distance. I stepped over the great Gate, and passed very gently, and
                                <ref target="c0005" corresp="n0005">sideling</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0005" target="c0005">Moving sideways. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note> through the two principal streets, only in
                            my short waistcoat, for fear of damaging the roofs and eaves of the
                            houses with the skirts of my coat. I walked with the utmost <ref
                                target="c0006" corresp="n0006">circumspection</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0006" target="c0006">Caution. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, to avoid treading on any stragglers, that might
                            remain in the streets, although the orders were very strict, that all
                            people should keep in their houses at their own peril. The <ref
                                target="c0007" corresp="n0007">garret windows</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0007" target="c0007">Garret windows are windows in the
                                roofs of buildings. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> and
                            tops of houses were so crowded with spectators, that I thought in all my
                            travels I had not seen a more populous place. The city is an exact
                            square, each side of the wall being five hundred feet long. The two
                            great streets, which run cross and divide it into four quarters, are
                            five feet wide. The lanes and alleys, which I could not enter, but only
                            viewed them as I passed, are from <pb n="67"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p67.jpg"/> twelve to eighteen inches.
                            The town is capable of holding five hundred thousand souls. The houses
                            are from three to five stories. The shops and markets well provided. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The Emperor's palace is in the centre of the city, where the two great
                            streets meet. It is enclosed by a wall of two feet high, and twenty feet
                            distant from the buildings. I had his Majesty's permission to step over
                            this wall; and the space being so wide between that and the palace, I
                            could easily view it on every side. The outward court is a square of
                            forty feet, and includes two other courts: in the inmost are the royal
                            apartments, which I was very desirous to see, but found it extremely
                            difficult; for the great gates, from one square into another, were but
                            eighteen inches high and seven inches wide. Now the buildings of the
                            outer court were at least five feet high, and it was impossible for me
                            to stride over them with <pb n="68" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p68.jpg"
                            /> out infinite damage to the pile, though the walls were strongly built
                            of hewn stone, and four inches thick. At the same time the Emperor had a
                            great desire that I should see the magnificence of his palace; but this
                            I was not able to do till three days after, which I spent in cutting
                            down with my knife some of the largest trees in the royal park, about a
                            hundred yards distant from the city. Of these trees I made two stools,
                            each about three feet high, and strong enough to bear my weight. The
                            people having received notice a second time, I went again through the
                            city to the palace, with my two stools in my hands. When I came to the
                            side of the outer court, I stood upon one stool, and took the other in
                            my hand: this I lifted over the roof, and gently set it down on the
                            space between the first and second court, which was eight feet wide. I
                            then stepped over the buildings very conveniently from one stool to the
                            other, and drew up the first after me with a hooked stick. <pb n="69"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p69.jpg"/> By this <ref target="c0008"
                                corresp="n0008">contrivance</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0008" target="c0008"
                                >A mechanical device or invention for a particular situation.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> I got into the inmost
                            court; and lying down upon my side, I applied my face to the windows of
                            the middle stories, which were left open on purpose, and discovered the
                            most splendid apartments that can be imagined. There I saw the Empress
                            and the young Princes, in their several lodgings, with their chief
                            attendants about them. Her Imperial Majesty was pleased to smile very
                            graciously upon me, and gave me out of the window her hand to kiss. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>But I shall not anticipate the reader with farther descriptions of this
                            kind, because I reserve them for a greater work, which is now almost
                            ready for the press, containing a general description of this empire,
                            from its first erection, through a long series of princes, with a
                            particular account of their wars and politics, laws, learning, and
                            religion: their plants and animals, their peculiar manners and customs,
                            with other matters very curious and useful; my chief design <pb n="70"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p70.jpg"/> at present being only to
                            relate such events and transactions as happened to the public, or to
                            myself, during a residence of about nine months in that empire. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>One morning, about a fortnight after I had obtained my liberty,
                            Reldresal, principal Secretary (as they style him) of Private Affairs,
                            came to my house attended only by one servant. He ordered his coach to
                            wait at a distance, and desired I would give him an hour's audience;
                            which I readily consented to, on account of his quality and personal
                            merits, as well as the many good offices he had done me during my
                            solicitations at court. I offered to lie down, that he might the more
                            conveniently reach my ear; but he chose rather to let me hold him in my
                            hand during our conversation. He began with compliments on my liberty;
                            said he might pretend to some merit in it: but, however, added, that if
                            it had not been for the present situ- <pb n="71"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p71.jpg"/> ation of things at court,
                            perhaps I might not have obtained it so soon. For, said he, as
                            flourishing a condition as we may appear to be in to foreigners, we
                            labor under two mighty evils; a violent faction at home, and the danger
                            of an invasion by a most potent enemy from abroad. As to the first, you
                            are to understand, that for above seventy moons past there have been two
                            struggling parties in this empire, under the names of <ref
                                target="a078b" corresp="n078b">Tramecksan and Slamecksan</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n078b" target="a078b">"In the names themselves, Swift may,
                                by reversing foreign words, be indicating to the reader the original
                                difference between the two parties, a difference not in heels but in
                                noses. If we reverse the names "Tramecksan" and "Slamecksan" we find
                                that the former are "nas camard" (nas keemart) or snub-noses while
                                the latter are "nas camels" (nas keemals) or camels'-noses. "Nas" is
                                of course still a French variant for "nez"-or may be the root of
                                "nasus"-while "keemart" is a fairly accurate phonetic spelling of
                                "camard". "Kcenmals" is a phonetic spelling of camels with "e" and
                                "a" transposed." -H. D. Keller.
                                Source:http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/4172994.pdf?seq=1</note>,
                            from the high and low heels on their shoes, by which they distinguish
                            themselves. It is alleged indeed, that the high heels are most agreeable
                            to our ancient constitution: but however this be, his Majesty has
                            determined to make use of only low heels in the administration of the
                            government, and all offices in the gift of the Crown, as you cannot but
                            observe; and particularly, that his Majesty's Imperial heels are lower
                            at least by a drurr than any of his court; (drurr is a measure about the
                            fourteenth part <pb n="72" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p72.jpg"/> of an
                            inch). The animosities between these two parties run so high, that they
                            will neither eat nor drink, nor talk with each other. We compute the
                            Tramecksan, or High-Heels, to exceed us in number; but the power is
                            wholly on our side. We apprehend his Imperial Highness, the Heir to the
                            Crown, to have some tendency towards the High-Heels; at least we can
                            plainly discover one of his heels higher than the other, which gives him
                            a hobble in his gait. Now, in the midst of these <ref target="c0009"
                                corresp="n0009">intestine</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0009" target="c0009"
                                >Internal or domestic. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
                            disquiets, we are threatened with an invasion from the Island of
                            Blefuscu, which is the other great empire of the universe, almost as
                            large and powerful as this of his Majesty. For as to what we have heard
                            you affirm, that there are other kingdoms and states in the world
                            inhabited by human creatures as large as yourself, our philosophers are
                            in much doubt, and would rather conjecture that you dropped from the
                            moon, or one of the stars; because it is certain, that a hundred mor-
                                <pb n="73" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p73.jpg"/> tals of your bulk
                            would, in a short time, destroy all the fruits and cattle of his
                            Majesty's dominions. Besides, our histories of <ref target="c0010"
                                corresp="n0010">six thousand moons</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0010"
                                target="c0010">A little over 476 years. Source:
                                https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_phase</note> make no mention of
                            any other regions, than the two great empires of Lilliput and Blefuscu.
                            Which two mighty powers have, as I was going to tell you, been engaged
                            in a most obstinate war for <ref target="c0011" corresp="n0011">six and
                                thirty moons</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0011" target="c0011">Nearly three
                                years. Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_phase</note>
                            past. It began upon the following occasion. It is allowed on all hands,
                            that the primitive way of breaking eggs, before we eat them, was upon
                            the larger end: but his present Majesty's grandfather, while he was a
                            boy, going to eat an egg, and breaking it according to the ancient
                            practice, happened to cut one of his fingers. Whereupon the Emperor his
                            father published an edict, commanding all his subjects, upon great
                            penalties, to break the smaller end of their eggs. The people so highly
                            resented this law, that our histories tell us there have been six
                            rebellions raised on that account; wherein one Emperor lost his life,
                            and <pb n="74" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p74.jpg"/> another his crown.
                            These civil commotions were constantly <ref target="c0012"
                                corresp="n0012">fomented</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0012" target="c0012"
                                >Roused or instigated. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> by
                            the monarchs of Blefuscu; and when they were quelled, the exiles always
                            fled for refuge to that empire. It is computed, that eleven thousand
                            persons have, at several times, suffered death, rather than submit to
                            break their eggs at the smaller end. Many hundred large volumes have
                            been published upon this controversy: but the books of the <ref
                                target="c0013" corresp="n0013">Big-Endians</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0013"
                                target="c0013">(DRAFT-Sidebar? Jianna gave us slides)The concept of
                                Big and Little Endians was later used as a computer science term to
                                refer to the order of bytes within a binary representation of a
                                number. Source: Wikipedia</note> have been long forbidden, and the
                            whole party rendered incapable by law of holding employments. During the
                            course of these troubles, the Emperors of Blefuscu did frequently <ref
                                target="c0014" corresp="n0014">exposulate</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0014"
                                target="c0014">Express disapproval. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> by their ambassadors, accusing us of making a
                            schism in religion, by offending against a fundamental doctrine of our
                            great prophet Lustrog, in the fifty-fourth chapter of the Blundecral
                            (which is their <ref target="c0015" corresp="n0015">Alcoran</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0015" target="c0015">The Alcoran is the sacred book of
                                Islam. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>). This, however, is
                            thought to be a mere strain upon the text: for the words are these; That
                            all true believers shall break their eggs at the convenient <pb n="75"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p75.jpg"/> end: and which is the
                            convenient end, seems, in my humble opinion, to be left to every man's
                            conscience, or at least in the power of the chief magistrate to
                            determine. Now the Big-Endian exiles have found so much credit in the
                            Emperor of Blefuscu's court, and so much private assistance and
                            encouragement from their party here at home, that a bloody war has been
                            carried on between the two empires for six and thirty moons with various
                            success; during which time we have lost forty capital ships, and a much
                            greater number of smaller vessels, together with thirty thousand of our
                            best seamen and soldiers; and the damage received by the enemy is
                            reckoned to be somewhat greater than ours. However, they have now
                            equipped a numerous fleet, and are just preparing to make a descent upon
                            us; and his Imperial Majesty, placing great confidence in your valor and
                            strength, has commanded me to lay this account of his affairs before
                            you. </p>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="76" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p76.jpg"/>

                        <lb/>
                        <p>I desired the Secretary to present my humble duty to the Emperor, and to
                            let him know, that I thought it would not become me, who was a
                            foreigner, to interfere with parties; but I was ready, with the hazard
                            of my life, to defend his person and state against all invaders. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="5">

                        <pb n="77" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p77.jpg"/>

                        <head>CHAPTER V</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">The Author, by an extraordinary <ref
                                        target="c0016" corresp="n0016">strategem</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                        xml:id="n0016" target="c0016">Plan or strategy. Source:
                                        Oxford English Dictionary</note>, prevents an invasion. A
                                    high title of honour is conferred upon him. Ambassadors arrive
                                    from the emperor of </hi>Blefuscu, <hi rend="italics">and sue
                                    for peace. The empress's apartment on fire by accident; the
                                    Author instrumental in saving the rest of the palace.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The Empire of Blefuscu is an island situated to the north-northeast side
                            of Lilliput, from whence it is parted only by a channel of eight hundred
                            yards wide. I had not yet seen it, and upon this notice of an intended
                            invasion, I avoided appearing on that side of the coast, for fear of
                            being discovered by some of the enemy's ships, <pb n="78"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p78.jpg"/> who had received no
                            intelligence of me, all intercourse between the two empires having been
                            strictly forbidden during the war, upon pain of death, and an embargo
                            laid by our Emperor upon all vessels whatsoever. I communicated to his
                            Majesty a project I had formed of seizing the enemy's whole fleet:
                            which, as our scouts assured us, lay at anchor in the harbor ready to
                            sail with the first fair wind. I consulted the most experienced seamen,
                            upon the depth of the channel, which they had often <ref target="c0017"
                                corresp="n0017">plumbed</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0017" target="c0017"
                                >Measured the depths of. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,
                            who told me, that in the middle at high-water it was seventy glumgluffs
                            deep, which is about six feet of European measure; and the rest of it
                            fifty glumgluffs at most. I walked towards the northeast coast over
                            against Blefuscu; and lying down behind a <ref target="c0018"
                                corresp="n0018">hillock</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0018" target="c0018">A
                                little hill. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, took out my
                            small pocket perspective glass, and viewed the enemy's fleet at anchor,
                            consisting of about fifty <ref target="c0019" corresp="n0019">men of
                                war</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0019" target="c0019">A man-of-war is a
                                warship. Source: Oxford English Dictionary <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4e/Willem_van_de_Velde_II_-_Dutch_men-o%27-war_and_other_shipping_in_a_calm.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, and a great number of transports; I then came back to my house,
                            and gave order <pb n="79" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p79.jpg"/> (for
                            which I had a warrant) for a great quantity of the strongest cable and
                            bars of iron. The cable was about as thick as packthread, and the bars
                            of the length and size of a knitting needle. I trebled the cable to make
                            it stronger, and for the same reason I twisted three of the iron bars
                            together, binding the extremities into a hook. Having thus fixed fifty
                            hooks to as many cables, I went back to the northeast coast, and putting
                            off my coat, shoes, and stockings, walked into the sea in my leather
                            jerkin, about half an hour before high water. I waded with what haste I
                            could, and swam in the middle about thirty yards till I felt ground; I
                            arrived at the fleet in less than half an hour. The enemy was so
                            frighted when they saw me, that they leaped out of their ships, and swam
                            to shore, where there could not be fewer than thirty thousand souls. I
                            then took my tackling, and fastening a hook to a hole at the prow of
                            each, I tied all the cords together at the end. While I was thus <pb
                                n="80" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p80.jpg"/> employed, the enemy
                            discharged several thousand arrows, many of which stuck in my hands and
                            face; and besides the excessive smart, gave me much disturbance in my
                            work. My greatest apprehension was for my eyes, which I should have
                            infallibly lost, if I had not suddenly thought of an expedient. I kept
                            among other little necessaries a pair of spectacles in a private pocket,
                            which, as I observed before, had escaped the Emperor's searchers. These
                            I took out and fastened as strongly as I could upon my nose, and thus
                            armed went on boldly with my work in spite of the enemy's arrows, many
                            of which struck against the glasses of my spectacles, but without any
                            other effect, further than a little to discompose them. I now fastened
                            all the hooks, and taking the knot in my hand, began to pull; but not a
                            ship would stir, for they were all too fast held by their anchors, so
                            that the boldest part of my enterprise remained. I therefore let go the
                            cord, and leaving the hooks fixed to the ships, I resolutely <pb n="81"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p81.jpg"/> cut with my knife the cables
                            that fastened the anchors, receiving above two hundred shots in my face
                            and hands; then I took up the knotted end of the cables to which my
                            hooks were tied, and with great ease drew fifty of the enemy's
                            men-of-war after me. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The Blefuscudians, who had not the least imagination of what I intended,
                            were at first confounded with astonishment. They had seen me cut the
                            cables, and thought my design was only to let the ships run adrift or
                            fall foul on each other: but when they perceived the whole fleet moving
                            in order, and saw me pulling at the end, they set up such a scream of
                            grief and despair, that it is almost impossible to describe or conceive.
                            When I had got out of danger, I stopped awhile to pick out the arrows
                            that stuck in my hands and face, and rubbed on some of the same ointment
                            that was given me at my first arrival, as I have formerly mentioned. I
                            then took off my specta- <pb n="82" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p82.jpg"
                            /> cles, and waiting about an hour, till the tide was a little fallen, I
                            waded through the middle with my cargo, and arrived safe at the royal
                            port of Lilliput </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The Emperor and his whole court stood on the shore expecting the issue of
                            this great adventure. They saw the ships move forward in a large
                            half-moon, but could not discern me, who was up to my breast in water.
                            When I advanced to the middle of the channel, they were yet in more
                            pain, because I was under water to my neck. The Emperor concluded me to
                            be drowned, and that the enemy's fleet was approaching in a hostile
                            manner: but he was soon eased of his fears, for the channel growing
                            shallower every step I made, I came in a short time within hearing, and
                            holding up the end of the cable by which the fleet was fastened, I cried
                            in a loud voice, Long live the most <ref target="c0020" corresp="n0020"
                                >puissant</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0020" target="c0020">The french word
                                for powerful. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Emperor of
                            Lilliput! This great prince received me at my landing with all possible
                                <ref target="c0021" corresp="n0021">eco-</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0021"
                                target="c0021">Ecomiums are formal, written praises. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictioanry</note>
                            <pb n="83" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p83.jpg"/>
                            <ref target="c0021a" corresp="n0021a">miums</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0021a"
                                target="c0021a">Ecomiums are formal, written praises. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictioanry</note>, and created me a Nardac upon the spot,
                            which is the highest title of honor among them. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>His Majesty desired I would take some other opportunity of bringing all
                            the rest of his enemy's ships into his ports. And so unmeasurable is the
                            ambition of princes, that he seemed to think of nothing less than
                            reducing the whole empire of Blefuscu into a province, and governing it
                            by a Viceroy; of destroying the Big-Endian exiles, and compelling that
                            people to break the smaller end of their eggs, by which he would remain
                            the sole monarch of the whole world. But I endeavored to divert him from
                            this design, by many arguments drawn from the topics of policy as well
                            as justice; and I plainly protested, that I would never be an instrument
                            of bringing a free and brave people into slavery. And when the matter
                            was debated in council, the wisest part of the ministry were of my
                            opinion. </p>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="84" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p84.jpg"/>

                        <lb/>
                        <p>This open bold declaration of mine was so opposite to the schemes and
                            politics of his Imperial Majesty, that he could never forgive it; he
                            mentioned it in a very artful manner at council, where I was told that
                            some of the wisest appeared, at least by their silence, to be of my
                            opinion; but others, who were my secret enemies, could not forbear some
                            expressions, which by a <ref target="c0022" corresp="n0022"
                                >side-wind</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n0022" target="c0022">An indirect
                                means or influence. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
                            reflected on me. And from this time began an intrigue between his
                            Majesty and a <ref target="c0023" corresp="n0023">junto</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0023" target="c0023">A faction, generally in politics.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of ministers maliciously
                            bent against me, which broke out in less than two months, and had like
                            to have ended in my utter destruction. Of so little weight are the
                            greatest services to princes, when put into the balance with a refusal
                            to gratify their passions. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>About three weeks after this exploit, there arrived a solemn embassy from
                            Blefuscu, with humble offers of a peace; which was soon concluded upon
                            condi- <pb n="85" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p85.jpg"/> tions very
                            advantageous to our Emperor, wherewith I shall not trouble the reader.
                            There were six ambassadors, with a train of about five hundred persons,
                            and their entry was very magnificent, suitable to the grandeur of their
                            master, and the importance of their business. When their treaty was
                            finished, wherein I did them several good offices by the credit I now
                            had, or at least appeared to have at court, their Excellencies, who were
                            privately told how much I had been their friend, made me a visit in
                            form. They began with many compliments upon my valor and generosity,
                            invited me to that kingdom in the Emperor their master's name, and
                            desired me to show them some proofs of my prodigious strength, of which
                            they had heard so many wonders; wherein I readily obliged them, but
                            shall not trouble the reader with the particulars. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>When I had for some time entertained their Excellencies, to their
                            infinite satisfaction and surprise, I desired they <pb n="86"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p86.jpg"/> would do me the honor to
                            present my most humble respects to the Emperor their master, the renown
                            of whose had so justly filled the whole world with admiration, and whose
                            royal person I resolved to attend before I returned to my own country:
                            accordingly, the next time I had the honor to see our Emperor, I desired
                            his general license to wait on the Blefuscudian monarch, which he was
                            pleased to grant me, as I could plainly perceive, in a very cold manner;
                            but could not guess the reason, till I had a whisper from a certain
                            person, that Flimnap and Bolgolam had represented my intercourse with
                            those ambassadors as a mark of disaffection, from which I am sure my
                            heart was wholly free. And this was the first time I began to conceive
                            some imperfect idea of courts and ministers. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>It is to be observed, that these ambassadors spoke to me by an
                            interpreter, the languages of both empires differing as much from each
                            other as any two in <pb n="87" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p87.jpg"/>
                            Europe, and each nation priding itself upon the antiquity, beauty, and
                            energy of their own tongues, with an avowed contempt for that of their
                            neighbor; yet our Emperor, standing upon the advantage he had got by the
                            seizure of their fleet, obliged them to deliver their credentials, and
                            make their speech in the Lilliputian tongue. And it must be confessed,
                            that from the great intercourse of trade and commerce between both
                            realms, from the continual reception of exiles, which is mutual among
                            them, and from the custom in each empire to send their young nobility
                            and richer gentry to the other, in order to polish themselves by seeing
                            the world and understanding men and manners; there are few persons of
                            distinction, or merchants, or seamen, who dwell in the maritime parts,
                            but what can hold conversation both tongues; as I found some weeks
                            after, when I went to pay my respects to the Emperor of Blefuscu, which
                            in the midst of great misfortunes, through the malice of <pb n="88"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p88.jpg"/> my enemies, proved a very
                            happy adventure to me, as I shall relate in its proper place. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The reader may remember, that when I signed those articles upon which I
                            recovered my liberty, there were some which I disliked upon account of
                            their being too servile, neither could anything but an extreme necessity
                            have forced me to submit. But being now a Nardac, of the highest rank in
                            that empire, such offices were looked upon as below my dignity, and the
                            Emperor (to do him justice) never once mentioned them to me. However, it
                            was not long before I had an opportunity of doing his Majesty, at least,
                            as I then thought, a most signal service. I was alarmed at midnight with
                            the cries of many hundred people at my door; by which being suddenly
                            awaked, I was in some kind of terror. I heard the word burglum repeated
                            incessantly: several of the Emperor's court, making their way through
                            the crowd, entreated <pb n="89" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p89.jpg"/>
                            me to come immediately to the Palace, where her Imperial Majesty's
                            apartment was on fire, by the carelessness of a maid of honor, who fell
                            asleep while she was reading a romance. I got up in an instant; and
                            orders being given to clear the way before me, and it being likewise a
                            moonshine night, I made a shift to get to the Palace without trampling
                            on any of the people. I found they had already applied ladders to the
                            walls of the apartment, and were well provided with buckets, but the
                            water was at some distance. These buckets were about the size of a large
                            thimble, and the poor people supplied me with them as fast as they
                            could; but the flame was so violent that they did little good. I might
                            easily have stifled it with my coat, which I unfortunately left behind
                            me for haste, and came away only in my leathern jerkin. The case seemed
                            wholly desperate and deplorable; and this magnificent palace would have
                            infallibly been burned down to the ground, if, by a presence <pb n="90"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p90.jpg"/> of mind, unusual to me, I had
                            not suddenly thought of an expedient. I had the evening before drunk
                            plentifully of a most delicious wine, called glimigrim (the
                            Blefuscudians call it flunec, but ours is esteemed the better sort),
                            which is very <ref target="c0024" corresp="n0024">diuretic</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n0024" target="c0024">A substance that causes the increased
                                production of urine. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. By
                            the luckiest chance in the world, I had not discharged myself of any
                            part of it. The heat I had contracted by coming very near the flames,
                            and by laboring to quench them, made the wine begin to operate my urine;
                            which I voided in such a quantity, and applied so well to the proper
                            places, that in three minutes the fire was wholly extinguished, and the
                            rest of that noble pile, which had cost so many ages in erecting,
                            preserved from destruction. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>It was now daylight, and I returned to my house without waiting to
                            congratulate with the Emperor: because, although I had done a very
                            eminent piece of service, yet I could not tell how his Ma <pb n="91"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p91.jpg"/> jesty might resent the manner
                            by which I had performed it: for, by the fundamental laws of the realm,
                            it is capital in any person, of what quality soever, to make water
                            within the precincts of the palace. But I was a little comforted by a
                            message from his Majesty, that he would give orders to the Grand
                            Justiciary for passing my pardon in form; which, however, I could not
                            obtain. And I was privately assured, that the Empress, conceiving the
                            greatest abhorrence of what I had done, removed to the most distant side
                            of the court, firmly resolved that those buildings should never be
                            repaired for her use: and, in the presence of her chief confidants could
                            not forbear vowing revenge. </p>


                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="6">

                        <pb n="92" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p92.jpg"/>

                        <head>CHAPTER VI</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">Of the inhabitants of</hi> Lilliput; <hi
                                    rend="italics">their learning, laws, and customs, the manner of
                                    educating their children. The Author's way of living in that
                                    country. His vindication of a great Lady.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>


                        <p>Although I intend to leave the description of this empire to a particular
                            treatise, yet in the meantime I am content to gratify the curious reader
                            with some general ideas. As the common size of the natives is somewhat
                            under six inches high, so there is an exact proportion in all other
                            animals, as well as plants and trees: for instance, the tallest horses
                            and oxen are between four and five in <pb n="93"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p93.jpg"/> ches in height, the sheep an
                            inch and a half, more or less: their geese about the bigness of a
                            sparrow,and so the several gradations downwards till you come to the
                            smallest, which, to my sight, were almost invisible; but nature had
                            adapted the eyes of the Lilliputians to all objects proper for their
                            view: they see with great exactness, but at no great distance. And to
                            show the sharpness of their sight towards objects that are near, I have
                            been much pleased with observing a cook <ref target="a081"
                                corresp="n081">pulling a lark</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n081" target="a081"
                                >Plucking the lark’s feather. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, which was not so large as a common fly; and a
                            young girl threading an invisible needle with invisible silk. Their
                            tallest trees are about seven feet high; I mean some of those in the
                            great royal park, the tops whereof I could but just reach with my fist
                            clenched. The other vegetables are in the same proportion; but this I
                            leave to the reader's imagination. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I shall say but little at present of their learning, which for many ages
                            had <pb n="94" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p94.jpg"/> flourished in all
                            its branches among them; but their manner of writing is very peculiar,
                            being neither from the left to the right, like the Europeans; nor from
                            the right to the left, like the Arabians; nor from up to down, like the
                            Chinese; nor from down to up, like the <ref target="a082" corresp="n082"
                                >Cascagians</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n082" target="a082">(DRAFT-DC)Is this
                                just a fake one for continuity of the script line? Also perhaps to
                                add to that high academic charcter to casually mention this as
                                though its something his readers will know?</note>; but aslant from
                            one corner of the paper to the other, like ladies in England. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>They bury their dead with their heads directly downwards, because they
                            hold an opinion, that in eleven thousand moons they are all to rise
                            again, in which period the earth (which they conceive to be flat) will
                            turn upside down, and by this means they shall, at their resurrection,
                            be found ready standing on their feet. The learned among them confess
                            the absurdity of this doctrine, but the practice still continues, in
                            compliance to the vulgar. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>There are some laws and customs in this empire very peculiar; and if they
                                <pb n="95" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p95.jpg"/> were not so
                            directly contrary to those of my own dear country, I should be tempted
                            to say a little in their justification. It is only to be wished that
                            they were as well executed. The first I shall mention relates to
                            informers. All crimes against the state are punished here with the
                            utmost severity; but if the person accused makes his innocence plainly
                            to appear upon his trial, the accuser is immediately put to an <ref
                                target="a083" corresp="n083">ignominious</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n083"
                                target="a083">Involving shame or disgrace. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> death; and out of his goods or lands, the innocent
                            person is quadruply recompensed for the loss of his time, for the danger
                            he underwent, for the hardship of his imprisonment, and for all the <ref
                                target="a084" corresp="n084">charges he had been at</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n084" target="a084">Expenses incurred. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note> in making his defense. Or, if that fund be
                            deficient, it is largely supplied by the Crown. The Emperor does also
                            confer on him some public mark of his favor, and proclamation is made of
                            his innocence through the whole city. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>They look upon fraud as a greater crime than theft, and therefore seldom
                                <pb n="96" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p96.jpg"/> fail to punish it
                            with death; for they allege, that care and vigilance, with a very common
                            understanding, may preserve a man's goods from thieves, but honesty has
                            no fence against superior cunning; and since it is necessary that there
                            should be a perpetual intercourse of buying and selling, and dealing
                            upon credit, where fraud is permitted and connived at, or has no law to
                            punish it, the honest dealer is always undone, and the <ref
                                target="a085" corresp="n085">knave</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n085"
                                target="a085">A dishonest unprincipled man; a cunning unscrupulous
                                rogue; a villain. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> gets the
                            advantage. I remember when I was once interceding with the King for a
                            criminal who had wronged his master of a great sum of money, which he
                            had received by order, and ran away with; and happening to tell his
                            Majesty, by way of <ref target="a086" corresp="n086"
                                >extenuation</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n086" target="a086">The action of
                                representing something as slight; underrating. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note>, that it was only a breach of trust; the
                            Emperor thought it monstrous in me to offer, as a defense, the greatest
                            aggravation of the crime: and truly I had little to say in return,
                            farther than the common answer, that different nations had different
                            customs; for, I confess, I was heartily ashamed. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="97" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p97.jpg"/>


                        <p>Although we usually call reward and punishment the two hinges upon which
                            all government turns, yet I could never observe this maxim to be put in
                            practice by any nation except that of Lilliput. Whoever can there bring
                            sufficient proof that he has strictly observed the laws of his country
                            for seventy-three moons, has a claim to certain privileges, according to
                            his quality and condition of life, with a proportionable sum of money
                            out of a fund appropriated for that use: he likewise acquires the title
                            of Snilpall, or Legal, which is added to his name, but does not descend
                            to his posterity. And these people thought it a prodigious defect of
                            policy among us, when I told them that our laws were enforced only by
                            penalties without any mention of reward. It is upon this account that
                            the image of justice, in their courts of judicature, is formed with six
                            eyes, two before, as many behind, and on each side one, to signify
                            circum- <pb n="98" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p98.jpg"/> spection; with
                            a bag of gold open in her right hand, and a sword sheathed in her left,
                            to show she is more disposed to reward than to punish. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In choosing persons for all employments, they have more regard to good
                            morals than to great abilities; for, since government is necessary to
                            mankind, they believe-that the common size of human understandings is
                            fitted to some station or other, and that Providence never intended to
                            make the management of public affairs a mystery, to be comprehended only
                            by a few persons of sublime genius, of which there seldom are three born
                            in an age: but they suppose truth, justice, temperance, and the like, to
                            be in every man's power; the practice of which virtues, assisted by
                            experience and a good intention, would qualify any man for the service
                            of his country, except where a course of study is required. But they
                            thought the want of moral virtues was so far from being supplied by su-
                                <pb n="99" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p99.jpg"/> perior endowments
                            of the mind, that employments could never be put into such dangerous
                            hands as those of persons so qualified; and at least, that the mistakes
                            committed by ignorance in a virtuous disposition, would never be of such
                            fatal consequence to the public weal, as the <ref target="a087"
                                corresp="n087">practices</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n087" target="a087"
                                >Schemes, intrigues, maneuvers. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> of a man whose inclinations led him to be corrupt,
                            and had great abilities to manage, and multiply, and defend his
                            corruptions. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In like manner, the disbelief of a Divine Providence renders a man
                            incapable of holding any public station; for, since kings avow
                            themselves to be the deputies of Providence, the Lilliputians think
                            nothing can be more absurd than for a prince to employ such men as
                            disown the authority under which he acts. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In relating these and the following laws, I would only be understood to
                            mean the original institutions, and not the most scandalous corruptions
                            into <pb n="100" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p100.jpg"/> which these
                            people are fallen by the degenerate nature of man. For as to that
                            infamous practice of acquiring great employments by dancing on the
                            ropes, or badges of favor and distinction by leaping over sticks and
                            creeping under them, the reader is to observe, that they were first
                            introduced by the grandfather of the <ref target="t001" corresp="t001"
                                >Emperor now reigning</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="t001" target="t001">"James
                                I. in whose reign the distribution of honours and titles was carried
                                to a scandalous excess. He also created the order of baronets with
                                the object of swelling the treasury." <figure>
                                    <graphic width="300px" style="float:right"
                                        url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/JamesIEngland.jpg"
                                    />
                                </figure>
                            </note>, and grew to the present height by the gradual increase of party
                            and faction. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p> Ingratitude is among them a capital crime, as we read it to have been in
                            some other countries; for they reason thus, that whoever makes ill
                            returns to his benefactor, must needs be a common enemy to the rest of
                            mankind, from whom he has received no obligation, and therefore such a
                            man is not fit to live. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Their notions relating to the duties of parents and children differ
                            extremely from ours. For since the conjunction of male and female is
                            founded <pb n="101" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p101.jpg"/> upon the
                            great law of nature, in order to propagate and continue the species, the
                            Lilliputians will needs have it, that men and women are joined together
                            like other animals, by the motives of <ref target="a088" corresp="n088"
                                >concupiscence</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n088" target="a088">Eager or
                                vehement desire; the coveting of carnal things. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note>; and that their tenderness towards their
                            young proceeds from the like natural principle: for which reason they
                            will never allow, that a child is under any obligation to his father for
                            begetting him, or his mother for bringing him into the world; which,
                            considering the miseries of human life, was neither a benefit itself,
                            nor intended so by his parents, whose thoughts in their love-encounters
                            were otherwise employed. Upon these, and the like reasonings, their
                            opinion is, that parents are the last of all others to be trusted with
                            the education of their own children: and therefore they have in every
                            town public nurseries, where all parents, except cottagers and laborers,
                            are obliged to send their infants of both sexes to be reared and
                            educated when they come to the age of <pb n="102"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p102.jpg"/>
                            <ref target="a462" corresp="n462">twenty moons</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n462"
                                target="a462">Knowing that there is a full moon once every 29.5
                                days, twenty moons would be a little under one and a half years.
                                Source: Wikipedia</note>, at which time they are supposed to have
                            some rudiments of docility. These schools are of several kinds, suited
                            to different qualities, and to both sexes. They have certain professors
                            well skilled in preparing children for such a condition of life as
                            befits the rank of their parents, and their own capacities as well as
                            inclinations. I shall say something of the male nurseries, and then of
                            the female. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The nurseries for males of noble or eminent birth are provided with grave
                            and learned professors, and their several deputies. The clothes and food
                            of the children are plain and simple. They are bred up in the principles
                            of honor, justice, courage, modesty, <ref target="a089" corresp="n089"
                                >clemency</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n089" target="a089">Mildness or
                                gentleness of temper, as shown in the exercise of authority or
                                power; mercy, leniency. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,
                            religion, and love of their country; they are always employed in some
                            business, except in the times of eating and sleeping, which are very
                            short, and two hours for diversions, consisting of bodily exercises.
                            They are dressed by men <pb n="103"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p103.jpg"/> till four years of age, and
                            then are obliged to dress themselves, although their quality be ever so
                            great; and the women attendants, who are aged proportionably to ours at
                            fifty, perform only the most menial offices. They are never suffered to
                            converse with servants, but go together in small or greater numbers to
                            take their diversions, and always in the presence of a professor, or one
                            of his deputies; whereby they avoid those early bad impressions of folly
                            and vice to which our children are subject. Their parents are suffered
                            to see them only twice a year; the visit is to last but an hour. They
                            are allowed to kiss the child at meeting and parting; but a professor,
                            who always stands by on those occasions, will not suffer them to
                            whisper, or use any fondling expressions, or bring any presents of toys,
                            sweetmeats, and the like. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The pension from each family for the education and entertainment of a <pb
                                n="104" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p104.jpg"/> child, upon failure
                            of due payment, is levied by the Emperor's officers. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The nurseries for children of ordinary gentlemen, merchants, traders, and
                            handicrafts, are managed proportionably after the same manner; only
                            those designed for trades are put out apprentices at eleven years old,
                            whereas those of persons of quality continue in their exercises till
                            fifteen, which answers to one and twenty with us: but the confinement is
                            gradually lessened for the last three years. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In the female nurseries, the young girls of quality are educated much
                            like the males, only they are dressed by orderly servants of their own
                            sex; but always in the presence of a professor or deputy, till they come
                            to dress themselves, which is at five years old. And if it be found that
                            these nurses ever presume to entertain the girls with frightful or
                            foolish stories, or the common follies <pb n="105"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p105.jpg"/> practiced by chambermaids
                            among us, they are publicly whipped thrice about the city, imprisoned
                            for a year and banished for life to the most desolate part of the
                            country. Thus the young ladies there are as much ashamed of being
                            cowards and fools as the men, and despise all personal ornaments beyond
                            decency and cleanliness: neither did I perceive any difference in their
                            education, made by their difference of sex, only that the exercises of
                            the females were not altogether so robust; and that some rules were
                            given them relating to domestic life, and a smaller compass of learning
                            was enjoined them: for their maxim is, that among people of quality a
                            wife should be always a reasonable and agreeable companion, because she
                            cannot always be young. When the girls are twelve years old, which among
                            them is the marriageable age, their parents or guardians take them home,
                            with great expressions of gratitude to the professors, and seldom
                            without tears <pb n="106" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p106.jpg"/> of the
                            young lady and her companions. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In the nurseries of females of the meaner sort, the children are
                            instructed in all kinds of works proper for their sex, and their several
                            degrees: those intended for apprentices are dismissed at nine years old,
                            the rest are to thirteen. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The meaner families who have children at these nurseries, are obliged,
                            besides their annual pension, which is as low as possible, to return to
                            the steward of the nursery a small monthly share of their gettings, to
                            be a portion for the child; and therefore all parents are limited in
                            their expenses by the law. For the Lilliputians think nothing can be
                            more unjust, than for people, in subservience to their own appetites, to
                            bring children into the world and leave the burden of supporting them on
                            the public. As to persons of quality, they give security to appropriate
                            a <pb n="107" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p107.jpg"/> certain sum for
                            each child, suitable to their condition; and these funds are always
                            managed with good husbandry, and the most exact justice. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The cottagers and laborers keep their children at home, their business
                            being only to till and cultivate the earth, and therefore their
                            education is of little consequence to the public; but the old and
                            diseased among them are supported by hospitals: for begging is a trade
                            unknown in this kingdom. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>And here it may perhaps divert the curious reader to give some account of
                            my domestics, and my manner of living in this country, during a
                            residence of nine months and thirteen days. Having a head mechanically
                            turned, and being likewise forced by necessity, I had made for myself a
                            table and chair convenient enough, out of the largest trees in the royal
                            park. Two hundred seamstresses were employed to make me shirts, <pb
                                n="108" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p108.jpg"/> and linen for my bed
                            and table, all of the strongest and coarsest kind they could get; which,
                            however, they were forced to quilt together in several folds, for the
                            thickest was some degrees finer than lawn. Their linen is usually three
                            inches wide, and three feet make a piece. The seamstresses took my
                            measure as I lay on the ground, one standing at my neck, and another at
                            my mid-leg, with a strong cord extended, that each held by the end,
                            while the third measured the length of the cord with a rule an inch
                            long. Then they measured my right thumb, and desired no more; for by a
                            mathematical computation, that twice round the thumb is once round the
                            wrist, and so on to the neck and the waist, and by the help of my old
                            shirt, which I displayed on the ground before them for a pattern, they
                            fitted me exactly. Three hundred tailors were employed in the same
                            manner to make me clothes; but they had another contrivance for taking
                            my measure. I kneeled <pb n="109" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p109.jpg"
                            /> down, and they raised a ladder from the ground to my neck; upon this
                            ladder one of them mounted, and let fall a <ref target="a090"
                                corresp="n090">plumb-line</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n090" target="a090">A
                                line or cord with a weight at one end, for determining the vertical.
                                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> from my collar to the
                            floor, which just answered the length of my coat; but my waist and arms
                            I measured myself. When my clothes finished, which was done in my house
                            (for the largest of theirs would not have been able to hold them) they
                            looked like the patch-work made by the ladies in England, only that mine
                            were all of a color. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I had three hundred cooks to dress my victuals, in little convenient huts
                            built about my house, where they and their families lived, and prepared
                            me two dishes apiece. I took up twenty waiters in my hand, and placed
                            them on the table; a hundred more attended below on the ground, some
                            with dishes of meat, and some with barrels of wine, and other liquors,
                            slung on their shoulders; all which the waiters above drew up as I
                            wanted, in a very ingenious man- <pb n="110"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p110.jpg"/> ner, by certain cords, as we
                            draw the bucket up a well in Europe. A dish of their meat was a good
                            mouthful, and a barrel of their liquor a reasonable draught. Their
                            mutton yields to ours, but their beef is excellent. I have had a sirloin
                            so large, that I have been forced to make three bits of it; but this is
                            rare. My servants were astonished to see me eat it bones and all, as in
                            our country we do the leg of a lark. Their geese and turkeys I usually
                            ate at a mouthful, and I must confess they far exceed ours. Of their
                            smaller fowl I could take up twenty or thirty at the end of my knife. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>One day his Imperial Majesty, being informed of my way of living, desired
                            that himself and his Royal Consort, with the young Princes of the blood
                            of both sexes, might have the happiness (as he was pleased to call it)
                            of dining with me. They came accordingly, and I placed them upon chairs
                            of state on my table, just <pb n="111"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p111.jpg"/> over against me, with their
                            guards about them. Flimnap, the Lord High Treasurer, attended there
                            likewise with his <ref target="a092" corresp="n092">white
                                staff</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n092" target="a092">Symbol of the office of
                                Lord High Treasurer. Source: (need a source)</note>; and I observed
                            he often looked on me with a sour countenance, which I would not seem to
                            regard, but ate more than usual, in honor to my dear country, as well as
                            to fill the court with admiration. I have some private reasons to
                            believe, that this visit from his Majesty gave Flimnap an opportunity of
                            doing me ill offices to his master. That minister had always been my
                            secret enemy, though he outwardly caressed me more than was usual to the
                            moroseness of his nature. He represented to the Emperor the low
                            condition of his treasury; that he was forced to take up money at great
                            discount; that <ref target="a093" corresp="n093">exchequer</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n093" target="a093">A royal or national treasury. Source:
                                Oxford English Dictionary</note> bills would not circulate under
                            nine per cent below par; that in short I had cost his Majesty above a
                            million and a half of sprugs (their greatest gold coin, about the
                            bigness of a <ref target="a094" corresp="n094">spangle</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n094" target="a094">A small round thin piece of glittering
                                metal (usually brass) with a hole in the centre to pass a thread
                                through, used for the decoration of textile fabrics and other
                                materials of various sorts. Source: Oxford English
                            Dictionary</note>) and upon the whole, that it would be advisable in the
                                <pb n="112" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p112.jpg"/> Emperor to take
                            the first fair occasion of dismissing me. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I am here obliged to vindicate the reputation of an excellent lady, who
                            was an innocent sufferer upon my account. The Treasurer took a fancy to
                            be jealous of his wife, from the malice of some evil tongues, who
                            informed him that her Grace had taken a violent affection for my person;
                            and the court-scandal ran for some time, that she once came privately to
                            my lodging. This I solemnly declare to be a most infamous falsehood,
                            without any grounds, farther than that her Grace was pleased to treat me
                            with all innocent marks of freedom and friendship. I own she came often
                            to my house, but always publicly, nor ever without three more in the
                            coach, who were usually her sister and young daughter, and some
                            particular acquaintance; but this was common to many other ladies of the
                            court. And I still appeal to my servants round, whether <pb n="113"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p113.jpg"/> they at any time saw a coach
                            at my door without knowing what persons were in it. On those occasions,
                            when a servant had given me notice, my custom was to go immediately to
                            the door; and, after paying my respects, to take up the coach and two
                            horses very carefully in my hands (for if there were six horses, the
                            postillion always unharnessed four) and place them on a table, where I
                            had fixed a moveable rim quite round, of five inches high, to prevent
                            accidents. And I have often had four coaches and horses at once on my
                            table full of company, while I sat in my chair leaning my face towards
                            them; and when I was engaged with one set, the coachmen would gently
                            drive the others round my table. I have passed many an afternoon very
                            agreeably in these conversations. But I defy the Treasurer, or his two
                            informers (I will name them, and let them make their best of it)
                            Clustril and Drunlo, to prove that any person ever came to me <hi
                                rend="italics">incognito</hi>, except the secretary Rel- <pb n="114"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p114.jpg"/> dresal, who was sent by
                            express command of his Imperial Majesty, as I have before related. I
                            should not have dwelt so long upon this particular, if it had not been a
                            point wherein the reputation of a great lady is so nearly concerned, to
                            say nothing of my own; though I then had the honor to be a Nardac, which
                            the Treasurer himself is not; for all the world knows he is only a
                            Glumglum, a title inferior by one degree, as that of a Marquis is to a
                            Duke in England, although I allow he preceded me in right of his post.
                            These false informations, which I afterwards came to the knowledge of,
                            by an accident not proper to mention, made Flimnap the Treasurer show
                            his lady for some time an ill countenance, and me a worse; and although
                            he were at last undeceived and reconciled to her, yet I lost all credit
                            with him, and found my interest decline very fast with the Emperor
                            himself, who was indeed too much governed by that favorite. </p>


                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="7">
                        <pb n="115" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p115.jpg"/>
                        <head>CHAPTER VII</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">The Author, being informed of a design to accuse
                                    him of high-treason, maketh his escape to </hi> Blefuscu. <hi
                                    rend="italics">His reception there.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <p>Before I proceed to give an account of my leaving this kingdom, it may be
                            proper to inform the reader of a private intrigue which had been for two
                            months forming against me. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I had been hitherto all my life a stranger to courts, for which I was
                            unqualified by the meanness of my condition. I had indeed heard and read
                            enough of the dispositions of great princes and ministers; but never
                            expected to <pb n="116" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p116.jpg"/> have
                            found such terrible effects of them in so remote a country, governed, as
                            I thought, by very different maxims from those in Europe. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>When I was just preparing to pay my attendance on the Emperor of
                            Blefuscu, a considerable person at court (to whom I had been very
                            serviceable at a time when he lay under the highest displeasure of his
                            Imperial Majesty) came to my house very privately at night in a close
                            chair, and without sending his name, desired admittance. The chairmen
                            were dismissed; I put the chair, with his Lordship in it, into my
                            coat-pocket: and giving orders to a trusty servant to say I was
                            indisposed and gone to sleep, I fastened the door of my house, placed
                            the chair on the table, according to my usual custom, and sat down by
                            it. After the common salutations were over, observing his Lordship's
                            countenance full of concern, and enquiring into the reason, he desired I
                            would hear <pb n="117" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p117.jpg"/> him with
                            patience in a matter that highly concerned my honor and my life. His
                            speech was to the following effect, for I took notes of it as soon as he
                            left me. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>You are to know, said he, that several Committees of Council have been
                            lately called in the most private manner on your account; and it is but
                            two days since his Majesty came to a full resolution. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>You are very sensible that Skyresh Bolgolam (Galbet, or High Admiral) has
                            been your mortal enemy almost ever since your arrival. His original
                            reasons I know not, but his hatred is much increased since your great
                            success against Blefuscu, by which his glory as Admiral is obscured.
                            This Lord, in conjunction with Flimnap the High Treasurer, whose enmity
                            against you is notorious on account of his lady, <ref target="a078a"
                                corresp="n078a">Limtoc the General</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n078a"
                                target="a078a">"Swift may be using the phrase milles cottes -
                                thousand coats - then neatly removing the phonetically valueless
                                [les] and [tes], reversing the two words and obtaining Limtoc." -H.
                                D. Kelling. Source:
                                http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/4172994.pdf?seq=1</note>, Lalcon the
                            Chamberlain, and Balmuff the Grand Justiciary, have prepared ar- <pb
                                n="118" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p118.jpg"/> ticles of
                            impeachment against you, for treason, and other capital crimes. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This preface made me so impatient, being conscious of my own merits and
                            innocence, that I was going to interrupt; when he entreated me to be
                            silent, and thus proceeded. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Out of gratitude for the favors you have done me, I procured information
                            of the whole proceedings, and a copy of the articles, wherein I venture
                            my head for your service. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p><hi rend="italics">Articles of Impeachment against</hi> Quinbus
                            Flestrin<lb/> (<hi rend="italics">the </hi>Man-Mountain) </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>ARTICLE I<lb/> Whereas, by a statute made in the reign of his Imperial
                            Majesty Calin Deffar Plune, it is enacted, that whoever shall make water
                            within the precincts of the royal palace, should be liable to the pains
                            and penalties of high <pb n="119" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p119.jpg"
                            /> treason; notwithstanding, the said Quinbus Flestrin, in open breach
                            of the said law, under color of extinguishing the fire kindled in the
                            apartment of his Majesty's most dear Imperial Consort, did maliciously,
                            traitorously, and devilishly, by discharge of his urine, put out the
                            said fire kindled in the said apartment, lying and being within the
                            precincts of the said royal palace, against the statute in that case
                            provided, etc., against the duty, etc. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>ARTICLE II.<lb/> That the said Quinbus Flestrin having brought the
                            imperial fleet of Blefuscu into the royal port, and being afterwards
                            commanded by his Imperial Majesty to seize all the other ships of the
                            said empire of Blefuscu, and reduce that empire to a province, to be
                            governed by a Viceroy from hence, and to destroy and put to death not
                            only all the Big-Endian exiles, but likewise all the people of that
                            empire, who would not im- <pb n="120"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p120.jpg"/> mediately forsake the
                            Big-Endian heresy: He, the said Flestrin, like a false traitor against
                            his most Auspicious, Serene, Imperial Majesty, did petition to be
                            excused from the said service upon pretense of unwillingness to force
                            the consciences, or destroy the liberties and lives of an innocent
                            people. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>ARTICLE III.<lb/> That, whereas certain ambassadors from the court of
                            Blefuscu, to sue for peace in his Majesty's court: He, the said
                            Flestrin, did, like a false traitor, aid, abet, comfort, and divert the
                            said ambassadors, although he knew them to be servants to a Prince who
                            was lately an open enemy to his Imperial Majesty, and in open war
                            against his said Majesty. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>ARTICLE IV.<lb/> That the said Quinbus Flestrin, contrary to the duty of
                            a faithful subject, is now preparing to make a voyage to the court and
                            empire of Blefuscu, for which <pb n="121"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p121.jpg"/> he had received only verbal
                            license from his Imperial Majesty; and under color of the said license,
                            doth falsely and traitorously intend to take the said voyage, and hereby
                            to aid, comfort, and abet the Emperor of Blefuscu, so late an enemy, and
                            in open war with his Imperial Majesty aforesaid.<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>There are some other articles, but these are the most important, of which
                            I have read you an abstract. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In the several debates upon this impeachment, it must be confessed that
                            his Majesty gave many marks of his great lenity, often urging the
                            services you had done him, and endeavoring to extenuate your crimes. The
                            Treasurer and Admiral insisted that you should be put to the most
                            painful and ignominious death, by setting fire on your house at night,
                            and the General was to attend with twenty thousand men armed with
                            poisoned arrows to shoot you on the face and hands. <pb n="122"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p122.jpg"/> Some of your servants were
                            to have private orders to strew a <ref target="a067" corresp="n067"
                                >poisonous juice on your shirts</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n067"
                                target="a067">Reference to the “Shirt of Nessus," which was the
                                piece of clothing given to Hercules by his wife that poisoned and
                                ultimately killed him. Source:
                                http://www.getty.edu/art/collection/objects/105154/unknown-maker-hercules-poisoned-by-the-shirt-of-nessus-french-about-1413-1415/</note>,
                            which would soon make you tear your own flesh, and die in the utmost
                            torture. The General came into the same opinion, so that for a long time
                            there was a majority against you. But his Majesty resolving, if
                            possible, to spare your life, at last brought off the Chamberlain. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Upon this incident, Reldresal, principal Secretary for Private Affairs,
                            who always approved himself your true friend, was commanded by the
                            Emperor to deliver his opinion, which he accordingly did; and therein
                            justified the good thoughts you have of him. He allowed your crimes to
                            be great, but that still there was room for mercy, the most commendable
                            virtue in a prince, and for which his Majesty was so justly celebrated.
                            He said, the friendship between you and him was so well known to the
                            world, that perhaps the most honorable board <pb n="123"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p123.jpg"/> might think him partial:
                            however, in obedience to the command he had received, he would freely
                            offer his sentiments. That if his Majesty, in consideration of your
                            services, and pursuant to his own merciful disposition, would please to
                            spare your life, and only give order to <ref target="a068"
                                corresp="n068">put out both your eyes</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n068"
                                target="a068">(DRAFT-is this a good annotation? other than the eyes
                                things this doesn't seem to house much other connection to my
                                knowledge? Especially because this seems to be just the eyes where
                                as the bible verses listed include prison and working till death.
                                Omit or keep?) Possible Biblical allusion to the likewise fates of
                                Zedekiah (Jeremiah 52:11) or Samson (Judges 16:21) Source: (need a
                                source, or should it just be the bible)</note>, he humbly conceived
                            that by this expedient justice might in some measure be satisfied, and
                            all the world would applaud the lenity of the Emperor, as well as the
                            fair and generous proceedings of those who have the honor to be his
                            counsellors. That the loss of your eyes would be no impediment to your
                            bodily strength, by which you might still be useful to his Majesty. That
                            blindness is an addition to courage, by concealing dangers from us; that
                            the fear you had for your eyes was the greatest difficulty in bringing
                            over the enemy's fleet, and it would be sufficient for you to see by the
                            eyes of the ministers, since the greatest princes do no more. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="124" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p124.jpg"/>


                        <p>This proposal was received with the utmost disapprobation by the whole
                            board. <ref target="a069" corresp="n069">Bolgolam</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n069" target="a069">“The last name of Skyresh Bolgolam, the
                                Lilliputian admiral, seems quite clearly to contain the Italian or
                                Spanish gola-" throat" or " gluttony " and the French bol or Italian
                                bolo (or the root of Latin bolus) -bolus, pill, or mouthfull.
                                Bolgolam's gustatory prowess is not mentioned, to be sure, but his
                                name can imply more general connotations of greed..." -H.D. Kelling.
                                Source: http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/4172994.pdf?seq=1</note>,
                            the Admiral, could not preserve his temper, but rising up in fury said
                            he wondered how the Secretary dared presume to give his opinion for
                            preserving the life of a traitor: that the services you had performed,
                            were, by all true <ref target="a070" corresp="n070">reasons of
                                state</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n070" target="a070">A purely political
                                ground of action on the part of a ruler or government, esp. as
                                involving expediency or some departure from strict justice, honesty,
                                or open dealing. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, the great
                            aggravation of your crimes; that you, who were able to extinguish the
                            fire, by discharge of urine in her Majesty's apartment (which he
                            mentioned with horror), might at another time, raise an inundation by
                            the same means, to drown the whole palace; and the same strength which
                            enabled you to bring over the enemy's fleet, might serve, upon the first
                            discontent, to carry it back: that he had good reasons to think you were
                            a Big-Endian in your heart; and as treason begins in the heart, before
                            it appears in overt acts, so he accused you as a traitor on that
                            account, and therefore insisted you should be put to death. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="125" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p125.jpg"/>


                        <p>The Treasurer was of the same opinion; he showed to what straits his
                            Majesty's revenue was reduced by the charge of maintaining you, which
                            would soon grow insupportable: that the Secretary's expedient of putting
                            out your eyes was so far from being a remedy against this evil, it would
                            probably increase it, as it is manifest from the common practice of
                            blinding some kind of fowl, after which they fed the faster, and grew
                            sooner fat: that his sacred Majesty and the Council, who are your
                            judges, were in their own consciences fully convinced of your guilt,
                            which was a sufficient argument to condemn you to death, without the
                            formal proofs required by the strict letter of the law. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>But his Imperial Majesty, fully determined against capital punishment,
                            was graciously pleased to say, that since the Council thought the loss
                            of your eyes too easy a censure, some other may be <pb n="126"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p126.jpg"/> inflicted hereafter. And
                            your friend the Secretary humbly desiring to be heard again, in answer
                            to what the Treasurer had objected concerning the great charge his
                            Majesty was at in maintaining you, said that his Excellency, who had the
                            sole disposal of the Emperor's revenue, might easily provide against
                            that evil, by gradually lessening your establishment; by which, for want
                            of sufficient food, you would grow weak and faint, and lose your
                            appetite, and consequently decay and consume in a few months; neither
                            would the stench of your carcass be then so dangerous, when it should
                            become more than half diminished; and immediately upon your death, five
                            or six thousand of his Majesty's subjects might, in two or three days,
                            cut your flesh from your bones, take it away by cartloads, and bury it
                            in distant parts to prevent infection, leaving the skeleton as a
                            monument of admiration to posterity. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="127" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p127.jpg"/>

                        <p>Thus by the great friendship of the Secretary, the whole affair was
                            compromised. It was strictly enjoined, that the project of starving you
                            by degrees should be kept a secret, but the sentence of putting out your
                            eyes was entered on the books; none dissenting except Bolgolam the
                            Admiral, who, being a creature of the Empress, was perpetually
                            instigated by her Majesty to insist upon your death, she having borne
                            perpetual malice against you, on account of that infamous and illegal
                            method you took to extinguish the fire in her apartment. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In three days your friend the Secretary will be directed to come to your
                            house, and read before you the articles of impeachment; and then to
                            signify the great lenity and favor of his Majesty and Council, whereby
                            you are only condemned to the loss of your eyes, which his Majesty does
                            not question you will gratefully and humbly submit to; and <pb n="128"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p128.jpg"/> twenty of his Majesty's
                            surgeons will attend, in order to see the operation well performed, by
                            discharging very sharp-pointed arrows into the balls of your eyes, as
                            you lie on the ground. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I leave to your prudence what measures you will take; and to avoid
                            suspicion, I must immediately return in as private a manner as I came. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>His Lordship did so, and I remained alone, under many doubts and
                            perplexities of mind. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>It was a custom introduced by this prince and his ministry (very
                            different, as I have been assured, from the practices of former times)
                            that after the court had decreed any cruel execution, either to gratify
                            the monarch's resentment, or the malice of a favorite, the Emperor
                            always made a speech to his whole Council, expressing his great lenity
                            and tenderness, as qualities known and confessed by all the <pb n="129"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p129.jpg"/> world. This speech was
                            immediately published through the kingdom; nor did anything terrify the
                            people so much as those <ref target="a071" corresp="n071">encomiums on
                                his Majesty's mercy</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n071" target="a071">
                                Allusions to King George I's speeches about his treatment of
                                Jacobite rebels, where he talks about the “numerous instances of
                                mercy which [he has] shown." Source: Swift's Politics: A Study in
                                Disaffection by Ian Higgins</note>; because it was observed, that
                            the more these praises were enlarged and insisted on, the more inhuman
                            was the punishment, and the sufferer more innocent. And as to myself, I
                            must confess, having never been designed for a courtier either by my
                            birth or education, I was so ill a judge of things, that I could not
                            discover the lenity and favor of this sentence, but conceived it
                            (perhaps erroneously) rather to be rigorous than gentle. I sometimes
                            thought of standing my trial, for although I could not deny the facts
                            alleged in the several articles, yet I hoped they would admit of some
                            extenuations. But having in my life perused many state trials, which I
                            ever observed to terminate as the judges thought fit to direct, I dared
                            not rely on so dangerous a decision, in so critical a juncture, and
                            against such powerful enemies. Once I <pb n="130"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p130.jpg"/> was strongly bent upon
                            resistance, for while I had liberty, the whole strength of that empire
                            could hardly subdue me, and I might easily with stones pelt the
                            metropolis to pieces; but I soon rejected that project with horror, by
                            remembering the oath I had made to the Emperor, the favors I received
                            from him, and the high title of Nardac he conferred upon me. Neither had
                            I so soon learned the gratitude of courtiers, to persuade myself that
                            his Majesty's present severities quitted me of all past obligations. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>At last I fixed upon a resolution, for which it is probable I may incur
                            some censure, and not unjustly; for I confess I owe the preserving of my
                            eyes, and consequently my liberty, to my own great rashness and want of
                            experience: because if I had then known the nature of princes and
                            ministers, which I have since observed in many other courts, and their
                            methods of treating criminals less obnoxious than myself, I should with
                            great <pb n="131" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p131.jpg"/> alacrity and
                            readiness have submitted to so easy a punishment. But hurried on by the
                            precipitancy of youth, and having his Imperial Majesty's license to pay
                            my attendance upon the Emperor of Blefuscu, I took this opportunity,
                            before the three days were elapsed, to send a letter to my friend the
                            Secretary, signifying my resolution of setting out that morning Blefuscu
                            pursuant to the leave I had got; and without waiting for an answer, I
                            went to that side of the island where our fleet lay. I seized a large
                            man of war, tied a cable to the prow, and, lifting up the anchors, I
                            stripped myself, put my clothes (together with my coverlet, which I
                            brought under my arm) into the vessel, and drawing it after me between
                            wading and swimming, arrived at the royal port of Blefuscu, where the
                            people had long expected me; they lent me two guides to direct me to the
                            capital city, which is of the same name. I held them in my hands till I
                            came within two hundred yards of the gate, and desired them to <pb
                                n="132" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p132.jpg"/> signify my arrival
                            to one of the secretaries, and let him know, I there waited his
                            Majesty's commands. I had an answer in about an hour, that his Majesty,
                            attended by the Royal Family, and great officers of the court, was
                            coming out to receive me. I advanced a hundred yards. The Emperor and
                            his train alighted from their horses, the Empress and ladies from their
                            coaches, and I did not perceive they were in any fright or concern. I
                            lay on the ground to kiss his Majesty's and the Empress's hand. I told
                            his Majesty that I had come according to my promise, and with the
                            license of the Emperor, my master, to have the honor of seeing so mighty
                            a monarch, and to offer him any service in my power, consistent with my
                            duty to my own prince; not mentioning a word of my disgrace, because I
                            had hitherto no regular information of it, and might suppose myself
                            wholly ignorant of any such design; neither could I reasonably conceive
                            that the Emperor would discover the secret <pb n="133"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p133.jpg"/> while I was out of his
                            power: wherein, however, it soon appeared I was deceived. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I shall not trouble the reader with the particular account of my
                            reception at this court, which was suitable to the generosity of so
                            great a prince; nor of the difficulties I was in for want of a house and
                            bed, being forced to lie on the ground, wrapped up in my coverlet. </p>



                    </div>

                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <div type="chapter" n="8">

                        <pb n="134" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p134.jpg"/>

                        <head>CHAPTER VIII</head>
                        <lb/>
                        <argument>
                            <head/>
                            <p><hi rend="italics">The Author, by a lucky accident, finds means to
                                    leave</hi> Blefuscu; <hi rend="italics">and, after some
                                    difficulties, returns safe to his native country.</hi></p>
                        </argument>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <p>Three days after my arrival, walking out of curiosity to the northeast
                            coast of the island, I observed, about half a league off, in the sea,
                            something that looked like a boat overturned. I pulled off my shoes and
                            stockings, and wading two or three hundred yards, I found the object to
                            approach nearer by force of the tide; and then plainly saw it to be a
                            real boat, which I supposed might, by some tempest, have been driven
                            from a ship; whereupon I returned immediately towards the city, and <pb
                                n="135" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p135.jpg"/> desired his Imperial
                            Majesty to lend me twenty of the tallest vessels he had left after the
                            loss of his fleet, and three thousand seamen under the command of his
                            Vice-Admiral. This fleet sailed round, while I went back the shortest
                            way to the coast where I first discovered the boat; I found the tide had
                            driven it still nearer. The seamen were all provided with cordage, which
                            I had beforehand twisted to a sufficient strength. When the ships came
                            up, I stripped myself, and waded till I came within a hundred yards of
                            the boat, after which I was forced to swim till I got up to it. The
                            seamen threw me the end of the cord, which I fastened to a hole in the
                            forepart of the boat, and the other end to a man of war; but I found all
                            my labor to little purpose; for being out of my depth, I was not able to
                            work. In this necessity, I was forced to swim behind, and push the boat
                            forwards as often as I could, with one of my hands; and the tide
                            favoring me, I advanced so far, that I could just hold up my chin and
                            feel the <pb n="136" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p136.jpg"/> ground. I
                            rested two or three minutes, and then gave the boat another shove, and
                            so on till the sea was no higher than my arm-pits; and now the most
                            laborious part being over, I took out my other cables, which were stowed
                            in one of the ships, and fastening them first to the boat, and then to
                            nine of the vessels which attended me; the wind being favorable, the
                            seamen towed, and I shoved till we arrived within forty yards of the
                            shore; and waiting till the tide was out, I got dry to the boat, and by
                            the assistance of two thousand men, with ropes and engines, I made a
                            shift to turn it on its bottom, and found it was but little damaged. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I shall not trouble the reader with the difficulties I was under by the
                            help of certain paddles, which cost me ten days making, to get my boat
                            to the royal port of Blefuscu, where a mighty concourse of people
                            appeared upon my arrival, full of wonder at the sight of so <pb n="137"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p137.jpg"/> prodigious a vessel. I told
                            the Emperor that my good fortune had thrown this boat in my way, to
                            carry me to some place from whence I might return into my native
                            country, and begged his Majesty's orders for getting materials to fit it
                            up, together with his license to depart; which, after some kind
                            expostulations, he was pleased to grant. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I did very much wonder, in all this time, not to have heard of any
                            express relating to me from our Emperor to the court of Blefuscu. But I
                            was afterwards given privately to understand, that his Imperial Majesty,
                            never imagining I had the least notice of his designs, believed I was
                            only gone to Blefuscu in performance of my promise, according to the
                            license he had given me, which was well known at our court, and would
                            return in a few days when that ceremony was ended. But he was at last in
                            pain at my long absence; and after consulting with the Treasurer, and
                            the rest of that <pb n="138" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p138.jpg"/>
                            cabal, a person of quality was dispatched with the copy of the articles
                            against me. This envoy had instructions to represent to the monarch of
                            Blefuscu the great lenity of his master, who was content to punish me no
                            farther than with the loss of my eyes; that I had fled from justice, and
                            if I did not return in two hours, I should be deprived of my title of
                            Nardac, and declared a traitor. The envoy further added, that in order
                            to maintain the peace and amity between both empires, his master
                            expected, that his brother of Blefuscu would give orders to have me sent
                            back to Lilliput, bound hand and foot, to be punished as a traitor. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>The Emperor of Blefuscu having taken three days to consult, returned an
                            answer consisting of many civilities and excuses. He said, that as for
                            sending me bound, his brother knew it was impossible; that although I
                            had deprived him of his fleet, yet he owed great obligations to me for
                            many good offices I <pb n="139" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p139.jpg"/>
                            had done him in making the peace. That however both their Majesties
                            would soon be made easy; for I had found a prodigious vessel on the
                            shore, able to carry me on the sea, which he had given order to fit up
                            with my own assistance and direction; and he hoped in a few weeks both
                            empires would be freed from so insupportable an incumbrance. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>With this answer the envoy returned to Lilliput, and the monarch of
                            Blefuscu related to me all that had past, offering me at the same time
                            (but under the strictest confidence) his gracious protection, if I would
                            continue in his service; wherein although I believed him sincere, yet I
                            resolved never more to put any confidence in princes or ministers, where
                            I could possibly avoid it; and therefore, with all due acknowledgements
                            for his favorable intentions, I humbly begged to be excused. I told him
                            that since fortune, whether good or evil, had thrown a vessel in my way,
                            I was re- <pb n="140" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p140.jpg"/> solved to
                            venture myself in the ocean, rather than be an occasion of difference
                            between two such mighty monarchs. Neither did I find the Emperor at all
                            displeased; and I discovered by a certain accident, that he was very
                            glad of my resolution, and so were most of his ministers. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <p>These considerations moved me to hasten my departure somewhat sooner than
                            I intended; to which the court, impatient to have me gone, very readily
                            contributed. Five hundred workmen were employed to make two sails to my
                            boat, according to my directions, by quilting thirteen fold of their
                            strongest linen together. I was at the pains of making ropes and cables,
                            by twisting ten, twenty or thirty of the thickest and strongest of
                            theirs. A great stone that I happened to find, after a long search, by
                            the sea-shore, served me for an anchor. I had the <ref target="a072"
                                corresp="n072">tallow</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n072" target="a072">The
                                fat, adipose tissue, of an animal. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note> of three hundred cows for greasing my boat, and
                            other uses. <pb n="141" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p141.jpg"/> I was at
                            incredible pains in cutting down some of the largest timber-trees for
                            oars and masts, wherein I was, however, much assisted by his Majesty's
                            ship carpenters, who helped me in smoothing them, after I had done the
                            rough work. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>In about a month, when all was prepared, I sent to receive his Majesty's
                            commands, and to take my leave. The Emperor and Royal Family came out of
                            the palace; I lay down on my face to kiss his hand, which he very
                            graciously gave me: so did the Empress and young Princes of the blood.
                            His Majesty presented me with fifty purses of two hundred sprugs apiece,
                            together with his picture at full length, which I put immediately into
                            one of my gloves, to keep it from being hurt. The ceremonies at my
                            departure were too many to trouble the reader with at this time. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I stored the boat with the carcases of a hundred oxen, and three hundred
                                <pb n="142" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p142.jpg"/> sheep, with
                            bread and drink proportionable, and as much meat ready dressed as four
                            hundred cooks could provide. I took with me six cows and two bulls
                            alive, with as many ewes and rams, intending to carry them into my own
                            country, and propagate the breed. And to feed them on board, I had a
                            good bundle of hay, and a bag of corn. I would gladly have taken a dozen
                            of the natives, but this was a thing the Emperor would by no means
                            permit; and besides a diligent search into my pockets, his Majesty
                            engaged my honor not to carry away any of his subjects, although with
                            their own consent and desire. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>Having thus prepared all things as well as I was able, I set sail on the
                            twenty-fourth day of September, 1701, at six in the morning; and when I
                            had gone about four leagues to the northward, the wind being at
                            southeast, at six in the evening I descried a small island about half a
                            league to the northwest. I ad- <pb n="143"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p143.jpg"/> vanced forward, and cast
                            anchor on the leeside of the island, which seemed to be uninhabited. I
                            then took some refreshment, and went to my rest. I slept well, and I
                            conjecture at least six hours, for I found the day broke in two hours
                            after I awaked. It was a clear night. I ate my breakfast before the sun
                            was up; and heaving anchor, the wind being favorable, I steered the same
                            course that I had done the day before, wherein I was directed by my
                            pocket compass. My intention was to reach, if possible, one of those
                            islands, which I had reason to believe lay to the northeast of Van
                            Diemen's Land. I discovered nothing all that day; but upon the next,
                            about three in the afternoon, when I had by my computation made
                            twenty-four leagues from Blefuscu, I descried a sail steering to the
                            southeast; my course was due east. I hailed her, but could get no
                            answer; yet I found I gained upon her, for the wind slackened. I made
                            all the sail I could, and in half an hour she spied me, then <pb n="144"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p144.jpg"/> hung out her <ref
                                target="a073" corresp="n073">ancient</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n073"
                                target="a073">An ensign, standard, or flag. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, and discharged a gun. It is not easy to express
                            the joy I was in upon the unexpected hope of once more seeing my beloved
                            country, and the dear pledges I had left in it. The ship slackened her
                            sails, and I came up with her between five and six in the evening,
                            September 26; but my heart leaped within me to see her English colors. I
                            put my cows and sheep into my coat pockets, and got on board with all my
                            little cargo of provisions. The vessel was an English merchantman,
                            returning from Japan by the North and South Seas; the Captain, Mr. John
                            Biddle of Deptford, a very civil man, and an excellent sailor. We were
                            now in the latitude of 30 degrees south; there were about fifty men in
                            the ship; and here I met an old comrade of mine, one Peter Williams, who
                            gave me a good character to the Captain. This gentleman treated me with
                            kindness, and desired I would let know what place I came from last, and
                            whither I was bound; <pb n="145" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p145.jpg"/>
                            which I did in few words, but he thought I was raving, and that the
                            dangers I underwent had disturbed my head; whereupon I took my black
                            cattle and sheep out of my pocket, which, after great astonishment,
                            clearly convinced him of my veracity. I then showed him the gold given
                            me by the Emperor of Blefuscu, together with his Majesty's picture at
                            full length, and some other rarities of that country. I gave him two
                            purses of two hundred sprugs each, and promised, when we arrived in
                            England, to make him a present of a cow and a sheep big with young. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>I shall not trouble the reader with a particular account of this voyage,
                            which was very prosperous for the most part. We arrived in <ref
                                target="a074" corresp="n074">the Downs</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n074"
                                target="a074">The part of the sea within the Goodwin Sands, off the
                                east coast of Kent, a famous rendezvous for ships. (It lies opposite
                                to the eastern termination of the North Downs.)Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note> on the 13th of April, 1702. I had only one
                            misfortune, that the rats on board carried away one of my sheep; I found
                            her bones in a hole, picked clean from the <pb n="146"
                                facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p146.jpg"/> flesh. The rest of my cattle
                            I got safe on shore, and set them grazing in a bowling-green at
                            Greenwich, where the fineness of the grass made them feed very heartily,
                            though I had always feared the contrary: neither could I possibly have
                            preserved them in so long a voyage, if the Captain had not allowed me
                            some of his best biscuit, which, rubbed to powder, and mingled with
                            water, was their constant food. The short time I continued in England, I
                            made considerable profit by showing my cattle to many persons of
                            quality, and others: and before I began my second voyage, I sold them
                            for six hundred pounds. Since my last return, I find the breed is
                            considerably increased, especially the sheep; which I hope will prove
                            much to the advantage of the woollen manufacture, by the <ref
                                target="a075" corresp="n075">fineness of the fleeces</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n075" target="a075">Swift actually blamed England for
                                encroaching upon Ireland's wool production, as he claims they
                                convinced Ireland to only produce raw wool instead of turning the
                                wool into valuable cloth for exportation. Source:
                                https://muse.jhu.edu/article/537310/summary</note>. </p>
                        <lb/>
                        <lb/>

                        <pb n="147" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p147.jpg"/>


                        <p>I stayed but two months with my wife and family; for my insatiable desire
                            of seeing foreign countries would suffer me to continue no longer. I
                            left fifteen hundred pounds with my wife, and fixed her in a good house
                            at Redriff. My remaining stock I carried with me, part in money, and
                            part in goods, in hopes to improve my fortunes. My eldest uncle John had
                            left me an estate in land, near Epping, of about thirty pounds a year;
                            and I had a long lease of the Black Bull in Fetter Lane, which yielded
                            me as much more; so that I was not in any danger of <ref target="a076"
                                corresp="n076">leaving my family upon the parish</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff"
                                xml:id="n076" target="a076">The parish at this time, acting as the
                                basic unit of local government, collected funds that were dispersed
                                to the poor as needed. Source:
                                https://eh.net/encyclopedia/english-poor-laws/</note>. My son
                            Johnny, named so after his uncle, was at the Grammar School, and a <ref
                                target="a077" corresp="n077">towardly</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n077"
                                target="a077">Promising, ‘hopeful’, forward; apt to learn, docile:
                                chiefly of young persons or their dispositions. Source: Oxford
                                English Dictionary</note> child. My daughter Betty (who is now well
                            married, and has children) was then at her needlework. I took leave of
                            my wife, and boy and girl, with tears on both sides, and went <pb
                                n="148" facs="pageImages/Gulliver-1-p148.jpg"/> on board the
                            Adventure, a merchantship of three hundred tons, bound for <ref
                                target="a078" corresp="n078">Surat</ref><note resp="editors.xml#UVAstudstaff" xml:id="n078"
                                target="a078">A city in Gujarat, India. Source: Oxford English
                                Dictionary</note>, Captain John Nicholas of Liverpool, Commander.
                            But my account of this voyage must be referred to the second part of my
                            Travels. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
