<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hay-fan">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Fantomina; or, Love in a Maze</title>
            <author>
               <persName xml:id="xxx" type="lccn" key="n79008228">Haywood, Eliza Fowler</persName>
            </author>
            <editor xml:id="TH"><persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">Howe, Tonya</persName>                
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name xml:id="MUstudstaff">Students and Staff of Marymount University</name>
               <name xml:id="AF">Freeland, Ally</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor></sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Marymount University Department of Literature and Languages</addrLine>
               <addrLine>2807 N. Glebe Road</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Arlington, VA </addrLine>
               <addrLine>22207</addrLine>
               <addrLine>thowe@marymount.edu</addrLine>
               <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>"Fantomina; or, Love in a Maze"</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName type="lccn" key="n79008228">Haywood, Eliza Fowler</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>Secret Histories, Novels, and Poems</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed for Dan Browne, jun. at the Black Swan without
                        Temple-Bar</publisher>
                     <publisher>S. Chapman at the Angel in Pallmall.</publisher>
                     <date when="1725">1725</date>
                     <note source="ESTC">Each section has a separate titlepage. The titlepage of the
                        first volume only is in red and black. The third volume was printed by
                        Samuel Aris on the evidence of the ornaments.</note>
                     <note>Page images are drawn from the second edition in ECCO.</note>
                     <note>For more information about this item, see the ESTC entry at 
                        <ref target="http://estc.bl.uk/T66936">http://estc.bl.uk/T66936</ref>.
                     </note>
                  </imprint>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>University of Pennsylvania, Celebration of Women Writers</publisher>
                     <date>n.d.</date>
                     <note>Text drawn from <ref target="http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/haywood/fantomina/fantomina.html">http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/haywood/fantomina/fantomina.html</ref> and checked against the second
                        edition text via ECCO.</note>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>4v.,plate ; 12°</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">III</biblScope>
                  <biblScope>pp 256-291</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <creation>1724</creation>
        <textDesc n="novella">
           <channel mode="w">print</channel>
           <constitution type="single"/>
           <derivation type="original"/>
           <domain></domain>
           <factuality type="fiction"/>
           <interaction></interaction>
           <preparedness type="prepared"/>
           <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
           <purpose type="inform" degree="medium"/>
        </textDesc>
        <settingDesc>
           <setting>
              <name>London, England</name>
              <name>Bath, England</name>
              <time>Early 18th Century</time>
           </setting>
        </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
               sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
               the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
               and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
               </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                  indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lccn">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-10-02" who="TH">First pass XML file</change>
         <change when="2019-01-02" who="TH">Added note placeholders</change>
         <change when="2019-01-05" who="TH">Finished notes; updated teiHeader</change>
         <change when="2019-01-07" who="TH">Added profileDesc to teiHeader</change>
         <change when="2019-01-08" who="TH">For distribution purposes, deleted @facs page images</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[TP]" facs="images/HF-256.jpg"/>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart>FANTOMINA:<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>OR,<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>LOVE in a Maze.<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>BEING A<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>Secret History<ref target="a001" corresp="n001"/><note xml:id="n001"
               target="a001" type="editorial" resp="TH">While there are many critical understandings of the secret history in literature, <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=h3iJDgAAQBAJ">as the essays in <hi rend="italic">The Secret History in Literature: 1660-1820</hi> (2017)</ref>, the genre usually offers a glimpse into the secret lives of public individuals. In the amatory tradition of <hi rend="italic">Fantomina</hi>, this "private" side is typically filled with sexual or political intrigue.</note><lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>OF AN<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>AMOUR<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>Between Two<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>PERSONS OF CONDITION.<lb/></titlePart>
            <titlePart>By Mrs. ELIZA HAYWOOD.<ref target="a002" corresp="n002"/><note xml:id="n002"
                  target="a002" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/25/Eliza-haywood.jpg"
                  />Eliza Haywood (c.1693-1756) was a prolific author, actor, and publisher of the
                  early- to mid-eighteenth century. She is most famous, today, for her novels and
                  novellas, among which <hi rend="italic">Fantomina</hi>is numbered. The image
                  included here, <ref
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Eliza-haywood.jpg">via
                     Wikimedia Commons</ref>, is an engraved frontispiece portrait by George Vertue.
                  Haywood wrote in a number of different genres, including amatory fiction, domestic
                  fiction, and essay.</note><lb/></titlePart>
            <epigraph>
               <quote>
                  <lg>
                     <l><hi rend="italic">In Love the Victors from the Vanquish'd fly</hi>.</l>
                     <l><hi rend="italic">They fly that wound, and they pursue that dye.</hi></l>
                  </lg></quote>
               <bibl><persName>WALLER.</persName><ref target="a003" corresp="n003"/><note
                     xml:id="n003" target="a003" type="editorial" resp="TH">This epigraph is
                     composed of the last couplet from <ref
                        target="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eebo/A67331.0001.001/1:2.71?rgn=div2;vid=62068;view=fulltext"
                        >"To A. H: Of the Different Successe of Their Loves," a poem by Edmund
                        Waller (1606-1687)</ref>. Waller's poem, published in 1645, takes a
                     Petrarchan perspective of the relationship between the male lover and the
                     female beloved. This couplet was oft-quoted during the period, and features in
                     George Etheredge's Restoration comedy <hi rend="italic">Man of Mode</hi>,
                     where it is spoken by the protagonist Dorimant. Read more about Waller at <ref
                        target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Edmund-Waller"><hi
                           rend="italics">Encyclopaedia Britannica</hi></ref>.</note></bibl>
               <lb/>
            </epigraph>
            <docImprint><pubPlace><placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName></pubPlace>:<lb/>
               <publisher>Printed for <persName>D. BROWNE jun</persName>. at the
                     <placeName>Black-Swan<lb/> without Temple-Bar</placeName>, and <persName>S.
                     CHAPMAN</persName>, <placeName>at<lb/> the Angel in
                  Pallmall</placeName>.</publisher><ref target="a004" corresp="n004"/><note
                  xml:id="n004" target="a004" type="editorial" resp="TH">Note about publisher</note>
               <date>M.DCC.XXV.</date><lb/></docImprint>



         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb n="[257]" facs="images/HF-257.jpg"/>
            <head>FANTOMINA:<lb/> OR,<lb/> LOVE in a Maze.<lb/></head>
            <p> A YOUNG Lady of distinguished Birth, Beauty, Wit, and Spirit, happened to be in a
                  Box<ref target="a005" corresp="n005"/><note xml:id="n005" target="a005"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="http://www.vam.ac.uk/__data/assets/image/0008/183473/2006ac5629_the_rio_during_artaxerxes.jpg"
                  />Playhouses during the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries in England organized
                  seating according to price and social status. Boxes were the most expensive of
                  seating areas, and could hold several people in style. The image included here,
                  from the Victoria and Albert Museum, depicts a famous riot at Covent Garden
                  theater during a performance of the opera <hi rend="italic">Artaxerxesto</hi> in
                  1763. For more information about the development of theater in the eighteenth
                  century, see <ref
                     target="https://www.bl.uk/restoration-18th-century-literature/articles/18th-century-british-theatre"
                     >Andrew Dickson's introduction at the British Library</ref>.</note> one Night
               at the Playhouse; where, though there were a great Number of celebrated Toasts<ref
                  target="a006" corresp="n006"/><note xml:id="n006" target="a006" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">According to the OED, a "toast" is a "[a] lady who is named as the
                  person to whom a company is requested to drink; often one who is the reigning
                  belle of the season" (n2.1).</note>, she perceived several Gentlemen extremely
               pleased themselves with entertaining a Woman who sat in a Corner of the Pit<ref
                  target="a007" corresp="n007"/><note xml:id="n007" target="a007" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">The "pit" was a mixed-sex seating area in the eighteenth-century,
                  notable for its energy and activity. According to <hi rend="italic">The Oxford
                     Companion to Theatre and Performance</hi>, the "pit occupied the floor of the
                  theatre at a lower level than the stage and, unlike the standing pit of earlier
                  public theatres, contained rows of backless benches set on a raked floor. Seats in
                  the pit were half the price of a seat in the box and attracted a mixed audience of
                  men and women. The activity of the audience in the pit and the behaviour of the
                  occupants of the boxes, especially with the King present, were part of the
                  theatregoing spectacle." Prostitutes, wits, and rakes frequented the pit and the
                  middle galleries. For more information, see Douglas Canfield's introduction to <hi
                     rend="italics">The Broadview Anthology of Restoration and Early
                     Eighteenth-Century Drama</hi> (vxiii).</note>, and, by her Air and Manner of
               receiving them, might easily be known to be one of those who come there for no other
               Purpose, than to create Acquaintance with as many as seem desirous of it. She could
               not help testifying her Contempt of Men, who, regardless either of the Play, or
               Circle, threw away their Time in such a Manner, to some Ladies that sat by her: But
               they, either less surprised by being more accustomed to such Sights, than she who had
               been bred for the most Part in the Country, or not of a Disposition to consider any
               Thing very deeply, took but little Notice of it. She still thought of it, however;
               and the longer she reflected on it, the greater was her Wonder, that Men, some of
               whom she knew were accounted to have Wit, should have Tastes so <pb n="258"
                  facs="images/HF-258.jpg"/> very Depraved. – This excited a Curiosity in her to
               know in what Manner these Creatures were address'd:– She was young, a Stranger to the
               World, and consequently to the Dangers of it; and having no Body in Town, at that
               Time, to whom she was oblig'd to be accountable for her Actions, did in every Thing
               as her Inclinations or Humours render'd most agreeable to her: Therefore thought it
               not in the least a Fault to put in practice a little Whim which came immediately into
               her Head, to dress herself as near as she could in the Fashion of those Women who
               make sale of their Favours, and set herself in the Way of being accosted as such a
               one, having at that Time no other Aim, than the Gratification of an innocent
               Curiosity.— She had no sooner design'd this Frolick, than she put it in Execution;
               and muffling her Hoods<ref target="a008" corresp="n008"/><note xml:id="n008"
                  target="a008" type="editorial" resp="TH">Throughout the seventeenth and early
                  eighteenth centuries, <ref
                     target="https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/90514?img=1">hoods and
                     hooded cloaks</ref> were both practical and fashionable garments for women. In
                  the winter, hoods and masks protected the body from icy air, and they generally
                  allowed women more freedom to move un-seen throughout the city, as described in
                     <ref
                     target="https://www.historyextra.com/period/stuart/dressing-to-impress-in-the-17th-century/"
                     >this article from the BBC's <hi rend="italic">History
                  Magazine</hi></ref>.</note> over her Face, went the next Night into the
                  Gallery-Box<ref target="a009" corresp="n009"/><note xml:id="n009" target="a009"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">The gallery-box or middle gallery is a seating area in
                  cost between pit and box seats. Servants often sat in the inexpensive upper
                  gallery seats. When Fantomina goes again tho the playhouse on her "frolick," she
                  sits in the gallery areas that signify her sexual availability. Often, sex workers
                  found partners and keepers at the playhouse, earning the theater a reputation for
                  sexual display.</note>, and practising as much as she had observ'd, at that
               Distance, the Behaviour of that Woman, was not long before she found her Disguise had
               answer'd the Ends she wore it for: – A Crowd of Purchasers of all Degrees and
               Capacities were in a Moment gather'd about her, each endeavouring to out-bid the
               other, in offering her a Price for her Embraces. – She listen'd to 'em all, and was
               not a little diverted in her Mind at the Disappointment she shou'd give to so many,
               each of which thought himself secure of gaining her. – She was told by 'em all, that
               she was the most lovely Woman in the World; and some <said>cry'd, Gad, she is mighty
                  like my fine Lady Such-a-one</said>, – naming her own Name. She was naturally
               vain, and receiv'd no small Pleasure in hearing herself prais'd, tho' in the Person
               of another, and a suppos'd Prostitute; but she dispatch'd as soon as she cou'd all
               that had hitherto attack'd her, when she saw the accomplish'd Beauplaisir<ref
                  target="a010" corresp="n010"/><note xml:id="n010" target="a010" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">Beauplaisir is a French portmanteau word meaning "beautiful pleasure."
                  Beau was also a generic term in the eighteenth century for a lady's suitor or
                  sweetheart, according to the OED.</note> was making his Way thro' the Crowd as
               fast as he was able, to reach the Bench she sat on. She had often seen him in the
                  Drawing-Room<ref target="a011" corresp="n011"/><note xml:id="n011" target="a011"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">The drawing or "withdrawing" room was a room in the
                  home of a wealthier class of people to which women would "withdraw" after dinner,
                  to brew tea and converse. Later, the male contingent would join the women in the
                  drawing room for polite conversation and mingling. For more information on the
                  history and evolution of the drawing room, see <ref
                     target="https://www.countrylife.co.uk/out-and-about/theatre-film-music/history-country-house-drawing-room-63348"
                     >this review of Jeremy Musson's <hi rend="italic">Drawing
                  Room</hi></ref>.</note>, had talk'd with him; but then her Quality and reputed
               Virtue kept him from using her with that Freedom she now expected he wou'd <pb
                  n="259" facs="images/HF-259.jpg"/> do, and had discover'd something in him, which
               had made her often think she shou'd not be displeas'd, if he wou'd abate some Part of
               his Reserve. – Now was the Time to have her Wishes answer'd: – He look'd in her Face,
               and fancy'd, as many others had done, that she very much resembled that Lady whom she
               really was; but the vast Disparity there appear'd between their Characters, prevented
               him from entertaining even the most distant Thought that they cou'd be the same. – He
               address'd her at first with the usual Salutations<ref target="a012" corresp="n012"
                  /><note xml:id="n012" target="a012" type="editorial" resp="TH">Salutations refer
                  to customary greetings.</note> of her pretended Profession, as, A<said>re you
                  engag'd, Madam? – Will you permit me to wait on you home after the Play? – By
                  Heaven, you are a fine Girl! – How long have you us'd this House?</said> – And
               such like Questions; but perceiving she had a Turn of Wit, and a genteel<ref
                  target="a013" corresp="n013"/><note xml:id="n013" target="a013" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">Used here as an adjective, "genteel" refers to a quality of polite
                  refinement thought to be possessed by those of the gentry class. According to <ref
                     target="https://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/402">this review of Peter
                     Cross's <hi rend="italic">The Origins of the English Gentry</hi>, the gentry
                     class is "a type of lesser nobility, based on landholding," that often
                     dispensed justice in the locality and wielded great social power.</ref></note>
               Manner in her Raillery<ref target="a014" corresp="n014"/><note xml:id="n014"
                  target="a014" type="editorial" resp="TH">According to the OED, raillery refers to
                  "[g]ood-humoured ridicule or banter," which can sometimes be more satirical or
                  mocking.</note>, beyond what is frequently to be found among those Wretches, who
               are for the most part Gentlewomen but by Necessity, few of 'em having had an
               Education suitable to what they affect to appear, he chang'd the Form of his
               Conversation, and shew'd her it was not because he understood no better, that he had
               made use of Expressions so little polite. – In fine, they were infinitely charm'd
               with each other: He was transported to find so much Beauty and Wit in a Woman, who he
               doubted not but on very easy Terms he might enjoy; and she found a vast deal of
               Pleasure in conversing with him in this free and unrestrain'd Manner. They pass'd
               their Time all the Play with an equal Satisfaction; but when it was over, she found
               herself involv'd in a Difficulty, which before never enter'd into her Head, but which
               she knew not well how to get over. – The Passion he profess'd for her, was not of
               that humble Nature which can be content with distant Adorations: – He resolv'd not to
               part from her without the Gratifications of those Desires she had inspir'd; and
               presuming on the Liberties which her suppos'd Function allow'd off, told her she must
               either go with him to some convenient House of his procuring, or permit him to wait
               on her to her own <pb n="260" facs="images/HF-260.jpg"/> Lodgings. – Never had she
               been in such a Dilemma: Three or four Times did she open her Mouth to confess her
               real Quality;<ref target="a015" corresp="n015"/><note xml:id="n015" target="a015"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">"Quality" is a difficult concept to grasp; in the
                  eighteenth century, it typically referred to rank or social position, and more
                  particularly, noble or high social position, as indicated by senses 4 and 5 in the
                  OED.</note> but the influence of her ill Stars prevented it, by putting an Excuse
               into her Head, which did the Business as well, and at the same Time did not take from
               her the Power of seeing and entertaining him a second Time with the same Freedom she
               had done this. – She told him, <said>she was under Obligations to a Man who
                  maintain'd her, and whom she durst not disappoint, having promis'd to meet him
                  that Night at a House hard by.</said> – This Story so like what those Ladies
               sometimes tell, was not at all suspected by Beauplaisir; and assuring her he wou'd be
               far from doing her a Prejudice, desir'd that in return for the Pain he shou'd suffer
               in being depriv'd of her Company that Night, that she wou'd order her Affairs, so as
               not to render him unhappy the next. She gave a solemn Promise to be in the same Box
               on the Morrow Evening; and they took Leave of each other; he to the Tavern to drown
               the Remembrance of his Disappointment; she in a Hackney-Chair<ref target="a016"
                  corresp="n0161"/><note xml:id="n016" target="a016" type="editorial" resp="TH"
                     ><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://media.vam.ac.uk/media/thira/collection_images/2014GW/2014GW5284_jpg_ds.jpg"
                  />A hackney or sedan chair was a hireable mode of transportation that consisted of
                  a single enclosed seat carried, on poles, by two strong men. It was small enough
                  to enter into the front doors of a well-appointed house, thus ensuring secresy.
                  Read more about the hackney or sedan chair in <ref
                     target="https://thebathmagazine.co.uk/taking-sitting-history-sedan-chair-bath/"
                     >this article from <hi rend="italic">Bath Magazine</hi></ref>. The image
                  included here shows an early eighteenth-century Italian sedan chair, without the
                  horizontal carrying poles, <ref
                     target="http://collections.vam.ac.uk/item/O109491/sedan-chair/">housed in the
                     VAM</ref>.</note> hurry'd home to indulge Contemplation on the Frolick she had
               taken, designing nothing less on her first Reflections, than to keep the Promise she
               had made him, and hugging herself with Joy, that she had the good Luck to come off
               undiscover'd.</p>

            <p> But these Cogitations<ref target="a017" corresp="n017"/><note xml:id="n017"
                  target="a017" type="editorial" resp="TH">"Cogitations" are thoughts; often, the
                  word contains a humourously exaggerated connotation.</note> were but of a short
               Continuance, they vanish'd with the Hurry of her Spirits, and were succeeded by
               others vastly different and ruinous: – All the Charms of Beauplaisir came fresh into
               her Mind; she languish'd, she almost dy'd for another Opportunity of conversing with
               him; and not all the Admonitions of her Discretion were effectual to oblige her to
               deny laying hold of that which offer'd itself the next Night. – She depended on the
               Strength of her Virtue, to bear her fate thro' Tryals more dangerous than she
               apprehended this to be, and never having been address'd by him as Lady, — was
               resolv'd to receive his Devoirs<ref target="a018" corresp="n018"/><note xml:id="n018"
                  target="a018" type="editorial" resp="TH">From the French word for duty, "devoirs"
                  are dutiful addresses paid to someone out of respect or courtesy. See sense 4 in
                  the OED.</note> as a Town-Mistress, imagining a world of Satisfaction to herself
               in engaging him in the Character <pb n="261" facs="images/HF-261.jpg"/> of such a
               one, and in observing the Surprise he would be in to find himself refused by a Woman,
               who he supposed granted her Favours without Exception. – Strange and unaccountable
               were the Whimsies she was possess'd of, – wild and incoherent her Desires, – unfix'd
               and undetermin'd her Resolutions, but in that of seeing Beauplaisir in the Manner she
               had lately done. As for her Proceedings with him, or how a second Time to escape him,
               without discovering who she was, she cou'd neither assure herself, nor whither or not
               in the last Extremity she wou'd do so. – Bent, however, on meeting him, whatever
               shou'd be the Consequence, she went out some Hours before the Time of going to the
               Playhouse, and took lodgings<ref target="a019" corresp="n019"/><note xml:id="n019"
                  target="a019" type="editorial" resp="TH">Fantomina explains that she rented rooms
                  near the playhouse, which were centrally located and more expensive than houses or
                  rooms in houses further afield. She would likely have rented the furnished first
                  floor for between 2 and 4 guineas per week, according to <ref
                     target="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/ecco/004859210.0001.000/1:7?rgn=div1;view=fulltext"
                     >John Trusler's late eighteenth-century <hi rend="italic">London Adviser and
                        Guide</hi></ref>. For a sense of the cost of living in the period, see <ref
                     target="https://www.oldbaileyonline.org/static/Coinage.jsp">"Currency, Coinage
                     and the Cost of Living" at the Old Bailey Online</ref>. For a good overview of
                  early Georgian town houses, see <ref
                     target="https://artsandculture.google.com/exhibit/kAIy8l4S5n_gKA">this Google
                     Arts and Culture <hi rend="italic">Spotter's Guide</hi></ref>.</note> in a
               House not very far from it, intending, that if he shou'd insist on passing some Part
               of the Night with her, to carry him there, thinking she might with more Security to
               her Honour entertain him at a Place where she was Mistress, than at any of his own
               chusing.</p>

            <p> THE appointed Hour being arriv'd, she had the Satisfaction to find his Love in his
               Assiduity: He was there before her; and nothing cou'd be more tender than the Manner
               in which he accosted her: But from the first Moment she came in, to that of the Play
               being done, he continued to assure her no Consideration shou'd prevail with him to
               part from her again, as she had done the Night before; and she rejoic'd to think she
               had taken that Precaution of providing herself with a Lodging, to which she thought
               she might invite him, without running any Risque, either of her Virtue or Reputation.
               – Having told him she wou'd admit of his accompanying her home, he seem'd perfectly
               satisfy'd; and leading her to the Place, which was not above twenty Houses distant,
               wou'd have order'd a Collation<ref target="a020" corresp="n020"/><note xml:id="n020"
                  target="a020" type="editorial" resp="TH">A "collation," according to the OED, is a
                  light, often cold meal of meats, fruits, and wine that has little to no need of
                  preparation.</note> to be brought after them. But she wou'd not permit it, telling
               him she was not one of those who suffer'd themselves to be treated at their own
               Lodgings; and as soon as she was come in, sent a Servant, belonging to the House<ref
                  target="a021" corresp="n021"/><note xml:id="n021" target="a021" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">When renting furnished rooms, a lodger might bring their own servant or
                  use the servants who work consistently at the house. Here, we learn that Fantomina
                  did not bring her own servant, but drew on the services of those from whom she
                  rented.</note>, to provide a very handsome Supper, and Wine, and every Thing was
                  <pb n="262" facs="images/HF-262.jpg"/> serv'd to Table in a Manner which shew'd
               the Director neither wanted Money, nor was ignorant how it shou'd be laid out.</p>

            <p> THIS Proceeding, though it did not take from him the Opinion that she was what she
               appeared to be, yet it gave him Thoughts of her, which he had not before. – He
               believ'd her a Mistress, but believ'd her to be one of a superior Rank, and began to
               imagine the Possession of her would be much more Expensive than at first he had
               expected: But not being of a Humour to grudge any Thing for his Pleasures, he gave
               himself no further Trouble, than what were occasioned by Fears of not having Money
               enough to reach her Price, about him.</p>

            <p> SUPPER being over, which was intermixed with a vast deal of amorous Conversation, he
               began to explain himself more than he had done; and both by his Words and Behaviour
               let her know, he would not be denied that Happiness the Freedoms she allow'd had made
               him hope. – It was in vain; she would have retracted the Encouragement she had given:
               – In vain she endeavoured to delay, till the next Meeting, the fulfilling of his
               Wishes: – She had now gone too far to retreat: – He was bold; – he was resolute: She
               fearful, – confus'd, altogether unprepar'd to resist in such Encounters, and rendered
               more so, by the extreme Liking she had to him. – Shock'd, however, at the
               Apprehension of really losing her Honour<ref target="a022" corresp="n022"/><note
                  xml:id="n022" target="a022" type="editorial" resp="TH">Honor, in this sense, is
                  being used to refer to Fantomina's "virtue as regards sexual morality," according
                  to sense 7 in the OED--or, "a reputation for this, one's good name."</note>, she
               struggled all she could, and was just going to reveal the whole Secret of her Name
               and Quality, when the Thoughts of the Liberty he had taken with her, and those he
               still continued to prosecute, prevented her, with representing the Danger of being
               expos'd, and the whole Affair made a Theme for publick Ridicule. – Thus much, indeed,
               she told him, that she was a Virgin, and had assumed this Manner of Behaviour only to
               engage him. But that he little regarded, or if he had, would have been far from
               obliging him to desist; – nay, in the present burning Eagerness of Desire, 'tis
               probable, that had he been <pb n="263" facs="images/HF-263.jpg"/> acquainted both
               with who and what she really was, the Knowledge of her Birth would not have
               influenc'd him with Respect sufficient to have curb'd the wild Exuberance of his
               luxurious Wishes, or made him in that longing, – that impatient Moment, change the
               Form of his Addresses. In fine, she was undone; and he gain'd a Victory, so highly
               rapturous, that had he known over whom, scarce could he have triumphed more. Her
               Tears, however, and the Destraction she appeared in, after the ruinous Extasy was
               past, as it heighten'd his Wonder, so it abated his Satisfaction: – He could not
               imagine for what Reason a Woman, who, if she intended not to be a Mistress, had
               counterfeited the Part of one, and taken so much Pains to engage him, should lament a
               Consequence which she could not but expect, and till the last Test, seem'd inclinable
               to grant; and was both surpris'd and troubled at the Mystery. – He omitted nothing
               that he thought might make her easy; and still retaining an Opinion that the Hope of
               Interest had been the chief Motive which had led her to act in the Manner she had
               done, and believing that she might know so little of him, as to suppose, now she had
               nothing left to give, he might not make that Recompense she expected for her Favours:
               To put her out of that Pain, he pulled out of his Pocket a Purse of Gold, entreating
               her to accept of that as an Earnest of what he intended to do for her; assuring her,
               with ten thousand Protestations, that he would spare nothing, which his whole Estate
               could purchase, to procure her Content and Happiness. This Treatment made her quite
               forget the Part she had assum'd, and throwing it from her with an Air of Disdain,
                  <said>Is this a Reward (said she) for Condescensions, such as I have yeilded to? –
                  Can all the Wealth you are possessed of, make a Reparation for my Loss of Honour?
                  – Oh! no, I am undone beyond the Power of Heaven itself to help me!</said> – She
               uttered many more such Exclamations; which the amaz'd Beauplaisir heard without being
               able to reply to, till by Degrees sinking <pb n="264" facs="images/HF-264.jpg"/> from
               that Rage of Temper, her Eyes resumed their softning Glances, and guessing at the
               Consternation he was in, <said>No, my dear Beauplaisir, (added she,) your Love alone
                  can compensate for the Shame you have involved me in; be you sincere and constant,
                  and I hereafter shall, perhaps, be satisfy'd with my Fate, and forgive myself the
                  Folly that betray'd me to you.</said></p>

            <p> BEAUPLAISIR thought he could not have a better Opportunity than these Words gave him
               of enquiring who she was, and wherefore she had feigned herself to be of a Profession
               which he was now convinc'd she was not; and after he had made her thousand Vows of an
               Affection, as inviolable and ardent as she could wish to find in him, entreated she
               would inform him by what Means his Happiness has been brought about, and also to whom
               he was indebted for the Bliss he had enjoy'd. – Some remains of yet unextinguished
               Modesty, and Sense of Shame, made her Blush exceedingly at this Demand; but
               recollecting herself in a little Time, she told him so much of the Truth, as to what
               related to the Frolick she had taken of satisfying her Curiosity in what Manner
               Mistresses, of the Sort she appeared to be, were treated by those who addressed them;
               but forbore discovering her true Name and Quality, for the Reasons she had done
               before, resolving, if he boasted of this Affair, he should not have it in his Power
               to touch her Character: She therefore said she was the Daughter of a Country
                  Gentleman<ref target="a023" corresp="n023"/><note xml:id="n023" target="a023"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">A country gentleman would be a member of the landed
                  gentry, residing most likely in a country house or mansion where the business of
                  the locality was often conducted. The country gentleman would likely have also had
                  a town house in London. To read more about the country house, see <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books?id=8KmrdrHhZusC"
                     >Mark Girouard's <hi rend="italic">Life in the English Country House: A Social
                        and Architectural History</hi> (1978)</ref>.</note>, who was come to town to
               buy Cloaths, and that she was call'd Fantomina. He had no Reason to distrust the
               Truth of this Story, and was therefore satisfy'd with it; but did not doubt by the
               Beginning of her Conduct, but that in the End she would be in Reality, the Thing she
               so artfully had counterfeited; and had good Nature enough to pity the Misfortunes he
               imagin'd would be her Lot: But to tell her so, or offer his Advice in that Point, was
               not his Business, as least, as yet. <pb n="265" facs="images/HF-265.jpg"/></p>

            <p> THEY parted not till towards Morning; and she oblig'd him to a willing Vow of
               visiting her the next Day at Three in the Afternoon. It was too late for her to go
               home that Night, therefore contented herself with lying there. In the Morning she
               sent for the Woman of the House to come up to her; and easily perceiving, by her
               Manner, that she was a Woman who might be influenced by Gifts, made her a Present of
               a Couple of Broad Pieces<ref target="a024" corresp="n024"/><note xml:id="n024"
                  target="a024" type="editorial" resp="TH">A broad piece is a coin approximately the
                  same as a pound, worth 20 shillings. It was called a "broad piece" because it was
                  thicker and and bigger than newer coins, minted after 1663. See <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books?id=klvjJDtpllwC">"A Note on British
                     Money", included in the Broadview edition of <hi rend="italic">Anti-Pamela and
                        Shamela</hi>(50ff)</ref>.</note>, and desir'd her, <said>that if the
                  Gentleman, who had been there the night before, should ask any Questions
                  concerning her, that he should be told, she was lately come out of the Country,
                  had lodg'd there about a Fortnight, and that her Name was Fantomina. I shall (also
                  added she) lie but seldom here; nor, indeed, ever come but in those Times when I
                  expect to meet him: I would, therefore, have you order it so, that he may think I
                  am but just gone out, if he should happen by any Accident to call when I am not
                  here; for I would not, for the World, have him imagine I do not constantly lodge
                  here.</said> The Landlady assur'd her she would do every Thing as she desired, and
               gave her to understand she wanted not the Gift of Secrecy.</p>

            <p> EVERY Thing being ordered at this Home for the Security of her Reputation, she
               repaired to the other, where she easily excused to an unsuspecting Aunt, with whom
               she boarded, her having been abroad all Night, saying, she went with a Gentleman and
               his Lady in a Barge<ref target="a025" corresp="n025"/><note xml:id="n025"
                  target="a025" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://www.rct.uk/sites/default/files/styles/rctr-scale-1300-500/public/collection-online/e/3/255748-1330621559.jpg"
                  />The river Thames was a source of work, pleasure, and transportation in the
                  eighteenth century; it connected many significant country towns to London, and
                  access to Hampton Court Palace as well as the many London pleasure gardens was
                  primarily accomplished via the river. <ref
                     target="https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-london-18185000">To learn more
                     about the history of the Thames, see this BBC article by Andy
                     Dangerfield.</ref> The image included here, <ref
                     target="https://www.rct.uk/collection/404760/a-view-of-hampton-court">an early
                     eighteenth-century painting by Leonard Knyff via the Royal Collection
                     Trust</ref>, shows Hampton Court Palace and the barges passing on the river
                  Thames.</note>, to a little Country Seat of theirs up the River, all of them
               designing to return the same Evening; but that one of the Bargemen happ'ning to be
               taken ill on the sudden, and no other Waterman to be got that Night, they were
               oblig'd to tarry till Morning. Thus did this Lady's Wit and Vivacity assist her in
               all, but where it was most needful. – She had Discernment to forsee, and avoid all
               those Ills which might attend the Loss of her Reputation, but was wholly blind to
               those of the Ruin of her Virtue; and having managed her Affairs so as to secure the
               one, grew perfectly easy with the Remembrance, <pb n="266" facs="images/HF-265.jpg"
               />she had forfeited the other. – The more she reflected on the Merits of Beauplaisir,
               the more she excused herself for what she had done; and the Prospect of that
               continued Bliss she expected to share with him, took from her all Remorse for having
               engaged in an Affair which promised her so much Satisfaction, and in which she found
               not the least Danger of Misfortune. – <said>If he is really (said she, to herself)
                  the faithful, the constant Lover he has sworn to be, how charming will be our
                  Amour? – And if he should be false, grow satiated, like other Men, I shall but, at
                  the worst, have the private Vexation of knowing I have lost him; – the
                     Intreague<ref target="a026" corresp="n026"/><note xml:id="n026" target="a026"
                     type="editorial" resp="TH">According to the OED, an "intrigue" is at once a
                     secret intimacy between lovers, as well as an intricate or maze-like
                     contrivance, perhaps enabling the clandestine romance.</note> being a Secret,
                  my Disgrace will be so too: – I shall hear no Whispers as I pass, – She is
                  Forsaken: – The odious Word Forsaken will never wound my Ears; nor will my Wrongs
                  excite either the Mirth or Pity of the talking World: – It will not be even in the
                  Power of my Undoer himself to triumph over me; and while he laughs at, and perhaps
                  despises the fond, the yielding Fantomina, he will revere and esteem the virtuous,
                  the reserv'd Lady.</said> – In this Manner did she applaud her own Conduct, and
               exult with the Imagination that she had more Prudence than all her Sex beside. And it
               must be confessed, indeed, that she preserved an OEconomy in the management of this
               Intreague, beyond what almost any Woman but herself ever did: In the first Place, by
               making no Person in the World a Confident in it; and in the next, in concealing from
               Beauplaisir himself the Knowledge who she was; for though she met him three or four
               Days in a Week, at the Lodging she had taken for that Purpose, yet as much as he
               employ'd her Time and Thoughts, she was never miss'd from any Assembly she had been
               accustomed to frequent. – The Business of her Love has engross'd her till Six in the
               Evening, and before Seven she has been dress'd in a different Habit<ref target="a027"
                  corresp="n027"/><note xml:id="n027" target="a027" type="editorial" resp="TH">A
                  habit used in this sense refers to a particular garment or mode of dress, often
                  specific to a profession or activity. See the OED senses 1 and 2.</note>, and in
               another Place. – Slippers, and a Nightgown loosely flowing, has been the Garb in
               which he has left the languishing Fantomina; – Lac'd, and <pb n="267"
                  facs="images/HF-267.jpg"/> adorn'd with all the Blaze of Jewels, has he, in less
               than an Hour after, beheld at the Royal Chapel<ref target="a028" corresp="n028"
                  /><note xml:id="n028" target="a028" type="editorial" resp="TH">Fantomina here
                  likely refers to the Chapel Royal at St. James's Palace. During the Georgian period,
                  the Chapel Royal became "a significant cultural centre." For more information on
                  the Chapel Royal, see <ref target="http://www.royalhistorian.com/the-chapel-royal-at-st-jamess-palace-from-king-henry-viii-to-prince-george-of-cambridge/">this article by Carolyn Harris.</ref></note>,
               the Palace Gardens<ref target="a029" corresp="n029"/><note xml:id="n029"
                  target="a029" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/2f/Kip_St_James%27s_Palace_and_Park.jpg"
                  />The palace gardens at St. James's Palace, which was the primary royal residence
                  until early nineteenth century, are pictured in the bird's eye plan by Jan Kip
                  shown here. Something of the spirit of the parks and gardens of the period can be
                  grasped by examining <ref
                     target="http://twonerdyhistorygirls.blogspot.com/2014/04/an-afternoon-in-st-jamess-park-c-1745.html"
                     >the 1745 painting of St. James's Park and the Mall, by Joseph Nickolls,
                     discussed here.</ref></note>, Drawing-Room, Opera<ref target="a030"
                  corresp="n030"/><note xml:id="n030" target="a030" type="editorial" resp="TH"
                     ><graphic width="300px"
                     url="http://www.vam.ac.uk/__data/assets/image/0008/183473/2006ac5629_the_rio_during_artaxerxes.jpg"
                  />Opera became extraordinarily fashionable during the eighteenth century. Read
                  more about the history of opera during the period <ref
                     target="http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/0-9/18th-century-opera/">from the
                     Victoria and Albert Museum</ref>. The image included here shows a riot during
                  an opera at Covent Garden Theatre in 1763.</note>, or Play, the Haughty
               Awe-Inspiring Lady – A thousand Times has he stood amaz'd at the prodigious Likeness
               between his little Mistress, and this Court Beauty; but was still as far from
               imagining they were the same, as he was the first Hour he had accosted her in the
               Playhouse, though it is not impossible, but that her Resemblance to this celebrated
               Lady, might keep his Inclination alive something longer than otherwise they would
               have been; and that it was to the Thoughts of this (as he supposed) unenjoy'd
               Charmer, she ow'd in great measure the Vigour of his latter Caresses.</p>

            <p> BUT he varied not so much from his Sex as to be able to prolong Desire, to any great
               Length after Possession: The rifled Charms of Fantomina soon lost their Poinancy<ref
                  target="a031" corresp="n031"/><note xml:id="n031" target="a031" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">According to the OED, "poingnancy" refers to the sharpness or piquancy
                  of a feeling.</note>, and grew tastless and insipid; and when the Season of the
               Year inviting the Company to the Bath, she offer'd to accompany him, he made an
               Excuse to go without her. She easily perceiv'd his Coldness, and the Reason why he
               pretended her going would be inconvenient, and endur'd as much from the Discovery as
               any of her Sex could do: She dissembled<ref target="a032" corresp="n032"/><note
                  xml:id="n032" target="a032" type="editorial" resp="TH">To "dissemble" is to
                  disguise or feign--to appear otherwise (OED).</note> it, however, before him, and
               took her Leave of him with the Shew of no other Concern than his Absence occasion'd:
               But this she did to take from him all Suspicion of her following him, as she
               intended, and had already laid a Scheme for. – From her first finding out that he
               design'd to leave her behind, she plainly saw it was for no other Reason, than being
               tir'd of her Conversation, he was willing to be at liberty to pursue new Conquests;
               and wisely considering that Complaints, Tears, Swooning, and all the Extravagancies
               which Women make use of in such Cases, have little Prevailence over a Heart inclin'd
               to rove, and only serve to render those who practice them more contemptible, by
               robbing them of that Beauty which alone can bring back the <pb n="268"
                  facs="images/HF-268.jpg"/> fugitive Lover, she resolved to take another Course;
               and remembring the Height of Transport she enjoyed when the agreeable Beauplaisir
               kneel'd at her Feet, imploring her first Favours, she long'd to prove the same again.
               Not but a Woman of her Beauty and Accomplishments might have beheld a Thousand in
               that Condition Beauplaisir had been; but with her Sex's Modesty, she had not also
               thrown off another Virtue equally valuable, tho' generally unfortunate, Constancy:
               She loved Beauplaisir; it was only he whose Solicitations could give her Pleasure;
               and had she seen the whole Species despairing, dying for her sake, it might, perhaps,
               have been a Satisfaction to her Pride, but none to her more tender Inclination. – Her
               Design was once more to engage him, to hear him sigh, to see him languish, to feel
               the strenuous Pressures of his eager Arms, to be compelled, to be sweetly forc'd to
               what she wished with equal Ardour, was what she wanted, and what she had form'd a
               Stratagem to obtain, in which she promis'd herself Success.</p>

            <p> SHE no sooner heard he had left the Town, than making a Pretence to her Aunt, that
               she was going to visit a Relation in the Country, went towards Bath<ref target="a033"
                  corresp="n033"/><note xml:id="n033" target="a033" type="editorial" resp="TH">Bath
                  is a fashionable resort and thermal spa town located in the south west of England,
                  near Bristol. In the eighteenth century, it became a destination and, according to
                  the UNESCO World Heritage Convention, <ref
                     target="https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/428">"one of the most beautiful cities
                     in Europe, with architecture and landscape combined harmoniously for the
                     enjoyment of the spa town’s cure takers."</ref></note>, attended but by two
               Servants, who she found Reasons to quarrel with on the Road and discharg'd: Clothing
               herself in a Habit she had brought with her, she forsook the Coach, and went into a
                  Wagon<ref target="a034" corresp="n034"/><note xml:id="n034" target="a034"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">A wagon is a much ruder form of transportation than the
                  elegant coach, befitting Fantomina's new character. Travel by stage coach from
                  London to Bath during this period would have taken at least two days. </note>, in
               which Equipage she arriv'd at Bath. The Dress she was in, was a round-ear'd Cap<ref
                  target="a035" corresp="n035"/><note xml:id="n035" target="a035" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH"><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://media.vam.ac.uk/media/thira/collection_images/2006AV/2006AV6330_jpg_l.jpg"
                  />According to <ref
                     target="https://www.bloomsburyfashioncentral.com/products/berg-fashion-library/dictionary/the-dictionary-of-fashion-history/round-eared-cap"
                        ><hi rend="italic">The Dictionary of Fashion History</hi></ref>, a
                  round-eared cap is a "white indoor cap curving round the face to the level of the
                  ears or below," often ruffled, and drawn close with a string along the shallow
                  back edge of the cap. These caps were popular among all classes from around 1730
                  to 1760, making this an early reference. The image included here, <ref
                     target="http://collections.vam.ac.uk/item/O74088/quilted-petticoat-unknown/"
                     >from the Victoria and Albert Museum, shows a mannequin in a quilted green
                     petticoat and round-eared cap</ref>.</note>, a short Red Petticoat, and a
               little Jacket of Grey Stuff<ref target="a036" corresp="n036"/><note xml:id="n036"
                  target="a036" type="editorial" resp="TH">"Stuff" here refers to a type of woven
                  material made of worsted woollen cloth. See OED sense 5c.</note>; all the rest of
               her Accoutrements were answerable to these, and join'd with a broad Country Dialect,
               a rude unpolish'd Air, which she, having been bred in these Parts, knew very well how
               to imitate, with her Hair and Eye-brows black'd, made it impossible for her to be
               known, or taken for any other than what she seem'd. Thus disguis'd did she offer
               herself to Service in the House where Beauplaisir lodg'd, having made it her Business
               to find out immediately where he was. Notwithstanding this Metamorphosis <pb n="269"
                  facs="images/HF-269.jpg"/> she was still extremely pretty; and the Mistress of the
               House happening at that Time to want a Maid<ref target="a037" corresp="n037"/><note
                  xml:id="n037" target="a037" type="editorial" resp="TH">A maidservant was one of
                  the lowest-paid members of a domestic household, though others--like scullery
                  maids, who were responsible for scrubbing kitchen pans--earned much less. A
                  housemaid was typically responsible for airing rooms, emptying chamber pots,
                  cleaning and beating rugs and beds, and so on. For more information on female
                  domestic servants, see <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books?id=ak02IMkrQEUC">Part 12 of <hi
                        rend="italics">Eighteenth-Century Women: An Anthology</hi>, Volume
                  21</ref>.</note>, was very glad of the Opportunity of taking her. She was
               presently receiv'd into the Family; and had a Post in it (such as she would have
               chose, had she been left at her Liberty,) that of making the Gentlemen's Beds,
               getting them their Breakfasts, and waiting on them in their Chambers. Fortune in this
               Exploit was extremely on her side; there were no others of the Male-Sex in the House,
               than an old Gentleman, who had lost the Use of his Limbs with the Rheumatism, and had
               come thither for the Benefit of the Waters<ref target="a038" corresp="n038"/><note
                  xml:id="n038" target="a038" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/27/Thomas_Rowlandson_-_Comforts_of_Bath-_The_Pump_Room_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg/1600px-Thomas_Rowlandson_-_Comforts_of_Bath-_The_Pump_Room_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg"
                  />Througout the eighteenth century, Bath--known for its thermal springs--became a
                  fashionable place to relax and "take the waters." <ref
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Thomas_Rowlandson_-_Comforts_of_Bath-_The_Pump_Room_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg"
                     >Thomas Rowlandson's satirical 1798 watercolor, "The Comforts of Bath: The Pump
                     Room," included here via Wikimedia Commons</ref>, depicts patients suffering
                  from a variety of illnesses descending on the Pump Room to drink the hot mineral
                  spring waters. It was believed that the mineral spring waters had curative
                  properties, though many people went to Bath for relaxation and leisure in
                  general.</note>, and her belov'd Beauplaisir; so that she was in no Apprehensions
               of any Amorous Violence, but where she wish'd to find it. Nor were her Designs
               disappointed: He was fir'd with the first Sight of her; and tho' he did not presently
               take any farther Notice of her, than giving her two or three hearty Kisses, yet she,
               who now understood that Language but too well, easily saw they were the Prelude to
               more substantial Joys. – Coming the next Morning to bring his Chocolate, as he had
               order'd, he catch'd her by the pretty Leg, which the Shortness of her Petticoat did
               not in the least oppose; then pulling her gently to him, ask'd her, <said>how long
                  she had been at Service? – How many Sweethearts she had? If she had ever been in
                  Love?</said> and many other such Questions, befitting one of the Degree she
               appear'd to be: All which she answer'd with such seeming Innocence, as more enflam'd
               the amorous Heart of him who talk'd to her. He compelled her to sit in his Lap; and
               gazing on her blushing Beauties, which, if possible, receiv'd Addition from her plain
               and rural Dress, he soon lost the Power of containing himself. – His wild Desires
               burst out in all his Words and Actions: he call'd her little Angel, Cherubim, swore
               he must enjoy her, though Death were to be the Consequence, devour'd her Lips, her
               Breasts with greedy Kisses, held to his burning Bosom her half-yielding,
               half-reluctant Body, nor suffered her to get loose, <pb n="270"
                  facs="images/HF-270.jpg"/> till he had ravaged all, and glutted each rapacious
               Sense with the sweet Beauties of the pretty Celia<ref target="a039" corresp="n039"
                  /><note xml:id="n039" target="a039" type="editorial" resp="TH">Celia is a generic
                  pastoral female name.</note>, for that was the Name she bore in this second
               Expedition. – Generous as Liberality itself to all who gave him Joy this way, he gave
               her a handsome Sum of Gold, which she durst not now refuse, for fear of creating some
               Mistrust, and losing the Heart she so lately had regain'd; therefore taking it with
               an humble Curtesy, and a well counterfeited Shew of Surprise and Joy, cry'd, <said>O
                  Law, Sir! what must I do for all this?</said> He laughed at her Simplicity, and
               kissing her again, tho' less fervently than he had done before, bad her not be out of
               the Way when he came home at Night. She promis'd she would not, and very obediently
               kept her Word.</p>

            <p> His Stay at Bath exceeded not a Month; but in that Time his suppos'd Country Lass
               had persecuted him so much with her Fondness, that in spite of the Eagerness with
               which he first enjoy'd her, he was at last grown more weary of her, than he had been
               of Fantomina; which she perceiving, would not be troublesome, but quitting her
                  Service<ref target="a040" corresp="n040"/><note xml:id="n040" target="a040"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">"Service" in this sense refers to the position of
                  domestic servitude she has acquired (OED).</note>, remained privately in the Town
               till she heard he was on his Return; and in that Time provided herself of another
               Disguise to carry on a third Plot, which her inventing Brain had furnished her with,
               once more to renew his twice-decay'd Ardours. The Dress she had order'd to be made,
               was such as Widows wear in their first Mourning<ref target="a041" corresp="n041"
                  /><note xml:id="n041" target="a041" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     width="300px"
                     url="http://www.historicalportraits.co.uk/Artworkimages/Zincke%20Lady%20Strange%203188%20Z.jpg"
                  />In this enamel miniature portrait c.1710, via Philip Mould and Company,<ref
                     target="http://www.historicalportraits.co.uk/"
                     >the artist Christian Zincke has depicted Henrietta Maria, Lady Ashburnham, in
                     first mourning for her husband; Henrietta Maria is twenty-three in this
                     portrait</ref>. First or deep mourning lasted approximately three months after
                  the death of a spouse, during which time the mourner wore non-reflective black
                  fabrics like bombazine.</note>, which, together with the most afflicted and
               penitential Countenance that ever was seen, was no small Alteration to her who us'd
               to seem all Gaiety. – To add to this, her Hair, which she was accustom'd to wear very
               loose, both when Fantomina and Celia, was now ty'd back so straight, and her
                  Pinners<ref target="a042" corresp="n042"/><note xml:id="n042" target="a042"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">A pinner is, according to the OED, a cap with long
                  flaps on either side that fits more tightly around the head; it is often worn by
                  women of higher social standing. "Pinners" also refers to the flaps on either side
                  of the cap.</note> coming so very forward, that there was none of it to be seen.
               In fine, her Habit and her Air were so much chang'd, that she was not more difficult
               to be known in the rude Country Girl, than she was now in the sorrowful Widow. <pb
                  n="271" facs="images/HF-271.jpg"/></p>

            <p> SHE knew that Beauplaisir came alone in his Chariot to the Bath, and in the Time of
               her being Servant in the House where he lodg'd, heard nothing of any Body that was to
               accompany him to London, and hop'd he wou'd return in the same Manner he had gone:
               She therefore hir'd Horses and a Man to attend her to an Inn about ten Miles on this
               side Bath, where having discharg'd them, she waited till the Chariot should come by;
               which when it did, and she saw that he was alone in it, she call'd to him that drove
               it to stop a Moment, and going to the Door saluted the Master with these Words:</p>

            <p>
               <said>THE Distress'd and Wretched, Sir, (said she,) never fail to excite Compassion
                  in a generous Mind; and I hope I am not deceiv'd in my Opinion that yours is such:
                  – You have the Appearance of a Gentleman, and cannot, when you hear my Story,
                  refuse that Assistance which is in your Power to give to an unhappy Woman, who
                  without it, may be rendered the most miserable of all created Beings.</said></p>

            <p> IT would not be very easy to represent the Surprise, so odd an Address created in
               the Mind of him to whom it was made. – She had not the Appearance of one who wanted
               Charity; and what other Favour she requir'd he cou'd not conceive: But telling her,
               she might command any Thing in his Power, gave her Encouragement to declare herself
               in this Manner: <said>You may judge, (resumed she,) by the melancholy Garb I am in,
                  that I have lately lost all that ought to be valuable to Womankind; but it is
                  impossible for you to guess the Greatness of my Misfortune, unless you had known
                  my Husband, who was Master of every Perfection to endear him to a Wife's
                  Affections. — But, notwithstanding, I look on myself as the most unhappy of my Sex
                  in out-living him, I must so far obey the Dictates of my Discretion, as to take
                  care of the little Fortune he left behind him, which being in the hands of a
                  Brother of his in London, will be all carried off to Holland, where he is going to
                  settle; if I reach not the Town before <pb n="272" facs="images/HF-272.jpg"/>he
                  leaves it, I am undone for ever. – To which End I left Bristol<ref target="a043"
                     corresp="n043"/><note xml:id="n043" target="a043" type="editorial" resp="TH"
                     >Bristol is a port town about 15 miles west of Bath.</note>, the Place where we
                  liv'd, hoping to get a Place in the Stage at Bath, but they were all taken up
                  before I came; and being, by a Hurt I got in a Fall, render'd incapable of
                  travelling any long Journey on Horseback, I have no Way to go to London, and must
                  be inevitably ruin'd in the Loss of all I have on Earth, without you have good
                  Nature enough to admit me to take Part of your Chariot.</said></p>

            <p> HERE the feigned Widow ended her sorrowful Tale, which had been several Times
               interrupted by a Parenthesis of Sighs and Groans; and Beauplaisir, with a complaisant
               and tender Air, assur'd her of his Readiness to serve her in Things of much greater
               Consequence than what she desir'd of him; and told her, <said>it would be an
                  Impossibility of denying a Place in his Chariot to a Lady, who he could not behold
                  without yielding one in his Heart</said>. She answered the Compliments he made her
               but with Tears, which seem'd to stream in such abundance from her Eyes, that she
               could not keep her Handkerchief from her Face one Moment. Being come into the
               Chariot, Beauplaisir said a thousand handsome Things to perswade her from giving way
               to so violent a Grief, which, he told her, would not only be distructive to her
               Beauty, but likewise her Health. But all his Endeavours for Consolement appear'd
               ineffectual, and he began to think he should have but a dull Journey, in the Company
               of one who seem'd so obstinately devoted to the Memory of her dead Husband, that
               there was no getting a Word from her on any other Theme: – But bethinking himself of
               the celebrated Story of the Ephesian Matron<ref target="a044" corresp="n044"/><note
                  xml:id="n044" target="a044" type="editorial" resp="TH">In the story of the
                  Ephesian matron, first told in Petronius' <hi rend="italic">Satyricon</hi>, a new
                  widow in deep mourning for her husband and known for her chastity is seduced by a
                  soldier tasked with guarding the crucified bodies of three theives. While the
                  soldier and the beautiful young widow are otherwise employed, one of the bodies
                  disappears, and to save her lover, the widow replaces the missing thief with her
                  husband's corpse. This story was adapted in the seventeenth century by Jean de La
                  Fontaine. Read more about this story and the seventeenth-century adaptation that
                  Haywood would have known of in <ref
                     target="https://www-jstor-org.proxymu.wrlc.org/stable/3295480?seq=1#metadata_info_tab_contents"
                     >Robert Colton's article, "The Story of the Widow of Ephesus in Petronius and
                     La Fontaine."</ref>
               </note>, it came into his Head to make Tryal, she who seem'd equally susceptible of
               Sorrow, might not also be so too of Love; and having begun a Discourse on almost
               every other Topick, and finding her still incapable of answering, resolv'd to put it
               to the Proof, if this would have no more Effect to rouze her sleeping Spirits: – With
               a gay Air, therefore, though accompany'd with <pb n="273" facs="images/HF-273.jpg"/>
               the greatest Modesty and Respect, he turned the Conversation, as though without
               Design, on that Joy-giving Passion, and soon discover'd that was indeed the Subject
               she was best pleas'd to be entertained with; for on his giving her a Hint to begin
               upon, never any Tongue run more voluble than hers, on the prodigious Power it had to
               influence the Souls of those posses'd of it, to Actions even the most distant from
               their Intentions, Principles, or Humours. – From that she pass'd to a Description of
               the Happiness of mutual Affection; – the unspeakable Extasy of those who meet with
               equal Ardency; and represented it in Colours so lively, and disclos'd by the Gestures
               with which her Words were accompany'd, and the Accent of her Voice so true a Feeling
               of what she said, that Beauplaisir, without being as stupid, as he was really the
               contrary, could not avoid perceiving there were Seeds of Fire, not yet extinguish'd,
               in this fair Widow's Soul, which wanted but the kindling Breath of tender Sighs to
               light into a Blaze. – He now thought himself as fortunate, as some Moments before he
               had the Reverse; and doubted not, but, that before they parted, he should find a Way
               to dry the Tears of this lovely Mourner, to the Satisfaction of them both. He did
               not, however, offer, as he had done to Fantomina and Celia, to urge his Passion
               directly to her, but by a thousand little softning Artifices, which he well knew how
               to use, gave her leave to guess he was enamour'd. When they came to the Inn where
               they were to lie, he declar'd himself somewhat more freely, and perceiving she did
               not resent it past Forgiveness, grew more encroaching still: – He now took the
               Liberty of kissing away her Tears, and catching the Sighs as they issued from her
               Lips; telling her if Grief was infectious, he was resolv'd to have his Share;
               protesting he would gladly exchange Passions with her, and be content to bear her
               Load of Sorrow, if she would as willingly ease the Burden of his Love. – She said
               little in answer to the strenuous Pressures with which at last he <pb n="274"
                  facs="images/HF-274.jpg"/> ventur'd to enfold her, but not thinking it Decent, for
               the Character she had assum'd, to yield so suddenly, and unable to deny both his and
               her own Inclinations, she counterfeited a fainting, and fell motionless upon his
               Breast. – He had no great Notion that she was in a real Fit, and the Room they supp'd
               in happening to have a Bed in it, he took her in his Arms and laid her on it,
               believing, that whatever her Distemper was, that was the most proper Place to convey
               her to. – He laid himself down by her, and endeavour'd to bring her to herself; and
               she was too grateful to her kind Physician at her returning Sense, to remove from the
               Posture he had put her in, without his Leave.</p>

            <p> IT may, perhaps, seem strange that Beauplaisir should in such near Intimacies
               continue still deceiv'd: I<ref target="a045" corresp="n045"/><note xml:id="n045"
                  target="a045" type="editorial" resp="TH">While "Fantomina" appears to be told in
                  the third person omniscient, there is a first-person narrator who interjects at
                  points with her own thoughts, as she does here.</note> know there are Men who will
               swear it is an Impossibility, and that no Disguise could hinder them from knowing a
               Woman they had once enjoy'd. In answer to these Scruples, I can only say, that
               besides the Alteration which the Change of Dress made in her, she was so admirably
               skill'd in the Art of feigning, that she had the Power of putting on almost what Face
               she pleas'd, and knew so exactly how to form her Behaviour to the Character she
               represented, that all the Comedians at both Playhouses are infinitely short of her
               Performances: She could vary her very Glances, tune her Voice to Accents the most
               different imaginable from those in which she spoke when she appear'd herself. – These
               Aids from Nature, join'd to the Wiles of Art, and the Distance between the Places
               where the imagin'd Fantomina and Celia were, might very well prevent his having any
               Thought that they were the same, or that the fair Widow was either of them: It never
               so much as enter'd his Head, and though he did fancy he observed in the Face of the
               latter, Features which were not altogether unknown to him, yet he could not recollect
               when or where he had known them; – and being told by her, that from her Birth, she
               had <pb n="275" facs="images/HF-275.jpg"/> never remov'd from Bristol, a Place where
               he never was, he rejected the Belief of having seen her, and suppos'd his Mind had
               been deluded by an Idea of some other, whom she might have a Resemblance of.</p>

            <p> THEY pass'd the Time of their Journey in as much Happiness as the most luxurious
               Gratification of wild Desires could make them; and when they came to the End of it,
               parted not without a mutual Promise of seeing each other often. – He told her to what
               Place she should direct a Letter to him; and she assur'd him she would send to let
               him know where to come to her, as soon as she was fixed in Lodgings.</p>

            <p> SHE kept her Promise; and charm'd with the Continuance of his eager Fondness, went
               not home, but into private Lodgings, whence she wrote to him to visit her the first
               Opportunity, and enquire for the Widow Bloomer. – She had no sooner dispatched this
                  Billet<ref target="a046" corresp="n046"/><note xml:id="n046" target="a046"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">A "billet" is the French word for letter; a billet doux
                  is a love letter. </note>, than she repair'd to the House where she had lodg'd as
               Fantomina, charging the People if Beauplaisir should come there, not to let him know
               she had been out of Town. From thence she wrote to him, in a different Hand<ref
                  target="a047" corresp="n047"/><note xml:id="n047" target="a047" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">"Hand" here refers to the style of handwriting used in the
                  letter.</note>, a long Letter of Complaint, that he had been so cruel in not
               sending one Letter to her all the Time he had been absent, entreated to see him, and
               concluded with subscribing herself his unalterably Affectionate Fantomina. She
               received in one Day Answers to both these. The first contain'd these Lines:</p>


            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <opener>To the Charming Mrs. BLOOMER,</opener>
                  <p> IT would be impossible, my Angel! for me to express the thousandth Part of
                     that Infinity of Transport, the Sight of your dear Letter gave me. – Never was
                     Woman form'd to charm like you: Never did any look like you, – write like you,
                     – bless like you; – nor did ever Man adore as I do. – Since <pb n="276"
                        facs="images/HF-276.jpg"/> Yesterday we parted, I have seem'd a Body without
                     a Soul; and had you not by this inspiring Billet, gave me new Life, I know not
                     what by To-morrow I should have been. – I will be with you this Evening about
                     Five: – O, 'tis an Age till then! – But the cursed Formalities of Duty oblige
                     me to Dine with my Lord – who never rises from Table till that Hour; –
                     therefore Adieu till then sweet lovely Mistress of the Soul and all the
                     Faculties of</p>
                  <closer>
                     Your most faithful,<lb/>
                    BEAUPLAISIR.</closer> 
               </body>
            </floatingText>

            <p> The other was in this Manner:</p>



            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <opener>To the Lovely FANTOMINA.</opener>

                  <p> IF you were half so sensible as you ought of your own Power of charming, you
                     would be assur'd, that to be unfaithful or unkind to you, would be among the
                     Things that are in their very Natures Impossibilities. – It was my Misfortune,
                     not my Fault, that you were not persecuted every Post with a Declaration of my
                     unchanging Passion; but I had unluckily forgot the Name of the Woman at whose
                     House you are, and knew not how to form a Direction that it might come safe to
                     your Hands. – And, indeed, the Reflection how you might misconstrue my Silence,
                     brought me to Town some Weeks sooner than I intended – If you knew how I have
                     languish'd to renew those Blessings I am permitted to enjoy in your Society,
                     you would rather pity than condemn</p>

                  <closer>Your ever faithful,
                     <signed>BEAUPLAISIR.</signed></closer>
               
                     <pb n="277" facs="images/HF-277.jpg"/>
               <postscript><p>P.S. I fear I cannot see you till
                     To-morrow; some Business has unluckily fallen out that will engross my Hours
                     till then. – Once more, my Dear, Adieu.</p></postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>

            <p>
               <said>TRAYTOR!</said> (cry'd she,) as soon as she had read them, <said>'tis thus our
                  silly, fond, believing Sex are serv'd when they put Faith in Man: So had I been
                  deceiv'd and cheated, had I like the rest believ'd, and sat down mourning in
                  Absence, and vainly waiting recover'd Tendernesses. – How do some Women,
                  (continued she) make their Life a Hell, burning in fruitless Expectations, and
                  dreaming out their Days in Hopes and Fears, then wake at last to all the Horror of
                  Dispair? – But I have outwitted even the most Subtle of the deceiving Kind, and
                  while he thinks to fool me, is himself the only beguiled Person.</said></p>

            <p> SHE made herself, most certainly, extremely happy in the Reflection on the Success
               of her Stratagems; and while the Knowledge of his Inconstancy and Levity of Nature
               kept her from having that real Tenderness for him she would else have had, she found
               the Means of gratifying the Inclination she had for his agreeable Person, in as full
               a Manner as she could wish. She had all the Sweets of Love, but as yet had tasted
               none of the Gall<ref target="a048" corresp="n048"/><note xml:id="n048" target="a048"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH">Gall is another word for bile; figuratively, it refers
                  to bitterness, a feature of bile.</note>, and was in a State of Contentment, which
               might be envy'd by the more Delicate.</p>

            <p> WHEN the expected Hour arriv'd, she found that her Lover had lost no part of the
               Fervency with which he had parted from her; but when the next Day she receiv'd him as
               Fantomina, she perceiv'd a prodigious Difference; which led her again into
               Reflections on the Unaccountableness of Men's Fancies, who still prefer the last
               Conquest, only because it is the last. – Here was an evident Proof of it; for there
               could not be a Difference in Merit, because they were the same Person; but the Widow
               Bloomer was a more new Acquaintance than Fantomina, and therefore esteem'd more
               valuable. This, indeed, must be said of Beauplaisir, that he had a <pb n="278"
                  facs="images/HF-278.jpg"/> greater Share of good Nature than most of his Sex, who,
               for the most part, when they are weary of an Intreague, break it entirely off,
               without any Regard to the Despair of the abandon'd Nymph<ref target="a049"
                  corresp="n049"/><note xml:id="n049" target="a049" type="editorial" resp="TH"
                     ><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://images.metmuseum.org/CRDImages/dp/original/DP826799.jpg"/>A
                  "nymph" is a mythological nature spirit, usually depicted as a young woman
                  disporting, semi-nude, in woodlands or near water. The word is often used
                  allegorically or metaphorically to refer to elegant, flirtatious young women. The
                  image included here shows an engraving, <hi rend="italic">Les Nimphes au Bain
                     (The Nymphs at the Bath)</hi>, by Jean Ouvrier after Francois Boucher, via <ref
                     target="https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/413498">The
                     Metropolitan Museum of Art</ref>. </note>. Though he retain'd no more than a
               bare Pity and Complaisance for Fantomina, yet believing she lov'd him to an Excess,
               would not entirely forsake her, though the Continuance of his Visits was now become
               rather a Penance than a Pleasure.</p>

            <p> THE Widow Bloomer triumph'd some Time longer over the Heart of this Inconstant, but
               at length her Sway was at an End, and she sunk in this Character, to the same Degree
               of Tastelessness, as she had done before in that of Fantomina and Celia. – She
               presently perceiv'd it, but bore it as she had always done; it being but what she
               expected, she had prepar'd herself for it, and had another Project in embrio<ref
                  target="a050" corresp="n050"/><note xml:id="n050" target="a050" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">This is an archaic spelling of <hi rend="italic">embryo</hi>.</note>,
               which she soon ripen'd into Action. She did not, indeed, compleat it altogether so
               suddenly as she had done the others, by reason there must be Persons employ'd in it;
               and the Aversion she had to any Confidents in her Affairs, and the Caution with which
               she had hitherto acted, and which she was still determin'd to continue, made it very
               difficult for her to find a Way without breaking thro' that Resolution to compass
               what she wish'd. – She got over the Difficulty at last, however, by proceeding in a
               Manner, if possible, more extraordinary than all her former Behaviour: – Muffling
               herself up in her Hood one Day, she went into the Park<ref target="a051"
                  corresp="n051"/><note xml:id="n051" target="a051" type="editorial" resp="TH">St.
                  James's Park was radically redeveloped by Charles II after his return to the
                  throne as a public space associated with the court. Here, Fantomina recounts
                  visiting the park to acquire the services of some young men down on their luck and
                  willing to be hired for a variety of services. Edmund Waller, whom Haywood quotes
                  in her epigraph, praised the park as a grand, idealized gathering place for the
                  fashionable elite in <ref
                     target="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eebo/A97029.0001.001/1:2?rgn=div1;view=fulltext"
                     >"ON St. James's PARK As lately improved by his MAJESTY"</ref>; however, John
                  Wilmot, second Earl of Rochester, reveals the darker, seamier side of the park in
                  his satire, <ref
                     target="https://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poems/ramble-st-jamess-park">"A Ramble
                     in St. James's Park"</ref>. For more analysis of these competing readings of
                  St. James's Park in context, see <ref
                     target="https://open.conted.ox.ac.uk/sites/open.conted.ox.ac.uk/files/resources/Create%20Document/Two%20Restoration%20views%20of%20St%20James%20Park_Christian%20Verdu.pdf"
                     >Christian Verdú's ""‘Me thinks I see the love that shall be made’: Two
                     Restoration Views of St James Park"</ref>.</note> about the Hour when there are
               a great many necessitous Gentlemen, who think themselves above doing what they call
               little Things for a Maintenance, walking in the Mall<ref target="a052" corresp="n052"
                  /><note xml:id="n052" target="a052" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     width="300px"
                     url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f6/St_James%27s_Park_mall1745.jpg"
                  />The Mall here refers not to a shopping center but a wide path for walking or
                  formal processions. The accompanying image, attributed to Joseph Nickolls, shows a
                  crowd of fashionable people on the Mall in St. James's Park (<ref
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:St_James%27s_Park_mall1745.jpg"
                     >Via Wikimedia Commons</ref>). </note>, to take a Camelion Treat<ref
                  target="a053" corresp="n053"/><note xml:id="n053" target="a053" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">Chameleons were long thought to subsist on air. According to Pliny the
                  Elder's <hi rend="italic">The Natural History</hi>, the chameleon "always holds
                  the head upright and the mouth open, and is the only animal which receives
                  nourishment neither by meat nor drink, nor anything else, but from the air alone"
                     (<ref
                     target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0137%3Abook%3D8%3Achapter%3D51"
                     >8.51</ref>). These impecunious men subsist on air, except when an employer
                  happens upon them. It is worth noting that the chameleon, as Pliny goes on to say,
                  is also "very remarkable" for the "nature of its colour," which "is continually
                  changing; its eyes, its tail, and its whole body always assuming the colour of
                  whatever object is nearest, with the exception of white and red."</note>, and fill
               their Stomachs with Air instead of Meat. Two of those, who by their Physiognomy<ref
                  target="a054" corresp="n054"/><note xml:id="n054" target="a054" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">Physiognomy refers to a pseudoscience that assessed the moral character
                  of an individual--or a group of people--by their physical appearance. For more
                  information on physiognomy in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, see Sarah
                  Waldorf's essay for <hi rend="italic">The Iris</hi>, <ref
                     target="http://blogs.getty.edu/iris/physiognomy-the-beautiful-pseudoscience/"
                     >"Physiognomy, the Beautiful Pseudo-Science"</ref>. For a fuller scholarly
                  assessment, see <ref
                     target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14780038.2017.1290998"
                     >Kathryn Woods's "‘Facing’ Identity in a ‘Faceless’ Society: Physiognomy,
                     Facial Appearance and Identity Perception in Eighteenth-Century
                  London"</ref>.</note> she thought most proper for her Purpose, she beckon'd to
               come to her; and taking them into a Walk more remote from Company, began to
               communicate the Business she had with them in these Words: <said>I am sensible,
                  Gentlemen, <pb n="279" facs="images/HF-279.jpg"/>(said she,) that, through the
                  blindness of Fortune, and Partiality of the World, Merit frequently goes
                  unrewarded, and that those of the best Pretentions meet with the least
                  Encouragement: – I ask your Pardon, (continued she,) perceiving they seem'd
                  surpris'd, if I am mistaken in the Notion, that you two may, perhaps, be of the
                  Number of those who have Reason to complain of the Injustice of Fate; but if you
                  are such as I take you for, have a Proposal to make you, which may be of some
                  little Advantage to you.</said> Neither of them made any immediate Answer, but
               appear'd bury'd in Consideration for some Moments. <said>At length, We should,
                  doubtless, Madam, (said one of them,) willingly come into any Measures to oblige
                  you, provided they are such as may bring us into no Danger, either as to our
                  Persons or Reputations.</said>
               <said>That which I require of you, (resumed she,) has nothing in it criminal: All
                  that I desire is Secrecy in what you are intrusted, and to disguise yourselves in
                  such a Manner as you cannot be known, if hereafter seen by the Person on whom you
                  are to impose. – In fine, the Business is only an innocent Frolick, but if blaz'd
                  abroad, might be taken for too great a Freedom in me: – Therefore, if you resolve
                  to assist me, here are five Pieces to Drink my Health, and assure you, that I have
                  not discours'd you on an Affair, I design not to proceed in; and when it is
                  accomplish'd fifty more lie ready for your Acceptance.</said> These Words, and,
               above all, the Money, which was a Sum which, 'tis probable, they had not seen of a
               long Time, made them immediately assent to all she desir'd, and press for the
               Beginning of their Employment: But things were not yet ripe for Execution; and she
               told them, that the next Day they should be let into the Secret, charging them to
               meet her in the same Place at an hour she appointed. 'Tis hard to say, which of these
               Parties went away best pleas'd; they, that Fortune had sent them so unexpected a
               Windfall; or she, that she had found Persons, who appeared so well qualified to serve
               her. <pb n="280" facs="images/HF-280.jpg"/></p>

            <p> INDEFATIGABLE in the Pursuit of whatsoever her Humour was bent upon, she had no
               sooner left her new-engag'd Emissaries, than she went in search of a House for the
               compleating her Project. – She pitch'd on one very large, and magnificently
               furnished, which she hir'd by the Week<ref target="a055" corresp="n055"/><note
                  xml:id="n055" target="a055" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic width="300px"
                     url="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/Ps4lGG0I9zw/maxresdefault.jpg"/>As Incognita,
                  Fantomina would have rented what <ref
                     target="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/ecco/004859210.0001.000/1:7?rgn=div1;view=fulltext"
                     >John Trusler describes as a "high rented" townhouse in a central
                     location</ref>. He goes on to note that "Houses about twenty-one feet in front
                  will let from four guineas a week furnished to eight guineas, according to the
                  season of the year and the time they are engaged for." This house, which is much
                  more magnificent, would have been about two and a half to three times the price
                  per week of the lodgings she took near the theaters. To learn more about London
                  townhomes in the eighteenth century, see <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Town_House_in_Georgian_London.html?id=f1bqAAAAMAAJ"
                     >Rachel Stewart's <hi rend="italic">The Town House in Georgian
                     London</hi></ref> (2009). The image included here, from <ref
                     target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ps4lGG0I9zw">a video showing the
                     300-year history of the Handel home on Brook Street</ref>, depicts an excellent
                  example of a large town home built during the early eighteenth century.</note>,
               giving them the Money before-hand, to prevent any Inquiries. The next Day she
               repaired to the Park, where she met the punctual 'Squires of low Degree; and ordering
               them to follow her to the House she had taken, told them they must condescend to
               appear like Servants, and gave each of them a very rich Livery<ref target="a056"
                  corresp="n056"/><note xml:id="n056" target="a056" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic url="https://www.history.org/history/clothing/designcenter/timeline/photos/2002-1.jpg" width="300px"/>Livery is the term given to the uniform worn by a household servant. In this image, showing a formal ball entrance reconstructed at Colonial Williamsburg, the two flanking servants are wearing the livery of the house (via <ref target="https://www.history.org/history/clothing/designcenter/timeline/">Colonial Williamsburg Foundation</ref>).</note>. Then writing a Letter to Beauplaisir, in a Character vastly
               different from either of those she had made use of, as Fantomina, or the fair Widow
               Bloomer, order'd one of them to deliver it into his own Hands, to bring back an
               Answer, and to be careful that he sifted out nothing of the Truth. – <said>I do not
                  fear, (said she,) that you should discover to him who I am, because that is a
                  Secret, of which you yourselves are ignorant; but I would have you be so careful
                  in your Replies, that he may not think the Concealment springs from any other
                  Reasons than your great Integrity to your Trust. – Seem therefore to know my whole
                  Affairs; and let your refusing to make him Partaker in the Secret, appear to be
                  only the Effect of your Zeal for my Interest and Reputation.</said> Promises of
               entire Fidelity on the one side, and Reward on the other, being past, the Messenger
               made what haste he could to the House of Beauplaisir; and being there told where he
               might find him, perform'd exactly the Injunction that had been given him. But never
               Astonishment exceeding that which Beauplaisir felt at the reading this Billet, in
               which he found these Lines: <pb n="281" facs="images/HF-281.jpg"/></p>



            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <opener>To the All-conquering BEAUPLAISIR.</opener>

                  <p> I imagine not that 'tis a new Thing to you, to be told, you are the greatest
                     Charm in Nature to our Sex: I shall therefore, not to fill up my Letter with
                     any impertinent Praises on your Wit or Person, only tell you, that I am
                     infinite in Love with both, and if you have a Heart not too deeply engag'd,
                     should think myself the happiest of my Sex in being capable of inspiring it
                     with some Tenderness. – There is but one Thing in my Power to refuse you, which
                     is the Knowledge of my Name, which believing the Sight of my Face will render
                     no Secret, you must not take it ill that I conceal from you. – The Bearer of
                     this is a Person I can trust; send by him your Answer; but endeavour not to
                     dive into the Meaning of this Mystery, which will be impossible for you to
                     unravel, and at the same Time very much disoblige me: – But that you may be in
                     no Apprehensions of being impos'd on by a Woman unworthy of your Regard, I will
                     venture to assure you, the first and greatest Men in the Kingdom, would think
                     themselves blest to have that Influence over me you have, though unknown to
                     yourself acquir'd. – But I need not go about to raise your Curiosity, by giving
                     you any Idea of what my Person is; if you think fit to be satisfied, resolve to
                     visit me To-morrow about Three in the Afternoon; and though my Face is hid, you
                     shall not want sufficient Demonstration, that she who takes these unusual
                     Measures to commence a Friendship with you, is neither Old, nor Deform'd. Till
                     then I am,</p>

                  <closer>Yours, 
                     <signed>INCOGNITA.</signed><ref target="a057" corresp="n057"/><note xml:id="n057"
                           target="a057" type="editorial" resp="TH">Incognita is a feminine form of the Italian "incognito," meaning one who is unknown or in disguise (OED).</note></closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>



            <p> HE had scarce come to the Conclusion, before he ask'd the Person who brought it,
               from what Place he came; – the Name of the Lady he serv'd; – <pb n="282"
                  facs="images/HF-282.jpg"/> if she were a Wife, or Widow, and several other
               Questions directly opposite to the Directions of the Letter; but Silence would have
               avail'd him as much as did all those Testimonies of Curiosity: No Italian Bravo,
               employ'd in a Business of the like Nature, perform'd his Office with more Artifice;
               and the impatient Enquirer was convinc'd that nothing but doing as he was desir'd,
               could give him any Light into the Character of the Woman who declar'd so violent a
               Passion for him; and little fearing any Consequence which could ensue from such an
               Encounter, resolv'd to rest satisfy'd till he was inform'd of every Thing from
               herself, not imagining this Incognita varied so much from the Generality of her Sex,
               as to be able to refuse the Knowledge of any Thing to the Man she lov'd with that
               Transcendency of Passion she profess'd, and which his many Successes with the Ladies
               gave him Encouragement enough to believe. He therefore took Pen and Paper, and
               answer'd her Letter in terms tender enough for a Man who had never seen the Person to
               whom he wrote. The Words were as follows:</p>



            <floatingText>
               <body>
                  <opener>To the Obliging and Witty INCOGNITA.</opener>

                  <p> Though to tell me I am happy enough to be lik'd by a Woman, such, as by your
                     Manner of Writing, I imagine you to be, is an Honour which I can never
                     sufficiently acknowledge, yet I know not how I am able to content myself with
                     admiring the Wonders of your Wit alone: I am certain, a Soul like yours must
                     shine in your Eyes with a Vivacity, which must bless all they look on. – I
                     shall, however, endeavour to restrain myself in these Bounds you are pleas'd to
                     set me, till by the Knowledge of my inviolable Fedility, I may be thought
                     worthy of gazing on that Heaven I am now but to enjoy in Contemplation. – You
                     need not doubt my glad Compliance with your obliging Summons: <pb n="283"
                        facs="images/HF-283.jpg"/> There is a Charm in your Lines, which gives too
                     sweet an Idea of their lovely Author to be resisted. – I am all impatient for
                     the blissful Moment, which is to throw me at your Feet, and give me an
                     Opportunity of convincing you that I am,</p>

                  <closer>Your everlasting Slave, 
                     <signed>BEAUPLAISIR.</signed></closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>



            <p> NOTHING could be more pleas'd than she, to whom it was directed, at the Receipt of
               this Letter; but when she was told how inquisitive he had been concerning her
               Character and Circumstances, she could not forbear laughing heartily to think of the
               Tricks she had play'd him, and applauding her own Strength of Genius, and Force of
               Resolution, which by such unthought-of Ways could triumph over her Lover's
               Inconstancy, and render that very Temper, which to other Women is the greatest Curse,
               a Means to make herself more bless'd. – <said>Had he been faithful to me, (said she,
                  to herself,) either as Fantomina, or Celia, or the Widow Bloomer, the most violent
                  Passion, if it does not change its Object, in Time will wither: Possession
                  naturally abates the Vigour of Desire, and I should have had, at best, but a cold,
                  insipid, husband-like Lover in my Arms; but by these Arts of passing on him as a
                  new Mistress whenever the Ardour, which alone makes Love a Blessing, begins to
                  diminish, for the former one, I have him always raving, wild, impatient, longing,
                  dying. – O that all neglected Wives, and fond abandon'd Nymphs would take this
                  Method! – Men would be caught in their own Snare, and have no Cause to scorn our
                  easy, weeping, wailing Sex!</said> Thus did she pride herself as if secure she
               never should have any Reason to repent the present Gaiety of her Humour. The Hour
               drawing near in which he was to come, she dress'd herself in as magnificent a Manner,
               as if she were to be that Night <pb n="284" facs="images/HF-284.jpg"/> at a Ball at
                  Court<ref target="a058" corresp="n058"/><note xml:id="n058" target="a058"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="https://collections.museumoflondon.org.uk/mol/mediaLib/236/617/83_531_va.jpg"
                     width="300px"/>Court dress for both women and men was both political and
                  sumptuous, some of which can be seen in the accompanying image, showing an
                  extravagant court dress made from Spitalfields silk and <ref
                     target="https://collections.museumoflondon.org.uk/online/object/85096.html"
                     >housed in the Museum of London</ref>. Click <ref
                     target="http://hdl.handle.net/10079/digcoll/940974">this link to view a
                     high-resolution image of a ball at St. James's Palace, c.1766, via the Lewis
                     Walpole Library</ref>. To learn more about fashion at court balls in the
                  eighteenth century, see <ref
                     target="https://journals.openedition.org/apparences/1311">Hannah Greig's
                     "Faction and Fashion : The Politics of Court Dress in Eighteenth-Century
                     England."</ref></note>, endeavouring to repair the want of those Beauties which
               the Vizard<ref target="a059" corresp="n059"/><note xml:id="n059" target="a059"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="https://neiljeffares.files.wordpress.com/2018/02/nattier-mme-royer.jpg"
                     width="300px"/>A "vizard" is a black velvet mask worn by elite women in the
                  Renaissance to protect the skin from sunburn. It became a fashionable accoutrement
                  during the eighteenth century, when masquerades were popular, and it was also
                  often worn to the theater. The image included here is a French pastel drawing
                  (c.1750) by Jean-Marc Nattier showing an aristocratic woman with vizard and fan
                     (<ref
                     target="https://neiljeffares.wordpress.com/2018/02/03/nattiers-portraits-of-m-et-mme-royer/"
                     >via Neil Jeffares</ref>). For more information on masquerade in the eighteenth
                  century, see <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books/about/Masquerade_and_Civilization.html?id=e1uwbUxKsLIC"
                     >Terry Castle's <hi rend="italic">Masquerade and Civilization: The
                        Carnivalesque in Eighteenth-century English Culture and Fiction</hi>
                     (1986)</ref>.</note> should conceal, by setting forth the others with the
               greatest Care and Exactness. Her fine Shape, and Air, and Neck, appear'd to great
               Advantage; and by that which was to be seen of her, one might believe the rest to be
               perfectly agreeable. Beauplaisir was prodigiously charm'd, as well with her
               Appearance, as with the Manner she entertain'd him: But though he was wild with
               Impatience for the Sight of a Face which belong'd to so exquisite a Body, yet he
               would not immediately press for it, believing before he left her he should easily
               obtain that Satisfaction. – A noble Collation being over, he began to sue for the
               Performance of her Promise of granting every Thing he could ask, excepting the Sight
               of her Face, and Knowledge of her Name. It would have been a ridiculous Piece of
               Affection in her to have seem'd coy in complying with what she herself had been the
               first in desiring: She yielded without even a Shew of Reluctance: And if there be any
               true Felicity in an Armour such as theirs, both here enjoy'd it to the full. But not
               in the Height of all their mutual Raptures, could he prevail on her to satisfy his
               Curiosity with the Sight of her Face: She told him that she hop'd he knew so much of
               her, as might serve to convince him, she was not unworthy of his tenderest Regard;
               and if he cou'd not content himself with that which she was willing to reveal, and
               which was the Conditions of their meeting, dear as he was to her, she would rather
               part with him for ever, than consent to gratify an Inquisitiveness, which, in her
               Opinion, had no Business with his Love. It was in vain that he endeavour'd to make
               her sensible of her Mistake; and that this Restraint was the greatest Enemy
               imaginable to the Happiness of them both: She was not to be perswaded, and he was
               oblig'd to desist his Solicitations, though determin'd in his Mind to compass what he
               so ardently desir'd, before he left the House. He then turned the Discourse wholly on
               the Violence of <pb n="285" facs="images/HF-285.jpg"/> the Passion he had for her;
               and express'd the greatest Discontent in the World at the Apprehensions of being
               separated; – swore he could dwell for ever in her Arms, and with such an undeniable
               Earnestness pressed to be permitted to tarry with her the whole Night, that had she
               been less charm'd with his renew'd Eagerness of Desire, she scarce would have had the
               Power of refusing him; but in granting this Request, she was not without a Thought
               that he had another Reason for making it besides the Extremity of his Passion, and
               had it immediately in her Head how to disappoint him.</p>

            <p> THE Hours of Repose being arriv'd, he begg'd she would retire to her Chamber; to
               which she consented, but oblig'd him to go to Bed first; which he did not much
               oppose, because he suppos'd she would not lie in her Mask, and doubted not but the
               Morning's Dawn would bring the wish'd Discovery. – The two imagin'd Servants usher'd
               him to his new Lodging; where he lay some Moments in all the Perplexity imaginable at
               the Oddness of this Adventure. But she suffer'd not these Cogitations to be of any
               long Continuance: She came, but came in the Dark; which being no more than he
               expected by the former Part of her Proceedings, he said nothing of; but as much
               Satisfaction as he found in her Embraces, nothing ever long'd for the Approach of Day
               with more Impatience than he did. At last it came; but how great was his
               Disappointment, when by the Noises he heard in the Street, the hurry of the Coaches,
               and the Cries of Penny-Merchants<ref target="a060" corresp="n060"/><note
                  xml:id="n060" target="a060" type="editorial" resp="TH">Penny merchants were street
                  vendors or hawkers; their cries would fill the streets. To learn more about the
                  history of street hawking in London, see <ref
                     target="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/nov/24/lost-cries-of-london-liberty-vagabonds-street-theatre"
                     >"The Lost Cries of London: Reclaiming the Street Trader's Devalued Tradition,"
                     published in <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi></ref>.</note>, he was
               convinc'd it was Night no where but with him? He was still in the same Darkness as
               before; for she had taken care to blind the Windows in such a manner, that not the
               least Chink was left to let in the Day. – He complain'd of her Behaviour in Terms
               that she would not have been able to resist yielding to, if she had not been certain
               it would have been the Ruin of her Passion: – She, therefore, answered him only as
               she had done before; and getting out of the Bed from him, <pb n="286"
                  facs="images/HF-286.jpg"/> flew out of the Room with too much Swiftness for him to
               have overtaken her, if he had attempted it. The Moment she left him, the two
               Attendants enter'd the Chamber, and plucking down the Implements which had skreen'd
               him from the Knowledge of that which he so much desir'd to find out, restored his
               Eyes once more to Day: – They attended to assist him in Dressing, brought him Tea,
               and by their Obsequiousness, let him see there was but one Thing which the Mistress
               of them would not gladly oblige him in. – He was so much out of Humour, however, at
               the Disappointment of his Curiosity, that he resolv'd never to make a second Visit. –
               Finding her in an outer Room, he made no Scruples of expressing the Sense he had of
               the little Trust she reposed in him, and at last plainly told her, he could not
               submit to receive Obligations from a Lady, who thought him uncapable of keeping a
               Secret, which she made no Difficulty of letting her Servants into. – He resented, –
               he once more entreated, – he said all that Man could do, to prevail on her to unfold
               the Mystery; but all his Adjurations were fruitless; and he went out of the House
               determin'd never to re-enter it, till she should pay the Price of his Company with
               the Discovery of her Face and Circumstances. – She suffer'd him to go with this
               Resolution, and doubted not but he would recede from it, when he reflected on the
               happy Moments they had pass'd together; but if he did not, she comforted herself with
               the Design of forming some other Stratagem, with which to impose on him a fourth
               Time.</p>

            <p> SHE kept the House, and her Gentlemen-Equipage for about a Fortnight, in which Time
               she continu'd to write to him as Fantomina and the Widow Bloomer, and received the
               Visits he sometimes made to each; but his Behaviour to both was grown so cold, that
               she began to grow as weary of receiving his now insipid Caresses as he was of
               offering them: She was beginning to think in what Manner she <pb n="287"
                  facs="images/HF-287.jpg"/> should drop these two Characters, when the sudden
               Arrival of her Mother, who had been some Time in a foreign Country, oblig'd her to
               put an immediate Stop to the Course of her whimsical Adventures. – That Lady, who was
               severely virtuous, did not approve of many Things she had been told of the Conduct of
               her Daughter; and though it was not in the Power of any Person in the World to inform
               her of the Truth of what she had been guilty of, yet she heard enough to make her
               keep her afterwards in a Restraint, little agreeable to her Humour, and the Liberties
               to which she had been accustomed.</p>

            <p> BUT this Confinement was not the greatest Part of the Trouble of this now afflicted
               Lady: She found the Consequences of her amorous Follies would be, without almost a
               Miracle, impossible to be concealed: – She was with Child; and though she would
               easily have found Means to have skreen'd even this from the Knowledge of the World,
               had she been at liberty to have acted with the same unquestionable Authority over
               herself, as she did before the coming of her Mother, yet now all her Invention was at
               a Loss for a Stratagem to impose on a Woman of her Penetration: – By eating little,
               lacing prodigious strait<ref target="a061" corresp="n061"/><note xml:id="n061"
                  target="a061" type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="https://media.vam.ac.uk/media/thira/collection_images/2006BB/2006BB0967_jpg_l.jpg"
                     width="300px"/>Lacing here refers to the lacing up of the stays, a shaping
                  undergarment <ref
                     target="http://collections.vam.ac.uk/item/O115752/stays-unknown/">like the one
                     seen here, from the late eighteenth century, housed in the Victoria and Albert
                     Museum</ref>. According to Valerie Steele in <hi rend="italic">The Corset: A
                     Cultural History</hi>, tightly laced stays <ref
                     target="https://books.google.com/books?id=uk6I0-MDXVQC">were the visible sign
                     of strict morality" (26)</ref>.</note>, and the Advantage of a great
                  Hoop-Petticoat<ref target="a062" corresp="n062"/><note xml:id="n062" target="a062"
                  type="editorial" resp="TH"><graphic
                     url="https://images.metmuseum.org/CRDImages/ci/original/CI65.13.1a%E2%80%93c_Fv2.jpg"
                     width="300px"/>Throughout the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, women's
                  formal fashion was characterized by the exaggerated bell shape created by the hoop
                  petticoat, <ref target="http://collections.vam.ac.uk/item/O1318194/hoop-unknown/"
                     >an example of which can be seen in the Victoria and Albert Museum's digital
                     collections</ref>. By 1750, the hoop petticoat could be as large as 1.5 meters
                  in diameter, and with the addition of panniers, court dress like
                     that which Fantomina is described as wearing--and which the included image
                     shows--could be notably voluminous.</note>, however, her Bigness was not
               taken notice of, and, perhaps, she would not have been suspected till the Time of her
               going into the Country, where her Mother design'd to send her, and from whence she
               intended to make her escape to some Place where she might be delivered with Secrecy,
               if the Time of it had not happen'd much Sooner than she expected. – A Ball being at
               Court, the good Old Lady was willing she should partake of the Diversion of it as a
               Farewel to the Town. – It was there she was seiz'd with those Pangs, which none in
               her Condition are exempt from: – She could not conceal the sudden Rack which all at
               once invaded her; or had her Tongue been mute, her wildly rolling Eyes, the
               Distortion of her Features, and the Convulsions <pb n="288" facs="images/HF-288.jpg"
               />which shook her whole Frame, in spite of her, would have reveal'd she labour'd
               under some terrible Shock of Nature. – Every Body was surpris'd, every Body was
               concern'd, but few guessed at the Occasion. – Her Mother griev'd beyond Expression,
               doubted not but she was struct with the Hand of Death; and order'd her to be carried
               Home in a Chair, while herself follow'd in another. – A Physician was immediately
               sent for: But he was presently perceiving what was her Distemper, call'd the old Lady
               aside, and told her, it was not a Doctor of his Sex, but one of her own<ref
                  target="a063" corresp="n063"/><note xml:id="n063" target="a063" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">Until the mid to late eighteenth century, childbirth was an almost
                  exclusively female domain. Midwives were women who had experience in both giving
                  birth and attending at other births. During the eighteenth century, midwifery was
                  becoming professionalized and as a result masculinized into obsetetric science.
                  For more information on the shift in the science of childbirth from a feminine
                  tradition to a masculine profession, see <ref
                     target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09699080400200227">Ernelle
                     Fife's "Gender and Professionalism in Eighteenth-Century
                  Midwifery"</ref>.</note>, her Daughter stood in need of. – Never was Astonishment
               and Horror greater than that which seiz'd the Soul of this afflicted Parent at these
               Words: She could not for a Time believe the Truth of what she heard; but he insisting
               on it, and conjuring her to send for a Midwife, she was at length convinc'd if it. –
               All the Pity and Tenderness she had been for some Moment before possess'd of, now
               vanish'd, and were succeeded by an adequate Shame and Indignation: – She flew to the
               Bed where her Daughter was lying, and telling her what she had been inform'd of, and
               which she was now far from doubting, commanded her to reveal the Name of the Person
               whose Insinuations had drawn her to this Dishonour. – It was a great while before she
               could be brought to confess any Thing, and much longer before she could be prevailed
               on to name the Man whom she so fatally had lov'd; but the Rack of Nature growing more
               fierce, and the enraged old Lady protesting no Help should be afforded her while she
               persisted in her Obstinacy, she, with great Difficulty and Hesitation in her Speech,
               at last pronounc'd the Name of Beauplaisir. She had no sooner satisfy'd her weeping
               Mother, than that sorrowful Lady sent Messengers at the same Time, for a Midwife, and
               for that Gentleman who had occasion'd the other's being wanted. – He happen'd by
               Accident to be at home, and immediately obey'd the Summons, though prodigiously <pb
                  n="289" facs="images/HF-289.jpg"/> surpris'd what Business a Lady so much a
               Stranger to him could have to impart. – But how much greater was his Amazement, when
               taking him into her Closet, she there acquainted him with her Daughter's Misfortune,
               of the Discovery she had made, and how far he was concern'd in it? – All the Idea one
               can form of wild Astonishment, was mean to what he felt: – He assur'd her, that the
               young Lady her Daughter was a Person who he had never, more than at a Distance,
               admir'd: – That he had indeed, spoke to her in publick Company, but that he never had
               a Thought which tended to her Dishonour. – His Denials, if possible, added to the
               Indignation she was before enflam'd with: – She had no longer Patience; and carrying
               him into the Chamber, where she was just deliver'd of a fine Girl, cry'd out, <said>I
                  will not be impos'd on: The Truth by one of you shall be reveal'd.</said>
               —Beauplaisir being brought to the Bed side, was beginning to address himself to the
               Lady in it, to beg she would clear the Mistake her Mother was involv'd in; when she,
               covering herself with the Cloaths, and ready to die a second Time with the inward
               Agitations of her Soul, shriek'd out, O<said>h, I am undone! – I cannot live, and
                  bear this Shame</said>! – But the old Lady believing that now or never was the
               Time to dive into the Bottom of this Mystery, forcing her to rear her Head, told her,
               she should not hope to Escape the Scrutiny of a Parent she had dishonour'd in such a
               Manner, and pointing to Beauplaisir, <said>Is this the Gentleman, (said she,) to whom
                  you owe your Ruin? or have you deceiv'd me by a fictitious Tale?</said>
               <said>Oh! no, (resum'd the trembling Creature,) he is, indeed, the innocent Cause of
                  my Undoing: – Promise me your Pardon, (continued she,) and I will relate the
                  Means.</said> Here she ceas'd, expecting what she would reply, which, on hearing
               Beauplaisir cry <pb n="290" facs="images/HF-290.jpg"/> out, <said>What mean you
                  Madam? I your Undoing, who never harbour'd the least Design on you in my
                  Life,</said> she did in these Words, <said>Though the Injury you have done your
                  Family, (said she,) is of a Nature which cannot justly hope Forgiveness, yet be
                  assur'd, I shall much sooner excuse you when satisfied of the Truth, than while I
                  am kept in a Suspence, if possible, as vexatious as the Crime itself is to
                  me.</said> Encouraged by this she related the whole Truth. And 'tis difficult to
               determine, if Beauplaisir, or the Lady, were most surpris'd at what they heard; he,
               that he should have been blinded so often by her Artifices; or she, that so young a
               Creature should have the Skill to make use of them. Both sat for some Time in a
               profound Revery; till at length she broke it first in these Words: <said>Pardon, Sir,
                  (said she,) the Trouble I have given you: I must confess it was with a Design to
                  oblige you to repair the supposed Injury you had done this unfortunate Girl, by
                  marrying her, but now I know not what to say; – The Blame is wholly her's, and I
                  have nothing to request further of you, than that you will not divulge the
                  distracted Folly she has been guilty of.</said> – He answered her in Terms
               perfectly polite; but made no Offer of that which, perhaps, she expected, though
               could not, now inform'd of her Daughter's Proceedings, demand. He assured her,
               however, that if she would commit the new-born Lady to his Care, he would discharge
               it faithfully. But neither of them would consent to that; and he took his Leave, full
               of Cogitations, more confus'd than ever he had known in his whole Life. He continued
               to visit there, to enquire after her Health every Day; but the old Lady perceiving
               there was nothing likely to ensue from these Civilities, but, perhaps, a Renewing of
               the Crime, she entreated him to refrain; and as soon as <pb n="291"
                  facs="images/HF-291.jpg"/> her Daughter was in a Condition, sent her to a
               Monastery in France, the Abbess of which had been her particular Friend<ref
                  target="a064" corresp="n064"/><note xml:id="n064" target="a064" type="editorial"
                  resp="TH">The role of the French convent in English literary and cultural
                  imagination is complex. Elite young women might be educated in a convent before
                  their marriage; the convent might also be a house of reformation; for some women,
                  the convent offered an intellectual alternative alternative to marriage in the
                  company of other women. In the English protestant imagination, the French convent
                  was often seen as an erotically-charged place. <ref
                     target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/413815/summary">As Ana Acosta writes in
                     "Hotbeds of Popery: Convents in the English Literary Imagination,"</ref> the
                  convent "provided a site for amorous encounters, forced and broken vows,
                  sacrificed youth, and unrequited love" (619). Yet, the convent is also a
                  specifically female community, where women lived, worked, studied, and conversed
                  with other women outside of the male gaze. For futher information, see Elizabeth
                  Rapey's <hi rend="italic">A Social History of the Cloister</hi>, <ref
                     target="https://historicalstudiesineducation.ca/index.php/edu_hse-rhe/article/view/1708/1817"
                     >reviewed by Patrick Harrigan in <hi rend="italic">Historical Studies in
                        Education</hi></ref>. </note>. And thus ended an Intreague, which,
               considering the Time it lasted, was as full of Variety as any, perhaps, that many
               Ages has produced.</p>

            <p> FINIS.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
