<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="philips-god-reconciling-world">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>2.Cor.5.19. God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</title>
                
                <author>
                    
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n83206561">
                        <name>
                             <forename>Katherine</forename>
                             <surname>Philips</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    
                    
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
              
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">2.Cor.5.19. God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                                <placeName type="city" key="lon">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Henry Herringman</publisher>
                            <date when="1667">1667</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">This text is based on transcriptions created by the Early English Books Online Texts Creation Partnership, a library-based project directed by the University of Michigan and Oxford University. Their digital text was produced from the 1667 edition, published by Henry Herringman in London in 1667, three years after Philips's death, but with the collaboration of her late husband. We have also consulted <hi rend="italics">The Collected Works of Katherine Philips</hi>, edited by Patrick Thomas (Essex: Stump Cross Books, 1990), which takes Philips's manuscript versions of her poems as its copytext. Annotations have been provided by faculty and students at the University of Virginia. 
                            </note>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  <!--BEGINS Profile Description  -->
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
                    <time when="1667">1667</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>        
        <body>           
             <div>                         
                <head><ref target="a001" corresp="n001">2.Cor.5.19.</ref><note xml:id="a001" target="n001">2.Cor.5.19. in the Christian Bible is the verse "that God was reconciling the world to himself in Christ, not counting peopleís sins against them. And he has committed to us the message of reconciliation" (English Standard Version. Bible Gateway)</note> God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</head>
                <head>Katherine Philips</head>
                    
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l n="1">When God, contracted to Humanity,</l> 
                        <l n="2">Could sigh and suffer, could be sick and die;</l>
                        <l n="3">When all the heap of Miracles combin'd</l>
                        <l n="4">To form the greatest, which was, save Mankind:</l> 
                        <l n="5">Then God took stand in Christ, studying a way</l>
                        <l n="6">How to repair the Ruin'd World's decay.</l> 
                        <l n="7">His Love, Pow'r, Wisdom, must some mean procure</l>
                        <l n="8">His Mercy to advance, Justice secure:</l>
                        <l n="9">And since Man in Misery was <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">hurl'd</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">(draft)A potential reference to Adam and Eve ("Man") being hurled from the Garden of Eden into the world ("Misery")</note>,</l> 
                        <l n="10"><ref target="a003" corresp="n003">It cost him more to save then to make the World</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">(DRAFT) What did it cost him? Is this the death of Jesus?</note>.</l> 
                        <l n="11">Oh! what a desp'rate load of sins had we,</l> 
                        <l n="12">When God must plot for our <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Felicity</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Happiness. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>?</l> 
                        <l n="13">When <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">God must beg us</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT)Relationship dynamic of humans as being their own downfall, with God in the position of savior.</note> that he may forgive,</l> 
                        <l n="14">And dye himself before Mankind could live?</l> 
                        <l n="15">And what still are we, when our <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">King</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">God as a sovereign ruler; a very literal translation of the "divine ruler."</note> in vain</l>
                        <l n="16">Begs his lost Rebels to be Friends again?</l> 
                        <l n="17">What flouds of Love proceed from Heaven's smile,</l>
                        <l n="18">At once to pardon and to reconcile?</l>
                        <l n="19">What God himself hath made he cannot hate,</l>
                        <l n="20">For 'tis one act to Love and to Create:</l> 
                        <l n="21">And he's too perfect full of Majesty,</l>
                        <l n="22">To need additions from our Misery.</l> 
                        <l n="23">He hath a Father's, not a Tyrant's, joy;</l> 
                        <l n="24">Shews more his Pow'r to save, than to destroy.</l>
                        <l n="25">Did there ten thousand Worlds to ruine fall,</l>
                        <l n="26">One God could save, one Christ redeem them all.</l>
                        <l n="27">Be silent then, ye narrow <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Soulds</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">(DRAFT) I don't understand what this is meant to be</note>, take heed</l>
                        <l n="28">Lest you restrain the Mercy you will need.</l> 
                        <l n="29">But, O my Soul, from these be different,</l> 	
                        <l n="30">Imitate thou a nobler <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Precedent:</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">An earlier event or action that is to serve as an example. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>	</l> 
                        <l n="31">As God with open Arms the World does woo,</l>
                        <l n="32">Learn thou like God to be enlarged too;</l>
                        <l n="33">As he begs thy consent to pardon thee,</l> 
                        <l n="34">Learn to submit unto <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">thy Enemy;</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009" >(DRAFT is this right?)"thy Enemy" as God</note></l> 		                        
                        <l n="35">As he stands ready thee to entertain,</l>		
                        <l n="36">Be thou as forward to return again;</l>
                        <l n="37">As he was Crucify'd for thee and by thee</l> 
                        <l n="38">Crucifie thou what caus'd his Agony;</l> 
                        <l n="39">And like to him be mortify'd to sin,</l>
                        <l n="40">Die to the World as he dy'd for it then.</l>
                    </lg>
                    
            <figure>    
                <graphic url="http://www.tei-c.org/logos/TEI-glow.png"/>
            </figure>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
