<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Content, To my Dearest Lucasia</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-Content</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Content, To my Dearest Lucasia</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>Content, To my Dearest Lucasia</head>
                <author>Katherine Phillips</author>

                <lg>
                    <l>Content, the fals World's best disguise,</l>
                    <l>The search and faction of the Wise </l>
                    <l>Is so <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">abstruse</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Difficult to understand; obscure, recondite. (Oxford English Dictionary)</note> and hid in night,</l>
                    <l>That, like that <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Fairy Red-cross Knight</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Protagonist of Book I of Spenser's The Faerie Queene. The Red Cross Knight is a symbol for purity and the Anglican church. (Encyclopedia Brittanica)</note>,</l>
                    <l>Who treacherous Falshood for clear Truth had got,</l>
                    <l>Men think they have it when they have it not.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>For Courts Content would gladly own,</l>
                    <l>But she ne'er dwelt about a Throne:</l>
                    <l>And to be flatter'd, rich, and great,</l>
                    <l>Are things which do Mens senses cheat.</l>
                    <l>But grave Experience long since this did see,</l>
                    <l>Ambition and Content would ne'er agree.</l>
               </lg>
                        
               <lg>
                    <l>Some vainer would Content expect</l>
                    <l>From what their bright Out-sides reflect:</l>
                    <l>But sure Content is more Divine</l>
                    <l>Than to be digg'd from Rock or Mine<note type="gloss">Philips views content as more valuable than any jewel that can be mined from the earth.</note>:</l>
                    <l>And they that know her beauties will confess,</l>
                    <l>She needs no lustre from a glittering dress.</l>
               </lg>
                        
               <lg>
                    <l>In <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Mirth</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Pleasurable feeling; enjoyment, gratification; joy, happiness. Often used of religious joy and heavenly bliss. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> some place her, but she scorns</l>
                    <l>Th'assistance of such crackling thorns,</l>
                    <l>Nor owes her self no such thin sport,</l>
                    <l>That is so sharp and yet so short:</l>
                    <l>And Painters tell us they the same stroke place,</l>
                    <l>To make a laughing and a weeping face.</l>
              </lg>
                                
              <lg>
                    <l>Others there are that place Content</l>
                    <l>In Liberty from Government:</l>
                    <l>But whomsoe're Passions deprave,</l>
                    <l>Though free from shackles, he's a slave.</l>
                    <l>Content and Bondage differ only then,</l>
                    <l>When we are chain'd by Vices, not by Men.</l>
              </lg>
                                        
              <lg>
                    <l>Some think the Camp Content does know,</l>
                    <l>And that she sits o'th'Victor's brow:</l>
                    <l>But in his <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Laurel</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">The foliage of the laurel tree as an emblem of victory or of distinction in poetry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> there is seen</l>
                    <l>Often a <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Cypress-bow</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">Cypress is a common material for archery bows.</note> between.</l>
                    <l>Nor will Content her self in that place give,</l>
                    <l>Where Noise and Tumult and Destruction live.</l>
              </lg>
                                                
              <lg>
                    <l>But yet the most Discreet believe,</l>
                    <l>The Schools this Jewel do receive,</l>
                    <l>And thus far's true without dispute,</l>
                    <l><ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Knowledge is still the sweetest fruit</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Reference to the fruit of the Tree of Knowledge. (Genesis)</note>.</l>
                    <l>But whilst men seek for Truth they lose their Peace;</l>
                    <l>And <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">who heaps Knowledge, Sorrow doth increase</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Ecclesiastes 1:18</note>.</l>
              </lg>
                                                        
              <lg>
                    <l>But now some sullen <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Hermite</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">A hermit, one who from religious motives has retired into solitary life. (Oxford English Dictionary) </note> smiles,</l>
                    <l>And thinks he all the World beguiles,</l>
                    <l>And that his <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Cell and Dish</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Reference to the frugal nature of the life of a religious hermit who would have a single dish for eating and live in a cell.</note> contain</l>
                    <l>What all mankind wish for in vain.</l>
                    <l>But yet his pleasure's follow'd with a Groan,</l>
                    <l>For man was never born to be alone.</l>
              </lg>
                                                                
              <lg>
                    <l>Content her self best comprehends</l>
                    <l>Betwixt two souls, and they two friends,</l>
                    <l>Whose either joyes in both are fix'd,</l>
                    <l>And <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">multiply'd by being mix'd</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Sharing joy and being in a relationship together</note>:</l>
                    <l>Whose minds and interests are so the same;</l>
                    <l>Their Griefs, when once imparted, lose that name.</l>
             </lg>
                                                                        
             <lg>
                    <l>These far remov'd from all bold noise,</l>
                    <l>And (what is worse) all hollow joyes,</l>
                    <l>Who never had a mean design,</l>
                    <l>Whose flame is serious and divine,</l>
                    <l>And calm, and even, must contented be,</l>
                    <l>For they've both Union and Society.</l>
             </lg>
                                                                                
             <lg>                                                                                             <l>Then, my <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Lucasia</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Philips' pseudonym for her closest female friend, Anne Owens. She was a member of Philips' coterie and the object of this poem. Lucasia is a character in William Cartwright's play "The Lady Errant.</note>, we who have</l>                                        <l>Whatever Love can give or crave;</l>                                                   <l>Who can with pitying scorn survey</l>                                                  <l>The Trifles which the most betray;</l>                                                 <l>With innocence and perfect friendship fir'd</l>
                    <l>By Vertiue joyn'd, and by our Choice retir'd.</l>
             </lg>
                                                                                        
                                                                                                       <lg>
                                                                                                              <l>Whose Mirrours are the crystal Brooks,</l>                                             <l>Or else each others Heart and Looks;</l>
                    <l>Who cannot wish for other things</l>                                                   <l>Then Privacy and Friendship brings:</l>                                                <l>Whose thoughts and persons chang'd and mixt are one,</l>                               <l>Enjoy Content, or else the World hath none.</l>                                 </lg>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>







