<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>XXXXII. On Controversies in Religion</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-XXXII</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">XXXXII. On Controversies in Religion</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>XXXXII. On Controversies in Religion</head>
                <author>Katherine Phillips</author>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>Religion, which true Policy befriends,</l>
                    <l>Design’d by God to serve Man’s noblest ends,</l>
                    <l>Is by that old Deceiver’s subtle Play</l>
                    <l>Made the chief Party in its own decay,</l>
                    <l>And meets that Eagle’s destiny, whose Breast</l>
                    <l><ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Felt the same shaft which his own Feathers drest</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">An allusion to Aesop’s fable of The Eagle and The Arrow</note>.</l>
                        <l>For that great Enemy of Souls perceiv’d,</l>
                        <l>The notion of a Deity was weav’d</l>
                        <l>So closely in Man’s Soul; to ruin that,</l>
                        <l>He must at once the World depopulate.</l>
                        <l>But as those Tyrants who their Wills pursue,</l>
                        <l>If they expound old Laws, need make no new:</l>
                        <l>So he advantage takes of Nature’s Light,</l>
                        <l>And raises that to a bare useless height;</l>
                        <l>Or while we seek for Truth, he in the Quest</l>
                        <l>Mixes a Passion, or an Interest,</l>
                        <l>To make us lose it; that, I know not how,</l>
                        <l>’Tis not our Practice, but our Quarrel now.</l>
                        <l>As in the Moon’s Eclipse some Pagans thought</l>
                        <l>Their barb’rous Clamours her Deliv’rance wrought:</l>
                        <l>So we suppose that Truth oppressed lies,</l>
                        <l>And needs a Rescue by our Enmities.</l>
                        <l>But ’tis Injustice, and the Mind’s Disease,</l>
                        <l>To think of gaining Truth by losing Peace.</l>
                        <l>Knowledge and Love, if true, do still unite;</l>
                        <l>God’s Love and Knowledge are both Infinite.</l>
                        <l>And though indeed Truth does delight to lye</l>
                        <l>At some Remoteness from a common Eye; </l>
                        <l>Yet ’tis not in a Thunder or a Noise,</l>
                        <l>But in soft Whispers and the stiller Voice.</l>
                        <l>Why should we then Knowledge so rudely treat,</l>
                        <l>Making our Weapon what was meant our Meat?</l>
                        <l>’Tis Ignorance that makes us quarrel so;</l>
                        <l>The Soul that’s dark will be contracted too.</l>
                        <l><ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Chimera's</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A fabled fire-breathing monster of Greek mythology, with a lion's head, a goat's body, and a serpent's tail (or according to others with the heads of a lion, a goat, and a serpent), killed by Bellerophon. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> make a Noise, swelling and vain,</l>
                        <l>And soon resolve to their own Smoak again.</l>
                        <l>But a true Light the Spirit doth dilate,</l>
                        <l>And robs it of its proud and sullen State;</l>
                        <l>Makes Love admir’d because ’tis understood</l>
                        <l>And makes us Wise because it makes us Good.</l>
                        <l>’Tis a right Prospect of things that we</l>
                        <l>Owe our Uprightness and our Charity.</l>
                        <l>For who resists a Beam when shining bright,</l>
                        <l>Is not a Sinner of a common height.</l>
                        <l>That State’s a Forfeiture, and Helps are spent,</l>
                        <l>Not more a Sin, than ’tis a Punishment.</l>
                        <l>The Soul which sees things in their native Frame,</l>
                        <l>Without Opinion’s Mask or Custom’s Name,</l>
                        <l>Cannot be clogg’d to Sense, or count that high</l>
                        <l>Which hath its Estimation from a Lie.</l>
                        <l>(Mean forbid Things, which by mistake we prize,</l>
                        <l>And absent covet, but enjoy’d despise.)</l>
                        <l>But scorning these hath robb’d them of their Art,</l>
                        <l>Either to swell or to subdue the Heart;</l>
                        <l>And learn’d that gen’rous Frame to be above</l>
                        <l>The World in hopes, below it all in love:</l>
                        <l>Touch’d with Divine and Inward Life doth run,</l>
                        <l>Not resting ‘till it hath its Centre won;</l>
                        <l>Moves steadily until it safe doth lye</l>
                        <l>I’ th’ Root of all its Immortality;</l>
                        <l>And resting here hath yet activity</l>
                        <l>To grow more like unto the Deity;</l>
                        <l>Good, Universal, Wise and Just as he,</l>
                        <l>(The fame in kind, though diff’ring in degree)</l>
                        <l>‘Till at the last ’tis swallow’d up, and grown</l>
                        <l>With God and with the whole Creation one;</l>
                        <l>It self, so small a part, i’ th’ whole is lost,</l>
                        <l>And Generals have Particulars engross’d.</l>
                        <l>That dark contracted Personality,</l>
                        <l>Like Mists before the Sun, will from it flie.</l>
                        <l>And then the Soul, one shining Sphere,  at length</l>
                        <l>With true Love’s Wisdom fill’d and purged Strength,</l>
                        <l>Beholds her highest Good with open Face,</l>
                        <l>And like him all the World she can embrace.</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>










