<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Upon the Double Murder of King Charles I</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-Upon</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Upon the Double Murder of King Charles I</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>Upon the Double Murder of King Charles I</head>
                <author>Katherine Phillips</author>
                
                <l><hi type="italics">SI. Upon the <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">double Murder of K. CHARLES I.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Charles I was beheaded after he lost the English Civil War to Cromwell and the protestants. After his death, his name was slandered by many Parliament memebers as well as Vavasor Powell. Source: Wikipedia</note> in Answer to a Libellous Copy of Rimes made by <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Vavasor Powell</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A nonconformist Puritain preacher. Source: Wikipedia</note>.</hi></l>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                    
                <l>I think not on the State, nor am concern’d</l>
                <l>Which way soever the <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">great helm is turn'd</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">(DRAFT) Basically does this mean She doesn't care which Religion is favored? Protestant or Catholic</note>:</l>
                <l>But as that son whose father's dangers nigh</l>
                <l>Did force his native dumbness, and untie</l>
                <l>The <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">fetter'd</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Shackled or chained. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> organs; so here's a fair cause</l>
                <l>That will excuse the breach of Nature's laws.</l>
                <l>Silence were now a sin, nay Passion now</l>
                <l>Wise men themselves for Merit would allow.</l>
                <l>What noble eye could see (and careless pass)</l>
                <l><ref target="a005" corresp="n005">The dying Lion kick'd by every Ass</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">This is a reference to an Aesop fable. A dying lion was attacked by a variety of animals who wanted their revenge on him. After being kicked by an ass the lion declares, "this is a double death." Source: Wikipedia</note>?</l>
                <l>Has Charles so broke God's Laws, he must not have</l>
                <l>A quiet Crown nor yet a quiet Grave?</l>
                <l>Tombs have been Sanctuaries; Thieves lie there</l>
                <l>Secure from all their penalty and fear.</l>
                <l>Great Charles his double misery was this,</l>
                <l>Unfaithful Friends, <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">ignoble</ref><note xml:id="n006" corresp="a006">Not of noble birth or disposition. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Enemies.</l>
                <l>Had any Heathen been this Prince's foe,</l>
                <l>He would have wept to see him injur'd so.</l>
                <l>His Title was his Crime, they'd reason good</l>
                <l>To quarrel at the Right they had withstood.</l>
                <l>He broke God's Laws, and therefore he must die;</l>
                <l>And what shall then become of thee and I?</l>
                <l>Slander must follow Treason; but yet stay,</l>
                <l>Take not our Reason with our King away.</l>
                <l>Though you have seiz'd upon all our defence,</l>
                <l>Yet do not <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">sequester</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">To confiscate or forciable take. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> our common Sense.</l>
                <l>But I admire not at this new supply:</l>
                <l>No bounds will hold those who at Sceptres fly.</l>
                <l>Christ will be King, but I ne're understood</l>
                <l>His Subjects built his Kingdom up with bloud,</l>
                <l>Except their own; or that he would dispence</l>
                <l>With his commands, though for his own defence.</l>
                <l>Oh! to what height of horrour are they come</l>
                <l>Who dare pull down a Crown, tear up a Tomb!</l>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











