<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>On the 3. of September, 1651</title>
            
            <author>
                <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                <forename>Katherine</forename>
                <surname>Philips</surname>
                <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                <country>Great Britain</country>
            </author>
            
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                <name>John O'Brien</name>
                <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                </address>
                <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
            </distributor>
            <authority>
                <idno>Philips-On</idno>
            </authority>
            <availability status="free">
                <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2018</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Write source here
                <extent></extent>
            </bibl>
            <biblStruct>
                <monogr>
                    <author>
                        <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                    </author>
                    <title type="main">On the 3. of September, 1651</title>
                    
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>
                            <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                        </pubPlace>
                        <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                        <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                    </imprint>                    
                </monogr>
            </biblStruct>    
        </sourceDesc>        
    </fileDesc>
    
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc> <p>
            This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
            <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
            <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
            <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                <bibl></bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div>
    
    <head>On the 3. of September, <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">1651</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">This date marks the Battle of Worcester where Oliver Cromwell and his men defeated Charles II and the Royalists, thus marking the end of the English Civil War. Source: Wikipedia</note></head>
    <author>Katherine Phillips</author>
    
    <lg type="stanza">
        <l>As when the glorious <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Magazine of Light</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Magazine of light refers to the sun as an arsenal container of light</note></l>
        <l>Approaches to his Canopy of Night</l>
        <l>He with the new splendor clothes his dying Rays,</l>
        <l>And double brightness to his Beams conveys;</l>
        <l>And (as to <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">brave</ref><note xmlid="n003" target="a003">Brave here means to defy. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> and check his ending fate)</l>
        <l>Puts on his highest look in's lowest state</l>
        <l>Dreft in such terrour as to make us all</l>
        <l>Be <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi type="italics">Anti-Persians</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">(DRAFT-Is this right?)Anti-Persians, i.e. those against the sun. They are "rooting" for the sun to set. It was thought that Persians worshipped the sun. (Encyclopedia Britannica) </note> and adore his Fall</l>
        <l>Then quits the world depriving it of Day</l>
        <l>While Every Herb and Plant does droop away;</l>
        <l>So when our gasping <hi type="italics">English</hi> Royalty</l>
        <l>Perciev'd her <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Period</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">End. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> was now drawing nigh,</l>
        <l>She summons her whole strength to give one blow,</l>
        <l>To raise her self, or pull down others too.</l>
        <l>Big with revenge and hope she now spake more</l>
        <l>Of terror than in many months before;</l>
        <l>And musters her Attendants or to fave</l>
        <l>Her from, or else attend her to, the Grave:</l>
        <l>Yet but enjoy'd the miserable fate</l>
        <l>Of setting Majesty, to die in State.</l>
        <l><ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Unhappy Kings, who cannot keep a Throne</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">(DRAFT) I would like something on this but I can't figure out the kings this refers to</note>,</l>
        <l>Nor be so fortunate to fall alone!</l>
        <l>Thier weight sinks others: <ref target="a007" corresp="n007"><hi type="italics">Pompey</hi> could not fly</ref>,<note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Pompey was assassinated while fleeing to Egypt in 48 BCE, and was replaced by Caesar. Source: Wikipedia</note></l>
        <l>But half the World must bear him company;</l>
        <l>And captiv'd <ref target="a008" corresp="n008"><hi type="italics">Sampson</hi></ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">(DRAFT-I would love to have this double checked)Sampson is a nazirite who was gifted with superhuman strength. He was famed for killing a lion with his bare hands, and being taken captive and tortured after being betrayed by his lover Delilah. Source: Wikipedia</note> could not life conclude,</l>
        <l>Unless attended with a multitude.</l>
        <l>Who'd trust to greatness now, <ref target="a009" cooresp="n009">whose food is air</ref>,<note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Who survives on nothing or who has false hope.</note></l>
        <l>Whose ruine sudden, and whose end despair?</l>
        <l>Who would presume upon his Glorious Birth,</l>
        <l>Or quarrel for a spacious share of Earth</l>
        <l>That sees such <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Diadems</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Crowns. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> become so cheap,</l>
        <l>And Heros tumble in a common heap?</l>
        <l>Oh give me Vertue then, which sums up all,</l>
        <l>And firmly stands when Crowns and Scepters fall.</l>
    </lg>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>

</TEI>










