<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>To Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-To</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">To Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <title>To <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Anne Hyde, wife of future King James II of England</note></title>
                    <author>Katherine Philips</author>
                    
                    
                    <lg>
                        <l>To you whose Dignity strikes us with aw,</l>
                        <l>And whose far greater Judgment gives us law,</l>
                        <l>Your Mind b'ing more transcendent then your State,</l>
                        <l>For while but Knees to this, Hearts bow to that,</l>
                        <l>These humble Papers never <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">durst</ref><note>The simple past of dare.</note> come near,</l>
                        <l>Had not your pow'rful Word bid them appear;</l>
                        <l>In which such majesty, such sweetness dwells,</l>
                        <l>As in one act obliges and compells.</l>
                        <l>None can dispute commands <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">vouchsaf'd</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">To grant by graciousness or condescension</note> by you.</l>
                        <l>What shall my fears then and confusion doe?</l>
                        <l>They must resign and by their just pretence</l>
                        <l>Some value set on my obedience,</l>
                        <l>For in Religious Duties, 'tis confest,</l>
                        <l>The most Implicite are accepted best.</l>
                        <l>If on that score your Highness will excuse</l>
                        <l>This blushing tribute of an artless Muse,</l>
                        <l>She may (encourag'd by your least regard,</l>
                        <l>Which first did worth create, and then reward)</l>
                        <l>At modest distance with improved strains</l>
                        <l>That Mercy celebrate which now she gains.</l>
                        <l>But should you that severer justice use,</l>
                        <l>Which those too prompt Approches may produce,</l>
                        <l>As the swift Doe which hath escaped long,</l>
                        <l>Believes a Vulgar hand would be a wrong;</l>
                        <l>But wounded by a Prince falls without shame,</l>
                        <l>And what in life she loses, gains in fame:</l>
                        <l>So if a Ray from you chance to be sent,</l>
                        <l>Which to consume, and not to warm, is meant;</l>
                        <l>My trembling Muse at least more nobly dies,</l>
                        <l>And falls by that a truer sacrifice.</l>
                    </lg> 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
