<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="philips-death-walter-lloid-knight">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Death of the Truly Honorable Sir Walter Lloid Knight.</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Katherine</forename>
                            <surname>Philips</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-OnTheDeath</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">On the Death of the Truly Honorable Sir Walter Lloid Knight.</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>  
    
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>On the death of the truly honorable <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Sir Walter Lloid Knight</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">(DRAFT)I would love to have a small bio on him, but I can't find anything definitive about this man.</note>.</head>
                <head>Katherine Philips </head>
                
                
                <lg type="Stanza">
               <l n="1">At <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Obsequies</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A funeral or burial rite. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> where so much grief is due,</l>
                <l n="2"><ref target="a003" corresp="n003">The Muses</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">The nine daughters of Zeus who symbolized the arts and sciences as a source of inspiration. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> are in solemn mourning too,</l>
                <l n="3">And by their dead astonishment confess,</l>
                <l n="4">They can lament this loss, though not express:</l>
                <l n="5">Nay if those ancient <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Bards</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">A poet, traditionally one reciting epics and associated with a a particular oral tradition. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> had seen this <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Herse</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT) A military formation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,</l>
                <l n="6">Who once in <hi style="italics">British</hi> shades spoke living Verse,</l>
                <l n="7">Their high concern for him had made them be, </l>
                <l n="8">Apter to weep, then write his Elogy:</l>
                <l n="9">When on our land that <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">flood of woes</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">The English Civil War (1642-1651): A battle between the Protestant rebels and the Catholic monarchy of England at the time. Oliver Cromwell led the Protestants to victory and King Charles I was beheaded. Source: Wikipedia</note> was sent, </l>
                <l n="10">Which swallowed all things sacred as it went,</l>
                <l n="11">The injur'd Arts and Vertues, made his breast </l>
                <l n="12">The Ark wherein they did securely rest:</l>
                <l n="13">For as that old one was toss'd up and down,</l>
                <l n="14">And yet the angry billows could not drown;</l>
                <l n="15">So Heav'n did him in this worse deluge save,</l>
                <l n="16">And made him triumph o're th' unquiet wave:</l>
                <l n="17">Who while he did with that wild storm contest,</l>
                <l n="18">Such real magnanimity express'd;</l>
                <l n="19">That he dar'd to be loyal in a time </l>
                <l n="20">When 'twas a danger made, and though a crime:</l>
                <l n="21">Duty, and not ambition, was his aim,</l>
                <l n="22">Who study'd Conscience ever more than Fame,</l>
                <l n="23">And thought it so desirable a thing,</l>
                <l n="24">To be prefer'd to suffer for his <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">King</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007"> King Charles I.</note>, </l>
                <l n="25">That he all Fortunes spight had pardon'd her,</l>
                <l n="26">Had she not made his Prince a sufferer;</l>
                <l n="27">For whose lov'd cause he did both act and grieve,</l>
                <l n="28">And for it only did endure to live,</l>
                <l n="29">To teach the world what man can be and do,</l>
                <l n="30"><ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Arm'd by Allegiance and Religion</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Sir Walter Lloid Knight was a royalist to the Stuart line.</note> too.</l>
                <l n="31">His head and heart mutual assistance gave,</l>
                <l n="32">That being still so wise, and this so brave,</l>
                <l n="33">That 'twas acknowledg'd all he said and did,</l>
                <l n="34">From judgement, and and from honor did proceed:</l>
                <l n="35">Such was the useful mixture of his mind,</l>
                <l n="36">'Twas at once meek and and knowing, stout and kind;</l>
                <l n="37">For he was civil, bountiful, and learn'd,</l>
                <l n="38">And for his Friends so generously concern'd,</l>
                <l n="39">That both his heart and house, his his hand and tongue,</l>
                <l n="40">To them, more than himself, seem'd to belong;</l>
                <l n="41">As if to his wrong'd party he would be</l>
                <l n="42">Both an Example and Apology:</l>
                <l n="43">For when both Swords and Pens ceas'd the dispute,</l>
                <l n="44">His life alone Rebellion and confute.</l>
                <l n="45">But when his Vows <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">propitious</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Giving or indicating a good chance of success; favorable. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Heaven had heard,</l>
                <l n="46">And our unequal'd King at length appear'd,</l>
                <l n="47">As aged <ref target="a010" corresp="n010"><hi style="italics">Simeon</hi></ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Simeon of the New Testament in Luke(2:25-26) was a prophet whom the Holy Spirit appeared to with a promise that he would not die until he had seen Jesus Christ.</note> did his spirits yield,</l>
                <l n="48">When he had seen his dearest hopes fulfil'd,</l>
                <l n="49">He gladly saw the morning of that day,</l>
                <l n="50">Which <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Charles</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">King Charles II was Coronated in 1661 after the death of Oliver Cromwell. Source: Wikipedia</note> his growing spledour did display;</l>
                <l n="51">Then to Eternal joies made greater haste,</l>
                <l n="52">Because his present ones flow'd in so fast;</l>
                <l n="53">From which he fled out of pious fear,</l>
                <l n="54">Lest he by them should be rewarded here;</l>
                <l n="55">While his sad Country by his death have lost</l>
                <l n="56">Their noblest Pattern and their greatest boast.</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
