<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="philips-to-the-duchess-of-york">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>"To Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York"</title>
                
                <author>
                  
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n83206561">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Katherine</forename>
                            <surname>Philips</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                   
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                                </name>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">To Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                                <placeName type="city" key="lon">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Henry Herringman</publisher>
                            <date when="1667">1667</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">This text is based on transcriptions created by the Early English Books Online Texts Creation Partnership, a library-based project directed by the University of Michigan and Oxford University. Their digital text was produced from the 1667 edition, published by Henry Herringman in London in 1667, three years after Philips's death, but with the collaboration of her late husband. We have also consulted <hi rend="italics">The Collected Works of Katherine Philips</hi>, edited by Patrick Thomas (Essex: Stump Cross Books, 1990), which takes Philips's manuscript versions of her poems as its copytext. Annotations have been provided by faculty and students at the University of Virginia. 
                            </note>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  <!--BEGINS Profile Description  -->
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
                    <time when="1667">1667</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">
                
                <pb n="11" facs="pageImages/Philips-p11.jpg"/>
                <head type="title"><hi rend="italic">To <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Her Royal Highness the Duchess of York</ref>, on her commanding me to send her some things that I had written.</hi><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Anne Hyde, wife of future King James II of England</note></head>

                    
                    <lg>
                        <l n="1">To you whose Dignity strikes us with aw,</l>
                        <l n="2">And whose far greater Judgment gives us law,</l>
                        <l n="3">Your Mind b'ing more transcendent then your State,</l>
                        <l n="4">For while but Knees to this, Hearts bow to that,</l>
                        <l n="5">These humble Papers never <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">durst</ref><note>The simple past of dare.</note> come near,</l>
                        <l n="6">Had not your pow'rful Word bid them appear;</l>
                        <l n="7">In which such majesty, such sweetness dwells,</l>
                        <l n="8">As in one act obliges and compells.</l>
                        <l n="9">None can dispute commands <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">vouchsaf'd</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">To grant by graciousness or condescension</note> by you.</l>
                        <l n="10">What shall my fears then and confusion doe?</l>
                        <l n="11">They must resign and by their just pretence</l>
                        <l n="12">Some value set on my obedience,</l>
                        <l n="13">For in Religious Duties, 'tis confest,</l>
                        <l n="14">The most Implicite are accepted best.</l>
                        
                        <pb n="12" facs="pageImages/Philips-p12.jpg"/>
                        
                        <l n="15">If on that score your Highness will excuse</l>
                        <l n="16">This blushing tribute of an artless Muse,</l>
                        <l n="17">She may (encourag'd by your least regard,</l>
                        <l n="18">Which first did worth create, and then reward)</l>
                        <l n="19">At modest distance with improved strains</l>
                        <l n="20">That Mercy celebrate which now she gains.</l>
                        <l n="21">But should you that severer justice use,</l>
                        <l n="22">Which those too prompt Approches may produce,</l>
                        <l n="23">As the swift Doe which hath escaped long,</l>
                        <l n="24">Believes a Vulgar hand would be a wrong;</l>
                        <l n="25">But wounded by a Prince falls without shame,</l>
                        <l n="26">And what in life she loses, gains in fame:</l>
                        <l n="27">So if a Ray from you chance to be sent,</l>
                        <l n="28">Which to consume, and not to warm, is meant;</l>
                        <l n="29">My trembling Muse at least more nobly dies,</l>
                        <l n="30">And falls by that a truer sacrifice.</l>
                    </lg> 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
