<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="philips-double-murder">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>"Upon the Double Murder of King Charles I"</title>

                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n83206561">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Katherine</forename>
                            <surname>Philips</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>

                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>

                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"Upon the Double Murder of King Charles I"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename>Katherine</forename>
                                <surname>Philips</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Poems by the most deservedly admired Mrs. Katherine Philips, the matchless Orinda</title>
                        <title type="sub">to which is added Monsieur Corneille's Pompey &amp; Horace, tragedies; with several other translations out of French</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="TGN" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed by J.M. for H. Herringman</publisher>
                            <date when="1667">1667</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">This text is based on transcriptions created by the Early English Books Online Texts Creation Partnership, a library-based project directed by the University of Michigan and Oxford University. <ref target="http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A54716.0001.001
                                ">Their digital text</ref> was produced from the 1667 edition, published by Henry Herringman in London in 1667, three years after Philips's death, but with the collaboration of her late husband. We have also consulted <hi rend="italics">The Collected Works of Katherine Philips</hi>, edited by Patrick Thomas (Essex: Stump Cross Books, 1990), which takes Philips's manuscript versions of her poems as its copytext. Annotations have been provided by faculty and students at the University of Virginia. For a full description of this object, see <ref target="http://estc.bl.uk/R19299">its ESTC entry</ref>.
                            </note>
                        </imprint>     
                        <extent>[36], 198, [8], 112, [2] p. :  port. ;  2⁰.</extent>
                        <biblScope></biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
                
                
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7001306">Dulin, Ireland</name>
                    <time from="1631" to="1664">During her life time: 1631-1664.</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in
                        Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up
                    selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British
                    and American literature of the 18th century. This project is funded by the
                    National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University
                    of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="poem">


                <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/Philips-p1.jpg"/>
                <head type="title"><hi style="italic">Upon the <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"
                            >double Murder of K. CHARLES I.</ref></hi><note xml:id="n001" target="a001"
                            >Charles I was beheaded after he lost the English Civil War to Cromwell
                            and the protestants. After his death, his name was slandered by many
                            Parliament memebers as well as Vavasor Powell. Source: Wikipedia</note>
                        <hi rend="italic">in Answer to a Libellous Copy of Rimes made by</hi> <ref target="a002"
                            corresp="n002">Vavasor Powell</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A
                            nonconformist Puritain preacher. Source: Wikipedia</note>.</head>
                <lg>
                    <l n="1">I think not on the State, nor am concern’d</l>
                    <l n="2">Which way soever the <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">great helm is
                            turn'd</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">(DRAFT) Basically does
                            this mean She doesn't care which Religion is favored? Protestant or
                            Catholic</note>:</l>
                    <l n="3">But as that son whose father's dangers nigh</l>
                    <l n="4">Did force his native dumbness, and untie</l>
                    <l n="5">The <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">fetter'd</ref><note xml:id="n004"
                            target="a004">Shackled or chained. Source: Oxford English
                            Dictionary</note> organs; so here's a fair cause</l>
                    <l n="6">That will excuse the breach of Nature's laws.</l>
                    <l n="7">Silence were now a sin, nay Passion now</l>
                    <l n="8">Wise men themselves for Merit would allow.</l>
                    <l n="9">What noble eye could see (and careless pass)</l>
                    <l n="10"><ref target="a005" corresp="n005">The dying Lion kick'd by every
                            Ass</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">This is a reference to an
                            Aesop fable. A dying lion was attacked by a variety of animals who
                            wanted their revenge on him. After being kicked by an ass the lion
                            declares, "this is a double death." Source: Wikipedia</note>?</l>
                    <l n="11">Has Charles so broke God's Laws, he must not have</l>
                    <l n="12">A quiet Crown nor yet a quiet Grave?</l>
                    <l n="13">Tombs have been Sanctuaries; Thieves lie there</l>
                    <l n="14">Secure from all their penalty and fear.</l>
                    <l n="15">Great Charles his double misery was this,</l>
                    <l n="16">Unfaithful Friends, <ref target="a006" corresp="n006"
                            >ignoble</ref><note xml:id="n006" corresp="a006">Not of noble birth or
                            disposition. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Enemies.</l>
                    <l n="17">Had any Heathen been this Prince's foe,</l>
                    <l n="18">He would have wept to see him injur'd so.</l>
                    <l n="19">His Title was his Crime, they'd reason good</l>
                    <l n="20">To quarrel at the Right they had withstood.</l>
                    <l n="21">He broke God's Laws, and therefore he must die;</l>
                    <l n="22">And what shall then become of thee and I?</l>
                    <l n="23">Slander must follow Treason; but yet stay,</l>
                    <l n="24">Take not our Reason with our King away.</l>
                    <l n="25">Though you have seiz'd upon all our defence,</l>
                    <l n="26">Yet do not <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">sequester</ref><note
                            xml:id="n007" target="a007">To confiscate or forciable take. Source:
                            Oxford English Dictionary</note> our common Sense.</l>

                    <pb n="27" facs="pageImages/Philips-p2.jpg"/>

                    <l n="28">But I admire not at this new supply:</l>
                    <l n="29">No bounds will hold those who at Sceptres fly.</l>
                    <l n="30">Christ will be King, but I ne're understood</l>
                    <l n="31">His Subjects built his Kingdom up with bloud,</l>
                    <l n="32">Except their own; or that he would dispence</l>
                    <l n="33">Oh! to what height of horrour are they come</l>
                    <l n="34">Who dare pull down a Crown, tear up a Tomb!</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
