<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="keats-nightingale">
    
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Ode to a Nightingale"</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80035884">
                        
                        <name>John Keats
                            
                            <forename>John</forename> 
                            <surname>Keats</surname>
                        </name>
                        
                    </persName>
                </author>
                
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#StudStaffUVA"
                        >Students and Staff of the University of Virginia</name>
                    
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblStruct>
                    
                    <analytic>
                        
                        <title>Ode to a Nightingale</title>
                        
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename>John</forename>
                                <surname>Keats</surname>
                                
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        
                        <title>"Ode to a Nightingale</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781"
                                    >London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Taylor and Hessey</publisher>
                            <date when="1820">1820</date>
                            <note>?"Ode to a Nightingale" was first published in 1820 in a book entitled <hi rend="italic">Lamia, Isabella, The Eve of St. Agnes, and Other Poems</hi>.Our edition is based on the version in <hi rend="italic">The Poems of John Keats</hi> in the Oxford Text Archive: http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12024/3259. This is based on the 1978 print version edited by Jack Stillinger and published by the Belknap Press in Cambridge, Massachusetts. </note>
                            
                            
                        </imprint>
                        
                        <extent></extent>
                        <biblScope>pp. 369-72
                        </biblScope>
                        
                    </monogr>
                    
                </biblStruct>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            
            <creation/>
            
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <!-- common descriptors include poem, novel, novella, play, collection, letter, and so on. -->
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <!-- view the TEI guidelines for textDesc online at https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ -->
                <constitution type="single">single poem</constitution>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="inapplicable"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="revised"/>
                <purpose type="express"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="medium"/>
                <!-- interpretation in the textDesc will be necessary -->
            </textDesc>
            
            <settingDesc>
                
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
                    <!-- The name authority and key here are important; they allow the application to pull information directly from that record; in this context, the application could draw GIS data from the TGN key to create a map. The key should be the unique identifier for the element currently being described. -->
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011197">England</name>
                    <time from="1800" to="1825">Early 19th Century</time>
                    <!-- The time setting may be somewhat interpretive, though research should tell you more. -->
                </setting>
                
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
                    Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
                    University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-11-14" who="editors.xmlJOB#">John O'Brien created LIC edition</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>   
        <body>    
            <div type="poem">
                <head> Ode to a Nightingale</head>
                <l n="1">My heart aches, and a drowsy numbness pains</l>
                <l n="2">My sense, as though of hemlock I had drunk,</l>
                <l n="3">Or emptied some dull opiate to the drains</l>
                <l n="4">One minute past, and Lethe-wards had sunk</l>
                <l n="5">'Tis not through envy of thy happy lot,</l>
                <l n="6">But being too happy in thine happiness, —</l>
                <l n="7">That thou, light-winged Dryad of the trees,</l>
                <l n="8">In some melodious plot</l>
                <l n="9">Of beechen green, and shadows numberless,</l>
                <l n="10">Singest of summer in full-throated ease.</l>
                <l n="11">O, for a draught of vintage! that hath been</l>
                <l n="12">Cool'd a long age in the deep-delved earth,</l>
                <l n="13">Tasting of Flora and the country green,</l>
                <l n="14">Dance, and Provencal song, and sunburnt mirth!</l>
                <l n="15">O for a beaker full of the warm south,</l>
                <l n="16">Full of the true, the blushful Hippocrene,</l>
                <l n="17">With beaded bubbles winking at the brim,</l>
                <l n="18">And purple-stained mouth;</l>
                <l n="19">That I might drink, and leave the world unseen,</l>
                <l n="20">And with thee fade away into the forest dim</l>
                <l n="21">Fade far away, dissolve, and quite forget</l>
                <l n="22">The weariness, the fever, and the fret</l>
                <l n="23">Here, where men sit and hear each other groan;</l>
                <l n="24">Where palsy shakes a few, sad, last gray hairs,</l>
                <l n="25">Where youth grows pale, and spectre-thin, and dies;</l>
                <l n="26">Where but to think is to be full of sorrow</l>
                <l n="27">And leaden-eyed despairs,</l>
                <l n="28">Where Beauty cannot keep her lustrous eyes,</l>
                <l n="29">Or new Love pine at them beyond to-morrow.</l>
                <l n="30">Away! away! for I will fly to thee,</l>
                <l n="31">Not charioted by Bacchus and his pards,</l>
                <l n="32">But on the viewless wings of Poesy,</l>
                <l n="33">Though the dull brain perplexes and retards</l>
                <l n="34">Already with thee! tender is the night,</l>
                <l n="35">And haply the Queen-Moon- is on her throne,</l>
                <l n="36">Cluster'd around by all her starry Fays;</l>
                <l n="37">But here there is no light,</l>
                <l n="38">Save what from heaven is with the breezes blown</l>
                <l n="39">Through verdurous glooms and winding mossy ways.</l>
                <l n="40">I cannot see what flowers are at my feet,</l>
                <l n="50">Nor what soft incense hangs upon the boughs,</l>
                <l n="51">But, in embalmed darkness, guess each sweet</l>
                <l n="52">Wherewith the seasonable month endows</l>
                <l n="53">The grass, the thicket, and the fruit-tree wild;</l>
                <l n="54">White hawthorn, and the pastoral eglantine;</l>
                <l n="55">Fast fading violets cover'd up in leaves;</l>
                <l n="56">And mid-May's eldest child,</l>
                <l n="57">The coming musk-rose, full of dewy wine,</l>
                <l n="58">The murmurous haunt of flies on summer eves.</l>
                <l n="59">Darkling I listen; and, for many a time</l>
                <l n="60">I have been half in love with easeful Death,</l>
                <l n="61">Call'd him soft names in many a mused rhyme,</l>
                <l n="62">To take into the air my quiet breath;</l>
                <l n="63">Now more than ever seems it rich to die,</l>
                <l n="64">To cease upon the midnight with no pain,</l>
                <l n="65">While thou art pouring forth thy soul abroad</l>
                <l n="66">In such an ecstasy!</l>
                <l n="67">Still wouldst thou sing, and I have ears in vain —</l>
                <l n="68">To thy high requiem become a sod.</l>
                <l n="69">Thou wast not born for death, immortal Bird!</l>
                <l n="70">No hungry generations tread thee down;</l>
                <l n="71">The voice I hear this passing night was heard</l>
                <l n="72">In ancient days by emperor and clown</l>
                <l n="73">Perhaps the self-same song that found a path</l>
                <l n="74">She stood in tears amid the alien corn;</l>
                <l n="75">The same that oft-times hath</l>
                <l n="76">Charm'd magic casements, opening on the foam</l>
                <l n="77">Of perilous seas, in faery lands forlorn.</l>
                <l n="78">Forlorn! the very word is like a bell</l>
                <l n="79">To toll me back from thee to my sole self!</l>
                <l n="80">Adieu! the fancy cannot cheat so well</l>
                <l n="81">As she is fam'd to do, deceiving elf.</l>
                <l n="82">Adieu! adieu! thy plaintive anthem fades</l>
                <l n="83">Past the near meadows, over the still stream,</l>
                <l n="84">Up the hill-side; and now 'tis buried deep</l>
                <l n="85">In the next valley-glades</l>
                <l n="86">Was it a vision, or a waking dream?</l>
                <l n="87">Fled is that music — Do I wake or sleep?</l>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

