<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="keats-grecian">
   
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">"Ode on a Grecian Urn"</title>
            <author>
               <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80035884">
                  
                  <name>John Keats
                     
                     <forename>John</forename> 
                     <surname>Keats</surname>

                  </name>
              
               </persName>
            </author>

            <editor>
               <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                  <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                     <forename>John</forename>
                     <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </editor>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name ref="editors.xml#StudStaffUVA"
                  >Students and Staff of the University of Virginia</name>
               
            </respStmt>

            <sponsor/>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <address>
                  <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                  <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                  <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                  <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>

               </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>

            <biblStruct>

               <analytic>
                 
                  <title>"Ode on a Grecian Urn"</title>
                
               </analytic>
                 
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Keats</surname>
                        
                     </name>
                  </author>

                  <title>Lamia, Isabella, The Eve of St. Agnes, and Other Poems</title>

                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781"
                           >London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Taylor and Cressey</publisher>
                     <date when="1820">1820</date>
                     <note>"Ode on a Grecian Urn" was composed in 1819 and first published anonymously in the journal <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Fine Arts</hi> that year. It was then published in 1820 in an edition of Keats's poems entitled <hi rend="italic">Lamia, Isabella, The Eve of St, Agnes and other Poems</hi>issued by the London publisher Taylor and Cressey. Our edition follows the version in the 1820 volume, which differs slightly from the version published the year before (see especially the note to line 47). Page images have been sourced from Google Books.</note>
                   
                    
                  </imprint>

                  <extent><?oxy-placeholder content="physical dimensions from catalog record"?></extent>
                  <biblScope>113-116
                  </biblScope>

               </monogr>

            </biblStruct>

         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>

         <creation/>

         <textDesc n="poem">
            <!-- common descriptors include poem, novel, novella, play, collection, letter, and so on. -->
            <channel mode="w">print</channel>
            <!-- view the TEI guidelines for textDesc online at https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ -->
            <constitution type="single">single poem</constitution>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain/>
            <factuality type="inapplicable"/>
            <interaction/>
            <preparedness type="revised"/>
            <purpose type="express"/>
            <purpose type="inform" degree="medium"/>
            <!-- interpretation in the textDesc will be necessary -->
         </textDesc>

         <settingDesc>

            <setting>
               
            </setting>

         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
               primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
               literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
               Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
               University.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                  lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-11-13" who="editors.xmlJOB#">John O'Brien created LIC edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>   
      <body>
         <pb n="113" facs="pageImages/p113.png"/>
<div type="poem">
    <head>Ode on a Grecian Urn</head>
   <head>1.</head>
   
   <lg type="stanza"><l n="1">Thou still unravish'd bride of quietness,</l>
   <l rend="indent" n="2">Thou foster-child of silence and slow time,</l>
   <l n="3">Sylvan historian, who canst thus express</l>
   <l rend="indent" n="4">A flowery tale more sweetly than our rhyme:</l>
   <l n="5">What leaf-fring'd legend haunts about thy shape</l>
   <l rend="indent" n="6">Of deities or mortals, or of both,</l>
   <l rend="indent" n="7">In Tempe or the dales of Arcady?</l>
   <l rend="indent" n="8">What men or gods are these? What maidens loth?</l>
   <l n="9">What mad pursuit? What struggle to escape?</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="10">What pipes and timbrels? What wild ecstasy?</l></lg>
   
   <pb n="114" facs="pageImages/p114.png"/>
   <head>2.</head>
   <lg type="stanza"><l n="11">Heard melodies are sweet, but those unheard</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="12">Are sweeter; therefore, ye soft pipes, play on;</l>
   <l n="13">Not to the sensual ear, but, more endear'd,</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="14">Pipe to the spirit ditties of no tone:</l>
   <l n="15">Fair youth, beneath the trees, thou canst not leave</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="16">Thy song, nor ever can those trees be bare;</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="17">Bold lover, never, never canst thou kiss,</l>
   <l n="18">Though winning near the goal — yet, do not grieve;</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="19">She cannot fade, though thou hast not thy bliss,</l>
      <l rend="indent" n="20">For ever wilt thou love, and she be fair!</l></lg>
   
   <head>3.</head>
      <lg type="stanza"><l n="21">Ah, happy, happy boughs! that cannot shed</l>
         <l rend="indent" n="22">Your leaves, nor ever bid the Spring adieu;</l>
   <l n="23">And, happy melodist, unwearied,</l>
         <l rend="indent" n="24">For ever piping songs for ever new;</l>
   
         <pb n="115" facs="pageImages/p115.png"/>
   <l n="25">More happy love! more happy, happy love!</l>
         <l rend="indent" n="26">For ever warm and still to be enjoy'd,</l>
         <l rend="indent" n="27">For ever panting, and for ever young;</l>
   <l n="28">All breathing human passion far above,</l>
   <l n="29">That leaves a heart high-sorrowful and cloy'd,</l>
         <l rend="indent" n="30">A burning forehead, and a parching tongue.</l></lg>
   
   <head>4.</head>
         <lg type="stanza"><l n="31">Who are these coming to the sacrifice?</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="32">To what green altar, O mysterious priest,</l>
   <l n="33">Lead'st thou that heifer lowing at the skies,</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="34">And all her silken flanks with garlands drest?</l>
   <l n="35">What little town by river or sea shore,</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="36">Or mountain-built with peaceful citadel,</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="36">Is emptied of this folk, this pious morn?</l>
   <l n="37">And, little town, thy streets for evermore</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="37">Will silent be; and not a soul sto tell</l>
            <l rend="indent" n="38">Why thou art desolate, can e'er return.</l></lg>
   
   <pb n="116" facs="pageImages/p116.png"/>
   <head>5.</head>
            <lg type="stanza"><l n="39">O Attic shape! Fair attitude! with brede</l>
               <l rend="indent" n="40">Of marble men and maidens overwrought,</l>
   <l n="41">With forest branches and the trodden weed;</l>
               <l rend="indent" n="43">Thou, silent form, dost tease us out of thought</l>
   <l n="43">As doth eternity: Cold Pastoral!</l>
               <l rend="indent" n="44">When old age shall this generation waste,</l>
               <l rend="indent" n="45">Thou shalt remain, in midst of other woe</l>
   <l n="46">Than ours, a friend to man, to whom thou say'st,</l>
               <l rend="indent" n="47"><ref target="Beauty_" corresp="Beauty">Beauty is truth, truth beauty"</ref><note xml:id="Beauty" target="Beauty_">This closing couplet is a famous example of a situation where an important part of a poem exists in two different versions, versions that can lead to very different interpretations. In the version of "Ode on a Grecian Urn" that was published <hi rend="italic">Lamia, Isabella, The Eve of St. Agnes and other Poems</hi>, which is the version that we include in our anthology, Keats puts the phrase "Beauty is truth, truth beauty" in quotation marks, which makes it seem as though the speaker of the line might be the urn itself. But in the version that he published in the journal <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/keats-grecian/pageImages/annals.png"/><hi rend="italic">Annals of the Fine Arts</hi> in 1819 (depicted here), Keats did not, which makes it seem as if the speaker is the voice of the poet himself. Neither version is better or more authentic than the other; Keats never explained the why he added the quotation marks in 1820. But how we think about the poem can be quite different depending on which version of this closing couplet we are reading.</note>--that is all</l>
   <l n="48">Ye know on earth, and all ye need to know.</l></lg>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
