<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="edwards-sinners">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God: A Sermon Preached at Enfield, July 8, 1741,
                    at a Time of Great Awakenings, and Attended With Remarkable Impressions on Many of the Hearers</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79084179">\
                        <name>
                            <forename>Jonathan</forename>
                            <surname>Edwards</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
                            <forename>Tonya</forename>
                            <surname>Howe</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#UVAstudentsstaff">Students and Staff of The University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#VBS">Veronica Scott</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder />
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>                    
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God: A Sermon Preached at Enfield, July 8, 1741,
                            at a Time of Great Awakenings, and Attended With Remarkable Impressions on Many of the Hearers"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79084179">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Jonathan</forename>
                                    <surname>Edwards</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God: A Sermon Preached at Enfield, July 8, 1741,
                            at a Time of Great Awakenings, and Attended With Remarkable Impressions on Many of the Hearers</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>S. Kneeland and T. Green</publisher>
                            <date when="1741">1741</date>
                            <note>
                                The text for this digital editon was drawn from the 1741 published copy of the sermon from University of Nebraska's digital edition
                                <ref target="https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1053&amp;context=etas">https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1053&amp;context=etas</ref>
                                and check against the original found in Gale Primary Sources: Eighteenth Century Collections Online
                                <ref target="link.gale.com/apps/doc/CB0127258113/ECCO?u=viva_uva&amp;sid=bookmark-ECCO&amp;xid=f6dad230&amp;pg=1">
                                    link.gale.com/apps/doc/CB0127258113/ECCO?u=viva_uva&amp;sid=bookmark-ECCO&amp;xid=f6dad230&amp;pg=1</ref>
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
                            <date>n.d.</date>
                            <note>Base text for this digital edition has been drawn from Project Gutenberg
                                <ref target="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/43/43-h/43-h.htm">https://www.gutenberg.org/files/43/43-h/43-h.htm</ref>.
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="sermon">
                <channel mode="ws">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain />
                <factuality type="inapplicable"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="scripted"/>
                <purpose type="persuade" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting/>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the project Early American Fiction at the University
                    of Virginia Library. Sponsored by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation and
                    the University of Virginia.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p> Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.
                    </p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="gsafd">
                    <bibl>Guidelines on Subject Access to Individual Works of Fiction, Drama, Etc.</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="uva-etc">
                    <bibl>UVa Electronic Text Center Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-06" who="editors.xml#VBS">Initial XML file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-1.png"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart>
                        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Edwards's</hi>
                        <lb/>SERMON
                        <lb/>On the Danger of the
                        <lb/>UNCONVERTED.
                    </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor />
            </titlePage>
            <div type="contents">
                <pb n="2" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-2.png"/>
                <p>
                    SINNERS
                    <lb/>In the Hands of an
                    <lb/>Angry GOD.
                    <lb/>A SERMON
                    <lb/>Preached at <hi rend="italic">Enfield, July</hi> 8th 1741.
                    <lb/>At a Time of great Awakenings; at attended with<lb/>remarkable Impressions on many of the Hearers.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <lb/>By <hi rend="italic">Jonathan Edwards,</hi> A.M.
                    <lb/>Pastor of the Church of <hi rend="small-caps">Christ</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Northampton.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Amos ix. 2, 3. <hi rend="italc">Though they dig into Hell, thence shall mine Hand take them; though they climb up to Heaven, thence
                    will I bring them down. And though they hide themselves in the Top of Carmel, I will search and them them out thence;
                    and though they be hid from my Sight in the Bottom of the Sea, thence I will command the Serpent, and he
                    shall bite them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">BOSTON</hi>: Printed and Sold by S.<hi rend="small-caps">Kneeland</hi> and T. <hi rend="small-caps">Green</hi>
                    in Queen-Street over against the Prision. 1741.
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="3" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-3.png"/>
            <p>
                Sinners in the Hands of an angry GOD.
            </p>
            <p>
                DEUT. XXXII 35.
            </p>
            <p>
                --<hi rend="italic">Their Foot shall slide in due Time.</hi>--
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">I</hi>N this Verse is threatned the Vengeance of God on the wicked unbeliving Isralites,
                that were God's visible People, and lived under Means of Grace; and that, notwithstanding all God's wonderful Works
                that he had wrought towards that People, yet remained, as is expressed, <hi rend="italic">ver.</hi> 28. void of Counsel,
                having no Understanding in them; and that, under all the Cultivations of Heaven, brought forth bitter and poisonous Fruit;
                as in the two Verses next preceeding the Text.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Expression that I have chosen for my Text, <hi rend="italic">Their Foot shall slide in due Time;</hi> seems
                to imply the following Things, relating to the Punishment and Destruction that these wicked Israelites were exposed to.
            </p>
            <p>
                1. That<pb n="4" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-4.png"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                1. That they were <hi rend="italic">always</hi> exposed to Destruction, as one that stands or walks in slippery Places is always
                exposed to fall. This is implied in the Manner of their Destruction's coming upon them, being represented by their Foot's sliding.
                The same is express'd, <ref target="_psal" corresp="psal">Psal</ref><note target="_psal" xml:id="psal" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#VBS">Short form of the the book Psal of the Bible</note>.
                23.18 <hi rend="italic">Surely thou didst set them in slippery Places; thou castedst them down into Destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                2. It implies that they were always exposed to <hi rend="italic">sudden</hi> unexpected Destruction. As he that walks in slippery Places
                is every Moment liable to fall; he can't forsee one Moment whether he shall stand or fall the next; and when he does fall,
                he falls at once, without Warning. Which is also expressed in that, Psal. 73.18.19. <hi rend="italic">Surely thou didst set them
                in slippery Places; thou castdest them down into Destruction. How are they brought into Desolation as in a Moment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                3. Another Thing implied is that they are liable to fall <hi rend="italic">of themselves,</hi> without being thrown down by the Hand of
                another. As he that stands or walks on slippery Ground, needs nothing but his own Weight to throw him down.
            </p>
            <p>
                4. That the Reason why they are not fallen already, and don't fall now, is only that God's appointed Time is not come. For it is said,
                that when that due Time, or appointed Time comes, <hi rend="italic">their Foot shall slide.</hi> Then they shall be left to fall
                as they are inclined by their own Weight. God won't hold them up in these slippery Places any longer, but will let them go; and then, at that very
                Instant, they shall fall into Destruction; as he that stands in such slippery declining Ground on the Edge of a Pit that
                he can't stand alone, when he is let go he immediately falls and is lost.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Observation from the Words that I would now insist upon is this,
                <lb/>
                <hi rend="italic">There</hi><pb n="5" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-5.png"/>
                <hi rend="italic">There is nothing that keeps wicked Men at any one
                Moment, out of Hell, but the meer Pleasure of GOD.</hi>
                <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                By the meer Pleasure of God, I mean his sovereign Pleasure, his arbitrary Will, restrained by no Obligation,
                hinder'd by no manner of Difficulty, any more than if nothing else but God's meer Will had in the least Degree, or in any Respect
                whatsoever, any Hand in the Preservation of wicked Men one Moment.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Truth of this Observation may appear by the following Considerations.
            </p>
            <p>
                I. There is no Want of <hi rend="italic">Power</hi> in God to cast wicked Men into Hell at any Moment. Mens Hands can't be strong
                when God rises up: The strongest have no Power to resist him, nor can any deliver out of this Hands.
            </p>
            <p>
                He is not only able to cast wicked Men into Hell, but he can most <hi rend="italic">easily</hi> do it. Sometimes an earthy Prince
                meets with a great deal of Difficulty to subdue a Rebel, that has found Means to fortify himself, and has made himself strong by the Numbers
                of his Followers. But it is not so with God. There is no Fortress that is any Defence from the Power of God. Tho' Hand join in Hand,
                and vast Multitudes of God's Enemies combine and associate themselves they are easily broken in Pieces: They are as great Heaps of light Chaff before
                the Whirlwind; or large Quantities of dry Stubble before devouring Flames. We find it easy to tread on and crush a Worm that we see crawling on
                the Earth; so 'tis easy for us to cut or singe a slender Thread that any Thing hangs by; thus easy is it for God when he pleases to cast his Enemies
                down to Hell. What are we, that we should think to stand before him, at whose Rebuke<lb/>the<pb n="6" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-6.png"/>
                the Earth trembles, and before whom the ROcks are thrown down?
            </p>
            <p>
                2. They <hi rend="italic">deserve</hi> to be cast into Hell; so that divine Justice never stands in the Way, it makes
                no Objection against God's using his Power at any Moment to destroy them. Yea, on the contrary, Justice calls aloud for an infinite Punishment of their
                Sins. Divine Justice says of the Tree that brings forth such Grapes of Sodom, <hi rend="italic">Cut it down, why <ref target="_cumbreth" corresp="cumbreth">cumbreth</ref>
                <note target="_cumbreth" xml:id="cumbreth" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">To occupy obstructively, or inconveniently;
                to block up or fill with what hinders freedom of motion or action; to burden, load. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> it the Ground,</hi> <ref target="_luk" corresp="luk">Luk</ref>
                <note target="_luk" xml:id="luk" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#VBS">An abbreviation of the Bible book Luke</note>. 13.7.
                The Sword of divine Justice is every Moment brandished over their Heads, and 'tis nothing but the Hand of arbitrary Mercy, and God's meer
                Will, that holds it back.
            </p>
            <p>
                3. They are <hi rend="italic">already</hi> under a Sentence of Condemnation to Hell. They don't only justly deserve to be
                cast down thither; but the Sentence of the Law of God, that eternal and immutable Rule of Righteousness that God has fixed between him and Mankind,
                is gone out against them, and stands against them; so that they are bound over already to Hell. <ref target="_joh" corresp="joh">Joh</ref>
                <note target="_joh" xml:id="joh" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#VBS">An abbreviation of the Bible book John</note>. 3.18. <hi rend="italic">
                He that believeth not is condemned already.</hi> So that every unconverted Man properly belongs to Hell; that is his Place;
                from thence he is. Joh. 8.23. <hi rend="italic">Ye are from beneath.</hi> And <ref target="_thither" corresp="thither">thither</ref>
                <note target="_thither" xml:id="thither" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">To or towards that place. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> he is bound; 'tis the Place that Justice,
                and God's Word, and the Sentence of his unchangeable Law assigns to him.
            </p>
            <p>
                They are now the Objects of that very <hi rend="italic">same</hi> Anger&amp;Wrath of God that is expressed in the Torments
                of Hell: and the Reason why they don't go down to Hell at each Moment, is not because God, in whose Power they are, is not then
                very angry with them; as angry as he is with many of those miserable Creatures that he is now tormenting in Hell, and do there feel
                and bear the fierceness of his Wrath. Yea God is a great deal more angry with great Numbers that<lb/>are<pb n="7" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-7.png"/>are now on Earth, yea doubtless with
                many that are now in this Congregation, that it may be are at Ease and Quiet, than he is with many of those that are now in
                the Flames of Hell.
            </p>
            <p>
                So that it is not because God is unmindful of their Wickedness, and don't resent it, that he don't let loose his Hand
                and cut them off. God is not altogether such an one as themselves, tho' they may imagine him to be so. The Wrath of God burns against them,
                their Damnation don't slumber, the Pit is prepared, the Fire is made ready, the Furnace is now hot, ready to receive them, the Flames
                do now rage and glow. The glittering Sword is <ref corresp="whet" target="_whet">whet</ref><note target="_whet" xml:id="whet" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">
                In allusive and figurative phrases usually expressing preparation for attack. Source: Oxford English Dictionary   
                </note>, and held over them, and the Pit hath opened her Mouth under them.
            </p>
            <p>
                5. The <hi rend="italic">Devil</hi> stands ready to fall upon them and seize them as his own, at what Moment God shall permit him.
                They belong to him; he has their Souls in his Possession, and under his Dominion. The Scripture represents them as his <hi rend="italic">Goods</hi>,
                Luk. 11.21. The Devils watch them; they are every by them, at their right Hand; they stand waiting for them, like greedy hungry Lions that see their Prey,
                and expect to have it, but are for the present kept back, if God should withdraw his Hand, by which they are restrained, they would in one Moment fly
                upon their poor Souls. The old serpent is gaping for them; Hell opens its Mouth wide to receive them; and if God should permit it, they would be hastily
                swallowed up and lost.
            </p>
            <p>
                6. There are in the Souls of wicked Men those hellish <hi rend="italic">Principles</hi> reigning, that would presently kindle and flame out into Hell Fire,
                if it were not for God's Restraints. There is laid in the very Nature of <ref target="_carnal" corresp="carnal">carnal</ref><note target="_carnal" xml:id="carnal" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">
                Of or pertaining to the flesh or body; bodily, corporeal. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Men a Foundation for the Torments of Hell. There
                are those corrupt Principles, in regning Power in them, and in full Possession of them, that are Seeds of Hell <lb/> Fire.<pb n="8" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-8.png"/>
                Fire. These Principles are active and powerful, and exceeding violent in their Nature, and if it were not for the restraning Hand of God upon them, they would
                soon break out, they would flame out after the same Manner as the same Corruptions, the same Enmity does in the Hearts of damned Souls, and would beget the
                same Torments in 'em as they do in them. The Souls of the Wicked are in Scripture compared to the troubled Sea, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="_isai" corresp="isai">Isai</ref>
                <note target="_isai" xml:id="isai" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="editorial">Isai is an abbreviation of Isaiah, a book in the Bible.</note>. 57.20</hi>. For the present
                God restrains their Wickedness by his mighty Power, as he does the raging Waves of the troubled Sea, saying, <hi rend="italic">Hitherto shalt
                thou come, and no further;</hi> but if God should withdraw that restraining Power, it would soon carry all afore it. Sin is the Ruin and Misery of the Soul;
                it is destructive in it's Nature; and if God should leave it without Restraint, there would need nothing else to make the Soul perfectly miserable. The Corruption
                of the Heart of Man is a Thing that is immoderate and boundless in its Fury; and while wicked Men live here, it is like Fire pent up by God's Restraints,
                whenas if it were let loose it would set on Fire the Course of Nature; and as the Heart is now a Sink of Sin, so, if Sin was not restrain'd, it would immediately turn the Soul
                into a fiery Oven, or a Furnace of Fire and Brimstone.
            </p>
            <p>
                7. It is no Security to wicked Men for one Moment, that there are no <hi rend="italic">visible Means of Death</hi> at Hand.
                'Tis no Security to a natural Man, that he is now in Health, and that he don't see which Way he should now immediately go out
                of the World by any Accident, and that there is no visible Danger in any Respect in his Circumstances. The manifold and continual Experience
                of the World in all Ages, shews that this is no Evidence that a Man is not on the very Brink of Eternity, and that the next Step won't be in-<lb/>to<pb n="9" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-9.png"/>to
                another World. The unseen, unthought of Ways and Means of Persons going suddenly out of the World are innumerable and inconceivable. Unconverted Men walk over the Pit of Hell
                on a rotten Covering, and there are innumerable Places in this Covering so weak that they won't bear their Weight, and these Places
                are not seen. The Arrows of Death fly unseen at Noon-Day; the sharpest Sight can't discern them. God has so many different unsearchable Ways of taking
                wicked Men out of the World and sending 'em to Hell, that there is nothing to make it appear that God had need to be at the Expence of a Miracle, or go
                out of the ordinary Course of his Providence, to destroy any wicked Man, at any Moment. All the Means that there are of Sinners going out of the World, are
                so in God's Hands, and so universally absolutely subject to his Power and Determination, that it don't depend at all less on the meer Will of God,
                whether Sinners shall at any Moment go to Hell, than if Means were never made use of, or at all concerned in the Case.
            </p>
            <p>
                8. Natural Men's <hi rend="italic">Prudence</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Care</hi> to preserve their own <hi rend="italic">Lives,</hi> or the Care of others to preserve
                them, don't secure 'em a Moment. This divine Providence and universal Experience does also bear Testimony to. There is this clear Evidence that Men's
                own Wisdom is no Security to them from Death; That if it were otherwise we should see some Difference between the wife and politick Men of the World,
                and others, with Regard to their Liableness to early and unexpected Death; but how is it in Fact? <ref target="_eccles" corresp="eccles">Eccles</ref>
                <note target="_eccles" xml:id="eccles" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="editorial">Eccles is an abbreviation of Ecclesiastes, a book in the Bible.</note>. 2.16.
                <hi rend="italic">How dieth the wise Man? as the Fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                9. All wicked Men's <hi rend="italic">Pains</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Contrivance</hi> they use to escape <hi rend="italic">Hell,</hi> while
                they continue to reject Christ, and so remain wicked Men, don't secure 'em from Hell one Moment. Almost every natural Man that<lb/>hears<pb n="10" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-10.png"/>hears
                of Hell, flatters himself that the shall escape it; he depends upon himself for his own Security; he flatters himself in what he has done,
                in what he is now doing, or what he intends to do; every one lays out Matters in his own Mind how he shall avoid Damnation, and flatters himself that he
                contrives well for himself, and that his Schemes won't fail. They hear indeed that there are but few saved, and that the bigger Part of Men that have died heretofore are
                gone to Hell; but each one imagines that he lay out Matters better for his own escape than others have done: He don't intend to come to that Place of Torment; he says
                within himself, that he intends to take Care that shall be <ref target="_effectual" corresp="effectual">effectual</ref>
                <note target="_effectual" xml:id="effectual" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">Powerful in effect, having powerful effects.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and to order Matters so for himself as not to fail.
            </p>
            <p>
                But the foolish Children of Men do miserably delude themselves in their own Schemes, and in their Confidence in their own Strength and Wisdom;
                they trust to nothing but a Shadow. The bigger Part of those that heretofore have lived under the same Means of Grace, and are now dead, are undoubtedly gone
                to Hell: and it was not because they were not as wise as those that are now alive: it was not because they did not lay out Matters as well for themselves to secure
                their own escape. If it were so, that we could come to speak with them, and could inquire of them, one by one, whether they expected when alive,
                and when they used to hear about Hell, ever to be the Subjects of that Misery, we doubtless should hear one and another reply,<lb/>
                <!-- TODO: Figure out format for bullet points -->
                <quote>No, I never intended to come here; I had laid out Matters otherwise in my Mind; I thought I should contrive well for my self;
                I thought my Scheme good; I intended to take effectual Care; but it came upon me unexpected; I did <ref target="_not-not" corresp="not-not">not not</ref>
                    <note target="_not-not" xml:id="not-not" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#VBS">The use of the double negative was to intensify the negation, not to create
                a positive.</note> look for it at that Time, and in that Manner;
                    it came as a <lb/>Thief;<pb n="11" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-11.png"/>Thief; Death outwitted me; God's Wrath was too quick for me; O my cursed Foolishness!
                I was flattering my self, and pleasing my self with vain. Dreams of what I would do hereafter, and when I was saying Peace and Safety, then
                sudden Destruction came upon me.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>
                10. God has laid himself under <hi rend="italic">no Obligation</hi> by any Promise to keep any natural Man out of Hell one Moment. God certainly has
                made no Promises either of eternal Life, or of any Deliverance or Preservation from eternal Death, but what are contained in the <ref target="_covenant" corresp="covenant">Covenant</ref>
                <note xml:id="covenant" target="_covenant" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">Applied esp. to an engagement entered into by the Divine Being with some other being or persons.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>of Grace,
                the Promises that are given in Christ, in whom all the Promises are Yea and Amen. But surely they have no Interest in the Promises of the Convenant of Grace
                that are not the Children of the Covenant, and that don't believe in any of the Promises of the Covenant, and have no Interest in the <hi rend="italic">Mediator</hi>
                of the Covenant.
            </p>
            <p>
                So that whatever some have imagined and pretended about Promises made to natural Men's earnest seeking and knocking,
                'tis plain and manifest that whatever Pains a natural Man takes in Religion, whatever Prayers he makes, till he
                believes in Christ, God is under no manner of Obligation to keep him a <hi rend="italic">Moment</hi> from eternal Destruction.
            </p>
            <p>
                So that thus it is, that natural Men are held in the Hand of God over the Pit of Hell; they have deserved the fiery Pit, and
                are already sentenced to it; and God is dreadfully provoked, his Anger is as great towards them as to those that are
                actually suffering the Executions of the fierceness of his Wrath in Hell, and they have done nothing in the least to appease
                or abate that Anger, neither is God in the least bound by any Promise to hold 'em up one moment; the Devil is waiting for them,
                Hell is gaping for them, the Flames <lb/>gather<pb n="12" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-12.png"/>gather and flash about them, and would fain lay hold on them,
                and swallow them up; the Fire pent up in their own Hearts is struggling to break out; and they have no Interest in any Mediator, there are no
                Means within Reach that can be any Security to them. In short, they have no Refuge, nothing to take hold of
                all that preserves them every Moment is the meer arbitrary Will, and uncovenanted unobliged Forbearance of an incensed God.
            </p>
            <head type="sub">APPLICATION</head>
            <p>
                The Use may be of <hi rend="italic">Awakening</hi> to unconverted Persons in this Congregation. This that you have heard is the Case of
                every one of you that are out of Christ. That World of Misery, that Lake of burning dreadful Pit of the glowing Flames of the Wrath of God; there is Hell's wide gaping Mouth open;
                and you have nothing to stand upon, nor any Thing to take hold of: there is nothing between you and Hell but the Air; 'tis
                only the Power and meer Pleasure of God that holds you up.
            </p>
            <p>
                You probably are not sensible of this; you find you are kept out of Hell, but don't see the Hand of God in it, but look at other Things,
                as the good State of your bodily Constitution, your Care of your own Life, and the Means you sue for your own Preservation. But indeed these Things
                are nothing; if God should withdraw his Hand, they would avail no more to keep you from falling, than the thin Air to hold up a Person that is suspended in it.
            </p>
            <p>
                Your Wickedness makes you as it were heavy as Lead and tend downwards with great Weight and Pressure towards Hell; and if God should let you go, you would
                immediately sink and swiftly descend &amp; plunge<lb/>into<pb n="13" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-13.png"/>into the bottomless Gulf, and your healthy Constitution, and your own Care
                and Prudence, and best Contrivance, and all your Righteousness, would have no more Influence to uphold your and keep you out of Hell,
                than a Spider's Web would have to stop a falling Rock. Were it not that so is the sovereign Pleasure of God, the Earth would not bear you one Moment;
                for you are a Burden to it; the Creation groans with you; the Creature is made Subject to the Bondage of your Corruption, not willingly;
                the Sun don't willingly shine upon you to give you Light to serve Sin and Satan; the Earth don't willingly yield her Increase to
                satisfy your Lusts; nor is it willingly a Stage for your Wickedness to be acted upon; the Air don't willingly serve you for Breath to maintain the Flame
                of Life in your Vitals, while you spend your Life in the Service of God's Enemies. God's Creatures are Good, and were made for Men to serve God
                with, and don't willingly subserve to any other Purpose, and groan when they are abused to Purposes so directly contrary to their Nature and End. And the World would
                <ref target="_spue" corresp="spue">spue</ref><note target="_spue" xml:id="spue" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">An archaic spelling of "spew".
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> you out, were it not for the soverign Hand of him who hath subjected it in Hope. There are the black Clouds of
                God's Wrath now hanging directly over your Heads, full of the dreadful Storm, and big with Thunder; and were it not for the restraining Hand of God
                it would immediately burst forth upon you. The sovereign Pleasure of God for the present stays his rough Wind; otherwise
                it would come with Fury, and your Destruction would come like a Whirlwind, and you would be like the Chaff of the Summer
                <ref target="_threshing" corresp="threshing">threshing</ref><note target="_threshing" xml:id="threshing" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">To separate the grain of a cereal crop from the husks and straw, and related senses. Source: Oxford English Dictionary   
                </note> Floor.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Wrath of God is like great Waters that are dammed for the present; they increase more and more, &amp; rise higher and higher,
                till an Outlet is given, and the lon<lb/>ger<pb n="14" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-14.png"/>ger the Stream is stop'd, the more rapid and mighty is it's Course, when once it is let loose.
                'Tis true, that Judgment against your evil Works has not been executed hitherto; the Floods of God's Vengeance have been with-held; but your Guilt in the mean Time is constantly
                increasing, and you are every Day treasuring up more Wrath; the Waters are continually rising and waxing more and more mighty; and there is nothing but
                the meer Pleasure of God that holds the Waters back that are unwilling to be stopped, and press hard to go forward; if God should only withdraw
                his Hand from the Flood-Gate, it would immediately fly open, and the fiery Floods of the Fierceness and Wrath of God would rush forth with inconceivable
                Fury, and would come upon you with omnipotent Power; and if your Strength were ten thousand Times greater than it is, yea ten thousand Times greater than the Strength of
                the stoutest, sturdiest Devil in Hell, it would be nothing to withstand or endure it.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Bow of God's Wrath is bent, and the Arrow made ready on the String, and Justice bends the Arrow at your Heart, and strains the Bow, and is nothing but the
                meer Pleasure of God, and that an angry God, without any Promise or Obligation at all, that keeps the Arrow one Moment from being made drunk with your Blood.
            </p>
            <p>
                Thus are all you that never passed under a great Change of Heart, by the mighty Power of the <hi rend="small-caps">Spirit</hi> of GOD upon your Souls;
                all that were never born again, to a State of new, and before althogether unexperienced Light and Life, (however you may have reformed your Life
                in many Things, and may have had religious Affections, and may keep up a Form of Religion in your Families and Closets, and in the House<lb/>of<pb n="15" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-15.png"/>of
                God, and may be strict in it,) you are thus in the Hands of an angry God; 'tis nothing but his meer Pleasure that keeps you from
                being this Moment swallowed up in everlasting Destruction.
            </p>
            <p>
                However unconvinced you may now be of the Truth of what you hear, by &amp; by you will be fully convinced of it. Those
                that are gone from being in the like Circumstances with you, see that it was so with them; for Destruction came suddenly upon most of them, when they expected nothing of it,
                and while they were saying, <hi rend="italic">Peace and Safety</hi>: Now they see, that those Things that they depended on for Peace and Safety,
                were nothing but thin Air and empty Shadows.
            </p>
            <p>
                The God that holds you over the Pit of Hell, much as one holds a Spider, or some loathsome Insect, over the Fire, abhors you, and is dreadfully
                provoked; his Wrath towards you burns like Fire; he looks upon you as worthy of nothing else, but to be cast into the Fire; he is of purer Eyes than to bear
                to have you in his Sight; you are ten thousand Times so abominable in this Eyes as the most hateful venomous Serpent is in ours. You have offended him infinitely
                more than ever a stubborn Rebel did his Prince: and yet 'tis nothing but his Hand that holds you from falling into the Fire every Moment: 'Tis to be ascribed to nothing else,
                that you did not go to Hell the last Night; that you was suffer'd to awake again in this World, after you closed your Eyes to sleep: and there is no other
                Reason to be given why you have not dropped into Hell since you arose in the Morning, but that God's Hand has held you up: There is no other Reason to be
                given why you han't gone to Hell since you have sat here in the House of God, provoking his pure Eyes by your sinful wicked Manner of attending<lb/>his<pb n="16" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-16.png"/>his
                solemn Worship: Yea, there is nothing else that is to be given as a Reason why you don't this very Moment drop down into Hell.
            </p>
            <p>
                O Sinner! Consider the fearful Danger you are in: 'Tis a great Furnace of Wrath, a wide and bottomless Pit, full of the Fire Wrath, that you are
                held over in the Hand of that God, whose Wrath is provoked and incensed as much against you as against many of the Damned in Hell: You hang by a slender Thread, with the
                Flames of divine Wrath flashing about it, and ready every Moment to singe it, and burn it asunder; and you have no Interest in any Mediator, and nothing to 
                lay hold of to save yourself, nothing to keep off the Flames of Wrath, nothing of your own, nothing that you ever have done, nothing that you can do, to induce
                God to spare you one Moment.
            </p>
            <p>
                1. <hi rend="italic">Whose</hi> Wrath it is: It is the Wrath of the Infinite GOD. If it were only the Wrath of Man, tho' it were of the most
                potent Prince, it would be comparatively little to be regarded. The Wrath of Kings is very much dreaded, specially of absolute Monarchs, that
                have the Possessions and Lives of their Subjects wholly in their Power, to be disposed of at their meer Will. <ref target="_prov" corresp="prov">Prov</ref>
                <note target="_prov" xml:id="prov" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="editorial">Prov. is an abbreviation of Proverbs, a book in the Bible.</note>. 20.2 <hi rend="italic">The Fear of a
                King is as the Roaring of a Lion: who so provoketh him to Anger, sinneth against his own Soul.</hi> The Subject that very much enrages an
                arbitrary Prince, is liable to suffer the most extream Torments, that human Art can invent or human Power can inflict. But the greatest earthy Potentates,
                in their greatest Majesty and Strength, and when cloathed in their greatest Terrors, are but feeble despicable Worms of the Dust, in Comparison
                of the great and almighty Creator and King of Heaven and<lb/>Earth:<pb n="17" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-17.png"/>Earth: It is but little that they can do, when
                most enraged, and when they have exerted the utmost of their Fury. All the Kings of the Earth before GOD are as Grashoppers, they are nothing and less than nothing:
                Both their Love and their Hatred is to be despised. The Wrath of the great King of Kings is as much more terrible than their's, as his Majesty is
                greater. Luke 12.4,5. <hi rend="italic">And I say unto you my Friends, be not afraid of them that kill the Body, and after that have no more that they can do:
                But I will forewarn you whom ye shall fear; fear him, which after he hath killed, hath Power to cast into Hell; yea I say unto you, fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                2. 'Tis the <hi rend="italic">Fierceness</hi> of his Wrath that you are exposed to. We often read of the <hi rend="italic">Fury</hi>
                of God; as in Isai. 59. 18. <hi rend="italic">According to their Deeds, accordingly he will repay Fury to his Adversaries</hi> So Isai. 66. 15.
                <hi rend="italic">For behold, the Lord will come with Fire, and with Chariots like a Whirlwind, to render his Anger with Fury,
                and his Rebukes with Flames of Fire.</hi> And so in many other Places. So we read of God's <hi rend="italic">Firecenses</hi>. <ref target="_rev" corresp="rev">Rev</ref>
                <note target="_rev" xml:id="rev" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="editorial">Rev. is an abbreviation of the Book of Revelation in the Bible</note>. 19.15. There we read of
                <hi rend="italic">the Winepress of the Fierceness and Wrath of Almighty God.</hi> The Words are exceeding terrible: if it had only said,
                <hi rend="italic">the Wrath of God</hi>, the Words would have implied that which is infinitely dreadful: But 'tis not only said so, but <hi rend="italic">the
                Fierceness and Wrath of God:</hi> the Fury of God! the Fierceness of Jehovah! Oh how dreadful must that be! Who can utter or conceive what such
                Expressions carry in them! But it is not only said so, but <hi rend="italic">the Fierceness and Wrath of ALMIGHTY GOD.</hi>
                As tho' there would be a very great Manifestation of this almighty Power, in what the fierceness of his Wrath should inflict,
                as tho' Omnipotence should be as it were enraged, and exerted, as Men are wont to exert<lb/>their<pb n="18" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-18.png"/>their Strength in the fierceness
                of their Wrath. Oh! then what will be the Consequence! What will become of the poor Worm that shall suffer it! Whose Hands can be strong? and whose Heart endure?
                To what a dreadful, inexpressible, inconceivable Depth of Misery must the poor Creature be sunk, who shall be the Subject of this!
            </p>
            <p>
                Consider this, you that are here present, that yet remain in an <ref target="_unregenerate" corresp="unregenerate">unregenerate</ref>
                <note target="_unregenerate" xml:id="unregenerate" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">  Not reformed, spiritually or (now usually) morally or intellectually.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> State. That God will execute the fierceness of his Anger, implies that he will inflict
                Wrath without any Pity: when God beholds the ineffable Extremity of your Case, and sees your Torment to be so vastly disproportion'd to
                your Strength, and sees how your poor Soul is crushed and sinks down, as it were into an infinite Gloom, he will have no Compassion upon,
                he will not forbear the Executions of his Wrath, or in the least lighten his Hand; there shall be no Moderation or Mercy, nor will God then
                at all stay his rough Wind; he will have no Regard to your Welfare, nor be at all careful lest you should suffer too much, in any
                other Sense than only that shall not suffer beyond what strict Justice requires: nothing shall be with-held, because it's so
                hard for you to bear. Ezek. 8. 18. <hi rend="italic">Therefore will I also deal in Fury; mine Eye shall not spare,
                neither will I have Pity; and tho' they cry in mine Ears with a loud Voice, yet I will not hear them.</hi> Now God stands
                ready to pity you; this is a Day of Mercy; you may cry now with some Encouragement of obtaining Mercy: but when
                once the Day of Mercy is past, your most lamentable and dolorous Cries and Shrieks will be in vain; you will be wholly lost and thrown away of God
                as to any Regard to your Welfare; God will have no other Use to put you to but only to suffer Misery; you shall be continued in Being to no
                other<lb/>End;<pb n="19" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-19.png"/>End; for you will be a Vessel of Wrath fitted to Destruction; and there will be no other Use of this Vessel
                but only to be filled full of Wrath: God will be so far from pitying you when you cry to him, that 'tis said he will only said
                he will only <hi rend="italic">Laugh and Mock,</hi> Prov. 1. 25, 26, &amp;c.
            </p>
            <p>
                How awful are those Words, Isai. 63.3. which are the Words of the great God, <hi rend="italic">I will tread them in mine
                Anger, and will trample them in my Fury, and their Blood shall be sprinkled upon my Garments, and I will stain all my 
                <ref target="_raiment" corresp="raiment">Raiment</ref><note target="_raiment" xml:id="raiment" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">
                An article of clothing or adornment, a garment; an outfit. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>.</hi> 'Tis perhaps impossible to conceive of
                Words that carry in them greater Manifestations of these three Things, <hi><ref corresp="viz" target="_viz">viz</ref>
                <note xml:id="viz" type="gloss" target="_viz" resp="editors.xml#VBS">An abbreviation of videlicet meaning that is to say; namely; to wit: used to introduce an
                amplification, or more precise or explicit explanation, of a previous statement or word. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>.</hi>
                Contempt, and Hatred, and fierceness of <ref target="_indignation" corresp="indignation">Indignation</ref><note target="_indignation" xml:id="indignation" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">
                The wrath of a superior. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>.
                If you cry to God to pity you, he will be so far from pitying you in your <ref target="_doleful" corresp="doleful">doleful</ref>
                <note target="_doleful" xml:id="doleful" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">Full of pain, grief, or suffering; sorrowful, sad.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Case, or shewing you the least Regard or Favour, that instead of
                that he'll only tread you under Foot: And tho' he will know that you can't bear the Weight of Omnipotence treading upon you, yet he won't
                regard that, but he will crush you under his Feet without Mercy; he'll crush out your Blood, and make it fly, and it shall be sprinkled on his Garments,
                so as to stain all his Raiment. He will not only hate you, but he will have you in the utmost Contempt no Place shall be
                thought fit for you, but under his Feet, to be trodden down as the <ref target="_mire" corresp="mire">Mire</ref>
                <note target="_mire" xml:id="mire" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="gloss">
                An undesirable state or condition (formerly esp. of sin or moral degradation) from which it is difficult to extricate oneself.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of the Streets.
            </p>
            <p> <!-- TODO: Pick up from here -->
                3. The Misery you are exposed to is that which God will inflict to that End, that he might <hi rend="italic">shew</hi> what that <hi rend="italic">Wrath</hi> of <hi rend="small-caps">Jehova</hi> is. God
                hath had it on his Heart to shew to Angles and Men, both <ref target="_shew" corresp="shew">shew</ref><note target="_shew" xml:id="shew" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">Archaic form of "show".
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> how terrible <hi rend="italic">their</hi> Wrath is, by the extream Punishments they would
                execute on those that provoke 'em, <hi rend="italic">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>, that mighty and haughty Monarch<lb/>of<pb n="20" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-20.png"/>of the <hi rend="italic">Chadlean</hi> Empire,
                was willing to shew <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Wrath, when enraged with <hi rend="italic">Sadrach, Meshech,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Abednego</hi>;
                and accordingly gave Order that the burning fiery Furnace should be <ref corresp="het" target="_het">het</ref><note target="_het" xml:id="het" type="gloss" resp="editor.xml#VBS">
                Heated. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> seven Times hotter than it was before; doubtless it was raised to the utmost Degree of
                Fierceness that humane Art could raise it: But the great GOD is also willing to shew <hi rend="italic">his Wrath,</hi> and magnify his awful Majesty and mighty
                Power in the extream Sufferings of his Enemies <ref target="_rom" corresp="rom">Rom</ref><note target="_rom" xml:id="rom" resp="editors.xml#VBS" type="editoral">
                Rom. is short for the book of Romans in the Bible.</note>. 9. 22. <hi rend="italic">What if God willing to shew HIS
                Wrath, and to make his Power known, endured with much Long-suffering the Vessels of Wrath fitted to Destruction?</hi>
                And feeling this is his Design, and what he has determined, to shew how terrible the unmixed unrestrained Wrath, the Fury and Fierceness
                of <hi rend="small-caps">Jehova</hi> is, he will do it to Effect. There will be something accomplished and brought to pass, that will be
                dreadful with a Witness. When the great and angry God hath risen up and executed his awful Vengeance on
                the poor Sinner; and the Wretch is actually suffering the infinite Weight and Power of his Indignation,
                then will God call upon the whole Universe to behold that awful Majesty, and mighty Power that is to be seen it it.
                Isai. 33.12, 13, 14. <hi rend="italic">And the People shall be as the burning of Lime, as Thorns cut up shall they be burnt in the Fire.
                Hear ye that are far off what I have done; and ye that are near acknowledge my Might. The Sinners in <ref target="_zion" corresp="zion">Zion</ref>
                <note target="_zion" xml:id="zion" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">A biblical name for: the city of Jerusalem; (hence) the land of Israel.
                Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> are afraid, fearfulness hath surprized
                the Hypocrites &amp; c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                Thus it will be with you that are in an unconverted State, if you continue in it; the infinite Might, and Majesty
                and Terribleness of the <hi rend="small-caps">Omnipotent</hi> GOD shall be magnified upon you, in the
                <ref corresp="ineffable" target="_ineffable">ineffable</ref><note target="_ineffable" xml:id="ineffable" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">
                That cannot be expressed or described in language; too great for words. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> strength
                of your Torments: You shall be tormented in the Presence of the holy Angels, and in the Presence of<lb/>the<pb n="21" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-21.png"/>the
                Lamb; and when you shall be in this State of Suffering, the glorious Inhabitants of Heaven shall go forth and look on the awful Spectacle,
                that they may see what the Wrath and Fierceness of the Almighty is, and when they have seen it, they will fall down and
                adore that great Power and Majesty. Isai. 66.23, 24. <hi rend="italic">And it shall come to pass, that from one new Moon to another,
                and from one Sabbath to another, shall all Flesh come to Worship before me, saith the Lord; and they shall go forth and look upon
                the Carcasses of the Men that have transgressed against me; for their Worm shall not die, neither shall their Fire be quenched, and they shall
                be an abhorring unto all Flesh.</hi>
            </p>  
            <p>
                4. 'Tis <hi rend="italic">everlasting</hi> Wrath. It would be dreadful to suffer this Fierceness and Wrath of Almighty God
                one Moment; but you must suffer it to all Eternity: there will be no End to this exquisite horrible Misery: When you look forward,
                you shall see a long Forever, a boundless Duration before you, which will swallow up your Thoughts, and amaze your Soul;
                and you will absolutely despair of ever having any Deliverance, any End, any Mitigation, any Rest at all; you will know
                certainly that you must wear out long Ages, Millions of Millions of Ages, in wrestling and conflicting with this almighty
                merciless Vengeance; and then when you have so done, when so many Ages have actually been spent by you in this Manner, you
                will know that all is but a Point to what remains. So that your Punishment will indeed be infinite. Oh who can
                express what the State of a Soul in such Circumstances is! All that we can possibly say about it, gives but a very
                feeble faint Representation of it; 'tis inexpressible and inconceivable: for <hi rend="italic">who knows the Power of God's
                Anger?</hi><lb/>How<pb n="22" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-22.png"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                How dreadful is the State of those that are daily and hourly in Danger of this great Wrath, and infinite Misery! But this is the dismal
                Case of every Soul in this Congregation, that has not been born again, however moral and strict, sober and religious they may otherwise be.
                Oh that you would consider it, whether you be Young or Old. There is Reason to think, that there are many in this Congregation now haring this
                Discourse, that will actually be the Subjects of this very Misery to all Eternity. We know not who they are, or in what Seats they sit, or
                what Thoughts they now have: it may be they are now at Ease, and hear all there Things without much Disturbance,
                and are now flattering themselves that they are not the Persons, promising themselves that they shall escape. If we
                knew that there was one Person, and but one, in the whole Congregation that was to be the Subject of this Misery, what an awful Thing
                would it be to think of! If we knew who it was, what an awful Sight would it be to see such a Person! How might all
                the rest of the Congregation lift up a lamentable and bitter Cry over him! But alass! instead of one, how many is it likely will
                remember this Discourse in Hell? And it would be a Wonder if some that are now present, should not be in Hell in a very
                short Time, before this Year is out. And it would be no Wonder if some Person that now sits here in some Seat of this Meeting House
                in Health, and quiet &amp; secure, should be there before to morrow Morning. Those of you that finally continue in a natural Condition, that
                shall keep out of Hell longest, will be there in a little Time! your Damnation don't slumber; it will come swiftly, and
                in all probability very suddenly upon many of you. You have Reason to wonder, that you are not already in Hell. 'Tis doubtless
                the Case of some that here-<lb/>tofore<pb n="23" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-23.png"/>tofore you have seen and known, that never deserved Hell more
                than you, and that heretofore appeared as likely to have been now alive as you: Their Case is past all Hope; they are crying in extream Misery
                and perfect Despair; but here you are in the Land of the Living, and in the House of God, and have an Opportunity to obtain Salvation.
                What would not those poor damned, hopeless Souls give for one Day's such Opportunity as you now enjoy!
            </p>
            <p>
                And now you have an extraordinary Opportunity, a Day wherein <hi rend="small-caps">Christ</hi> has flung the Door of Mercy wide open,
                and stands in the Door calling and crying with a loud Voice to poor Sinners; a Day wherein many are flocking to him, and pressing into the Kingdom of God;
                many are daily coming from the East, West, North and South; many that were very lately in the same miserable Condition that you are in,
                are in now an happy State, with their Hearts filled with Love to Him that has loved them and washed them from their Sins
                in his own Blood, and rejoycing in Hope of the Glory of God. How awful is it to be left behind at such a Day!
                To see so many others feasting, while you are pining and perishing! To see so many rejoycing and singing for Joy of Heart, while you
                have Cause to mourn for Sorrow of Heart, and how for Vexation of Spirit! How are your Souls as precious as the Souls of the People
                at * <hi rend="italic">Suffield</hi>, where they are flocking from Day to Day to Christ?
            </p>
            <p>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                * The next Neighbour Town
            </p>
            <p>
                Are there not many here that have lived <hi rend="italic">long</hi> in the World, that are not to this Day born again, and so are Aliens from the Common-wealth
                of Israel, and have<pb n="24" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-24.png"/>done nothing ever since they have lived, but treasure up Wrath against the Day of Wrath? Oh Sirs,
                your Case in an especial Manner is extreamly dangerous; your Guilt and Hardness of Heart is extreamly great. Don't you see how generally
                Persons of your Years are pass'd over and left, in the present remarkable &amp; wonderful Dispensation of God's Mercy? You had
                need to consider your selves, and wake throughly out of Sleep; you cannot bear the Fierceness and Wrath of the infinite GOD.
            </p>
            <p>
                And you that are <hi rend="italic">young Men,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">young Women,</hi> will you neglect this precious Season that you now enjoy, when
                so many others of your Age are renouncing all youthful Vanities, and flocking to <hi rend="small-caps">Christ</hi>? You especially have now an extraordinary
                Opportunity; but if you neglect it, it will soon be with you as it is with those Persons that spent away all the precious Days
                of Youth in Sin and are now come to such a dreadful pass in blindness and hardness.
            </p>
            <p>
                And you <hi rend="italic">Children</hi> that are unconverted, don't you know know that you are going down to Hell, to bear the dreadful Wrath of that God
                that is now angry with you every Day, and every Night? Will you be content to be the Children of the Devil, when so many other Children in the
                Land are converted, and are become the holy and happy Children of the King of Kings?
            </p>
            <p>
                And let every one that is yet out of Christ, and hanging over the Pit of Hell whether they be old Men and Women, or middle Aged,
                or young People, or middle Aged, or young People, or little Children, now hearken to the loud Calls of God's Word and Providence. This acceptable
                Year of the <hi rend="small-caps">Lord,</hi> that is a Day of such great Favour to some, will doubtless be a Day
                of as remarkable Vengeance to others. Men's Hearts harden<lb/>and<pb n="25" facs="pageImages/edwards-sinners-25.png"/>and their Guilt increases <ref target="_apace" corresp="apace">apace</ref>
                <note target="_apace" xml:id="apace" type="gloss" resp="editors.xml#VBS">
                At a pace, i.e. at a considerable or good pace; hence, With speed; swiftly, quickly, fast. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> at such a Day as this
                if they neglect their Souls: and never was there so great Danger of such Persons being given up to hardness of Heart, and blindness of Mind.
                God seems now to be hastily gathering in his Elect in all Parts of the Land; and probably the bigger Part of adult Persons that
                ever shall be saved, will be brought in now a little Time, and that it will be as it was on the great out-pouring of the <hi rend="small-caps">Spirit</hi> upon
                the <hi rend="italic">Jews</hi> in the Apostles Days, the Election will obtain, and the rest will be blinded. If this should
                be the Case with you, you will eternally curse this Day, and will curse the Day that ever you was born, to see such a Season
                of the pouring out of God's Spirit; and will wish that you have died and gone to Hell before you had seen it. Now undoubtedly it is,
                as it was in the Days of <hi rend="italic">John the Baptist</hi>, the Ax is in an extraordinary Manner laid at the Root of the Trees, that
                every Tree that brings not forth good Fruit, may be hewen down, and cast into the Fire.
            </p>
            <p>
                Therefore let every one that is out of <hi rend="small-caps">Christ</hi>, now awake and fly from the Wrath to come. The Wrath
                of almighty GOD is now undoubtedly hanging over great Part of this Congregation: Let every one fly out of <hi rend="italic">Sodom:
                Haste and escape for your Lives, look not behind you, escape to the Mountain, least you be consumed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic">FINIS.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>