<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="addison-spectator-1">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Spectator</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Joseph</forename>
                            <surname>Addison</surname>
                            <date when="1711">March 1, 1711</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>England</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Joseph</forename>
                                    <surname>Addison</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Spectator</title>
                        <title type="sub">1</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7002445">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1711">1711</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="essay">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="medium"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7002445">England</name>
                    <time when="1711">1711</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <pb facs=""/> <!-- Page Image Needed Still -->
                    THE SPECTATOR <lb/><lb/>
                    Thursday, March 1, 1711. <lb/><lb/>
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi>Non fumum exfulgere, sed ex fumo dare lucem
                    Cogitat, ut speciosa dehinc miracula promat.--Hor.</hi></ref>
                    <note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"He intends not smoke from the flame, but fire from the smoke, so as to reveal wonderful things. Horace." Addison is quoting here from "The Art of Poetry", a verse treatise by the Roman poet Horace that was widely read in the eighteenth century; Addison could count on most of his educated readers knowing the allusion, since the poem was so widely taught in secondary schools. The joke here is that Addison is imagining this essay as being read aloud in smoke-filled coffeehouses.</note>
                    
                         <lb/><lb/><lb/>       
                </head>
                <p>I HAVE observed, that a Reader seldom peruses a Book with Pleasure 'till he knows whether the Writer of it be a <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">black or a fair Man</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Dark or light skinned. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, of a <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">mild or cholerick Disposition</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">A relaxed or angry disposition. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, Married or a Batchelor, with other Particulars of the like nature, that <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">conduce</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Contribute to. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> very much to the right Understanding of an Author. To gratify this Curiosity, which is so natural to a Reader, I design this Paper, and my next, as <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Prefatory</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">Introductory. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Discourses to my following Writings, and shall give some Account in them of the several persons that are engaged in this Work. As the chief trouble of Compiling, Digesting, and Correcting will fall to my Share, I must do myself the Justice to open the Work with my own History.</p> <lb/> <lb/>
                <p>I was born to a small Hereditary Estate, which according to the tradition of the village where it lies, was bounded by the same Hedges and Ditches in <ref target="a002" corresp="n002"><hi>William</hi> the Conqueror's</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">The Norman warlord who defeated the English king Harold at the Battle of Hastings in 1066 and became William I. Source: Oxford English dictionary</note> Time that it is at present, and has been delivered down from Father to Son whole and entire, without the Loss or Acquisition of a single Field or Meadow, during the Space of six hundred Years. There runs a Story in the Family, that when my Mother was gone with Child of me about three Months, she dreamt that she was brought to Bed of a Judge. Whether this might proceed from a Law-suit which was then depending in the Family, or my Fathers being a Justice of the Peace, I cannot determine; for I am not so vain as to think it <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">presaged</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">Predict or foretell. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> any Dignity that I should arrive at in my future Life, though that was the Interpretation the Neighbourhood put upon it. The Gravity of my Behaviour at my very first Appearance in the World, and all the Time that I <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">sucked</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">Breastfed. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, seemed to favour my Mothers Dream: For, as she has often told me, I threw away my Rattle before I was two Months old, and would that was the Interpretation which the Neighbourhood put upon not make use of my <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Coral</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">That is, his teething ring,w hich was often made of coral in this period. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> till they had taken away the Bells from it.</p> <lb/><lb/>
                <p>As for the rest of my Infancy, there being nothing in it remarkable, I shall pass it over in Silence. I find that, during my <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Nonage</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">Youth or childhood. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, I had the reputation of a very sullen Youth, but was always a Favourite of my School-master, who used to say, that my <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">parts</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">Characteristics or elements of a person. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> were solid and would wear well. I had not been long at the University, before I distinguished myself by a most profound Silence: For, during the Space of eight Years, excepting in the publick Exercises of the College, I scarce uttered the Quantity of an hundred Words; and indeed do not remember that I ever spoke three Sentences together in my whole Life. Whilst I was in this Learned Body, I applied myself with so much Diligence to my Studies, that there are very few celebrated Books, either in the Learned or the Modern Tongues, which I am not acquainted with.</p> <lb/><lb/>
                <p>Upon the Death of my Father I was resolved to travel into Foreign Countries, and therefore left the University, with the Character of an odd unaccountable Fellow, that had a great deal of Learning, if I would but show it. An insatiable Thirst after Knowledge carried me into all the Countries of Europe, in which there was any thing new or strange to be seen; nay, to such a Degree was my curiosity raised, that having read the controversies of some great Men concerning the Antiquities of <hi>Egypt</hi>, I made a Voyage to <hi>Grand Cairo</hi>, on purpose to take the Measure of a Pyramid; and, as soon as I had set my self right in that Particular, returned to my Native Country with great Satisfaction.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I have passed my latter Years in this City, where I am frequently seen in most publick Places, tho there are not above half a dozen of my select Friends that know me; of whom my next Paper shall give a more particular Account. There is no place of general Resort wherein I do not often make my appearance; sometimes I am seen thrusting my Head into a Round of Politicians at <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi>Wills</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Wills was a popular coffee shop. Over the next few lines, Mr. Spectator names several of the most popular coffee shops in central London at the time.</note>,  and listening with great Attention to the Narratives that are made in those little Circular Audiences. Sometimes I smoak a Pipe at <hi>Childs</hi>; and, while I seem attentive to nothing but the <ref targt="a005" corresp="n005"><hi>Post-man</hi></ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">A daily newspaper. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, over-hear the Conversation of every Table in the Room. I appear on <hi>Sunday</hi> nights at <hi>St. James's Coffee</hi> House,  and sometimes join the little Committee of Politicks in the Inner-Room, as one who comes there to hear and improve. My Face is likewise very well known at the <hi>Grecian</hi>, the <hi>Cocoa-Tree</hi>, and in the <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Theaters both of <hi>Drury Lane and the Hay-Market</hi></ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">These were the two state-licensed theaters in London.</note>. I have been taken for a Merchant upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> for above these ten Years, and sometimes pass for a <hi>Jew</hi> in the Assembly of <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">Stock-Jobbers</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">A stockbroker. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> at <hi>Jonathans</hi>. In short, where-ever I see a Cluster of People, I always mix with them, tho I never open my Lips but in my own Club.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Thus I live in the World, rather as a Spectator of Mankind, than as one of the Species; by which means I have made my self a Speculative Statesman, Soldier, Merchant, and Artizan, without ever medling with any Practical Part in Life. I am very well versed in the Theory of an Husband, or a Father, and can discern the Errors in the Oeconomy, Business, and Diversion of others, better than those who are engaged in them; as Standers-by discover <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Blots</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Exposed pieces in a game like backgammon, checkers, or chess. Source: Oxford English Dictioonary</note>, which are apt to escape those who are in the Game. I never espoused any Party with Violence, and am resolved to observe an exact Neutrality between the <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Whigs and Tories</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">The two main political factions of the day. The Spectator positioned itself as a neutral journal, and part of the reason why Addison and Steele tried to stay anonymous was to keep up that pretense, since they were both well known to be Whigs. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, unless I shall be forcd to declare myself by the Hostilities of either side. In short, I have acted in all the parts of my Life as a Looker-on, which is the <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Character</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Addison is punning here on the sense of character as personal identity and character as a printed mark on a page.</note> I intend to preserve in this Paper.</p><lb/><lb/>     
                <p>I have given the Reader just so much of my History and Character, as to let him see I am not altogether unqualified for the Business I have undertaken. As for other Particulars in my Life and Adventures, I shall insert them in following Papers, as I shall see occasion. In the mean time, when I consider how much I have seen, read, and heard, I begin to blame my own <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">Taciturnity</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">Silence, and disinclination to converse. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; and since I have neither Time nor Inclination to communicate the Fulness of my Heart in Speech, I am resolved to do it in Writing; and to Print my self out, if possible, before I Die. I have been often told by my Friends that it is Pity so many useful Discoveries which I have made, should be in the possession of a Silent Man. For this Reason therefore, I shall publish a Sheet full of Thoughts every Morning, for the Benefit of my Contemporaries; and if I can any way contribute to the Diversion or Improvement of the Country in which I live, I shall leave it, when I am summoned out of it, with the secret Satisfaction of thinking that I have not Lived in vain.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>There are three very material Points which I have not spoken to in this Paper, and which, for several important Reasons, I must keep to my self; at least for some Time: I mean, an Account of my Name, my Age, and my Lodgings. I must confess I would gratify my Reader in any thing that is reasonable; but as for these three Particulars, though I am sensible they might tend very much to the Embellishment of my Paper, I cannot yet come to a Resolution of communicating them to the Publick. They would indeed draw me out of that Obscurity which I have enjoyed for many Years, and expose me in Publick Places to several Salutes and Civilities, which have been always very disagreeable to me; for the greatest pain I can suffer, is the being talked to, and being stared at. It is for this Reason likewise, that I keep my Complexion and Dress, as very great Secrets; tho it is not impossible, but I may make Discoveries of both in the Progress of the Work I have undertaken.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>After having been thus particular upon my self; I shall in toMorrows Paper give an Account of those Gentlemen who are concerned with me in this Work. For, as I have before <ref target="a021" corresp="n021">intimated</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">Announced or Made known in a formal manner. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, a Plan of it is laid and <ref target="a022" corresp="n022">concerted</ref><note xml:id="n022" target="a022">Arranged or contrived by two or more people. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> (as all other Matters of Importance are) in a Club. However, as my Friends have engaged me to stand in the Front, those who have a mind to correspond with me, may direct their Letters <hi>To the Spectator</hi>, at Mr. <hi>Buckleys</hi>, in <hi>Little Britain</hi>. For I must further acquaint the Reader, that tho our Club meets only on <hi>Tuesdays</hi> and <hi>Thursdays</hi>, we have appointed a Committee to sit every Night, for the Inspection of all such Papers as may contribute to the Advancement of the Public <ref target="a023" corresp="n023">Weal</ref><note xml:id="n023" target="a023">Welfare and happiness. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>.</p><lb/><lb/> <lb/>
                <p><ref target="a010" corresp="n010">C.</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Addison identified the essays that he wrote with the letters C, L, I, or O, which collectively spell out Clio, the muse of history.</note></p><lb/><lb/>                                          
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>