<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="spectator-introduction">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Spectator</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <date when="2019">2019</date>     
                            <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>John</forename>
                                    <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Spectator</title>
                        <title type="sub">Introduction</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="2019">2019</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident=""></language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="introduction">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="medium"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <pb facs=""/> 
                    The Spectator <lb/><lb/><lb/>       
                </head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> is the most famous work of journalism of the eighteenth century in English, and there it helped define what journalism could be. It set the pattern for a kind of essay writing that persists to the present day. Comparatively short essays on topics of interest to middle-class readers (politics, fashion, the arts), written in straightforward, unfussy prose without partisanship or professional jargon: this is a mode that is still standard in print and online journalism. A collaboration between Joseph Addison and Richard Steele, <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> was for a long time after its initial run in 1711 and 1712 held up to English students and readers as a model of prose style, and although to our eyes there are moments where the prose feels a little archaic, Addison and Steele's version of English prose is light years closer to the way that we write now than the prose from a hundred, or even fifty years earlier, which might be testimony to their influence on writers and readers over the last three hundred years. In modern times, <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>has been credited with being essential to the formation of what the sociologist Jürgen Habermas has influentially dubbed “the bourgeois public sphere.” Habermas describes the bourgeois public sphere as being made up of private individuals coming together to constitute a public, in this case a public that was not affiliated with the government or the church, but an independent body that could discuss important issues on its own. Gathered together in coffee houses, over tea tables, or simply in their studies, readers of <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> were among the first citizens to have a print publication that became a common frame of reference for middle-class English-speaking people. The journal set an agenda and a way of thinking about society and the arts that seemed derived, not from the aristocracy or the church, but from the shared world of the readers themselves.</p> <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/addison-steele-spectator/Spectator_page.jpeg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Spectator </hi>followed on the heels of <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi>, which had run from April 12, 1709 to  December 30, 1710. Steele had taken the lead with <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi>, asking for help from Addison and others on occasion to fill out the pages. But it was Addison who seems to have been the leader for <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, supplying the first issue. In this case, timing was everything. Addison and his Whig party had just lost a parliamentary election towards the end of 1710 (Addison was a cabinet member, at the center of government policy-making), so he suddenly found himself kicked out of office with time to devote to something other than party politics and governance. <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> differed in format in significant ways from its immediate predecessor. It was published daily, except for Sunday; <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> had come out three days a week. Where <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> had generally had several items in each issue, most issues of <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> focused on a single topic. The new journal had a different framing device than the older one. Where Steele had arranged the articles in <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> by the imagined location in London from which various “correspondents” were sending him information (theater news coming from Will's Coffee House, political news from the St. James Coffee House, the whole thing being a parody of the way that official newspapers published correspondence from foreign cities), <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> had a fictional “club” that would come up with ideas. Steele described its members in the second issue: there was a country squire, Sir Roger de Coverly, a lawyer, a businessman (Sir Andrew Freeport), a soldier (Major Sentry), an aging libertine (Will Honeycomb), and a clergyman. Between them, the Club represented many of the important segments of middle-class and polite culture in the eighteenth century. The Spectator Club never worked quite as it seems to have been intended—relatively few issues feature it in any central way—but it was another means by which the journal was projecting itself as giving a voice to a variety of middle-class interests.</p> And the journal occasionally referred to the coffee-house culture that middle-class people (well, middle-class men, since women were generally not welcome) had developed in this period, a milieu (depicted here), where men met to socialize, gossip, talk over issues of the day, read from the coffee-shop's stock of newspapers and journals (which were expensive enough that individuals might not subscribe), and get their caffeine fix satisfied.<graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/addison-steele-spectator/London_coffee_shop1700.jpg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>
                <p>Most importantly, <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> introduces a new kind of persona, what critics call an <hi rend="italic">eidolon</hi>, in the figure of “Mr. Spectator,” in whose voice all of the essays were composed, no matter which of the two men was the actual author. <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> did not invent the concept of the <hi rend="italic">eidolon</hi>, but it provided perhaps its most influential model, one imitated over and over again in works such as Benjamin Franklin’s “Silence Dogood” pieces in <hi rend="italic">The New England Courant</hi> (1721), Samuel Johnson’s<hi rend="italic">Rambler</hi> essays (1750-52), and even the Federalist essays composed by Alexander Hamilton, James Madison, and John Jay to defend the U. S. Constitution. Mr. Spectator projected himself as a civilized man of the world, an observer looking on society like a fly on the wall. He is well educated, but not a specialist in anything, which enables him to comment on all sorts of things. In the course of its run, The Spectator offers essays on fashion, on politics, on religion, on literature. Steele’s essay on Inkle and Yarico (#11) popularized the story to eighteenth-century readers; it would become a cultural phenomenon, with plays, musicals, and poems about the doomed pair of lovers abounding in English-speaking culture over the next few decades. Addison’s essays on John Milton's epic <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost </hi>and the series generally known as “the pleasures of the imagination” became widely influential works of literary criticism and aesthetic theory that to some extent established a paradigm for what modern criticism could be. To be sure, this is a very male <hi rend="italic">eidolon</hi>, and it is no surprise to discover that <hi rend="italic">The Spectator’s</hi> essays are very frequently condescending towards women readers. In the 1740s, Eliza Haywood published a journal called <hi rend="italic">The Female Spectator</hi> http://www2.scc.rutgers.edu/spectator/haywood/, one that forms a nice counterweight to the bluff masculinity of Addison and Steele’s journal.</p> 
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> ran from March 3, 1711 to December 6, 1712, comprising 555 issues in all. (On his own, Addison revived <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> briefly for a few months in 1714, but these essays were generally not as popular.) Of these, about 250 issues each were written by Addison and Steele; Addison’s cousin Eustace Budgell contributed a small number, as did the poet John Hughes. Over time, we hope to add more issues of both <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> to this digital anthology.</p><lb/><lb/>                                     
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>