<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="coleridge-kubla">
   
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">"Kubla Khan"</title>
            <author>
              
               <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78095462">     
                 <name>           
                     <forename>Samuel Taylor</forename> 
                    <surname>Coleridge</surname></name>
                   
               </persName>
            </author>

            <editor>
               <persName type="orcid" key="000000-0001-6453-8721">
                  <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                     <forename>John</forename>
                     <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </editor>

            <respStmt>
             
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name ref="editors.xml#StudStaff"
                  >Students and Staff of the University of Virginia</name>
               
            </respStmt>

            <sponsor/>
            <funder><?oxy-placeholder content="Who is funding this work?"?></funder>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            
            <address>
               <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA</addrLine>
               <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
               <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>

            <biblStruct>

               <analytic>
                 
                  <title>"Kubla Khan"</title>
                
               </analytic>
                 
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <forename>Samuel Taylor</forename>
                        <surname>Coleridge</surname>
                      
                     </name>
                  </author>

                  <title><?oxy-placeholder content="Title of the Monograph/Container"?></title>

                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781"
                           >London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>John Murray</publisher>
                     <date when="1816">1816</date>
                     <note>"Kubla Khan" was first published in 1816, in a volume containing three poems by Coleridge: this one, "Cristabel" and "The Pains of Sleep." We are reproducing the text of that first printing, which Coleridge did not alter much afterwards. Coleridge's claim that the poem was originally written 1798 seems entirely plausible, but is impossible to prove. We do know that the "poet of great and deserved celebrity" mentioned in Coleridge's prefatory note was Byron, who heard Coleridge recite the poem in 1815 or 1816 and urged him to publish it.</note>
                     
                     <note><?oxy-placeholder content="Where are page images sourced from? Add or delete NOTE elements as needed."?></note>
                  </imprint>

                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <publisher/>
                     <date/>
                     <note><?oxy-placeholder content="Add information for other copies, like digital surrogates available on the web. If a base reading text was used, add another IMPRINT element."?></note>
                  </imprint>

                  <extent><?oxy-placeholder content="physical dimensions from catalog record"?></extent>
                  <biblScope><?oxy-placeholder content="if document contained in another document, include page span here, as in 'pp 62-64'."?></biblScope>
                  <!-- Indicate page numbers of the poem from the book described in this <monogr> -->

               </monogr>

            </biblStruct>

         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>

         <creation/>

         <textDesc n="poem">
            
            <channel mode="w">print</channel>
            
            <constitution type="single">single poem</constitution>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain/>
            <factuality type="fiction"/>
            <interaction/>
            <preparedness type="revised"/>
            <purpose type="express"/>
            <purpose type="inform" degree="medium"/>
       
         </textDesc>

         <settingDesc>

            <setting/>
               
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <!-- Please keep this language, and follow these encoding guidelines. If in rare circumstances, these guidelines cannot be followed, edit them to indicate your editing guidelines. -->
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
               primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
               literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
               Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
               University.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                  lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-11-20" who="editors.xml#JOB"
            >John O'Brien created Literature in Context edition.</change>
        
      </revisionDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>

      <body>
        
         <div type="poem">
        
            <pb n="" facs=""/>
            
         <head type="title">KUBLA KHAN </head>
         <head type="sub">A Vision</head>
         <head type="sub"><hi rend="small caps">OF THE</hi><lb/>
         FRAGMENT OF KUBLA KHAN</head>
          <p>The following fragment is here published at the request
          of a poet of great and deserved celebrity, and,
          as far as the Author's own opinions are concerned, rather as
          a psychological curiosity, than on the ground of any supposed
          poetic merits.</p>
          
          <p>In the summer of the year 1797, the Author, then in ill
          health, had retired to a lonely farm-house between Porlock
          and Linton, on the Exmoor confines of Somerset and Devonshire.
          In 
          
             <pb n="52" facs=""/>
          consequence of a slight indisposition, an anodyne
          had been prescribed, from the effects of which he fell asleep
          in his chair at the moment that he was reading the following
          sentence, or words of the same substance, in "Purchas's
          Pilgrimage:" "Here the Khan Kubla commanded a palace
          to be built, and a stately garden thereunto. And thus ten
          miles of fertile ground were inclosed with a wall." The
          Author continued for about three hours in a profound sleep,
          at least of the external senses, during which time he has the
          most vivid confidence, that he could not have composed less
          than from two to three hundred lines; if that indeed can
          be called composition in which all the images rose up before
          him as things, with a parallel production of the correspondent
          expressions, without any sensation or consciousness of effort.
          On awaking he appeared to himself to have a distinct recollection
          of the whole, and taking his pen, ink, and paper, instantly
          and eagerly wrote down the lines that are here preserved. At
          this 
          
             <pb n="53" facs=""/>
             moment he was unfortunately called out by a person on
          business from Porlock, and detained by him above an hour,
          and on his return to his room, found, to his no small surprise
          and mortification, that though he still retained some vague
          and dim recollection of the general purport of the vision, yet,
          with the exception of some eight or ten scattered lines and
          images, all the rest had passed away like the images on the
          surface of a stream into which a stone has been cast, but, alas!
          without the after restoration of the latter:</p>
          
          <div type="poem">
          <lg type="stanza">
              <l rend="indent">Then all the charm</l>
              <l>Is broken—all that phantom-world so fair</l>
              <l>Vanishes, and a thousand circlets spread,</l>
              <l>And each mis-shape the other. Stay awhile,</l>
              <l>Poor youth! who scarcely dar'st lift up thine eyes—</l>
              <l>The stream will soon renew its smoothness, soon</l>
              <l>The visions will return! And lo, he stays,</l>
              <l>And soon the fragments dim of lovely forms</l>
              <l>Come trembling back, unite, and now once more</l>
              <l>The pool becomes a mirror.</l></lg></div>
          
            <p>Yet from the still surviving recollections in his    <pb n="54" facs=""/>
               mind, the Author has frequently purposed to finish for himself what had
          been originally, as it were, given to him. Σαμερον αδιον ασω: but the to-morrow is yet to come.</p>
          
          <p>As a contrast to this vision, I have annexed a fragment of a
          very different character, describing with equal fidelity the
          dream of pain and disease.</p>
          
            <pb n="55" facs=""/>
          <head>KUBLA KHAN.</head>
          <div type="stanza">
             <lg><l>In Xanadu did <hi rend="small caps">Kubla Khan</hi></l>
              <l>A stately pleasure-dome decree:</l>
                <l>Where <hi rend="small caps">Alph</hi>, the sacred river, ran</l>
              <l n="5">Through caverns measureless to man</l>
              <l rend="indent">Down to a sunless sea.</l>
              <l>So twice five miles of fertile ground</l>
              <l>With walls and towers were girdled round:</l>
                <pb n="56" facs=""/>
              <l>And there were gardens bright with sinuous rills,</l>
              <l>Where blossomed many an incense-bearing tree;</l>
              <l n="10"> And here were forests ancient as the hills,10</l>
              <l>Enfolding sunny spots of greenery.</l></lg>
             
             <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But oh! that deep romantic chasm which slanted</l>
              <l>Down the green hill athwart a cedarn cover!</l>
              <l>A savage place! as holy and enchanted</l>
              <l n="15">As e'er beneath a waning moon was haunted15</l>
              <l>By woman wailing for her demon-lover!</l>
              <l>And from this chasm, with ceaseless turmoil seething,</l>
              <l>As if this earth in fast thick pants were breathing,</l>
              <l>A mighty fountain momently was forced:</l>
              <l n="20">Amid whose swift half-intermitted Burst</l>
              <l>Huge fragments vaulted like rebounding hail,</l>
              <l>Or chaffy grain beneath the thresher's flail:</l>
              <l>And 'mid these dancing rocks at once and ever</l>
              <l>It flung up momently the sacred river.</l>
                
                <pb n="57" facs=""/>
              <l n="25">Five miles meandering with a mazy motion</l>
              <l>Through wood and dale the sacred river ran,</l>
              <l>Then reached the caverns measureless to man</l>
              <l>And sank in tumult to a lifeless ocean:</l>
              <l>And 'mid this tumult Kubla heard from far</l>
              <l n="30">Ancestral voices prophesying war!</l></lg>
             
             <lg type="stanza">
              <l rend="indent">The shadow of the dome of pleasure</l>
             <l rend="indent">Floated midway on the waves;</l>
             <l rend="indent">Where was heard the mingled measure</l>
             <l rend="indent">From the fountain and the caves.</l>
              <l n="35">It was a miracle of rare device,</l>
              <l>A sunny pleasure-dome with caves of ice!</l>
             </lg>
             
             <lg type="stanza">
                <l rend="indent">A damsel with a dulcimer</l>
                <l rend="indent">In a vision once I saw:</l>
                <l rend="indent">It was an Abyssinian maid,</l>
                <l rend="indent" n="40">And on her dulcimer she played,</l>
                <pb n="58" facs=""/>
                <l>rend="indent"Singing of Mount Abora.</l>
                <l rend="indent">Could I revive within me</l>
                   <l rend="indent">Her symphony and song,</l>
                      <l rend="indent">To such a deep delight 'twould win me,</l>
              <l n="45">That with music loud and long,</l>
              <l>I would build that dome in air,</l>
              <l>That sunny dome! those caves of ice!</l>
              <l>And all who heard should see them there,</l>
              <l>And all should cry, Beware! Beware!</l>
              <l n="50"> His flashing eyes, his floating hair!</l>
              <l> Weave a circle round him thrice,</l>
              <l> And close your eyes with holy dread,</l>
              <l>For he on honey-dew hath fed,</l>
              <l>And drunk the milk of Paradise.</l>
          </lg> </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>



