<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="rowlandson-sovereignty">

    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> The soveraignty and goodness of God, together, with the faithfulness of his
                    promises displayed; being a narrative of the captivity and restauration of Mrs.
                    Mary Rowlandson. </title>
                <author>
                    <persName>type="lcnaf" key="n50022304"> <name>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <surname>Rowlandson</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name>
                            <forename> John </forename>
                            <surname> O'Brien </surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp> Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup </resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#RR"> Rachel Retica
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>

            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Literature in Context </publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> 434-924-7105 </addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported Licence </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename>Mary</forename>
                                <surname>White</surname>
                                <surname>Rowlandson</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title> The soveraignty and goodness of God, together, with the faithfulness
                            of his promises displayed; being a narrative of the captivity and
                            restauration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson. </title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">Cambridge,
                                    Massachusetts</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green</publisher>
                            <date when="1682">1682</date>
                            <note source="ESTC">Mary Rowlandson's book was first published by the printer Samuel Green in 1682, whose press was in Cambridge, Massachusetts. We do not have a copy of the 
                                the first edition. Our text is based on the transcription done in 2011-2012 by the Text Creation Partnership of the second edition, which was also printed by Green in the same year, which suggests
                                that the work was popular and in high demand among readers in New England. The book was reprinted by the London printer/bookseller, again in 1682, under the title <hi rend="italic">A True History of the Captivity and Restoration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson</hi>.  </note>
                            <note>For more information about this item, see the ESTC entry at <ref
                                    target="http://estc.bl.uk/R213983"
                                    >http://estc.bl.uk/R213983</ref></note>
                        </imprint>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace key="7013304">Ann Arbor, MI; Oxford, UK</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
                            <date>2011-12</date>
                            <note>Text for this digital edition drawn from <ref
                                    target="http://name.umdl.umich.edu/B09906.0001.001">
                                    http://name.umdl.umich.edu/B09906.0001.001</ref></note>
                        </imprint>

                        <extent>[6], 73, [1] p</extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="novella">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>

            </textDesc>

            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013527">Cambridge, MA</name>
                    <time from="1635" to="1682">Early 18th Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-08-16" who="Rachel Retica">created LiC text</change>
        </revisionDesc>


    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[TP]"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart><ref target="headnote_" corresp="headnote">THE <hi rend="italic">Soveraignty &amp;; Goodness</hi><lb/> OF<lb/> GOD,<lb/>
                        Together, <lb/>With the Faithfulness of His Promises <lb/>Displayed;<lb/> Being a <lb/>NARRATIVE<lb/>
                        Of the <hi rend="italic">Captivity</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Restauration</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="italic"> M</hi>
                        <hi rend="sup">rs.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mary Rowlandson.</hi></ref><lb/>
                        <note xml:id="headnote" target="headnote_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><p>
                            Mary Rowlandson’s gripping account of her experience as a captive of native Americans was enormously popular in her own time and became widely influential as the paradigm for the “captivity narrative,” a genre that would have hundreds of examples over the next two centuries and would also help shape works like Daniel Defoe’s <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi>. The book was originally printed in 1682, first in Massachusetts and then, quickly, in London as well, and was reprinted over and over again for the next century and more. For good reason. Rowlandson’s work taps into colonial fears about the indigenous population, Puritan conceptions of the relationship between the material world and the unseen world of the divine, and the perennial fears of all patriarchal cultures about women’s sexuality. Her experience is compelling and she writes vividly about it.
                        </p>
                            <p>Rowlandson was born Mary White in England in around 1637, and her family moved to the Massachusetts Bay Colony when she was in her early teens. She married Joseph Rowlandson, a Puritan minister, in the 1650s, and they moved to Lancaster, in central Massachusetts, which was then essentially frontier territory for the English colonial settlers. In 1675, the native American leader Metacomet, head of the Wampanoag confederation of indigeneous peoples, led a series of attacks on English settlements. The conflict that followed for the next three years is remembered by English-speaking historians as “Prince Philip’s War,” because “Philip” was the name that the English settlers used for Metacomet. Metacomet’s forces attacked Lancaster on the morning of February 11, 1675, killing thirteen people, including Rowlandson’s sister and her sister’s children, as well as her brother-in-law. The natives took twenty-four English settlers prisoner, including Rowlandson and her three children. (Rowlandson’s husband Joseph was at this moment in Boston, trying to secure appropriations from the Massachusetts legislature to strengthen Lancashire’s defenses against the Wampanoag.) Rowlandson’s six-year-old daughter Sarah died of wounds suffered in the fight. Mary and her surviving children were held captive for eleven weeks, where they were moved progressively further away from the colonial settlements, into what is now the state of Vermont. She was eventually ransomed with funds raised by women in Boston.</p>
                            <p>Joseph Rowlandson died in 1678, and Mary moved with her children to Boston. She remarried there, and published the first edition of her <hi rend="italic">Narrative </hi>with the Cambridge, Massachusetts printer Samuel Greene. This version was entitled <hi rend="italic">The Sovereignty and Goodness of God, together with the Faithfulness of His Promises Displayed, being a Narrative of the Captivity and Restauration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson.</hi> It included a preface that was probably written by Increase Mather, the leading Puritan minister in the colonies at the time, and also the author of a narrative account of the war with Metacomet, <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of the War with the Indians, in New-England</hi>, published in Boston in 1676. The first London edition of Rowlandson’s more personal account, printed in 1682, came out under the title <hi rend="italic">A True History of the Captivity and Restoration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson.</hi> The fact that this book was printed three times in a single year on both sides of the Atlantic attests to its significance among the settler-colonists of North America and those in England who were interested in their experience. It also, however, reminds us of the partial and one-sided nature of this account; it is largely because Rowlandson, as a high-ranking woman in the colonial heirarchy, had access to publication that her story was recorded in this way. The native peoples who allied against the colonists preserved their version of the conflict in oral accounts that were, at best, fragmented in the course of the progressive destruction of their culture over the next years and decades. We have much still to learn and understand about the often-violent encounters in this period between European settler-colonists and the indigenous peoples of the land that still typically goes--strangely, if you think about it for a moment--by the name "New England."</p></note>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart> Commended by her, to all that desires to<lb/> know the Lords doings to,
                        and <lb/>dealings with Her. <lb/></titlePart>
                    <titlePart>
                        <hi rend="italic">Especially to her dear Children and Relations,</hi><lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart>The second Addition Corrected and amended.<lb/></titlePart>
                    <titlePart>Written by Her own Hand for Her private Use, and now <lb/>made Publick at
                        the earnest Desire of some Friends, <lb/>and for the benefit of the
                        Afflicted.<lb/></titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <epigraph>
                    <quote>
                        <bibl> Deut. 32.29 </bibl> See now that I, even I am he, and there is no <lb/>God
                        with me: I kill and I make alive, I wound and I heal<lb/> neither is there any
                        can deliver out of my hand. </quote>
                   
                </epigraph>
<lb/>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">CAMBRIDGE</placeName></pubPlace>:<lb/>
                    <publisher>Printed by<persName><hi rend="italic"> Samuel
                        Green, </hi></persName></publisher>
                    <docDate>1682</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div type="preface">

                <head><ref target="preface_" corresp="preface"> The Preface to the <hi rend="italic">READER.</hi></ref></head>
                <note xml:id="preface" target="preface_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                    <p> Increase Mather (1639-1723), a Puritan minister, is widely considered to be the author
                        of this preface. He was active in soliciting and collecting accounts of what
                        English-speakers referred to as “King Philip’s War,” including his own “A
                        Brief History of the Warr with the Indians in New England.” Mather also
                        collected essays on miracles and illustrations of divine providence among
                        New Englanders. It is likely that he encouraged Rowlandson to publish this account of her experience.</p>
                </note>

                <p> IT was on <ref target="calendar_" corresp="calendar"><hi rend="italic">Tuesday,
                        Feb.</hi> 1. 1675.</ref>
                    <note xml:id="calendar" target="calendar_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> Rowlandson followed the Julian calendar for her dates. In the Georgian
                            calendar, this would be February 1st, 1676. The same is true for the
                            years given throughout the narrative.</p>
                    </note> in the afternoon, when the <ref target="narrhagansets_" corresp="narrhagansets">
                        <hi rend="italic">Narrhagansets</hi>
                    </ref>
                    <note xml:id="narrhagansets" target="narrhagansets_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> Archeological evidence indicates that ancestors of the Narragansett people lived along what is now
                            the southern New England coast for thousands of years.
                            At their greatest extent, the tribe controlled most of what is now Rhode
                            Island. In “King Philip’s War,” as the English-speakers termed it, the
                            Narragansetts initially tried to stay neutral. They entered the conflict
                            after the English attacked a large Narragansett and Wampanoag
                            fortification in December of 1675. The war was possibly one of the
                            bloodiest in American history; the Narragansetts were decimated, and the
                            end of the war marked the end of most of their resistance to English
                            settlement in Southern New England. </p>
                    </note> quarters (in or toward the <ref target="nipmug_" corresp="nipmug">
                        <hi rend="italic">Nipmug</hi>
                    </ref>
                    <note xml:id="nipmug" target="nipmug_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> The Nipmuc nation once controlled a large territory in central
                            Massachusetts. The town of Lancaster, where the Rowlandsons lived, was
                            located in the Nipmuc territory of “Nashaway.” In “King Philip’s war,”
                            the Nipmucs joined the Wampanoags and Narragansetts to combat the
                            spreading influence of English settlers. In 1676, in a series of raids
                            that included Lancaster, they forced the colonists to abandon the
                            settlements on Nipmuc land. The English tried to settle again in 1701,
                            abandoned the area a second time, and in a third attempt in 1713, formed
                            a permanent settlement of what is now Worcester County. Nipmucs continue
                            to live in and around Worcester today.</p>
                    </note> Country, whither they are now retyred for fear of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >English</hi> Army lying in their own Country) were the second time beaten
                    up by the Forces of the united Colonies, who thereupon soon betook themselves to
                    flight, and were all the next day pursued by the <hi rend="italic">English,</hi>
                    some overtaken and destroyed, But on <hi rend="italic">Thursday,</hi> Feb. 3.
                    The <hi rend="italic">English</hi> having now been six dayes on their march,
                    from their head quarters, at <hi rend="italic">Wickford,</hi> in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Narrhaganset</hi> Country, toward, and after the Enemy, and
                    provision grown exceeding short, insomuch that they were fain to kill some
                    Horses for the supply, especially of their <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>
                    friends, they were necessitated to consider what was best to be done: And about
                    noon (having hitherto followed the chase as hard as they might) a Councill was
                    called, and though some few were of another mind, yet it was concluded by far
                    the greater part of the Councill of War, that the Army should desist the
                    pursuit, and retire: the Forces of <hi rend="italic">Plimouth</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Bay</hi> to the next Town of the <hi rend="italic">Bay,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi> Forces to their own next Towns: Which
                    determination was immediately put in execution. The consequent whereof, as it
                    was not difficult to be foreseen by those that knew the causless enmity of these
                        <hi rend="italic">Barbarians,</hi> against the <hi rend="italic"
                        >English,</hi> and the malicious and revengefull spirit of these Heathen: so
                    it soon proved dismall. </p>
                <p> The <hi rend="italic">Narrhagansets</hi> were now driven quite from their own
                    Countrey, and all their provisions there hoarded up, to which they durst not at
                    present return, and being so numerous as they were, soon devoured those to whom
                    they went, whereby both the one and other were now reduced to extream straits,
                    and so necessitated to take the first and best opportunity for supply, and very
                    glad, no doubt of such an opportunity as this, to provide for themselves, and
                    make spoil of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> at once; and seeing themselves
                    thus discharged of their pursuers, and a little refreshed after their flight,
                    the very next week on <ref target="attack_" corresp="attack">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thurseday, Feb.</hi> 10. </ref>
                    <note xml:id="attack" target="attack_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> Forces made up of Narragansett, Wampanoag, and Nipmuc men attacked
                            Lancaster on the morning of February 10th, 1676. They set fire to the
                            town’s bridge and many homes, including the Rowlandson’s. The attackers
                            secured food and supplies for the winter and took twenty-four captives,
                            including Rowlandson and her three children. Lancaster was mostly
                            abandoned after the raid.</p></note> they fell with mighty force and
                    fury upon <hi rend="italic">Lancaster:</hi> which small Town, remote from aid of
                    others, and not being Gerisoned as it might, the Army being now come in, and as
                    the time indeed required (the design of the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi>
                    against <pb facs="tcp:192319:4"/> that place being <ref target="warning_"
                        corresp="warning"> known to the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> some time
                        before) </ref>
                    <note xml:id="warning" target="warning_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> The English had been warned of plans to attack Lancaster by James
                            Quannapohit and Job Kattenanit, two Nipmuc men reportedly converted to
                            Christianity by Daniel Gookin. Even with this advance information, the
                            English did not garrison the town quickly or effectively enough to
                            counter the attack. Daniel Gookin went on to write an account of his
                            efforts to convert native peoples in his “An historical account of the
                            doings and sufferings of the Christian Indians in New England in the
                            years 1675, 1676, 1677.” </p></note> was not able to make effectual
                    resistance: but notwithstanding utmost endeavour of the Inhabitants, most of the
                    buildings were turned into ashes; many People (Men, Women and Children) slain,
                    and others captivated. The most solemn and remarkable part of this Trajedy, may
                    that justly be reputed, which fell upon the Family of that reverend Servant of
                    God, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Joseph Rolandson,</hi> the faithfull Pastor of Christ
                    in that place, who being gone down to the Councill of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Massachusets</hi> to seek aid for the defence of the place, at his return
                    found the Town in flames, or smoke, his own house being ser on fire by the
                    Enemy, through the disadvantage of a defective Fortification, and all in it
                    consumed: his precious yoke-fellow, and dear Children, wounded and captivated
                    (as the issue evidenced, and following Narrative declares) by these cruel and
                    barbarous Salvages. A sad Catestrophe! Thus all things come alike to all: None
                    knows either love or hatred by âll that is before him. It is no new thing for
                    Gods precions ones to drink as deep as others, of the Cup of common Calamity:
                    Take just <hi rend="italic">Lot</hi> (yet captivated) for instance beside
                    others. But it is not my business to dilate on these things, but only in few
                    words introductively to preface to the following script, which is a Narrative of
                    the wonderfully awfull, wise, holy, powerfull, and gracious providence of God,
                    towards that worthy and precious Gentle woman, the dear Consort of the said
                    Reverend Mr. <hi rend="italic">Rowlandson,</hi> and her Children with her, as in
                    casting of her into such a waterless pit, so in preserving, supporting, and
                    carrying thorow so many such extream hazards, unspeakable difficulties and
                    disconsolateness, and at last delivering her out of them all, and her surviving
                    Children also. It was a strange and amazing dispensation, that the Lord should
                    so afflict his precious Servant, and Hand maid: It was as strange, if not more,
                    that he should so bear up the spirits of his Servant under such bereavments, and
                    or his handmaid under such captivity, travels and hardships (much too hard for
                    flesh and blood) as he did, and at length deliver and restore But he was their
                    Saviour, who hath said, <hi rend="italic"> When thou passest through the Waters,
                        I will be with thee, and thorough the Rivers, they shall not overflow thee:
                        When thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burnt, nor shall the
                        flame kindle upon thee, </hi> Isa. 93. ver. 2. and again. <hi rend="italic">
                        He woundeth and his hands make whole. He shall deliver thee in troubles, yea
                        in seven there shall no evil touch thee: In Famine he shall redeem thee from
                        Death, and in War from the power of the sword, </hi>
                    Job 5.18, 19, 20. Methinks this dispensation doth bear some
                    resemblance to those of <hi rend="italic">Joseph, David</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Daniel;</hi> yea, and of the three Children too, the Stories
                    whereof do represent us with the excellent textures of divine providence,
                    curious pieces of divine work: and truly so doth this, and therefore not to be
                    forgotten, but worthy to be exhibited to, and viewed, and pondered by all, that
                    disdain not to consider the operation of his hands. </p>
                <p> The works of the Lord (not only of Creation, but of Providence also, especially
                    those that do more peculiarly concern his <pb facs="tcp:192319:4"/> dear ones,
                    that are as the Apple of his Eye, as the Signet upon His Hand, the Delight of
                    his Eyes, and the Object of his tenderest Care and great, sought out of all
                    those that have pleasure therein. And of these verily this is none of the least. </p>
                <p> This Narrative was penned by the Gentlewoman her self, to be to her a memorandum
                    of Gods dealing with her, that she might never forget, but remember the same,
                    &amp;; the severall circumstances thereof, all the dayes of her life. A pious
                    scope which deserves both commendation and imitation: Some friends having
                    obtained a sight of it, could not but be so much affected with the many passages
                    of working providence discovered therein, as to judge it worthy of publick view,
                    and altogether unmeet that such works of God should be hid from present and
                    future Generations: And therefore though this Gentlewomans modesty would not
                    thrust it into the Press, yet her gratitude unto God made her not hardly
                    perswadable to let it pass, that God might have his due glory, and others
                    benefit by it as well as her self. I hope by this time none will cast any
                    reflection upon this Gentlewoman, on the score of this publication of her
                    affliction and deliverance. If any should, doubtless they may be reckoned with
                    the <ref target="lepers_" corresp="lepers"> nine lepers</ref>
                    <note xml:id="lepers" target="lepers_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        Luke 17:11-10.</note>, of whom it is said, <hi rend="italic">
                        Were there not ten cleansed, where are the nine? but one returning to give
                        God thanks. </hi> Let such further know that this was a dispensation of
                    publick note, and of universall concernment, and so much the more, by how much
                    the nearer this Gentlewoman stood related to that faithfull Servant of God,
                    whose capacity and employment was publick in the house of God, and his name on
                    that account of a very sweet savour in the Churches of Christ, who is there of a
                    true Christian spirit, that did not look upon himself much concerned in this
                    bereavment, this Captivity in the time thereof, and in his deliverance when it
                    came, yea more then in many others; and how many are there, to whom so
                    concerned, it will doubtless be a very acceptable thing to see the way of God
                    with this Gentlewoman in the aforesaid dispensation, thus laid out and
                    pourtrayed before their eyes. </p>
                <p> To conclude whatever any coy phantasies may deem, yet it highly concerns those
                    that have so deeply tasted, how good the Lord is, to enquire with <hi
                        rend="italic"> David, What shall I render to the Lord for all his benefits
                        to me. Psal. </hi> 116.12. He thinks nothing too great; yea, being sensible
                    of his own disproportion to the due praises of God he cals in help. <hi
                        rend="italic"> Oh, magnifie the Lord with me, let us exalt his Name
                        together, Psal. </hi> 34.3 And it is but reason, that out praises should
                    hold proportion with our prayers: and that as many hath helped together by
                    prayer for the obtaining of his Mercy, so praises should be returned by many on
                    this behalf; And forasmuch as not the generall but particular knowledge of
                    things makes deepest impression upon the affections, this Narrative
                    particularizing the several passages of this providence will nor a little
                    conduce thereunto. And therefore holy <hi rend="italic"> David </hi> in order to
                    the attainment of that end, accounts himself concerned to declare what God had
                    done for his soul, <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 66.16. <hi rend="italic"> Come
                        and hear, all ye that fear God, and I will declare what God hath done for </hi>
                    <pb facs="tcp:192319:4"/>
                    <hi rend="italic"> my soul, </hi> i. e. <hi rend="italic">for his life,</hi> see
                    v. 9, 10. <hi rend="italic"> He holdeth our soul in life, and suffers not our
                        feet to be moved, for thou our God hast proved us, thou hast tryed us, as
                        silver is tryed. </hi> Life-mercies, are heart-affecting-mercies, of great
                    impression and force, to enlarge pious hearts in the praises of God, so that
                    such know not how but to talk of Gods acts, and to speak of and publish his
                    wonderfull works. Deep troubles, when the waters come in unto thy soul, are wont
                    to produce vowes: vowes must be paid, <ref target="ecclesiastes_" corresp="ecclesiastes">
                        <hi rend="italic">It is better not vow, than vow and not to pay.</hi>
                    </ref>
                    <note xml:id="ecclesiastes" target="ecclesiastes_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> See Ecclesiastes 5:5-12. </p></note> I may say, that as none knows what
                    it is to fight and pursue such an enemy as this, but they that have fought and
                    pursued them: so none can imagine what it is to be captivated, and enslaved to
                    such atheisticall proud, wild, cruel, barbarous, bruitish (in one word)
                    diabolicall creatures as these, the worst of the heathen; nor what difficulties,
                    hardships, hazards, sorrows, anxieties and perplexities do unavoidably wait upon
                    such a condition, but those that have tryed it. No serious spirit then
                    (especially knowing any thing of this Gentlewomans piety) can imagine but that
                    the vows of God are upon her. Excuse her then if she come thus into publick, to
                    pay those vows. Come and hear what she hath to say. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic"> I am confident that no Friend of divine Providence will ever
                        repent his time and pains, spent in reading over these sheets, but will judg
                        them worth perusing again and again. </hi>
                </p>
                <p> Hear <hi rend="italic">Reader,</hi> you may see an instance of the Soveraignty
                    of God, who doth what he will with his own as well as others; and who may say to
                    him, <ref target="job_" corresp="job">
                        <hi rend="italic">What dost thou?</hi>
                    </ref>
                    <note xml:id="job" target="job_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                       See Job 9:12.</note> Here you may see an instance of the faith and
                    patience of the Saints, under the most heart-sinking tryals; here you may see,
                    the promises are breasts full of consolation, when all the world besides is
                    empty, and gives nothing but sorrow. That God is indeed the supream Lord of the
                    world, ruling the most unruly, weakening the most cruel and salvage, granting
                    his People mercy in the sight of the unmercifull, curbing the lusts of the most
                    filthy, holding the hands of the violent, delivering the prey from the mighty,
                        <hi rend="italic">and gathering together the out casts of</hi> Israel. Once
                    and again you have heard, but hear you may see, <hi rend="italic">that power
                        belongeth unto God;</hi> that our God is the God of Salvation, and to him
                    belong the issues from Death. That our God is in the Heavens, and doth what ever
                    pleases him. Here you have <ref target="sampson_" corresp="sampson">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sampsons</hi> Riddle </ref>
                    <note xml:id="sampson" target="sampson_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                         See Judges 14:14.</note> examplified, and that great promise, <hi
                        rend="italic">Rom.</hi> 8.28. verified, <hi rend="italic"> Out of the Eater
                        comes forth meat, and sweetness out of the strong; </hi> The worst of evils
                    working together for the best good. How evident is it that the Lord hath made
                    this Gentlewoman a gainer by all this affliction, that she can say, <hi
                        rend="italic"> 'tis good for her, yea better that she hath been, then that
                        she should not have been, thus afflicted. </hi>
                </p>
                <p> Oh how doth God shine forth in such things as these; </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Reader,</hi> if thou gettest no good by such a Declaration as
                    this, the fault must needs be thine own. Read therefore, Peruse, Ponder, and
                    from hence lay up something from the experience of another, against thine own
                    turn comes, that so thou also through patience and consolation of the Scripture
                    mayest have hope. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="text">
                <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192319:5"/>

                <head> A Narrative of the <hi rend="italic">CAPTIVITY AND</hi> RESTAURATION OF Mrs.
                    Mary Rowlandson. </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="decorInit">O</hi>N the tenth of <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1675.
                    Came the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> with great numbers upon <hi
                        rend="italic">Lancaster:</hi> Their first coming was about Sun-rising;
                    hearing the noise of some Guns, we looked out; several Houses were burning, and
                    the Smoke ascending to Heaven. There were five persons taken in one house, the
                    Father, and the Mother and a sucking Child, they knockt on the head; the other
                    two they took and carried away alive. Their were two others, who being out of
                    their Garison upon some occasion were set upon; one was knockt on the head, the
                    other escaped: Another their was who running along was shot and wounded, and
                    fell down; he pegged of them his life, promising them Money (as they told me)
                    but they would not hearken to <pb n="2" facs="tcp:192319:6"/> him but knockt him
                    in head, and stript him naked, and split open his Bowels. Another seeing many of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> about his Barn, ventured and went out, but
                    was quickly shot down. There were three others belonging to the same Garison who
                    were killed; the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> getting up upon the roof of the
                    Barn, had advantage to shoot down upon them over their Fortification. Thus these
                    murtherous wretches went on, burning, and destroying before them, </p>
                <p> At length they came and beset our own house, and quickly it was the dolefullest
                    day that ever mine eyes saw. The House stood upon the edg of a hill; some of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> got behind the hill, others into the Barn,
                    and others behind any thing that could shelter them; from all which places they
                    shot against the House, so that the Bullets seemed to fly like hail; and quickly
                    they wounded one man among us, then another, and then a third, About two hours
                    (according to my observation, in that amazing time) they had been about the
                    house before they prevailed to fire it (which they did with Flax and Hemp, which
                    they brought out of the Barn, and there being no desence about the House, only
                    two Flankers at two opposite corners, and one of them not finished) they fired
                    it once, and one ventured out and quenched it, but they quickly fired it again,
                    and that took. Now is that dreadfull hour come, that I have often heard of (in
                    time of War, as it was the case of others) but now mine eyes see it. Some in our
                    house were fighting <pb n="3" facs="tcp:192319:6"/> for their lives, others
                    wallowing in their blood, the House on fire over our heads, and the bloody
                    Heathen ready to knock us on the head, if we stired our: Now might we hear
                    Mothers &amp;; Children crying out for themselves, and one another, <hi
                        rend="italic">Lord, What shall we do?</hi> Then I took my Children (and one
                    of my sisters, hers) to go forth and leave the house: but as soon as we came to
                    the dore and appeared, the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> shot so thick that the
                    bulletts rattled against the House, as if one had taken an handfull of stones
                    and threw them, so that we were fain to give back. We had six stout Dogs
                    belonging to our Garrison, but none of them would stir, though another time, if
                    any <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> had come to the door, they were ready to fly
                    upon him and tear him down. The Lord hereby would make us the more to
                    acknowledge his hand, and to see that our help is alwayes in him. But out we
                    must go, the fire increasing, and coming along behind us, roaring, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Indians</hi> gaping before us with their Guns, Spears and
                    Hatchets to devour us. No sooner were we out of the House, but my Brother in Law
                    (being before wounded, in defending the house, in or near the throat) fell down
                    dead, wherat the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> scornfully shouted, and
                    hallowed, and were presently upon him, stripping off his cloaths, the bulletts
                    flying thick, one went through my side, and the same (as would seem) through the
                    bowels and hand of my dear Child in my arms. One of my elder Sisters Children,
                    named <hi rend="italic">William,</hi> had then his Leg broken, which the <hi
                        rend="italic">Indians</hi> perceiving, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192319:7"/> they
                    knockt him on head. Thus were we butchered by those merciless Heathen, standing
                    amazed, with the blood running down to our heels. My eldest Sister being yet in
                    the House, and seeing those wofull sights, the Infidels haling Mothers one way,
                    and Children another, and some wallowing in their blood: and her elder Son
                    telling her that her Son <hi rend="italic">William</hi> was dead, and my self
                    was wounded, she said, And, <hi rend="italic">Lord let me dy with them;</hi>
                    which was no sooner said, but she was struck with a Bullet, and fell down dead
                    over the threshold. I hope she is reaping the fruit of her good labours, being
                    faithfull to the service of God in her place. In her younger years she lay under
                    much trouble upon spiritual accounts, till it pleased God to make that precious
                    Scripture take hold of her heart, 2 <hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi
                        rend="italic"> And be said unto me my Grace is sufficient for thee. </hi>
                    More then twenty years after I have heard her tell how sweet and comfortable
                    that place was to her, But to return: The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> laid
                    hold of us, pulling me on way, and the Children another, and said, <hi
                        rend="italic">Come go along with us;</hi> I told them they would kill me:
                    they answered, <hi rend="italic"> If I were willing to go along with them, they
                        would not hurt me. </hi>
                </p>
                <p> Oh the dolefull sight that now was to behold at this House! <ref target="psalm_"
                        corresp="psalm">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Come, behold the works of the Lord, what dissolations he
                            has made in the Earth. </hi>
                    </ref>
                    <note xml:id="psalm" target="psalm_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        See Psalm 46:8-10. </note> Of thirty seven persons who were in this
                    one House, none escaped either present death, or a bitter captivity, save only
                    one, who might say as he. <hi rend="italic">Job</hi> 1.15. <hi rend="italic">And
                        I only am escaped alone to tell the News.</hi> There <pb n="5"
                        facs="tcp:192319:7"/> were twelve killed, some shot, some stab'd with their
                    Spears, some knock'd down with their Hatchets. When we are in prosperity, Oh the
                    little that we think of such dreadfull sights, and to see our dear Friends, and
                    Relations ly bleeding out their heart-blood upon the ground. There was one who
                    was chopt into the head with a Hatchet, and stript naked, and yet was crawling
                    up and down. It is a solemn sight to see so many Christians lying in their
                    blood, some here, and some there, like a company of Sheep torn by Wolves. All of
                    them stript naked by a company of hell-hounds, roaring, singing, ranting and
                    insulting, as if they would have torn our very hearts out; yet the Lord by his
                    Almighty power preserved a number of us from death, for there were twenty-four
                    of us taken alive and carried Captive. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">I had often before this said, that if the</hi> Indians <hi
                        rend="italic"> should come, I should chuse rather to be killed by them then
                        taken alive </hi> but when it came to the tryal my mind changed; their
                    glittering weapons so daunted my spirit, that I chose rather to go along with
                    those (as I may say) ravenous <ref target="beasts_" corresp="beasts"> Beats </ref>
                    <note xml:id="beasts" target="beasts_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p> beasts </p></note>, then that moment to end my dayes; and that I may
                    the better declare what happened to me during that grievous Captivity I shall
                    particularly speak of the severall Removes we had up and down the Wilderness. </p>
                <div n="1" type="part">
                    <head>
                        <ref target="remove_" corresp="remove"> The first Remove. </ref>
                    </head>
                    <note xml:id="remove" target="remove_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                        <p>
                            <graphic
                                url="https://www.ourbelovedkin.com/media/maps/marys-removes-base-map-water-layer-enhance-MAP-CL-7.jpg"
                            /> Rowlandson tells her story in a series of removals, or “removes,”
                            that mark changes to her location as the raiding party traveled across
                            New England. Lisa Brooks, professor of English and American Studies at Amherst College and the author of <hi rend="italic">Our Beloved Kin:  New History of King Philip's War</hi> created an interactive map of their movements as part of that project that is available <ref
                                target="https://amherstcollege.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapJournal/index.html?appid=2fa5ce906bc749cf849d576feeb6a9d1"
                                > here. </ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>

                    <p> Now away we must go with those Barbarous <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192319:8"/>
                        Creatures, with our bodies wounded and bleeding, and our hearts no less than
                        our bodies. About a mile we went that night, up upon a hill within sight of
                        the Town where they intended to lodge. There was hard by a vacant house
                        (deserted by the English before, for fear of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi>) I asked them whither I might not lodge in the house that
                        night? to which they answered, what will you love <hi rend="italic"> English
                            men </hi> still? this was the dolefullest night that ever my eyes saw.
                        Oh the roaring, and singing and danceing, and yelling of those black
                        creatures in the night, which made the place a lively resemblance of hell.
                        And as miserable was the wast that was there made, of Horses, Cuttle, Sheep,
                        Swine, Calves, Lambssia, Roasting Pigs, and Fowls [which they bad plundered
                        in the Town] some roasting, some lying and burning, and some boyling to feed
                        our merciless Enemles; who were joyfull enough though we were disconsolate.
                        To add to the dolefulness of the former day, and the dismalness of the
                        present night: my thoughts ran upon my losses and sad bereaved condition.
                        All was gone, my Husband gone (at least separated from me, he being in the
                        Bay; and to add to my grief, the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> told me they
                        would kill him as he came homeward) my Children gone, my Relations and
                        Friends gone, our House and home and all our comforts within door, and
                        without, all was gone, (except my life) and I knew not but the next moment
                        that might go too. There remained nothing to me but one poor wounded <pb
                            n="7" facs="tcp:192319:8"/> babe, and it seemed at present worse than
                        death that it was in such a pitiful condition, bespeaking, Compassion, and I
                        had an refreshing for it, nor suitable things to revive it, Little do many
                        think what is the savageness and bruitishness of this barbarous Enemy! even
                        those that seem to profess more than others among them, when the <hi
                            rend="italic">English</hi> have fallen into their hands. </p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="lancaster_" corresp="lancaster"> Those seven that were killed at <hi
                                rend="italic">Lancaster</hi> the summer before upon a Sabbath day </ref>
                        <note xml:id="lancaster" target="lancaster_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Rowlandson is referring to an attack on Lancaster in August of 1675
                                that left seven colonists dead. The attack is thought to have been
                                led by the Nipmuc sachem Monoco, who the Anglo-Americans referred to
                                as “One-Eye’d John.”</p></note> , and the one that was afterward
                        killed upon a week day, were stain and mangled in a barbarous manner, by
                        one-ey'd <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> and <ref target="allies_"
                            corresp="allies">
                            <hi rend="italic">Marlborough's</hi> Praying <hi rend="italic"
                                >Indians,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="allies" target="allies_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Suspicion for the Lancaster attack also fell on the “Praying
                                Indians” (Indians who had converted to Christianity and allied with
                                the colonists) of whom there was a large community in nearby
                                Marlborough. This was one of many “Christian Indian” communities in
                                the Bay Colony at the time. At the beginning of the war, their men
                                were recruited to fight for the colonists; already by this time,
                                however, fear that their true loyalties lay with the other side led
                                Bay colony officials to remove them from service and to form five
                                “praying towns” at a greater distance from English settlers. Later,
                                fears that even these plantations were too close to colonists’ homes
                                resulted in a further removal to Deer Island, where hundreds of the
                                interned inhabitants died in the harsh winter that followed.
                            </p></note> which <ref target="moseley_" corresp="moseley"> Capt. <hi
                                rend="italic">Mosely</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="moseley" target="moseley_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Captain Moseley was an infamous military figure who earned his fame
                                by fighting pirates on the New England coast. In August 1675, he
                                arrived in Marlborough. Based on controversial evidence, Moseley
                                accused fifteen of the “Praying Indians” of the Lancaster attack. He
                                took the accused to Boston to parade them through the streets,
                                “pinioned and fastened with lines from neck to neck” as Daniel
                                Gookin wrote. Gookin thought that the affair marked "a foundation
                                and beginning of much trouble, that befell both the English and the
                                Indians afterward."</p></note> brought to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Boston,</hi> as the <hi rend="italic"> Indians </hi> told me. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="part">
                    <head>The second Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> But now, the next morning, I must turn my back upon the
                            Town, and travel with them into the vast and isolate Wilderness, I knew
                            not whether. </hi> It is not my tongue, or pen can express the sorrows
                        of my heart, and bitterness of my spirit, that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> had
                        at this departure: but God was with me, in a wonderfull manner, carrying me
                        along, and bearing up my spirit, that it did not quite fail One of the <hi
                            rend="italic"> Indians </hi> carried my poor wounded Babe upon a horse,
                        it went moaning all along, I shall dy, I shall dy. I went on foot after it,
                        with sorrow that cannot be exprest. At length I took it off the horse, and
                        carried it in my armes till my strength failed, and <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192319:9"/> fell down with it: Then they set me upon a
                        horse with my wounded Child in my lap, and there being no furnitunre upon
                        the horse back; as we were going down a steep hill, we both fell over the
                        horses head, at which they like inhumane creatures laught, and rejoyced to
                        see it, though I thought we should there have ended our dayes, as overcome
                        with so many difficulties. But the Lord renewed my strength still, and
                        carried me along, that I might see more of his Power; yea, so much that I
                        could never have thought of, had I not experienced it. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> After this it quickly began to snow, and when night came
                            on, they stopt: and now down I must sit in the snow, by a little fire,
                            and a few boughs behind me, with my sick Child in my lap; and calling
                            much for water, being now (through the wound) fallen into a violent
                            Fever. </hi> My own wound also growing so stiff, that I could scarce sit
                        down or rise up; yet so it must be, that I must sit all this cold winter
                        night upon the cold snowy ground, with my sick Child in my armes, looking
                        that every hour would be the last of its life; and having no Christian
                        friend near me, either to comfort or help me. <hi rend="italic">Oh,</hi> I
                            <hi rend="italic"> may see the wonderfull power of God, that my Spirit
                            did not utterly sink under my affliction: still the Lord upheld me with
                            his gracious and mercifull Spirit, and we were both alive to see the
                            light of the next morning. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="part">
                    <head>The third remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> The morning being come, they prepared to go </hi>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192319:9"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> their way: One of the </hi> Indians <hi rend="italic">
                            got up upon a horse, and they set me up behind him, with my poor sick
                            Babe in my lap. </hi> A very wearisome and tedious day I had of it; what
                        with my own wound, and my Childs being so exceeding sick, and in a
                        lamentable condition with her wound. It may be easily judged what a poor
                        feeble condition we were in, there being not the least crumb of refreshing
                        that came within either of our mouths, from <hi rend="italic">Wednesday</hi>
                        night to <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> night, except only a little cold
                        water. This day in the afternoon, about an hour by Sun, we came to the place
                        where they intendded, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> an <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian</hi> Town, called <ref target="menimiset_" corresp="menimiset">
                            <hi rend="italic">Wenimesset,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="menimiset" target="menimiset_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Menimiset was an important Nipmuc refuge and gathering place along
                                the Ware River. It had operated as a sanctuary for councils since
                                the beginning of the war, and marked the first “Indian Town” that
                                Rowlandson encountered. She was surprised at how many people lived
                                there. </p></note> Norward of <hi rend="italic">Quabaug.</hi> When
                        we were come, Oh the number of Pagans (now merciless enemies) that there
                        came about me, that I may say as <hi rend="italic">David,</hi> Psal. 27.13,
                            <hi rend="italic">I had fainted, unless I had believed, &amp;c</hi> The
                        next day was the Sabbath: I then remembred how careless <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> had been of Gods holy time: how many Sabbaths I had lost and
                        mispent, and how evily I had walked in Gods sight; which lay so close unto
                        my spirit, that it was easie for me to see how righteous it was with God to
                        cut off the threed of my life, and cast me out of his presence for ever. Yet
                        the Lord still shewed mercy to me, and upheld me; and as he wounded me with
                        one hand, so he healed me with the other. This day there came to me one <ref
                            target="pepper_" corresp="pepper">
                            <hi rend="italic">Robbert Pepper</hi>
                        </ref><note xml:id="pepper" target="pepper_" type="editorial"
                            resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Robert Pepper was captured on September 4th, 1675, when Captain
                                Beers and a group of 36 colonists were ambushed on their way to
                                reinforce the garrison in Northfield, Massachusetts. Beers and many
                                of his soldiers were killed in the conflict. </p></note> (a man
                        belonging to <hi rend="italic">Roxbury</hi> ) who was taken in Captain <hi
                            rend="italic">Beers</hi> his Fight, and had been now a considerable time
                        with the <hi rend="italic">Indians;</hi> and up with them almost as far as
                         <hi
                            rend="italic">Albany</hi> to see <ref target="metacom_" corresp="metacom">
                            king <hi rend="italic">Philip,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="metacom" target="metacom_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Wampanoag leader Metacom, called “King Philip” by the English
                                settlers.</p></note> as he told me, and was now very lately come
                        into these parts. Hearing, I say, that I was in this <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Town, he obtained leave to come and see me. He told me, he
                        himself was wounded in the leg at Captain <hi rend="italic">Beers</hi> his
                        Fight; and was not able some time to go, but as they carried him, and as he
                        took Oaken leaves and laid to his wound, and through the blessing of God he
                        was able to travel again. Then I took Oaken leaves and laid to my side, and
                        with the blessing of God it cured me also; yet before the cure was wrought,
                        I may say, as it is in <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 38.5, 6. <hi
                            rend="italic"> My wounds stink and are corrupt, I am troubled, I am
                            bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long. I </hi> sat much
                        alone with a poor wounded Child in my lap, which moaned night and day,
                        having nothing to revive the body, or cheer the spirits of her, but in stead
                        of that, sometimes one <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> would come and tell me
                        one hour, that your Master will knock your Child in the head, and then a
                        second, and then a third, your Master will quickly knock your Child in the
                        head. </p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="job_" corresp="job">
                            <hi rend="italic"> This was the comfort I had from them, miserable
                                comforters are ye all, as he said. </hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="job" target="job_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> See Job 16:2. </p></note> Thus nine dayes I sat upon my knees, with
                        my Babe in my lap, till my flesh was raw again; my Child being even ready to
                        depart this sorrowfull world, they bade me carry it out to another Wigwam (I
                        suppose because they would not be troubled with such spectacles) Whither I
                        went with a very heavy heart, and down I sat with the picture of death in my
                        lap. <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192319:10"/> About two houres in the night, my
                        sweet Babe, like a Lambe departed this life, on <hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi>
                        18. 1675. It being about <hi rend="italic">six yeares,</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">five months</hi> old. It was <hi rend="italic">nine
                            dayes</hi> from the first wounding, in this miserable condition, without
                        any refreshing of one nature or other, except a little cold water. I cannot
                        but take notice, how at another time I could not bear to be in the room
                        where any dead person was, but now the case is changed; I must and could ly
                        down by my dead Babe, side by side all the night after. I have thought since
                        of the wonderfull goodness of God to me, in preserving me in the use of my
                        reason and senses, in that distressed time, that I did not use wicked and
                        violent means to end my own miserable life. In the morning, when they
                        understood that my child was dead they sent for me home to my Masters
                        Wigwam: (by my Master in this writing, must be understood <ref
                            target="quanopin_" corresp="quanopin">
                            <hi rend="italic">Quanopin,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="quanopin" target="quanopin_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Quanopin, or Quanopen, was a Narragansett leader. He had three
                                wives, one of whom, Weetamoo (or Weetamoe) was Metacom's
                                brother-in-law and herself a sachem of the ​​Pocasset Wampanoag.
                                Rowlandson was sold to Quanopin by the Narragansett man who had
                                first captured her. </p></note> who was a <ref target="sagamore_"
                            corresp="sagamore">
                            <hi rend="italic">Saggamore,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="sagamore" target="sagamore_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Like “Sachem,” “Sagamore” is an anglicization of the Indigenous term
                                for a tribal leader. The word can be used to denote: 1. the leader
                                of a regional tribe or 2. the leader of a confederation of tribes.
                            </p></note> and married King <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi> wives
                        Sister; not that he first took me, but I was sold to him by another <hi
                            rend="italic"> Narrhaganset Indian, </hi> who took me when first I came
                        out of the Garison) <hi rend="italic">I</hi> went to take up my dead child
                        in my arms to carry it with me, but they bid me let it alone: there was no
                        resisting, but goe <hi rend="italic">I</hi> must and leave it. When <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> had been at my masters <hi rend="italic"
                            >wigwam,</hi> I took the first opportunity I could get, to go look after
                        my dead child: when I came <hi rend="italic">I</hi> askt them what they had
                        done with it? then they told me it was upon the hill: then they went and <pb
                            n="10" facs="tcp:192319:11"/> shewed me where it was, where I saw the
                        ground was newly digged, and there they told me they had buried it: <hi
                            rend="italic"> There I left that at Child in the Wilderness, and must
                            commit it, and my self also in this Wilderness-condition, to him who is
                            above all. </hi> God having taken away this dear Child, I went to see my
                        daughter <hi rend="italic">Mary,</hi> who was at this same <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian Town,</hi> at a <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> not very far off,
                        though we had little liberty or opportunity to see one another: she was
                        about ten years old, &amp; taken from the door at first by a <hi
                            rend="italic">Praying Ind</hi> &amp; afterward sold for a gun. When I
                        came in sight, she would fall a weeping; at which they were provoked, and
                        would not let me come near her, but bade me be gone; which was a
                        heart-cutting word to me. I had one Child dead, another in the Wilderness, I
                        knew not where, the third they would not let me come near to: <ref
                            target="genesis_" corresp="genesis">
                            <hi rend="italic">Me</hi> (as he said)</ref>
                        <note xml:id="genesis" target="genesis_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> See Genesis 42:36. </p></note>
                        <hi rend="italic"> have ye bereaved of my Children,</hi> Joseph <hi
                            rend="italic">is not, and</hi> Simeon <hi rend="italic">is not, and ye
                            will take</hi> Benjamin <hi rend="italic">also, all these things are
                            against me.</hi> I could not for still in this condition, but kept,
                        walking from one place to another. And as I was going along, my heart was
                        even overwhelm'd with the thoughts of my condition, and that I should have
                        Children, <hi rend="italic">and a Nation which</hi> I <hi rend="italic">knew
                            not ruled over them.</hi> Whereupon I earnestly entreated the Lord, that
                        he would consider my low estate, and shew me a token for good, and if it
                        were his blessed will, some sign and hope of some relief. And indeed quickly
                        the Lord answered, in some measure, my poor prayers: <pb n="11"
                            facs="tcp:192319:11"/> For as I was going up and down mourning and
                        lamenting my condition, my Son came to me, and asked me how I did; I had not
                        seen him before, since the destruction of the Town, and I knew not where he
                        was, till <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was informed by himself, that he was
                        amongst a smaller percel of <hi rend="italic">Indians,</hi> whose place was
                        about six miles off; with tears in his eyes, he asked me whether his Sister
                            <hi rend="italic">Sarah</hi> was dead; and told me he had seen his
                        Sister <hi rend="italic">Mary;</hi> and prayed me, that I would not be
                        troubled in reference to himself. The occasion of his coming to see me at
                        this time, was this: <hi rend="italic"> There was, as I said, about six
                            miles from us, a smal Plantation of </hi> Indians, <hi rend="italic">
                            where it seems he had been during his Captivity: and at this time, there
                            were some Forces of the </hi> Ind. <hi rend="italic"> gathered out of
                            our company, and some also from them (among whom was my Sons master) to
                            go to assault and burn </hi> Medfield: <hi rend="italic"> In this time
                            of the absence of his master, his dame brought him to see me. </hi> I
                        took this to be some gracious answer to my earnest and unfeigned desire. The
                        next day, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> to this, the <hi rend="italic">
                            Indians </hi> returned from <hi rend="italic">Medfield,</hi> all the
                        company, for those that belonged to the other smal company, came thorough
                        the Town that now we were at But before they came to us, Oh! the <ref
                            target="outragious_" corresp="outragious"> outragious </ref>
                        <note xml:id="outragious" target="outragious_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Rowlandson means something like “full of rage.” </p></note> roaring
                        and hooping that there was: They began their din about a mile before they
                        came to us. By their noise and hooping they signified how many they had
                        destroyed (which was at that time twenty three) Those that were with us at
                        home, were <pb n="12" facs="tcp:192319:12"/> gathered together as soon as
                        they heard the hooping, and every time that the other went over their
                        number, these at home gave a shout, that the very Earth rung again: And thus
                        they continued till those that had been upon the expedition were come up to
                        the <hi rend="italic">Sagamores Wigwam;</hi> and then, Oh, the hideous
                        insulting and triumphing that there was over some <hi rend="italic">English
                            mens</hi> scalps that they had taken (as their manner it) and brought
                        with them. I cannot but take notice of the wonderfull mercy of God to me in
                        those afflictions, in sending me a Bible one of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi> that came from <hi rend="italic">Medfield</hi> fight, had
                        brought some plunder, came to me, and asked me, if I would have a Bible, he
                        had got one in his Basket, I was glad of it, and asked him, whether be
                        thought the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> would let me read? he answered,
                        yes; so I took the Bible, and in that melancholy time, it came into my mind
                        to read first the 28. <hi rend="italic">Chap.</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Deut.</hi> which I did, and when I had read it, my dark heart wrought
                        on this manner, <hi rend="italic"> That there was no mercy for me, that the
                            blessings were gone, and the Curses Came in their room, and that </hi> I
                            <hi rend="italic">bad lost my opportunity.</hi> But the Lord helped me
                        still to go one reading till <hi rend="italic">I</hi> came to <hi
                            rend="italic">Chap.</hi> 30 the seven first verses, where I sound, <hi
                            rend="italic"> There was mercy promised again, if we would return to him
                            by reportance; and though we were scartered from one end of the Earth to
                            the other, yet the Lord would gather us together, and turn all those
                            curses upon our Enemies, </hi> I do not desire to live to forget this
                        Scripture, and what comfort it was to me. </p>
                    <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192319:12"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Now the</hi> Ind. <hi rend="italic"> began to talk of
                            removing from this place, some one way, and some another. </hi> There
                        were now besides my self nine, <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Captives in
                        this place (all of them Children, except one Woman) <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                        got an opportunity to go and take my leave of them; they being to go one
                        way, and I another, I <hi rend="italic"> asked them whether they were
                            earnest with God for deliverance, </hi> they told me, they did as they
                        were able, and it was some comfort to me, that the Lord stirred up <hi
                            rend="italic">Children to look to him.</hi> The Woman <hi rend="italic"
                            >viz.</hi> Goodwife <hi rend="italic">Jostin</hi> told me, she should
                        never see me again, and that she could find in her heart to run away; I
                        wisht her not to run away by any means, for we were near <hi rend="italic"
                            >thirty miles</hi> from any <hi rend="italic"> English Town, </hi> and
                        she very big with Child, and had but one week to reckon; and another Child
                        in her Arms, two years old, and bad Rivers there were to go over, &amp; we
                        were feeble, with our poor &amp; course entertainment. I had my Bible with
                        me, I pulled it out, and asked her whether she would read; we opened the
                        Bible and lighted on <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 27. in which Psalm we
                        especially took notice of that, <hi rend="italic"> ver. alt, Wait on the
                            Lord, Be of good courage, and he shall strengthen thine Heart, wait
                        </hi> I <hi rend="italic">say on the Lord.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="part">
                    <head>The fourth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">And now</hi> I <hi rend="italic">must part with that
                            little Company</hi> I <hi rend="italic">had.</hi> Here I parted from my
                        Daughter <hi rend="italic">Mary,</hi> (whom I never saw again till <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> saw her in <hi rend="italic">Dorcester,</hi>
                        returned from Captivity, and from four little Cousins <pb n="14"
                            facs="tcp:192319:13"/> and Neighbours, some of which I never saw
                        afterward: the Lord only knows the end of them. Amongst them also was that
                        poor Woman before mentioned, who came to a sad end, as some of the company
                        told me in my travel: She having much grief upon her Spirit, about her
                        miserable condition, being so near her time, she would be often asking the
                            <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> to let her go home; they not being
                        willing to that, and yet vexed with her importunity, gathered a great
                        company together about her, and stript her naked, and set her in the midst
                        of them; and when they had sung and danced about her (in their hellish
                        manner) as long as they pleased, they knockt her on head, and the child in
                        her arms with her: when they had done that, they made a fire and put them
                        both into it, and told the other Children that were with them, that if they
                        attempted to go home, they would serve them in like manner: The Children
                        said, she did not shed one tear, but prayed all the while. But to return to
                        my own Journey; we travelled about half a day or little more, and came to a
                        desolate place in the Wilderness, where there were no <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wigwams</hi> or <hi rend="italic"> Inhabitants </hi> before; we came
                        about the middle of the afternoon to this place; cold and wet, and snowy,
                        and hungry, and weary, and no refreshing, for man, but the cold ground to
                        sit on, and our poor <hi rend="italic">Indian cheer.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Heart-aking thoughts here</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> had
                            about my poor Children, who were scattered up and down among the </hi>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192319:14"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> wild beasts of the forrest: </hi> My head was light &amp;
                        dissey (either through hunger or hard lodging, or trouble or altogether) my
                        knees feeble, my body raw by sitting double night and day, that I cannot
                        express to man the affliction that lay upon my Spirit, but the Lord helped
                        me at that time to express it to himself. I opened my Bible to read, and the
                        Lord brought that precious Scripture to me, <hi rend="italic">Jer.</hi>
                        31.16. <hi rend="italic"> Thus saith the Lord, refrain thy voice from
                            weeping, and thine eyes from tears, for thy work shall be rewarded, and
                            they shall come again from the land of the Enemy. </hi> This was a sweet
                        Cordial to me, when <hi rend="italic">I</hi> sat down, and weept sweetly
                        over this Scripture. At this place we continued about four dayes. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="part">
                    <head>The fifth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> The occasion (as I thought) of their moving at this time,
                            was, the </hi> English <hi rend="italic"> Army it being near and
                            following them: </hi> For they went, as if they had gone for their
                        lives, for some considerable way, and then they made a stop, and chose some
                        of their stoutest men, and sent them back to hold the <hi rend="italic"
                            >English</hi> Army in play whilst the rest escaped: And then, <ref
                            target="jehu_" corresp="jenu">
                            <hi rend="italic">like</hi> Jehu </ref>
                        <note xml:id="jehu" target="jehu_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> like Jesus </p>
                        </note> , <hi rend="italic"> they marched on furiously, with their old, and
                            with their young: some carried their old decrepit mothers, some carried
                            one, and some another. </hi> Four of them carried a great <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian</hi> upon a Bier; but going through a thick Wood
                        with him, they were hindred, and could make no hast; whereupon they took <pb
                            n="16" facs="tcp:192319:15"/>
                        him upon their backs, and carried him, one
                        at a time, till they came to <ref target="bacquaug_" corresp="bacquaug">
                            <hi rend="italic">Bacquaug</hi> River.</ref>
                        <note xml:id="bacquaug" target="bacquaug_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Paquaug River, now called Miller's River. If it refers to the river,
                                “Paquaug” may translate to “clear water.” The word may also refer to
                                the town, Athol, near where the travelers were likely to have
                                crossed. Athol was originally called Pequiog or Pequoiag (“cleared
                                land”) by Nipmuc inhabitants.</p></note> Upon a <hi rend="italic"
                            >Friday,</hi> a little after noon we came to this River. When all the
                        company was come up, and were gathered together, I thought to count the
                        number of them, but they were so many, and being somewhat in motion, it was
                        beyond my skil. In this travel, because of my wound, I was somewhat favoured
                        in my load; I carried only my knitting work and two quarts of parched meal:
                        Being very faint I asked my mistriss to give me one spoonfull of the meal,
                        but she would not give me a taste. They quickly sell to cutting dry trees,
                        to make Rafts to carry them over the river: and soon my turn came to go
                        over:p By the advantage of some brush which they had laid upon the Raft to
                        sit upon, I did not wet my foot (which many of themselves at the other end
                        were mid-leg deep) which cannot but be acknowledged as a favour of God to my
                        weakned body, it being a very cold time. I was not before acquainted with
                        such kind of doings or dangers. <hi rend="italic">When thou passest through
                            the water</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> will be with thee, and through the
                            Rivers they overflow thee, Isai. </hi> 43.2. A certain number of us got
                        over the River that night, but it was the night after the Sabbath before all
                        the company was got over. On the <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> they boyled
                        an old Horses leg which they had got, and so we drank of the broth, as soon
                        as they thought it was ready, and when it was almost all gone, they filled
                        it up again. </p>
                    <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192319:15"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> The first week of my being among them, I hardly ate any
                            thing; the second week, I found my stomach grow very faint for want of
                            something; and yet it was very hard to get down their filthy trash: but
                            the third week, though I could think how formerly my stomach would turn
                            against this or that, and I could starve and dy before I could eat such
                            things, yet they were sweet and savoury to my taste. </hi> I was at this
                        time knitting a pair of white cotton stockins for my mistriss: and had not
                        yet wrought upon a Sabbath day; when the Sabbath came they bade me go to
                        work; I told them it was the Sabbath-day, and desired them to let me rest,
                        and told them I would do as much more to morrow; to which they answered me,
                        they would break my face. And here <hi rend="italic">I</hi> cannot but take
                        notice of the strange providence of God in preserving the heathen: They were
                        many hundreds, old and young, some sick, and some lame many had <ref
                            target="papoose_" corresp="papoose">
                            <hi rend="italic">Papooses</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="papoose" target="papoose_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Now generally regarded as an offensive term, “papoose” is a
                                borrowing from Algonquin to describe a young North American
                                indigenous child. In more recent use, it can also refer to cloth
                                baby carriers that wrap around the torso. </p></note> at their
                        backs, the greatest number at this time with us, were <ref target="squaw_"
                            corresp="squaw">
                            <hi rend="italic">Squaws,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="squaw" target="squaw_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Now generally regarded as an offensive term, “squaw” refers to a
                                North American indigenous woman or wife. The term has a split
                                history: as it derives from the Mohawk language, adapted by French
                                and Canadian settlers, it was always offensive. As it derives from
                                the Algonquin, “squaw” was originally a neutral term that took on
                                racist connotations through its Anglo-American usage through the
                                eighteenth century and afterwards. </p></note> and they travelled
                        with all they had, bag and baggage, and yet they got over this River
                        aforesaid; and on <hi rend="italic">Munday</hi> they set their <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwams</hi> on fire, and away they went: On that very day
                        came the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Army after them to this River, and
                        saw the smoak of their <hi rend="italic">Wigwams,</hi> and yet this River
                        put a stop to them. God did not give them courage or activity to go over
                        after us; we were not ready for so great a mercy as victory and deliverance;
                        if we had been, God would have sound out a way for the <hi rend="italic"
                            >English</hi>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:192319:16"/> to have passed this River, as well as for
                        the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> with their <hi rend="italic">Squaws</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">Children,</hi> and all their <hi rend="italic">
                            Luggage: Oh that my People had hearkened to me, and </hi> Israel <hi
                            rend="italic">had walked in my ways,</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> should
                            soon have subdued their Enemies, and turned my hand against their
                            Adversaries, </hi> Psal. 81.13.14. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="part">
                    <head>The sixth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">On</hi> Munday ( <hi rend="italic">as</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic">said</hi> ) <hi rend="italic">they set their</hi> Wigwams
                            <hi rend="italic">on fire, and went away.</hi> It was a cold morning,
                        and before us there was a great Brook with ice on it; some waded throgh it,
                        up to the knees &amp; higher, but others went till they came to a
                        Beaver-dam, and I amongst them, where through the good providence of God, I
                        did not wet my foot. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> went along that day mourning
                        and lamenting, leaving farther my own Country, and travelling into the vast
                        and howling <hi rend="italic">Wilderness,</hi> and I understood something of
                            <hi rend="italic">Lot</hi> 's Wife's Temptation, <ref target="lot_"
                            corresp="lot">
                            <hi rend="italic">when she looked back:</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="lot" target="lot_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> In the Old Testament, as Lot and his family fled their burning
                                cities, Lot’s wife looked back. They had been warned not to do so
                                and she was turned into a pillar of salt. In Luke 17:32, Jesus
                                references the story: “Remember Lot’s Wife!” The lesson of the tale
                                is ambiguous, and has been interpreted in different ways by various
                                traditions. </p></note> we came that day to a great Swamp, by the
                        side of which we took up our lodging that night. When I came to the brow of
                        the hill, that looked toward the Swamp, I thought we had been come to a great
                            <hi rend="italic"> Indian </hi> Town (though there were none but our own
                        Company) The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> were as thick as the trees: it
                        seemd as if there had been a thousand Hatchets going at once: if one looked
                        before one, there was nothing but <hi rend="italic">Indians,</hi> and behind
                        one, nothing but <hi rend="italic">Indians,</hi> and so on either hand, I my
                        self in the midst, and no Christian soul near me, <hi rend="italic"> and yet
                            how </hi>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192319:16"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> hath the Lord preserved me in safety? Oh the experience
                            that I have had of the goodness of God, to me and mine! </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="part">
                    <head>The seventh Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> After a restless and hungry night there, we had a
                            wearisome time of it the next day. </hi> The Swamp by which we lay, was,
                        as it were, a deep Dungeon, and an exceeding high and steep hill before it.
                        Before I got to the top of the hill, I thought my heart and legs, and all
                        would have broken, and failed me. What through faintness, and soreness of
                        body, it was a grievous day of travel to me. <hi rend="italic">As we went
                            along, I saw a place where</hi> English <hi rend="italic"> Cattle had
                            been: that was comfort to me, such as it was: quickly after that we came
                            to an </hi> English <hi rend="italic"> Path, which so took with me, that
                            I thought I could have freely lyan down and dyed. </hi> That day, a
                        little after noon, we came to <ref target="squaukheag_" corresp="squaukheag">
                            <hi rend="italic">Squaukheag,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="squaukheag" target="squaukheag_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> The travelers were here moving through Sokoki territory. The
                                colonists referred to the southernmost Sokoki town as Squaukheag.
                                Colonists later named it “Northfield,” as it was the northernmost
                                “field” habitat that they settled. Rowlandson was happy to see the signs
                                of settlement; she notes with hope a “place where English cattle had
                                once been.” </p></note> where the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi>
                        quickly spread themselves over the deserted <hi rend="italic">English</hi>
                        Fields, gleaning what they could find; some pickt up ears of Wheat that were
                        crickled down, some found ears of <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Corn, some
                        found <ref target= "ground-nut_" corresp="ground-nut"> Ground-nuts</ref><note xml:id="ground-nut" target="ground-nut_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Groundnuts refers to the plant Apios Americana, which is native to North America. Its tubers resemble potatoes and the plant was a common source of starch for Indigenous peoples. </p></note>, and others sheaves of Wheat that were frozen together
                            <ref target="shock_" corresp="shock"> in the shock </ref>
                        <note xml:id="shock" target="shock_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>
                                <graphic
                                    url="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Crops,_Northdale_-_geograph.org.uk_-_978259.jpg/"
                                > </graphic> A shock, or stook, is a pile of cut-grain (usually
                                wheat, oats, or barley) arranged in a conical stack to allow the
                                stalks to dry before threshing. Threshing is the process by which
                                farmers loosen the edible part of the grain from the husk and straw.
                            </p></note>, &amp; went to threshing of them out. My self got two ears
                        of <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Corn, and whilst I did but turn my back,
                        one of them was stolen from me, which much troubled me. There came an <hi
                            rend="italic"> Indian </hi> to them at that time, with a basket of
                        Horse-liver; I asked him to give me a piece: <hi rend="italic">What,</hi>
                        sayes he, <hi rend="italic">can you eat Horse-liver?</hi> I told him, I
                        would try, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192319:17"/>
                        if he would give a piece, which he did,
                        and I laid it on the coals to rost; but before it was half ready, they got
                        half of it away from me, so that I was fain to take the rest and eat it as
                        it was, with the blood about my mouth, and yet a savoury bit it was to me:
                            <hi rend="italic"> For to the hungry Soul every bitter thing is sweet.
                        </hi> A solemn sight methought it was, to see Fields of wheat and <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian</hi> Corn forsaken and spoiled: and the remainders
                        of them to be food for our merciless Enemies. That night we had a mess of
                        wheat for our Supper. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="part">
                    <head>The eighth Remove.</head>
                    <p> On the morrow morning we must go over <ref target="connecticot_" corresp="connecticot">
                            the River, <hi rend="italic">i. e. Connecticot,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="connecticot" target="connecticot_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> The Connecticut River. </p></note> to
                        meet with King <hi rend="italic">Philip,</hi> two <hi rend="italic"
                            >Cannoos</hi> full, they had carried over, the next Turn I my self was
                        to go; but as my foot was upon the <hi rend="italic">Cannoo</hi> to step in,
                        there was a sudden out-cry among them, and I must step back; and instead of
                        going over the River, I must go four or five miles up the River farther
                        Northward. Some of the <hi rend="italic">indians</hi> ran one way, and some
                        another. The cause of this rout was, as I thought, their espying some <hi
                            rend="italic">English Scouts,</hi> who were thereabout. In this travel
                        up the River; about noon the Company made a stop, and sate down; some to
                        eat, and others to rest them. As I sate amongst them, musing of things past,
                        my Son <hi rend="italic">Joseph</hi> unexpectedly came to me: we asked of
                        each others welfare, bemoaning our dolefull condition, and the change that
                        had come upon us: We had Husbands and </p>
                    <pb n="21" facs="tcp:192319:18"/>
                    <p> Father, and Children, and Sisters, and Friends, and Relations, and House,
                        and Home, and many Comforts of this Life: but now we may say, <ref
                            target="naked_" corresp="naked"> as Job, </ref>
                        <note xml:id="naked" target="naked_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> See Job 1:21. </p></note>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Naked came I out of my Mothers Womb, and naked shall I
                            return: The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, Blessed be the Name
                            of the Lord. </hi> I asked him whither he would read; he told me, he
                        earnestly desired it, I gave him my Bible, and he lighted upon that
                            comfortable Scripture, <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi
                            rend="italic"> I shall not dy but live, and declare the works of the
                            Lord: the Lord hath chastened me sore, yet he hath not given me over to
                            death. </hi> Look here, <hi rend="italic">Mother</hi> (sayes he) did you
                        read this? And here I may take occasion to mention one principall ground of
                        my setting forth these Lines: even as the Psalmist sayes, <hi rend="italic"
                            >To declare the Works of the Lord,</hi> and his wonderfull Power in
                        carrying us along, preserving us in the <hi rend="italic">Wilderness,</hi>
                        while under the Enemies hand, and returning of us in safety again. And His
                        goodness in bringing to my hand so many comfortable and suitable Scriptures
                        in my distress. But to Return, We travelled on till night; and in the
                        morning, we must go over the River to <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>'s Crew.
                        When I was in the Cannoo, I could not but be amazed at the numerous crew of
                        Pagans that were on the Bank on the other side. When I came ashore, they
                        gathered all about me, I sitting alone in the midst: I observed they asked
                        one another questions, and laughed, and rejoyced over their Gains and
                        Victories. </p>
                    <pb n="22" facs="tcp:192319:19"/>
                    <p> Then my heart began to fail: and I fell a weeping; which was the first time
                        to my remembrance, that I wept before them. Although I had met with so much
                        Affliction, and my heart was many times ready to break, yet could I not shed
                        one tear in their sight: but rather had been all this while in a maze, and
                        like one astonished: but now I may say as, <hi rend="italic">Psal</hi>
                        137.1. <hi rend="italic">By the Rivers of</hi> Babylon, <hi rend="italic">
                            there we sate down: yea, we wept when we remembred Zion. </hi> There one
                        of them asked me, why I wept, I could hardly tell what to say: yet I
                        answered, they would kill me: No, said he, none will hurt you. Then came one
                        of them and gave me two spoon-fulls of Meal to comfort me, and another gave
                        me half a pint of <ref target="pease_" corresp="pease"> Pease </ref>
                        <note xml:id="pease" target="pease_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Peas (archaic).</p></note> ; which was more worth than many Bushels
                        at another time. Then I went to see King <hi rend="italic">Philip,</hi> he
                        bade me come in and sit down, and asked me whether I would smoke it (a usual
                        Complement now adayes amongst Saints and Sinners) but this no way suited me.
                        For though I had formerly used Tobacco, yet I had left it ever since I was
                        first taken. <hi rend="italic"> It seems to be a Bait, the Devil layes to
                            make men loose their precious time: </hi> I remember with shame, how
                        formerly, when I had taken two or three pipes, I was presently ready for
                        another, such a bewitching thing it is: But I thank God, he has now given me
                        power over it: surely there are many who may be better imployed than to ly
                        sucking a stinking Tobacco-pipe. </p>
                    <p> Now the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> gather their Forces to go against <pb
                            n="23" facs="tcp:192319:19"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">North-Hampton:</hi> over-night one went about yelling and
                        hooting to give notice of the design. Whereupon they fell to boyling of
                        Ground-nuts, and parching of Corn (as many as had it) for their Provision:
                        and in the morning away they went: <hi rend="italic">During my abode in this
                            place,</hi> Philip <hi rend="italic">spake to me to make a shirt for his
                            boy, which</hi> I <hi rend="italic">did, for which he gave me a
                            shilling:</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> offered the mony to my master, but
                            he bade me keep it: and with it </hi> I <hi rend="italic">bought a piece
                            of Horse flesh.</hi> Afterwards he asked me to make a Cap for his boy,
                        for which he invited me to Dinner. I went, and he gave me a Pancake, about
                        as big as two fingers; it was made of parched wheat, beaten, and fryed in
                        Bears grease, but <hi rend="italic">I</hi> though <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                        never tasted pleasanter meat in my life. There was a <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw</hi> who spake to me to make a shirt for her <ref target="sannup_"
                            corresp="sannup">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sannup,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="sannup" target="sannup_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> A borrowing from Massachusett, Sannup refers to a North American
                                indigenous husband or alternately to a man with authority under that
                                of a chief.</p></note> for which she gave me a piece of Bear.
                        Another asked me to knit a pair of Stockins, for which she gave me a quart
                        of Pease: I boyled my Pease and Bear together, and invited my master and
                        mistriss to dinner, but the proud Gossip, be cause I served them both in one
                        Dish, would eat nothing, except one bit that he gave her upon the point of
                        his knife. Hearing that my son was come to this place, I went to see him,
                        and found him lying flat upon the ground: I asked him how he could sleep so?
                        he answered me, <hi rend="italic">That he was not asleep, but at
                            Prayer;</hi> and lay so that they might not observe what he was doing. I
                        pray God he may remember these things now he is returned in safety. At <pb
                            n="24" facs="tcp:192319:20"/> this Place (the Sun now getting higher)
                        what with the beams and heat of the Sun, and the smoak of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwams,</hi> I thought I should have been blind, I could
                        scarce discern one <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> from another, There was
                        here one <hi rend="italic">Mary Thurston</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Medfield,</hi> who seeing how it was with me, lent me a Hat to wear:
                        but as soon as I was gone, the <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> (who owned that
                            <hi rend="italic">Mary Thurston</hi> ) came running after me, and got it
                        away again. <hi rend="italic">Here was the</hi> Squaw <hi rend="italic">that
                            gave me one spoonfull of Meal.</hi> I put it in my Pocket to keep it
                        safe: yet notwithstanding some body stole it, but put five <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian</hi> Corns in the room of it: which Corns were the greatest
                        Provisions I had in my travel for one day. </p>
                    <p> The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> returning from <hi rend="italic"
                            >North-Hamptom,</hi> brought with them some Horses, and Sheep, and other
                        things which they had taken: I desired them, that they would carry me to <hi
                            rend="italic">Albany,</hi> upon one of those Horses, and sell me for
                        Powder: for so they had sometimes discoursed. I was utterly hopless of
                        getting home on foot, the way that I came. I could hardly bear to think of
                        the many weary steps I had taken, to come to this place. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="part">
                    <head>The ninth Remove.</head>
                    <p> But in stead of going either to <hi rend="italic">Albany</hi> or homeward,
                        we must go five miles up the River, and then go over it. Here we abode a
                        while. Here lived a sorry <hi rend="italic">Indian,</hi> who spoke to me to
                        make him a shirt, when I had done it, he would pay me nothing. But <pb
                            n="25" facs="tcp:192319:20"/> he living by the River side, where I often
                        went to fetch water, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> would often be putting of him
                        in mind, and calling for my pay: at last he told me, if <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> would make another shirt, for a <hi rend="italic">Papoos</hi>
                        not yet born, he would give me a knife, which he did when I had done it. <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> carried the knife in, and my master asked me to
                        give it him, and I was not a little glad that I had any thing that they
                        would accept of, and be pleased with. When we were at this place, my Masters
                        maid came home, she had been gone <hi rend="italic">three weeks</hi> into
                        the <hi rend="italic">Narrhaganset Country,</hi> to fetch Corn, where they
                        had stored up some in the ground: she brought home about a peck and half of
                        Corn. This was about the time that their great Captain, <ref target="naananto_"
                            corresp="naananto">
                            <hi rend="italic">Naananto,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="naananto" target="naananto_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Better known as Canonchet, he was a Narragansett sachem who, in 1675,
                                signed a treaty with the colonists that his people would remain
                                neutral in Metacom’s War. In defiance of that signature, he became a
                                war leader as the Narragansetts joined the fight. Canonchet was
                                captured by the English on April 2, 1676 and killed the next day in a public
                                execution. News of his death was shared and celebrated throughout
                                the Bay Colony. </p></note> was killed in the <hi rend="italic">
                            Narrhaganset Countrey. My Son being now about a mile from me, </hi> I
                            <hi rend="italic"> asked liberty to go and see him, they bade me go, and
                            away I went: but quickly lost my self, travelling over Hills and
                            thorough Swamps, and could not find the way to him. </hi> And I cannot
                        but admire at the wonderfull power and goodness of God to me, in that,
                        though I was gone from home, and met with all sorts of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian,</hi> and those I had no knowledge of, and there being no
                        Christian soul near me; yet not one of them offered the least imaginable
                        miscarriage to me. I turned homeward again, and met with my master, he
                        shewed me the way to my Son: When <hi rend="italic">I</hi> came to him I
                        found him not well; and withall he had a boyl on his side, which much
                        troubled him: We bemoaned one another <pb n="26" facs="tcp:192319:21"/>
                        while, as the Lord helped us, and then I returned again. When I was
                        returned, I found my self as unsatisfied as I was before. I went up and down
                        mourning and lamenting: and my spirit was ready to sink, with the thoughts
                        of my poor Children: my Son was ill, and I could not but think of his
                        mournfull looks, and no Christian-Friend was near him, to do any office of
                        love for him, either for Soul or Body. And my poor Girl, I knew not where
                        she was, nor whither she was sick, or well, or alive, or dead. I repaired
                        under these thoughts to my Bible (my great comfort in that time) and that
                        Scripture came to my hand, <hi rend="italic"> Cast thy burden upon the Lord,
                            and He shall sustain thee, </hi> Psal. 55.22. </p>
                    <p> But I was fain to go and look after something to fatisfie my hunger, and
                        going among the <hi rend="italic">Wigwams,</hi> I went into one, and there
                        found a <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> who, shewed her self very kind to me,
                        and gave me a piece of Bear. I put it <ref target="pocket_" corresp="pocket">
                            into my pocket </ref>
                        <note xml:id="pocket" target="pocket_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Rowlandson wore a pocket typical for a New England woman, which was
                                not part of her clothing but rather a small bag tied around her
                                waist. In it, she carried essentials: her Bible, needles and yarn,
                                and at times, morsels of food.</p></note>, and came home, but could
                        not find an opportunity to broil it, for fear they would get it from me, and
                        there it lay all that day and night in my stinking pocket. In the morning I
                        went to the same <hi rend="italic">Squaw,</hi> who had a Kettle of Ground
                        nuts boyling; I asked her to let me boyle my piece of Bear in her Kettle,
                        which she did, and gave me some Ground-nuts to eat with it: and I cannot but
                        think how pleasant it was to me. I have sometime seen Bear bake very
                        handsomly among the <hi rend="italic">English,</hi> and some liked it, but
                        the thoughts that it was Bear, made me <pb n="27" facs="tcp:192319:21"/>
                        tremble: but now that was savoury to me that one would think was enough to
                        turn the stomach of a bruit Creature. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> One bitter cold day, I could find no room to sit down
                            before the fire: I went out, and could not tell what to do, but I went
                            in to another </hi> Wigwam, <hi rend="italic"> where they were also
                            sitting round the fire, but the </hi> Squaw <hi rend="italic"> laid a
                            skin for me, and bid me sit down, and gave me some Ground-nuts, and bade
                            me come again: and told me they would buy me, if they were able, and yet
                            these were strangers to me that I never saw before. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="part">
                    <head>The tenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> That day a small part of the Company removed about three
                            quarters of a mile, intending further the next day. </hi> When they came
                        to the place where they intended to lodge, and bad pitched their <hi
                            rend="italic"> wigwams; </hi> being hungry I went again back to the
                        place we were before at, to get something to eat: being encouraged by the
                            <hi rend="italic">Squaws</hi> kindness, who bade me come again; when I
                        was there, there came an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> to look after me, who
                        when he had found me, kickt me all along: I went home and found Venison
                        roasting that night, but they would not give me one bit of it. Sometimes I
                        met with favour, and sometimes with nothing but frowns. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="part">
                    <head>The eleventh Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> The next day in the morning they took their Travel,
                            intending a dayes journey up the River, I took </hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb n="28" facs="tcp:192319:22"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> my load at my back, and quickly we came to wade over the
                            River: and passed over tiresome and wearisome hills. </hi> One hill was
                        so steep that I was fain to creep up upon my knees, and to hold by the
                        twiggs and bushes to keep my self from falling backward. My head also was so
                        light, that I usually reeled as I went; but I hope all these wearisome steps
                        that I have taken, are but a forewarning of me to the heavenly rest. I <hi
                            rend="italic"> know, O Lord, that thy Judgements are right, and that
                            thou in faithfulness hast afflicted me, </hi> Psal. 119 71. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="part">
                    <head>The twelfth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> It was upon a Sabbath-day-morning, that they prepared for
                            their Travel. </hi> This morning I asked my master whither he would sell
                        me to my Husband; he answered me <ref target="nux_" corresp="nux">
                            <hi rend="italic">Nux,</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="nux" target="nux_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Translates to “Yes” in Narragansett. </p></note> which did much
                        rejoyce my spirit. My mistriss, before we went, was gone to the burial of a
                            <hi rend="italic">Papoos,</hi> and returning, she found me sitting and
                        reading in my Bible; she snatched it hastily out of my hand, and threw it
                        out of doors; I ran out and catcht it up, and put it into my pocket, and
                        never let her see it afterward. Then they packed up their things to be gone,
                        and gave me my load: I complained it was too heavy, whereupon she gave me a
                        slap in the face, and bade me go; I lifted up my heart to God, hoping that
                        Redemption was not far off: and the rather because their insolency grew
                        worse and worse. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> But the thoughts of my going homeward (for we bent our
                            course) much cheared my Spirit, and </hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:192319:22"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> made my burden seem light, and almost nothing at all.
                        </hi> But (to my amazment and great perplexity) the scale was soon turned:
                        for when we had gone a little way, on a sudden my mistriss gives out, she
                        would go no further, but turn back again, and said. I must go back again
                        with her, and she called her <hi rend="italic">Sannup,</hi> and would have
                        had him gone back also, but he would not, but said, <hi rend="italic"> He
                            would go on, and come to us again in three dayes. </hi> My Spirit was
                        upon this, I confess, very impatient, and almost outragious. I thought <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> could as well have dyed as went back: I cannot
                        declare the trouble that I was in about it; but yet back again I must go. As
                        soon as I had an opportunity, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> took my Bible to
                        read, and that quieting Scripture came to my hand, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Psal.</hi> 46.10. <hi rend="italic">Be still, and know that</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic">am God.</hi> Which stilled my spirit for the present: But
                        a sore time of tryal, I concluded, I had to go through. My master being
                        gone, who seemed to me the best friend that I had of an <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian,</hi> both in cold and hunger, and quickly so it proved. Down I
                        sat, with my heart as full as it could hold, and yet so hungry that I could
                        not sit neither: but going out to see what I could find, and walking among
                        the Trees, I found six <hi rend="italic">Acorns,</hi> and two <hi
                            rend="italic">Ches-nuts,</hi> which were some refreshment to me. Towards
                        Night I gathered me some sticks for my own comfort, that I might not ly
                        a-cold: but when we came to ly down they bade me go out, and ly
                        some-where-else, for they had company (they said) come in more than <pb
                            n="30" facs="tcp:192319:23"/> their own: I told
                        them, I could not tell where to go, they bade me go look; I told them, if I
                        went to another <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> they would be angry, and send
                        me home again. Then one of the Company drew his sword, and told me he would
                        run me thorough if I did not go presently. Then was
                            I fain to stoop to this rude fellow, and to go
                        out in the night, I knew not whither. <hi rend="italic"> Mine eyes have seen
                            that fellow afterwards walking up and down </hi> Boston, <hi
                            rend="italic">under the appearance of a</hi> Friend-Indian, <hi
                            rend="italic">and severall others of the like Cut.</hi> I went to one
                            <hi rend="italic">Wigwam,</hi> and they told me they had no room. Then I
                        went to another, and they said the same; at last an old <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian</hi> bade me come to him, and his <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi>
                        give me some Ground-nuts; she gave me also something to lay under my head,
                        and a good fire we had: and through the good providence of God, I had a
                        comfortable lodging that night. In the morning, another <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian</hi> bade me come at night, and he would give me six Ground
                        nuts, which I did. We were at this place and time about two miles from <hi
                            rend="italic"> Connecticut River. </hi> We went in the morning to gather
                        Ground nuts, to the River, and went back again that night. <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> went with a good load at my back (for they when they went,
                        though but a little way, would carry all their trumpery with them) I told
                        them the skin was off my back, but I had no other comforting answer from
                        them than this, <hi rend="italic"> That it would be no matter if my head
                            were off too. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="part">
                    <pb n="31" facs="tcp:192319:23"/>
                    <head>The thirteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Instead of going toward the</hi> Bay, <hi rend="italic"
                            >which was that</hi> I <hi rend="italic">desired,</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic"> must go with them five or six miles down the River into a
                            mighty Thicket of Brush: where we abode almost a fortnight. </hi> Here
                        one asked me to make a shirt for her <hi rend="italic">Papoos,</hi> for
                        which she gave me a mess of Broth, which was thickened with meal made of the
                        Bark of a Tree, and to make it the better, she had put into it about a
                        handfull of Pease, and a few roasted Ground-nuts, I had not seen my son a
                        pritty while, and here was an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> of whom I made
                        inquiry after him, and asked him when he saw him: he answered me, that such
                        a time his master roasted him, and that himself did eat a piece of him, as
                        big as his two fingers, and that he was very good meat: <hi rend="italic">
                            But the Lord upheld my Spirit, under this discouragement; and I
                            considered their horrible addictedness to lying, and that there is not
                            one of them that makes the least conscience of speaking of truth. </hi>
                        In this place, on a cold night, as I lay by the fire, I removed a stick that
                        kept the heat from me, a <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> moved it down again,
                        at which I lookt up, and she threw a handfull of ashes in mine eyes; I
                        thought I should have been quite blinded, and have never seen more: but
                        lying down, the water run out of my eyes, and carried the dirt with it, that
                        by the morning, I recovered my sight again. Yet upon this, and the like
                        occasions, I hope it is not too much to say with <hi rend="italic"> Job,
                                <ref target="pity_" corresp="pity"> Have pitty upon me </ref>
                            <note xml:id="pity" target="pity_" type="editorial"
                                resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Job 19:21.</p></note>, have pitty upon me, O ye my Friends, for
                            the Hand </hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:192319:24"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">of the Lord has touched me. </hi> And here I cannot but
                        remember how many times sitting in their <hi rend="italic"> Wigwams, </hi>
                        and musing on things past, I should suddenly leap up and run out, as if I
                        had been at home, forgetting where I was, and what my condition was: But
                        when I was without, and saw nothing but <hi rend="italic">Wilderness,</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">Woods,</hi> and a company of barbarous heathens: my
                        mind quickly returned to me, which made me think of that, spoken concerning
                            <ref target="judges_" corresp="judges">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sampson,</hi> who said </ref>
                        <note xml:id="judges" target="judges_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> Judges 16:20. </p></note> , I <hi rend="italic"> will go out and
                            shake myself as at other times, but he wist not that the Lord was
                            departed from him. </hi> About this time I began to think that all my
                        hopes of Restoration would come to nothing. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> thought
                        of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Army, and hoped for their coming, and
                        being taken by them, but that failed. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> hoped to be
                        carried to <hi rend="italic">Albany,</hi> at the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi> had discoursed before, but that failed also. I thought of
                        being sold to my Husband, as my master spake, but in stead of that, my
                        master himself was gone, and I left behind, so that my Spirit was now quite
                        réady to sink. I asked them to let me go out and pick up some sticks, that I
                        might get alone, <hi rend="italic">And poure out my heart unto the
                            Lord.</hi> Then also I took my Bible to read, but I found no comfort
                        here neither: which many times I was went to find: <hi rend="italic"> So
                            easie a thing it is with God to dry up the Streames of Scripture-comfort
                            from us. </hi> Yet I can say, that in all my sorrows and afflictions,
                        God did not leave me to have my impatience work towards himself, as if his
                        wayes were unrighteous. <pb n="33" facs="tcp:192319:24"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> But I knew that he laid upon me less then I deserved
                        </hi> Afterward, before this dolefull time ended with me, I was turning the
                        leaves of my Bible, and the Lord brought to me some Scriptures, which did a
                        little revive me, as that <hi rend="italic">Isai.</hi> 55.8 <hi
                            rend="italic"> For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your
                            wayes my ways saith the Lord. </hi> And also that, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Psal.</hi> 37.5. <hi rend="italic"> Commit thy way unto the Lord, trust
                            also in him, and he shal bring it to pass. </hi> About this time they
                        came yelping from <hi rend="italic">Hadly,</hi> where they had killed three
                            <hi rend="italic">English men,</hi> and brought one Captive with them,
                            <hi rend="italic">viz. Thomas Read.</hi> They all gathered about the
                        poor Man, asking him many Questions. I desired also to go and see him; and
                        when I came, he was crying bitterly: supposing they would quickly kill him.
                        Whereupon I asked one of them, whether they intended to kill him; he
                        answered me, they would not: He being a little cheared with that, I asked
                        him about the welfare of my Husband, he told me he saw him such a time in
                        the <hi rend="italic">Bay,</hi> and he was well, but very melancholly. By
                        which I certainly understood <hi rend="italic">(though I suspected it
                            before)</hi> that whatsoever the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> told me
                        respecting him was vanity and lies. Some of them told me, he was dead, and
                        they had killed him: some said he was Married again, and that the Governour
                        wished him to Marry; and told him he should have his choice, and that all
                        perswaded I was dead. So like were these barbarous creatures to him who was
                        a lyar from the beginning. </p>
                    <pb n="34" facs="tcp:192319:25"/>
                    <p> As I was sitting once in the <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> here, <hi
                            rend="italic">Philips</hi> Maid came in with the Child in her arms, and
                        asked me to give het a piece of my Apron, to make a flap for it, I told her
                        I would not: then my Mistriss bad me give it, but still I said no: the maid
                        told me if I would not give her a piece, she would tear a piece off it: <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> told her I would tear her Coat then with that my
                        Mistriss rises up, and takes up a stick big enough to have killed me, and
                        struck at me with it, but I stept out, and she struck the stick into the Mat
                        of the Wigwam. But while she was pulling of it out, I ran to the Maid and
                        gave her all my Apron, and so that storm went over. </p>
                    <p> Hearing that my Son was come to this place, I went to see him, and told him
                        his Father was well, but very melancholly: he told me he was as much grieved
                        for his Father as for himself; I wondred at his speech, for I thought I had
                        enough upon my spirit in reference to my self, to make me mindless of my
                        Husband and every one else: they being safe among their Friends. He told me
                        also, that a while before, his Master (together with other <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi> ) where going to the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> for
                        Powder; but by the way <ref target="mohawks_" corresp="mohawks"> the <hi
                                rend="italic">Mohawks</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="mohawks" target="mohawks_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> The Mohawk people were one of six nations that formed the
                                confederation of the Haudenosaunee people (often referred to as the
                                Iroquois Confederacy in Anglo-American or French Canadian terms).
                                The Mohawk were the easternmost nation of the Haudenosaunee: at
                                their peak, they controlled most of New York state, southern
                                Ontario, and eastern Quebec. In Metacom’s war, the Mohawk allied
                                with the Bay Colony. </p></note> met with them, and killed four of
                        their Company which made the rest turn back again, for which I desire that
                        myself and he may bless the Lord; <ref target="french_" corresp="french"> for
                            it might have been worse with him </ref>
                        <note xml:id="french" target="french_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>The French in Canada were Catholic. Rowlandson and her fellow
                                Puritans despised them for this reason. </p></note>, had he been
                        sold to the <hi rend="italic">French,</hi> than it proved to be in his
                        remaining with the <hi rend="italic">Indians.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p> I went to see an <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Youth in this place, one <pb
                            n="35" facs="tcp:192319:25"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">John Gilberd</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Spring field</hi> I
                        found him lying without dores, upon to ground; I asked him how he did? he
                        told me he was very <ref target="flux_" corresp="flux"> sick of a flux </ref>
                        <note xml:id="flux" target="flux_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Flux was a common term for dysentery, a highly contagious, and potentially dangerous, infection
                                of the intestines. </p></note>, with eating so much blood: They had
                        turned him out of the Wigwam, and with him an <hi rend="italic">indian
                            Papoos,</hi> almost dead, (whose Parents had been killed) in a bitter
                        cold day, without fire or clothes: the young man himself had nothing on, but
                        his shirt &amp; wastcoat. This sight was enough to melt a heart of flint.
                        There they lay quivering in the Cold, the youth round like a dog; the <hi
                            rend="italic">Papoos</hi> stretcht out, with his eyes and nose and mouth
                        full of dirt, and yet alive, and groaning. I advised John to go and get to
                        some fire: he told me he could not stand, but I perswaded him still, left he
                        shouldly there and die: and with much adoe I got him to a fire, and went my
                        self home. As soon as I was got home, his Masters Daughter came after me, to
                        know what I had done with the <hi rend="italic">English man,</hi> I told her
                        I had got him to a fire in such a place. Now had I need to pray <hi
                            rend="italic">Pauls</hi> Prayer, 2 <hi rend="italic">Thess.</hi> 3.2.
                            <hi rend="italic"> That we may be delivered from unreasonable and wicked
                            men. </hi> For her satisfaction I went along with her, and brought her
                        to him; but before I got home again, it was noised about, that I was running
                        away and getting the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> youth along with me:
                        that as soon as I came in, they began to rant and domineer: asking me where
                        I had been, and what I had been doing? and saying they would knock him on
                        the head: I told them, I had been seeing <pb n="36" facs="tcp:192319:26"/>
                        the <hi rend="italic">English Youth,</hi> and that I would not run away,
                        they told me I lyed, and taking up a Hatchet, they came to me, and said they
                        would knock me down if I stirred out again; and so confined me to the <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwam.</hi> Now may I say with <hi rend="italic"
                            >David,</hi> 2 <hi rend="italic">Sam.</hi> 24.14. I <hi rend="italic">am
                            in a great strait.</hi> If I keep in, I must dy with hunger, and if <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> go out, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> must be knockt in
                        head. This distressed condition held that day, and half the next; <hi
                            rend="italic"> And then the Lord remembred me, whose mercyes are great.
                        </hi> Then came an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> to me with a pair of
                        stockings that were too big for him, and he would have me ravel them out,
                        and knit them fit for him. I shewed my self willing, and bid him ask my
                        mistriss if <hi rend="italic">I</hi> might go along with him a little way;
                        she said yes, I might, but I was not a little refresht with that news, that
                        I had my liberty again. Then I went along with him, and he gave me some
                        roasted Ground-nuts, which did again revive my feeble stomach. </p>
                    <p> Being got out of her sight: I had time and liberty again to look into my
                        Bible: <hi rend="italic">Which was my Guid by day, and my Pillow by
                            night.</hi> Now that comfortable Scripture presented it self to me, <hi
                            rend="italic">Isa.</hi> 54.7. <hi rend="italic"> For a smal moment have
                            I forsaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee. </hi> Thus
                        the Lord carried me along from one time to another, and made good to me this
                        precious promise, and many others. <hi rend="italic">Then my Son came to see
                            me,</hi> and I asked his master to <hi rend="italic">let</hi> him stay a
                        while with me, that I <pb n="37" facs="tcp:192319:26"/> might comb his head,
                        and look over him, for he was almost over come with lice. He told me, when
                            <hi rend="italic">I</hi> had done, that he was very hungry, but I had
                        nothing to relieve him; but bid him go into the Wigwams as he went along,
                        and see if he could get any thing among them. Which he did, and it seemes
                        tarried a little too long; for his Master was angry with him, and beat him,
                        and then sold him. Then he came running to tell me he had a new Master, and
                        that he had given him some Ground-nuts already. Then <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> went along with him to his new Master who told me he loved him:
                        and he should not want. So his Master carried him away, &amp; I never saw
                        him afterward. till I saw him at <ref target="pascataqua_" corresp="pascataqua">
                            <hi rend="italic"> Pascataqua </hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Portsmouth.</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <note xml:id="pascataqua" target="pascataqua_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>The Piscataqua River divides New Hampshire and Maine. The name is a
                                borrowing from Abenaki which refers both to the river and the land
                                around it. More specifically, the term may refer to where the river
                                branches into two or three channels: one theory of its etymology
                                divides the word into “peske” for branch and “tegwe” for a river
                                with a strong current. </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p> That night they bade me go out of the <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> again:
                        my Mistrisses Papoos was sick, and it died that night, and there was one
                        benefit in it, that there was more room. I went to a <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wigwam,</hi> and they bade me come in, and gave me a skin to ly upon,
                        and a mess of Venson and Ground-nuts, which was a choice Dish among them. On
                        the morrow they burried the <hi rend="italic">Papoos,</hi> and afterward,
                        both morning and evening, there came a company to mourn and howle with her:
                        though I confess, I could not much condole with them. Many sorrowfull dayes
                        I had in this place: often getting alone; <hi rend="italic"> like a Crane,
                            or a Swallow so did I chatter: I did mourn as a Dove, mine eyes fail
                            with looking upward Oh, Lord I am oppressed, undertake for me, </hi>
                        Isa. 38 14 <pb n="38" facs="tcp:192319:27"/> I could tell the Lord as <ref target= "hezekiah_" corresp="hezekiah"> <hi
                            rend="italic">Hezekiah,</hi> ver. 3. </ref><hi rend="italic"> </hi> <note xml:id="hezekiah" target="hezekiah_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Isaiah 38:3.</p></note>
                                    Remember now O
                            Lord, I <hi rend="italic">beseech thee, how</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic">have walked before thee in truth.</hi> Now had <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> time to examine al my wayes: my Conscience did not
                        accuse me of un-righteousness toward one or other: yet <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> saw how in my walk with God, I had been a careless creature. <ref target= "against_" corresp="against"> As
                                <hi rend="italic">David</hi> said </ref> <note xml:id="against" target="against_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                    <p>Psalm 51:4.</p></note>, <hi rend="italic">Against thee, thee
                            only have</hi> I <hi rend="italic">sinned:</hi> &amp; I might say with
                            <ref target= "publican_" corresp="publican">  the poor Publican </ref> <note xml:id="publican" target="publican_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>The tax collector speaks these words in Luke 18:13.</p></note>
                                    , <hi rend="italic">God be merciful unto me a sinner.</hi>
                        On the Sabbath-dayes, I could look upon the Sun and think how People were
                        going to the house of God, to have their Souls refresht; &amp; then home,
                        and their bodies also: but I was destitute of both; &amp; might say as the
                        poor Prodigal, <hi rend="italic"> he would fain have filled his belly with
                            the husks that the Swine did eat, and no mwaan gave unto him, </hi> Luke
                        15.16 For <hi rend="italic">I</hi> must say with him, <hi rend="italic">
                            Father I have sinned against Heaven, and in thy sight, </hi> <ref target= "luke_" corresp="luke"> ver 21.</ref> <note xml:id="luke" target="luke_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Luke 15:21.</p></note>
                                    <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> remembred how on the night before &amp; after the
                        Sabbath, when my Family was about me, and Relations and Neighbours with us,
                        we could pray and sing, and then refresh our bodies with the good creatures
                        of God; and then have a comfortable Bed to ly down on: but in stead of all
                        this, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> had only a little Swill for the body, and
                        then like a Swine, must ly down on the ground. I cannot express to man the
                        sorrow that lay upon my Spirit, the Lord knows it. Yet that comfortable
                        Scripture would often come to my mind, <hi rend="italic">For a small moment
                            have</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> forsaken thee, but with great mercies
                            will I gather thee. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="part">
                    <pb n="39" facs="tcp:192319:27"/>
                    <head>The fourteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p> Now must we pack up and be gone from this Thicket, bending our course toward
                        the Bay-towns. I haveing nothing to eat by the way this day, but a few
                        crumbs of Cake, that an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> gave my girle the same
                        day we were taken. She gave it me, and I put it in my pocket: there it lay,
                        till it was so mouldy (for want of good baking) that one could not tell what
                        it was made of; it fell all to crumbs, &amp; grew so dry and hard, that it
                        was like little flints; &amp; this refreshed me many times, when I was ready
                        to faint. It was in my thoughts when I put it into my mouth; that if ever I
                        returned, I would tell the World what a blessing the Lord gave to such mean
                        food. As we went along, they killed a <hi rend="italic">Deer,</hi> with a
                        young one in her, they gave me a piece of the <hi rend="italic">Fawn,</hi>
                        and it was so young and tender, that one might eat the bones as well as the
                        flesh, and yet I thought it very good. When night came on we sate down; it
                        rained, but they quickly got up a Bark Wigwam, where I lay dry that night. I
                        looked out in the morning, and many of them had <ref target= "line_" corresp="line"> line in the rain all night </ref> <note xml:id="line" target="line_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>That is, laid in the rain.</p></note>,
                        I saw by their Reaking. Thus the Lord dealt mercifully with me many times,
                        and I fared better than many of them. In the morning they took the blood of
                        the <hi rend="italic">Deer,</hi> and put it into the Paunch, and so boyled
                        it. I could eat nothing of that, though they ate it sweetly. And yet they
                        were <ref target= "nice_" corresp="nice"> so nice in other things </ref><note xml:id="nice" target="nice_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Rowlandson uses an older definition of “nice” to mean overly exacting or fastidious.</p></note>, <pb n="40" facs="tcp:192319:28"/> that when I
                        had fetcht water, and had put the Dish I dipt the water with, into the
                        Kettle of water which I brought, they would say, they would knock me down;
                        for they said, it was a sluttish trick. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="part">
                    <head>The fifteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p> We went on our Travel. I having got one handfull of Ground-nuts, for my
                        support that day they gave me my load, and I went on cheerfully [with the
                        thoughts of going homeward] haveing my burden more on my back than my
                        spirit: we came to <hi rend="italic">Baquang River</hi> again that day, near
                        which we abode a few dayes. Sometimes one of them would give me a Pipe,
                        another a little Tobacco, another a little Salt: which I would change for a
                        little Victuals. I cannot but think what a Wolvish appetite persons have in
                        a starving condition: for many times when they gave me that which was hot, I
                        was so greedy, that I should burn my mouth, that it would trouble me hours
                        after, and yet I should quickly do the same again. And after I was thorougly
                        hungry, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was never again satisfied. For though
                        sometimes it fell out, that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> got enough, and did eat
                        till I could eat no more, yet I was as unsatisfied as I was when I began.
                        And now could I see that Scripture verified (there being many Scriptures
                        which we do not take notice of, or understand till we are afflicted) <hi
                            rend="italic">Mic.</hi> 6.14. <hi rend="italic">Thou shalt eat and not
                            be satisfied.</hi> Now might I see more than ever before, the miseries
                        that <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192319:28"/> sin hath brought upon us: Many times
                        I should be ready to run out against the Heathen, but the Scripture would
                        quiet me again, <hi rend="italic">Amos,</hi> 3. 6. <hi rend="italic"> Shal
                            there be evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it? </hi> The Lord
                        help me to make a right improvment of His Word, and that I might learn that
                        great lesson, <hi rend="italic">Mic.</hi> 6.8, 9. <hi rend="italic"> He hath
                            shewed thee (Oh Man) what is good, and what doth the Lord require of
                            thee, but to do justly, and love mercy, and walk humbly with thy God?
                            Hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="part">
                    <head>The sixteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">We began this Remove with wading over</hi> Baquag <hi
                            rend="italic"> River: the water was up to the knees, and the stream very
                            swift, and so cold that I thought it would have cut me in sunder. </hi>
                        I was so weak and feeble, that I reeled as I went along, and thought there I
                        must end my dayes at last, after my bearing and getting thorough so many
                        difficulties; the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> stood laughing to see me
                        staggering along: but in my distress the Lord gave me experience of the
                        truth, and goodness of that promise, <hi rend="italic">Isai.</hi> 43.2. <hi
                            rend="italic">When thou passest thorough the Waters,</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic"> will be with thee, and through the Rivers, they shall not
                            overflow thee. </hi> Then I sat down to put on my stockins and shoos,
                        with the teares running down mine eyes, and many sorrowfull thoughts in my
                        heart, but I gat up to go along with them. Quickly there came up to us an
                            <hi rend="italic"> Indian, </hi> who informed them, that I must go to
                        <ref target= "wachuset_" corresp="wachuset"> <hi rend="italic"> Wachuset </hi> </ref><note xml:id="wachuset" target="wachuset_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Wachusett was a Nipmuc refuge and gathering place. The name refers both to a stand-alone mountain (Wachusett Mountain in Massachusetts) and the land around it, which is still an important place in Nipmuc culture today. In the spring of 1676, Quinnapin, Weetamo, and many other tribal leaders met for a council that discussed, among other things, the possibilities of peacemaking. </p></note>
                                to my master, for there was a Letter
                        come from <pb n="42" facs="tcp:192319:29"/> the Council to the <hi
                            rend="italic">Saggamores,</hi> about redeeming the Captives, and that
                        there would be another in fourteen dayes, and that I must be there ready. My
                        heart was so heavy before that I could scarce speak or go in the path; and
                        yet now so light, that I could run. My strength seemed to come again, and
                        recruit my feeble knees, and aking heart: yet it pleased them to go but one
                        mile that night, and there we stayed two dayes. In that time came a company
                        of <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> to us, near thirty, all on horse-back. My
                        heart skipt within me, thinking they had been <hi rend="italic">English
                            men</hi> at the first sight of them, for they were dressed in <hi
                            rend="italic">English</hi> Apparel, with Hats, white Neckcloths, and
                        Sashes about their wasts, and Ribbonds upon their shoulders: but when they
                        came near, their was a vast difference between the lovely faces of
                        Christians, and the foul looks of those Heathens, which much damped my
                        spirit again. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="part">
                    <head>The seventeenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> A comfortable Remove it was to me, because of my hopes.
                        </hi> They gave me a pack, and along we went chearfully; but quickly my will
                        proved more than my strength; having little or no refreshing my strength
                        failed me, and my spirits were almost quite gone. Now may I say with <hi
                            rend="italic">David, </hi> <ref target= "david_" corresp="david"> Psal. I 19.22, 23, 24. </ref> <note xml:id="david" target="david_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Psalm 109.</p></note>
                                    I <hi rend="italic"> am
                            poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me. </hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic"> am gone like the shadow when it declineth: </hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic"> am tossed up and down like the locusts: my knees are weak
                            through fasting, and my flesh faileth </hi>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:192319:29"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> of fatness. </hi> At night we came to an <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian Town,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi>
                        sate down by a <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> discoursing, but I was almost
                        spent, and could scarce speak. I laid down my load, and went into the <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwam,</hi> and there sat an <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian</hi> boyling of <hi rend="italic">Horses feet</hi> (they being
                        wont to eat the flesh first, and when the feet were old and dried, and they
                        had nothing else, they would cut off the feet and use them) I asked him to
                        give me a little of his Broth, or Water they were boiling in; he took a
                        dish, and gave me one spoonfull of <ref target= "samp_" corresp="samp"> Samp </ref><note xml:id="samp" target="samp_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>A porridge made of corn.</p></note>
                                , and bid me take as much of the
                        Broth as I would. Then <hi rend="italic">I</hi> put some of the hot water to
                        the Samp, and drank it up, and my spirit came again. He gave me also a piece
                        of <ref target= "ruff_" corresp="ruff"> the Ruff or Ridding of the small Guts </ref><note xml:id="ruff" target="ruff_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>The tough parts of the meat, or the parts that would normally have been disposed, because they were considered too hard to eat or inedible.</p></note>, and I broiled it on the coals; and
                        now may I say with <hi rend="italic">Jonathan, See,</hi> I <hi rend="italic"
                            > pray you, how mine eyes have been enlightened, because I tasted a
                            little of this honey, </hi> 1 <hi rend="italic">Sam.</hi> 14.29. Now is
                        my Spirit revived again, though means be never so inconsiderable, yet if the
                        Lord bestow his blessing upon them, they shall refresh both Soul and Body.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="part">
                    <head>The eighteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> We took up our packs and along we went, but a wearisome
                            day </hi> I <hi rend="italic">had of it.</hi> As we went along I saw an
                            <hi rend="italic">English-man</hi> stript naked, and lying dead upon the
                        ground, but knew not who it was. Then we came to another <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian Town,</hi> where we stayed all night. In this Town there were
                        four <hi rend="italic"> English Children, </hi> Captives; and <ref target= "children_" corresp="children"> one of them my
                            own Sisters. </ref><note xml:id="children" target="children_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>In other words, her sister’s child, her niece.</p></note>
                                    <pb n="44" facs="tcp:192319:30"/> I went to see how she did,
                        and she was well, considering her Captive-condition. I would have tarried
                        that night with her, but they that owned her would not suffer it. Then I
                        went into another <hi rend="italic"> Wigwam, </hi> where they were boyling
                        Corn and Beans, which was a lovely sight to see, but I could not get a taste
                        thereof. Then I went to another <hi rend="italic">Wigwam,</hi> where there
                        were two of the <hi rend="italic">English Children;</hi> the <hi
                            rend="italic">Squaw</hi> was boyling <hi rend="italic">Horses feet,</hi>
                        then she cut me off a little piece, and gave one of the <hi rend="italic">
                            English Children </hi> a piece also. Being very hungry I had quickly eat
                        up mine, but the Child could not bite it, it was so tough and sinewy, but
                        lay sucking, gnawing, chewing and slabbering of it in the mouth and hand,
                        then I took it of the Child, and eat it my self, and savoury it was to my
                        taste. Then I may say as <hi rend="italic">Job Chap.</hi> 6.7. <hi
                            rend="italic"> The things that my soul refused to touch, are as my
                            sorrowfull meat. </hi> Thus the Lord made that pleasant refreshing,
                        which another time would have been an abomination. Then I went home to my
                        mistresses <hi rend="italic">Wigwam;</hi> and they told me <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> disgraced my master with begging, and if I did so any more, they
                        would knock me in head: I told them, they had as good knock me in head as
                        starve me to death. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="part">
                    <head>The ninteenth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> They said, when we went out, that we must travel to </hi>
                        Wachuset <hi rend="italic">this day.</hi> But a bitter weary day I had of
                        it, travelling now three dayes to gether, without resting any day between.
                        At last, after many weary <pb n="45" facs="tcp:192319:30"/> steps, <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> saw <hi rend="italic">Wachuset</hi> hills, but many
                        miles off. Then we came to a great <hi rend="italic">Swamp,</hi> through
                        which we travelled up to the knees, in mud and water, which was heavy going
                        to one tyred before. Being almost spent, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> thought I
                        should have sunk down at last, and never gat out; but <hi rend="italic"
                            >I</hi> may say, as in <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 94.18. <hi
                            rend="italic"> When my foot slipped, thy mercy, O Lord held me up. </hi>
                        Going along, having indeed my life, but little spirit, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Philip,</hi> who was in the Company, came up and took me by the hand,
                        and said, <hi rend="italic">Two weeks more and you shal be Mistress again.
                            I</hi> asked him, if he spake true? he answered, Yes, <hi rend="italic"
                            >and quickly you shal come to your master again;</hi> who had been gone
                        from us three weeks. After many weary steps we came to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wachuset,</hi> <ref target= "quanopin_" corresp="quanopin"> where he was </ref><note xml:id="quanopin" target="quanopin_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Quanopin, Rowlandson's “master” at this point.</p></note>: and glad I was to see him. He asked me,
                            <hi rend="italic">When</hi> I <hi rend="italic">washt me?</hi> I told
                        him not this month, then he fetcht me some water himself, and bid me wash,
                        and gave me the Glass to see how I lookt; and bid his <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw</hi> give me something to eat: so she gave me a mess of Beans and
                        meat, and a little Ground-nut Cake. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was wonderfully
                        revived with this favour shewed me, <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 106.46 <hi
                            rend="italic"> He made them also to be pittied, of all those that
                            carried them Captives. </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">My master had three</hi> Squaws, <hi rend="italic"> living
                            sometimes with one, and sometimes with another one, this old </hi>
                        Squaw, <hi rend="italic">at whose</hi> Wigwan <hi rend="italic"> I was, and
                            with whom my Master had been those three weeks. </hi> Another was <hi
                            rend="italic">Wettimore,</hi> with whom I had lived and served all this
                        while: A severe and proud Dame she was; <pb n="46" facs="tcp:192319:31"/>
                        bestowing every day in dressing her self neat as much time as any of the
                        Gentry of the land: powdering her hair, and painting her face, going with
                        Neck-laces, with Jewels in her ears, and Bracelets upon her hands: When she
                        had dressed her self, her work was to make Girdles of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wampom</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Beads.</hi> The third <hi
                            rend="italic">Squaw</hi> was a younger one, by whom he had two <hi
                            rend="italic">Papooses.</hi> By that time I was refresht by the old <hi
                            rend="italic">Squaw,</hi> with whom my master was, <hi rend="italic">
                            Wettimores </hi> Maid came to call me home, at which I fell a weeping.
                        Then the old <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> told me, to encourage me, that if
                        I wanted victuals, I should come to her, and that I should ly there in her
                            <hi rend="italic">Wigwam.</hi> Then I went with the maid, and quickly
                        came again and lodged there. The <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> laid a Mat
                        under me, and a good Rugg over me; the first time I had any such kindness
                        showed me. I understood that <hi rend="italic">Wettimore</hi> thought, that
                        if she should let me go and serve with the old <hi rend="italic">Squaw,</hi>
                        she would be in danger to loose, not only my service, but the redemption pay
                        also. And I was not a little glad to hear this; being by it raised in my
                        hopes, that in Gods due time there would be an end of this sorrowfull hour.
                        Then came an <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> and asked me to knit him three
                        pair of Stockins, for which I had a Hat, and a silk handkerchief. Then
                        another asked me to make her a shift, for which she gave me an Apron. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Then came</hi> Tom <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Peter, <hi
                            rend="italic"> with the second Letter from the Council, about the
                            Captives. </hi> Though they were <hi rend="italic">Indians,</hi> I gat
                        them by the hand, and <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192319:31"/> burst out into
                        tears; my heart was so full that I could not speak to them; but recovering
                        my self, I asked them how my husband did, &amp; all my friends and
                        acquaintance? they said, <hi rend="italic">They are all very well but
                            melancohly.</hi> They brought me two Biskets, and a pound of Tobacco.
                        The Tobacco I quickly gave away; when it was all gone, one asked me to give
                        him a pipe of Tobacco, I told him it was all gone; <hi rend="italic">then
                            began he to rant and threaten.</hi> I told him when my Husband came I
                        would give him some: <hi rend="italic">Hang him Rogue (sayes he)</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic">will knock out his brains, if he comes here.</hi> And then
                        again, in the same breath they would say, <hi rend="italic"> That if there
                            should come an hunddred without Guns, they would do them no hurt. </hi>
                        So unstable and like mad men they were. So that fearing the worst, I durst
                        not send to my Husband, though there were some thoughts of his coming to
                        Redeem and fetch me, not knowing what might follow; <hi rend="italic"> For
                            there was little more trust to them then to the master they served.
                        </hi> When the Letter was come, the <hi rend="italic">Saggamores</hi> met to
                        consult about the Captives, and called me to them to enquire how much my
                        husband would give to redeem me, when I came I sate down among them, as I
                        was wont to do, as their manner is: <hi rend="italic">Then they bade me
                            stand up,</hi> and said, <hi rend="italic"> they were the General Court.
                            They bid me speak what I thought he would give, </hi> Now knowing that
                        all we had was destroyed by the <hi rend="italic"> Indians, </hi> I was in a
                        great strait: I thought if I should speak of but a little, it would be
                        slighted, and hinder <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192319:32"/> the matter; if of a
                        great sum, I knew not where it would be procured: yet at a venture, I said
                        <ref target= "pounds_" corresp="pounds"> <hi rend="italic">Twenty pounds,</hi> </ref> <note xml:id="pounds" target="pounds_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml.JOB">
                            <p>It is pretty much impossible to translate the value of twenty pounds into modern money, but this would be a subtantial but not astronomical sum, the equivalent of perhaps tens of thousands of dollars in twenty-first century purchasing power.</p></note>
                                yet desired them to take less; but
                        they would not hear of that, but sent that message to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Boston,</hi> that for <hi rend="italic">Twenty pounds</hi> I should be
                        redeemed. It was a Praying- <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> that wrote their
                        Letter for them. There was another Praying <hi rend="italic"> Indian, </hi>
                        who told me, that he had a brother, that would not eat Horse; his conscience
                        was so tender and scrupulous (though as large as hell, for the destruction
                        of poor <hi rend="italic">Christians</hi>) Then he said, he read that
                        Scripture to him, 2 <hi rend="italic">Kings,</hi> 6.25. <hi rend="italic"
                            >There was a famine in</hi> Samatia, <hi rend="italic"> and behold they
                            besieged it, untill an Asses head was sold for fourscore pieces of
                            silver, and the fourth part of a <ref target= "kab_" corresp="kab"> Kab </ref><note xml:id="kab" target="kab_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>An ancient Hebrew measurement of about two liters.</p></note>
                                    of Doves dung, for five pieces of
                            silver. </hi> He expounded this place to his brother, and shewed him
                        that it was lawfull to eat that in a Famine which is not at another time.
                        And now, sayes he, he will eat Horse with any <hi rend="italic">Indian of
                            them all.</hi> There was another Praying- <hi rend="italic">Indian,</hi>
                        who when he had done all the mischief that he could, betrayed his own Father
                        into the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> hands, thereby to purchase his own
                        life. Another Praying- <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> was at <ref target= "sudbury_" corresp="sudbury"> <hi
                            rend="italic">Sudbury-fight,</hi> </ref><note xml:id="sudbury" target="sudbury_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>The battle of Sudbury took place on April 21st, 1676. Indiginous forces raided Sudbury and ambushed the colonists who came to help. It is now generally considered the last major victory for the Indigenous fighters; their fortunes in battle declined from there, a narrative Rowlandson reinforced: she described the return of the Sudbury fighters who, though they had won, seemed strangely unhappy, like “Dogs. . . which have lost their ears.”</p></note>
                                    though, as he deserved, he was
                        afterward hanged for it. There was another Praying <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indian,</hi> so wicked and cruel, as to wear a string about his neck,
                        strung with <hi rend="italic">Christians</hi> fingers. Another Praying-<hi
                            rend="italic">Indian,</hi> when they went to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sudbury-fight,</hi> went with them, and his <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw</hi> also with him, with her <hi rend="italic">Papoos</hi> at her
                            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:192319:32"/> back: Before they went to that fight,
                        they got a company together to <ref target= "powaw_" corresp="powaw"> <hi rend="italic">Powaw;</hi> </ref> <note xml:id="powaw" target="powaw_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p> The term pow wow originated from the Algonquian “pau wau” for “medicine man.” English settlers used the term to refer to meetings of Indigenous medicine men or Indigenous gatherings of any kind, which is how the word is still understood <ref target="https://folklife.si.edu/online-exhibitions/american-indian-powwows/smithsonian">today </ref>.</p></note>
                                the manner was as followeth. There was one that kneeled upon a <hi rend="italic">Deer-skin,</hi> with the company round him in a ring who kneeled, and
                        striking upon the ground with their hands, and with sticks; and muttering or
                        humming with their mouths, besides him who kneeled in the ring, there also
                        stood one with a Gun in his hand: Then he one the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Deer-skin</hi> made a speech, and all manifested assent to it: and so
                        they did many times together. Then they bade him with the Gun go out of the
                        ring, which he did, but when he was out, they called him in again; but he
                        seemed to make a stand, then they called the more earnestly, till he
                        returned again: Then they all sang. Then they gave him two Guns, in either
                        hand one: And so he on the <hi rend="italic">Deer-skin</hi> began again; and
                        at the end of every sentence in his speaking, they all assented, humming or
                        muttering with their mouthes, and striking upon the ground with their hands.
                        Then they bade him with the two Guns go out of the ring again; which he did,
                        a little way. Then they called him in again, but he made a stand; so they
                        called him with greater earnestness; but he stood reeling and wavering as if
                        he knew not whither he should stand or fall, or which way to go. Then they
                        called him with exceeding great vehemency, all of them, one and another:
                        after a little while he turned in, staggering as he went, with his Armes
                        stretched out, in <pb n="50" facs="tcp:192319:33"/> either hand a Gun. As
                        soon as he came in, they all sang and rejoyced exceedingly a while. And then
                        he opened the <hi rend="italic">Deer-skin,</hi> made another speech unto
                        which they all assented in a rejoicing manner: and so they ended their
                        business, and forthwith went to <hi rend="italic">Sudbury fight.</hi> To my
                        thinking they went without any scruple, but that they should prosper, and
                        gain the victory: And they went out not so rejoycing, but they came home
                        with as great a Victory. For they said they had killed two Captains, and
                        almost an hundred men. One <hi rend="italic">English-man</hi> they brought
                        along with them: and he said, it was too true, for they had made sad work at
                            <hi rend="italic"> Sudbury, </hi> as indeed it proved. Yet they came
                        home without that rejoycing and triumphing over their victory, which they
                        were wont to shew at other times: but rather like Dogs (as they say) which
                        have lost their cars. Yet I could not pereceive that it was for their own
                        loss of men: They said, they had not lost above five or six: and I missed
                        none, excep in one <hi rend="italic">Wigwam.</hi> When they went, they acted
                        as if the Devil had told them that they should gain the victory: and now
                        they acted, as if the Devil had told them they should have a fall. Whither
                        it were so or no, I cannot tell, but so it proved, for quickly they began to
                        fall, and so held on that Summer, till they came to utter ruine. They came
                        home on a Sabbath day, and the <hi rend="italic">Powaw</hi> that kneeled
                        upon the <hi rend="italic">Deer-skin</hi> came home (I may say, without
                        abule) as black as the Devil. <pb n="51" facs="tcp:192319:33"/> When my
                        master came home, be came to me and bid me make a shirt for his <hi
                            rend="italic">Papoos,</hi> of a hollandlaced Pillowbeer. About that time
                        there came an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> to me and bid me come to his <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwam,</hi> at night, and he would give me some Pork
                        &amp; Ground nuts. Which I did, and as I was eating, another <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian</hi> said to me, he seems to be your good Friend,
                        but he killed two <hi rend="italic">Englishmen</hi> at <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sudbury,</hi> and there ly their Cloaths behind you: I looked behind
                        me, and there I saw bloody Cloaths, with Bullet holes in them; yet the Lord
                        suffered not this wretch to do me any hurt; Yea, instead of that, he many
                        times refresht me: five or six times did he and his <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw</hi> refresh my feeble carcass. If J went to their <hi
                            rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> at any time, they would alwayes give me
                        something, and yet they were strangers that I never saw before. Another <hi
                            rend="italic">Squaw</hi> gave me a piece of fresh Pork, and a little
                        Salt with it, and lent me her Pan to Fry it in; and I cannot but remember
                        what a sweet, pleasant and delightfull relish that bit had to me, to this
                        day. So little do we prize common mercies when we have them to the full.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="part">
                    <head>The twentieth Remove.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> It was their usual manner to remove, when they bad done
                            any mischief, lest they should be found out: and so they did at this
                            time. </hi> We went about three or four miles, and there they built a
                        great <hi rend="italic">Wigwam,</hi> big enough to hold an hundred <hi
                            rend="italic">Indians,</hi> which they did in preparation to a great day
                        of Dancing. <pb n="52" facs="tcp:192319:34"/> They would say now amongst
                        themselves, that the <hi rend="italic">Governour</hi> would be so angry for
                        his loss at <hi rend="italic"> Sudbury, </hi> that he would send no more
                        about the Captives, which made me grieve and tremble. My Sister being not
                        far from the place where we now were: and hearing that I was here, desired
                        her master to let her come and see me, and he was willing to it, and would
                        go with her: but she being ready before him, told him she wonld go before,
                        and was come within a Mile or two of the place; Then he overtook her, and
                        began to rant as if he had been mad; and made her go back again in the Rain;
                        so that I never saw her till I saw her in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Charlestown.</hi> But the Lord requited many of their ill doings, for
                        this <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> her Master, was hanged afterward at <hi
                            rend="italic">Boston.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> now began
                        to come from all quarters, against their merry dancing day. Among some of
                        them came one <ref target= "kettle_" corresp="kettle"> <hi rend="italic">Good wife Kettle:</hi> </ref><note xml:id="kettle" target="kettle_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Elizabeth Kettle, who had been captured in Lancaster.</p></note>
                                I told her my heart
                        was so heavy that it was ready to break: so is mine too said she, but yet
                        said, I hope we shall hear some good news shortly. I could hear how
                        earnestly my Sister desired to see me, &amp; I as earnestly desired to see
                        her: and yet neither of us could get an opportunity. My Daughter was also
                        now about a mile off, and I had not seen her in nine or ten weeks, as I had
                        not seen my Sister since our first taking. I earnestly desired them to let
                        me go and see them: yea, I intreated, begged, and perswaded them, but to let
                        me see my Daughter; and yet so hard hearted were they, that they would not
                            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:192319:34"/> suffer it. They made use of their
                        tyrannical power whilst they had it: but through the Lords wonderfull mercy,
                        their time was now but short. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> On a Sabbath day, the Sun being about an hour high in the
                            afternoon; came Mr. </hi> <ref target= "hoar_" corresp="hoar">John Hoar </ref><note xml:id="hoar" target="hoar_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>John Hoar was a lawyer enlisted by Mr. Rowlandson to negotiate the return of his wife. </p></note>
                                    (<hi rend="italic"> the Council
                            permitting him, and his own foreward spirit inclining him) together with
                            the two forementioned </hi> Indians, Tom <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
                        Peter <hi rend="italic">with their third Letter from the Council.</hi> When
                        they came near, I was abroad. though I saw them not, they presently called
                        me in, and bade me sit down and not stir. Then they catched up their Guns,
                        and away they ran, as if an Enemy had been at hand; and the Guns went off
                        apace I manifested some great trouble, and they asked me what was the
                        matter? I told them, I <hi rend="italic">thought they had killed the</hi>
                        English-man (for they had in the mean time informed me that an <hi
                            rend="italic">English-man</hi> was come) they said, <hi rend="italic"
                            >No;</hi> They shot over his Horse and under, and before his Horse; and
                        they pusht him this way and that way, at their pleasure: shewing what they
                        conld do: Then they let them come to their <hi rend="italic">Wigwams.</hi> I
                        begged of them to let me see the <hi rend="italic">English man,</hi> but
                        they would not. But there was I fain to sit their pleasure. When they had
                        talked their fill with him, they suffered me to go to him. We asked each
                        other of our welfare, and how my Husband did, and all my Friends? He told me
                        they were all well, and would be glad to see me. Amongst other things which
                        my Husband sent me, there came a pound of <hi rend="italic">Tobacco:</hi>
                        which I sold for nine shillings in <pb n="54" facs="tcp:192319:35"/> Money:
                        for many of the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> for want of <hi rend="italic"
                            > Tobacco, </hi> smoaked <hi rend="italic">Hemlock,</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">Ground-Ivy.</hi> It was a great mistake in any, who
                        thought I sent for <hi rend="italic">Tobacco:</hi> for through the savour of
                        God, that desire was overcome. I now asked them, whither I should go home
                        with Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hoar?</hi> They answered <hi rend="italic"
                            >No,</hi> one and another of them: and it being night, we lay down with
                        that answer; in the morning, Mr <hi rend="italic">Hoar</hi> invited the <hi
                            rend="italic">Saggamores</hi> to Dinner; but when we went to get it
                        ready, we fond that they had stollen the greatest part of the Provision Mr.
                            <hi rend="italic">Hoar</hi> had brought, out of his Bags, in the night:
                            <hi rend="italic"> And we may see the wonderfull power of God, in that
                            one passage, in that when there was such a great number of the </hi>
                        Indians <hi rend="italic"> together, and so greedy of a little good food;
                            and no </hi> English <hi rend="italic"> there, but Mr. Hoar and my self:
                            that there they did not knock us in the head, and take what we had:
                            there being not only some Provision, but also Trading-cloth, a part of
                            the twenty pounds agreed upon: But instead of doing us any mischief,
                            they seemed to be ashamed of the fact, and said, it were some </hi>
                        <ref target= "matchit_" corresp="matchit"> Matchit Indian </ref><note xml:id="matchit" target="matchit_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Translates to “bad.”</p></note>
                                <hi rend="italic">that did it.</hi> Oh, that we could believe
                        that there is no thing too hard for God! God shewed his Power over the
                        Heathen in this, <hi rend="italic">as he did ever the hungry Lyons when</hi>
                        <ref target= "daniel_" corresp="daniel"> Daniel </ref><note xml:id="daniel" target="daniel_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Daniel 6:22.</p></note>
                                <hi rend="italic">was cast into the Den.</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hoar</hi> called them betime to Dinner, but they are very little, they
                        being so busie in dressing themselves, and getting ready for their Dance:
                        which was carried one by eight of them; four <hi rend="italic">Men</hi> and
                            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:192319:35"/> four <hi rend="italic">Squaws:</hi> My
                        master and mistriss being two. He was dressed in his Holland shirt, with
                        great Laces sewed at the cail of it, he had his silver Buttons, his white
                        Stockins, his Garters were hung round with Shillings, and he had Girdles of
                            <hi rend="italic"> Wampom upon his head and shoulders. </hi> She had a
                        <ref target= "kersey_" corresp="kersey"> Kersey </ref><note xml:id="kersey" target="kersey_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>A coarse woolen cloth.</p></note>
                                Coat, and covered with Girdles of <hi rend="italic">Wampom</hi> from
                        the Loins upward: her armes from her elbows to her hands were covered with
                        Bracelets; there were handfulls of Neck-laces about her neck, and severall
                        sorts of Jewels in her ears. She had fine red Stokins, and white Shoos, her
                        hair powdered and face painted Red, that was alwayes before Black. And all
                        the Dancers were after the same manner. There were two other singing and
                        knocking on a Kettle for their musick. They keept hopping up and down one
                        after another, with a Kettle of water in the midst, standing warm upon some
                        Embers, to drink of when they were dry. They held on till it was almost
                        night, throwing out <hi rend="italic">Wampom</hi> to the standers by. At
                        night I asked them again, if I should go home? They all as one said No,
                        except my Husband would come for me. When we were lain down, my Master went
                        out of the <hi rend="italic"> Wigwam, </hi> and by and by sent in an <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian</hi> called <hi rend="italic">James</hi> the <hi
                            rend="italic">Printer,</hi> who told Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hoar,</hi>
                        that my Master would let me go home to morrow, if he would let him have one
                        pint of Liquors. Then Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hoar</hi> called his own <hi
                            rend="italic">Indians, Tom</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Peter,</hi> and
                        bid them &amp; go and see whither he would promise it before <pb n="56"
                            facs="tcp:192319:36"/> them three: and if he would, he should have it;
                        which he did, and he had it. Then <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi> smeling the
                        business cal'd me to him, and asked me what I would give him, to tell me
                        some good news, and speak a good word for me, I told him, I <hi
                            rend="italic"> could not tell what to give him, I would anothing I had,
                            and asked him what he would have? </hi> He said, two Coats and twenty
                        shillings in Mony, and half a bushel of seed Corn, and some Tobacco. I
                        thanked him for his love: but I knew the good news as well as the crafty <hi
                            rend="italic">Fox.</hi> My Master after he had had his drink, quickly
                        came ranting into the <hi rend="italic">Wigwam</hi> again, and called for
                        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hoar,</hi> drinking to him, and saying, <hi
                            rend="italic">He was a good man:</hi> and then again he would say, <hi
                            rend="italic">Hang him Rogue:</hi> Being almost drunk, he would drink to
                        him, and yet presently say he should be hanged. Then he called for me, I
                        trembled to hear him, yet I was sain to go to him, and he drank to me,
                        shewing no incivility. He was the first <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> I saw
                        drunk all the while that I was amongst them. At last his <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw</hi> ran out, and he after her, round the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wigwam,</hi> with his mony jingling at his knees: But she escaped him:
                        But having an old <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> he ran to her: and so through
                        the Lords mercy, we were no more troubled that night. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Yet</hi> I <hi rend="italic">had not a comfortable nights rest: for I
                            think</hi> I <hi rend="italic">can say,</hi> I <hi rend="italic">did not
                            sleep for three nights together.</hi> The night before the Letter came
                        from the Council, I could not rest. I was so full of feares and troubles,
                        God many times leaving us most in the dark, when deliverance <pb n="57"
                            facs="tcp:192319:36"/> is nearest: yea, at this time I could not rest,
                        night nor day. The next night I was overjoyed, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hoar</hi> being come, and that with such good tidings. The third night
                            <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was even swallowed up with the thoughts of
                        things, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that ever I should go home again; and
                        that I must go, leaving my Children behind me in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wilderness;</hi> so that sleep was now almost departed from mine eyes. </p>
                    <p> On <hi rend="italic">Tuesday morning</hi> they called their <hi
                            rend="italic">General</hi> Court (as they call it) to consult and
                        determine, whether I should go home or no: And they all as one man did
                        seemingly consent to it, that I should go home; except <hi rend="italic"
                            >Philip,</hi> <ref target= "captives_" corresp="captives"> who would not come among them. </ref> <note xml:id="captives" target="captives_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p> Metacom did not agree with the strategy to trade captives as part of the negotiations with the English settlers.</p> </note> </p>
                    <p> But before <hi rend="italic">I</hi> go any further, I would take leave to
                        mention a few remarkable passages of providence, which I took special notice
                        of in my afflicted time. </p>
                    <p> 1. <hi rend="italic"> Of the fair opportunity lost in the long March, a
                        little after the </hi> <ref target= "swamp_" corresp="swamp"> Fort-fight, </ref><note xml:id="swamp" target="swamp_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Rowlandson is referring to what is now called the “Great Swamp Fight,” which occurred in December 1675 when colonists attacked a large Narragansett and Wampanoag settlement in Rhode Island. Narragansett forces joined the war effort after this fight, which was one of the bloodiest battles of the war and destructive to both sides. 
                            </p></note>
                                <hi rend="italic">when our</hi>
                        English Army <hi rend="italic">was so numerous, and in pursuit of the</hi>
                        Enemy, <hi rend="italic"> and so near as to take several and destroy them:
                            and the </hi> Enemy <hi rend="italic"> in such distriss for food, that
                            our men might track them by their rooting in the earth for Groundnuts,
                            whilest they were flying for their lives. </hi> I say, that then our
                        Army should want Provision, and be forced to leave their pursuit and return
                        homeward: and the very next week the <hi rend="italic">Enemy</hi> came upon
                        our <hi rend="italic">Town,</hi> like Bears bereft of their whelps, or so
                        many ravenous Wolves, rending us and our Lambs to <pb n="58"
                            facs="tcp:192319:37"/> death. But what shall I say? God seemed to leave
                        his People to themselves, and order all things for his own holy ends. <hi
                            rend="italic"> <ref target= "amos_" corresp="amos"> Shal there be evil in the City </ref><note xml:id="amos" target="amos_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Amos 3:6, 6:6-7, Psalm 118:23.</p></note>
                                    and the Lord hath not done
                            it? They are not grieved for the affliction of </hi> Joseph, <hi
                            rend="italic"> therefore shal they go Captive, with the first that go
                            Captive. </hi> It is the Lords doing, and it should be marvelous in our
                        eyes. </p>
                    <p> 2. I cannot but remember how the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> derided the
                        slowness, and dulness of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Army, in its
                        setting out. For after the desolations at <hi rend="italic">Lancaster</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">Medfield,</hi> as I went along with them, they asked
                        me when I thought the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Army would come after
                        them? I told them I could not tell: It may be they will come in <hi
                            rend="italic">May,</hi> said they. Thus did they scoffe at us, as if the
                            <hi rend="italic">English</hi> would be a quarter of a year getting
                        ready </p>
                    <p> 3. <hi rend="italic">Which also I have hinted before, when the</hi> English
                            <hi rend="italic"> Army with new supplies were sent forth to pursue
                            after the enemy, &amp; they understanding it: fled before them till they
                            came to </hi> Baquaug <hi rend="italic"> River, where they forthwith
                            went over safely: that that River should be impassable to the </hi>
                        English. I can but admire to see the wonderfull providence of God in
                        preserving the heathen for farther affliction to our poor Countrey. They
                        could go in great numbers over, but the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> must
                        stop: God had an over-ruling hand in all those things. </p>
                    <p> 4. <hi rend="italic"> It was thought, if their Corn were cut down, they
                            would starve and dy with hunger: and all their Corn that could be found,
                            was destroyed, and </hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:192319:37"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">they driven from that little they had in store, into the
                            Woods in the midst of Winter; </hi> and yet how to admiration did the
                        Lord preserve them for his holy ends, and the destruction of many still
                        amongst the <hi rend="italic">English!</hi> strangely did the Lord provide
                        for them; that I did not see (all the time I was among them) one Man, Woman,
                        or Child, die with hunger. </p>
                    <p> Though many times they would eat that, that a Hog or a Dog would hardly
                        touch; yet by that God strengthned them to be a scourge to his People. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> The chief and commonest food was Ground-nuts: They eat
                            also Nuts and Acorns, Harty choaks, Lilly roots, Ground beans, </hi> and
                        several other weeds and roots, that I know nor. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> They would pick up old bones, and cut them to pieces at
                            the joynts, and if they were full of wormes and magots, they would scald
                            them over the fire to make the vermine come out, and then boile them,
                            and drink up the Liquor, and then beat the great end, of them in a
                            Morter, and so eat them. </hi> They would eat Horses guts, and ears, and
                        all sorts of wild Birds which they could catch: also Bear, Venison, Beaver,
                        Tortois, Frogs, Squirrels, Dogs, Skunks, Rattle-snakes; yea, the very Bark
                        of Trees; besides all sorts of creatures, and provision which they plundered
                        from the <hi rend="italic">English. I</hi> can but stand in admiration to
                        see the wonderful power of God, in providing for such a vast number of our
                        Enemies <pb n="60" facs="tcp:192319:38"/> in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wilderness,</hi> where there was nothing to be seen, but from hand to
                        mouth. Many times in a morning, the generality of them, would eat up all
                        they had, and yet have some further supply against they wanted. It is said,
                            <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi> 81.13, 14. <hi rend="italic">Oh, that my
                            People bad hearkned to me, and</hi> Israel <hi rend="italic"> had walked
                            in my wayes, I should soon have subdued their Enemies, and turned my
                            hand against their Adversaries. </hi> But now our perverse and evil
                        carriages in the sight of the Lord, have so offended him, that instead of
                        turning his hand against them, the Lord feeds &amp; nourishes them up to be
                        a scourge to the whole Land. </p>
                    <p> 5. <hi rend="italic">Another thing that</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> would
                            observe is, the strange providence of God in turning things about when
                            the </hi> Indians <hi rend="italic">was at the highest, and the</hi>
                        English <hi rend="italic">at the lowest.</hi> I was with the Enemy eleven
                        weeks and five dayes, and not one Week passed without the fury of the Enemy,
                        and some desolation by fire and sword upon one place or other. They mourned
                        (with their black faces) for their own losses: yet triumphed and rejoyced in
                        their inhumane, and many times devilish cruelty to the <hi rend="italic"
                            >English.</hi> They would boast much of their Victories; saying, that in
                        two hours time they had destroyed such a <hi rend="italic">Captain,</hi> and
                        his <hi rend="italic">Company</hi> at such a place; and such a <hi
                            rend="italic">Captain</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Company</hi> in
                        such a place; and such a <hi rend="italic">Captain</hi> and his <hi
                            rend="italic">Company</hi> in such a place: and boast how many <hi
                            rend="italic">Towns</hi> they had destroyed, and then scoffe, and say,
                            <hi rend="italic"> They had done them a </hi>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:192319:38"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> good turn, to send them to Heaven so soon. </hi> Again,
                        they would say, <hi rend="italic"> This Summer that they would knock all the
                            Rogues in the head, or drive them into the Sea, or make them flie the
                            Countrey:</hi> thinking surely, <ref target= "agag_" corresp="agag"><hi rend="italic">Agag-like</hi></ref>
                        <note xml:id="agag" target="agag_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Agag is a title for a biblical king, and the quote comes from the first book of Samuel 15:32.</p></note>
                        <hi rend="italic">, The bitterness of Death is past</hi>.Now the Heathen begins to think all is
                        their own, &amp; the poor Christians hopes to fail (as to man) and now their
                        eyes are more to God, and their hearts sigh heaven-ward: and to say in good
                        earnest, <hi rend="italic">Help Lord, or we perish:</hi> When the Lord had
                        brought his people to this, that they saw no help in any thing but himself;
                        then be takes the quarrel into his own hand: and though they had made a pit,
                        in their own imaginations, as deep as hell for the Christians that Summer,
                        yet the Lord hurll'd them selves into it. And the Lord had not so many wayes
                        before to preserve them, but now he hath as many to destroy them. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> But to return again to my going home, where we may see a
                            remarkable change of Providence: </hi> At first they were all against
                        it, except my Husband would come for me; but afterwards they assented to it,
                        and seemed much to rejoyce in it; some askt me to send them some Bread,
                        others some Tobacco, others shaking me by the hand, offering me a Hood and
                        Scarfe to ride in; not one moving hand or tongue against it. Thus hath the
                        Lord answered my poor desire, and the many earnest requests of others put up
                        unto God for me. In my travels an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> came to me,
                        and told me, if I were willing, <pb n="62" facs="tcp:192319:39"/> he and his
                            <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> would run away, and go home along with me:
                        I told him <hi rend="italic">No:</hi> I was not willing to run away, but
                        desired to wait Gods time, that I might go home quietly, and without fear.
                        And now God hath granted me my desire. O the wonderfull power of God that
                            <hi rend="italic">I</hi> have seen, and the experience that I have had:
                        I <hi rend="italic"> have been in the midst of those roaring Lyons, and
                            Salvage Bears, that feared neither God, nor Man, nor the Devil, by night
                            and day, alone and in company: sleeping all sorts together, and yet not
                            one of them ever offered me the least abuse of unchastity to me, in word
                            or action. </hi> Though some are ready to say, I speak it for my own
                        credit; <hi rend="italic"> But I speak it in the presence of God, and to his
                            Glory. </hi> Gods Power is as great now, and as sufficient to save, as
                        when he preserved <hi rend="italic">Daniel</hi> in the Lions Den; or the
                        three <hi rend="italic">Children in the fiery Furnace. </hi> I may well say
                        as his <hi rend="italic"> Psal. </hi> 107.12 <hi rend="italic"> Oh give
                            thanks unto the Lord for he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever.
                        </hi> Let the Redeemed of the Lord say so, whom he hath redeemed from the
                        hand of the Enemy, especially that I should come away in the midst of so
                        many hundreds of Enemies quietly and peacably, and not a Dog moving his
                        tougue. So I took my leave of them, and in coming along my heart melted into
                        tears, more then all the while I was with them, and I was almost swallowed
                        up with the thoughts that ever I should go home again. About the Sun going
                        down, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hoar,</hi> and my self, and the two <pb n="63"
                            facs="tcp:192319:39"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> came to <hi rend="italic">Lancaster,</hi> and
                        a solemn sight it was to me. There had I lived many comfortable years
                        amongst my Relations and Neighbours, and now not one <hi rend="italic"
                            >Christian</hi> to be seen, nor one house lest standing. We went on to a
                        Farm house that was yet standing, where we lay all night: and a comfortable
                        lodging we had, though nothing but straw to ly on The Lord preserved us in
                        safety that night, and raised us up again in the morning, and carried us
                        along, that before noon, we came to <hi rend="italic">Concord.</hi> Now was
                        I full of joy, and yet not without sorrow: joy to see such a lovely sight,
                        so many <hi rend="italic">Christians</hi> together, and some of them my
                        Neighbours: There <hi rend="italic">I</hi> met with my Brother, and my
                        Brother in Law, who asked me, if I knew where his Wife was? Poor heart! he
                        had helped to bury her, and knew it not; she being shot down by the house
                        was partly burnt: so that those who were at <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> at
                        the desolation of the <hi rend="italic">Town,</hi> and came back afterward,
                        and buried the dead, did not know her. Yet I was not without sorrow, to
                        think how many were looking and longing, and my own Children amongst the
                        rest, to enioy that deliverance that I had now received: and <hi
                            rend="italic">I</hi> did not know whither ever I should see them again.
                        Being recruited with food and raiment, we went to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Boston</hi> that day, where I met with my dear Husband, but the
                        thoughts of our dear Children, one being dead, and the other we could not
                        tell where, abated our comfort each to other. I <pb n="64"
                            facs="tcp:192319:40"/> was not before so much hem'd in with the
                        merciless and cruel Heathen, but now as much with pittiful, tender-hearted,
                        and compassionate Christians. In that poor, and destressed, and beggerly
                        condition I was received in, I was kindly entertained in severall Houses: so
                        much love I received from several (some of whom I knew, and others I knew
                        not] that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> am not capable to declare it. But the
                        Lord knows them all by name: <hi rend="italic"> The Lord reward them seven
                            fold into their bosoms of his spirituals, for their temporals. </hi> The
                            <hi rend="italic">twenty pounds</hi> the price of my redemption was
                        raised by some <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> Gentlemen, and <ref target= "usher_" corresp="usher"> Ms. <hi
                            rend="italic">Usher </hi> </ref><note xml:id="usher" target="usher_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>There's some kind of typographical error here, since "Ms." was not in use in seventeenth-century English. So whether this reference is to a man or a woman named Usher is uncertain. </p></note>, whose bounty and religious charity, I would
                        not forget to make mention of. Then Mr. <hi rend="italic">Thomas
                            Shepard</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Charlstown</hi> received us into his
                        House, where we continued eleven weeks; and a Father and Mother they were to
                        us. And many more tender-hearted Friends we met with in that place. We were
                        now in the midst of love, yet not without much and frequent heaviness of
                        heart for our poor Children, and other Relations, who were still in
                        affliction. The week following, after my coming in, the Governour and
                        Gouncil sent forth to the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> again; and that not
                        without saccess; for they brought in my Sister, and Good-wife <hi
                            rend="italic">Kettle:</hi> Their not knowing where our Children were,
                        was a sore tryal to us still, and yet we were not without secret hopes that
                        we should see them again. That which was dead lay heavier upon my spirit,
                        than those which were alive <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192319:40"/> and amongst
                        the Heathen; thinking how it suffered with its wounds, and I was no way able
                        to relieve it; and how it was buried by the Heathen in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wilderness</hi> from among all Christians. We were hurried up and down
                        in our thoughts, sometime we should hear a report that they were gone this
                        way, and sometimes that; and that they were come in, in this place or that:
                        We kept enquiring and listning to hear concerning them, but no certain news
                        as yet. About this time the Council had ordered a day of publick <hi
                            rend="italic">Thanks-giving:</hi> though I thought I had still cause of
                        mourning, and being unsettled in our minds, we thought we would ride toward
                        the <hi rend="italic">Eastward,</hi> to see if we could hear any thing
                        concerning our Children. And as we were riding along [God is the wise
                        disposer of all things] between <hi rend="italic">Ipswich</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">Rowly</hi> we met with Mr. <hi rend="italic">William
                            Hubbard,</hi> who told us that our Son <hi rend="italic">Joseph</hi> was
                        come in to Major <hi rend="italic">Waldrens,</hi> and another with him,
                        which was my Sisters Son. I asked him how he knew it? He said, the Major
                        himself told him so. So along we went till we came to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Newbury;</hi> and their Minister being absent, they desired my Husband
                        to Preach the <hi rend="italic">Thanks giving</hi> for them; but he was not
                        willing to stay there that night, but would go over to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Salisbury,</hi> to hear further, and come again in the morning; which
                        he did, and Preached there that day. At night, when he had done, one came
                        and told him that his Daughter was come isn at <hi rend="italic"
                            >Providence:</hi> Here was <pb n="66" facs="tcp:192319:41"/> mercy on
                        both hands. Now hath God fulfiled that precious Scripture which was such a
                        comfort to me in my distressed condition, When my heart was ready to sink
                        into the Earth [my Children being gone I could not tell whither] and my
                        knees trembled under me, <hi rend="italic">And</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> was
                            walking through the valley of the shadow of Death: </hi> Then the Lord
                        brought, and now has fulfilled that reviving word unto me: <ref target= "jeremiah_" corresp="jeremiah"> Thus saith the
                            Lord</ref>
                        <note xml:id="jeremiah" target="jeremiah_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Jeremiah 31:16.</p></note>,<hi rend="italic"> Refrain thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from
                            tears. for thy Work shall be rewarded, </hi> saith the Lord, <hi
                            rend="italic"> and they shall come again from the Land of the Enemy.
                        </hi> Now we were between them, the one on the <hi rend="italic">East,</hi>
                        and the other on the <hi rend="italic">West:</hi> Our Son being nearest, we
                        went to him first, to <hi rend="italic">Portsmouth,</hi> where we met with
                        him, and with the Major also: who told us he had done what he could, but
                        could not redeem him under <hi rend="italic">seven ponnds;</hi> which the
                        good People thereabouts were pleased to pay. The Lord reward the Major, and
                        all the rest, though unknown so me, for their labour of Love. My Sitters Son
                        was redeemed for <hi rend="italic">four pounds,</hi> which the Council gave
                        order for the payment of Having now received one of our Children, we
                        hastened toward the other: going back through <hi rend="italic">
                            Newbury,</hi> my Husband Preached there on the <hi rend="italic">
                            Sabbath-day:</hi> for which they rewarded him many fold. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">On</hi> Monday <hi rend="italic">we came to</hi>
                        Charlstown, <hi rend="italic">where we heard that the Governour of</hi>
                        Road-Island <hi rend="italic"> had sent over for our Daughter, to take care
                            of her, being now </hi>
                        <pb n="67"/>
                        <hi rend="italic"> within his Jurisdiction: which should not pass without
                            our acknowledgments. </hi> But she being nearer <hi rend="italic"
                            >Rehoboth</hi> than <hi rend="italic">Road-Island,</hi> Mr. <hi
                            rend="italic">Newman</hi> went over, and took care of her, and brought
                        her to his own House. And the goodness of God was admirable to us in our low
                        estate, in that he raised up passionate Friends on every side to us, when we
                        had nothing to recompance any for their love. The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi> were now gone that way, that it was apprehended dangerous
                        to go to her: But the Carts which carried Provision to the <hi rend="italic"
                            >English</hi> Army, being guarded, brought her with them to <hi
                            rend="italic">Dorchester,</hi> where we received her safe: blessed be
                        the Lord sor it, <hi rend="italic"> For great is his Power, and he can do
                            whatsoever seemeth him good. </hi> Her coming in was after this manner:
                        She was travelling one day with the <hi rend="italic">Indians,</hi> with her
                        basket at her back; the company of <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> were got
                        before her, and gone out of sight, all except one <hi rend="italic"
                            >Squaw;</hi> she followed the <hi rend="italic">Squaw</hi> till night,
                        and then both of them lay down, having nothing over them but the heavens,
                        and under them but the earth. Thus she travelled three dayes together, not
                        knowing whither she was going: having nothing to eat or drink but water, and
                        green <hi rend="italic">Hirtle-berries.</hi> At last they came into <hi
                            rend="italic">Providence,</hi> where she was kindly entertained by
                        several of that <hi rend="italic">Town.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Indians</hi> often said, that I should never have her under <hi
                            rend="italic">twenty pounds:</hi> But now the Lord hath brought her in
                        upon free-cost, and given her to me the second <pb n="68"
                            facs="tcp:192319:42"/> time. The Lord make us a blessing indeed, each to
                        others. Now have I seen that Scripture also fulfilled, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Deut.</hi> 30: 4, 7. <hi rend="italic"> If any of thine be driven out
                            to the outmost parts of heaven, from thence will the Lord thy God gather
                            thee, and from thence will he fetch thee. And the Lord thy God will put
                            all these curses upon thine enemies, and on them which hate thee, which
                            persecuted thee. </hi> Thus hath the Lord brought me and mine out of
                        that horrible pit, and hath set us in the midst of tender-hearted and
                        compassionate Christians. It is the desire of my soul, that we may walk
                        worthy of the mercies received, and which we are receiving. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic"> Our Family being now gathered together (those of us that
                            were living) the </hi> South Church <hi rend="italic">in</hi> Boston <hi
                            rend="italic">hired an House for us: Then were moved from Mr.</hi>
                        Shepards, <hi rend="italic">those cordial Friends, and went to</hi> Boston,
                            <hi rend="italic"> where we continued about three quarters of a year:
                            Still the Lord went along with us, and provided graciously for us. </hi>
                        I thought it somewhat strange to set up House keeping with bare walls; but
                        <ref target= "solomon_" corresp="solomon"> as <hi rend="italic"> Solomon </hi> sayes,</ref><note xml:id="solomon" target="solomon_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Ecclesiastes 10:19.</p></note>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mony answers
                            all things;</hi> and that we had through the benevolence of Christian
                        friends, some in this <hi rend="italic">Town,</hi> and some in that, and
                        others: And some from <hi rend="italic">England,</hi> that in a little time
                        we might look, and see the House furnished with love. The Lord hath been
                        exceeding good to us in our low estate, in that when we had neither house
                        nor home, nor other necessaries; the Lord so moved the hearts of these and
                        those towards us, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:192319:42"/> that we wanted neither
                        food, nor raiment for our selves or ours, <hi rend="italic">Prov.</hi>
                        18.24. <hi rend="italic"> There is a Friend which sticketh closer than a
                            Brother. </hi> And how many such Friends have we found, and now living
                        amongst? And truly such a Friend have we found him to be unto us, in whose
                        house we lived, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic">James
                            Whitcomb,</hi> a Friend unto us near hand, and afar off. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">I can remember the time, when</hi> I <hi rend="italic">
                            used to sleep quietly without workings in my thoughts, whole nights
                            together, but now it is other wayes with me. </hi> When all are fast
                        about me, and no eye open, but his who ever waketh, my thoughts are upon
                        things past, upon the awfull dispensation of the Lord towards us; upon his
                        wonderfull power and might, in carrying of us through so many difficulties,
                        in returning us in safety, and suffering none to hurt us. I remember in the
                        night season, how the other day I was in the midst of thousands of enemies,
                        &amp; nothing but death before me: It was then hard work to perswade my
                        self, that ever I should be satisfied with bread again. But now we are fed
                        with the finest of the Wheat, and, as I may say, <ref target= "honey_" corresp="honey"> <hi rend="italic">With
                            honey out of the rock:</hi></ref>
                        <note xml:id="honey_" target="honey" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                            <p>Psalm 81:16.</p></note>
                        <ref target= "husk_" corresp="husk"> In stead of the Husk, we have the fatted
                            Calf</ref><note xml:id="husk" target="husk_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>See Luke 15:11-32.</p></note>
                                    : The thoughts of these things in the particulars of them, and of the
                        love and goodness of God towards us, make it true of me, what <hi
                            rend="italic">David</hi> said of himself, <hi rend="italic">Psal.</hi>
                        6.6. I <hi rend="italic"> watered my Couch with my tears. </hi> Oh! the
                        wonderfull power of God that mine eyes have seen, affording <pb n="70"
                            facs="tcp:192319:43"/> matter enough for my thoughts to run in, that
                        when others are sleeping mine eyes are weeping. </p>
                    <p> I <hi rend="italic">have seen the extrem vanity of this World:</hi> One hour
                        I have been in health, and wealth, wanting nothing: But the next hour in
                        sickness and wounds, and death, having nothing but sorrow and affliction. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Before</hi> I <hi rend="italic">knew what affliction
                            meant,</hi> I <hi rend="italic"> was ready sometimes to wish for it.
                        </hi> When I lived in prosperity; having the comforts of the World about me,
                        my relations by me, my Heart chearfull: and taking little care for any
                        thing; and yet seeing many, whom I preferred before my self, under many
                        tryals and afflictions, in sickness, weakness, poverty, losses, crosses, and
                        cares of the World, I should be sometimes jealous least I should have my
                        portion in this life, and that Scripture would come to my mind, <hi
                            rend="italic">Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi rend="italic"> For whom the Lord
                            loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every Son whom he receiveth. </hi>
                        But now I see the Lord had his time to scourge and chasten me. The portion
                        of some is to have their afflictions by drops, now one drop and then
                        another; but the dregs of the Cup, the Wine of astonishment: like a sweeping
                        rain that leaveth no food, did the Lord prepare to be my portion Affliction
                        I wanted, and affliction I had, full measure (I thought) pressed down and
                        running over: yet I see, when God calls a Person to any thing, and through
                        never so many difficulties <pb n="71" facs="tcp:192319:43"/> yet he is fully
                        able to carry them through and make them see, and say they have been gainers
                        thereby. And I hope I can say in some measure, <ref target= "psalm_" corresp="psalm"> As <hi rend="italic"
                            >David</hi> did</ref><note xml:id="psalm" target="psalm_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Psalm 119:71.</p></note>, <hi rend="italic">It is good for me that</hi> I <hi
                            rend="italic">have been afflicted: </hi> The Lord hath shewed me the
                        vanity of these outward things. That they are the <ref target= "vanity_" corresp="vanity"> <hi rend="italic">Vanity
                            of vanities, and vexation of spirit;</hi></ref><note xml:id="vanity" target="vanity_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#RR">
                                <p>Ecclesiastes 1:2, 14. </p></note>
                                    that they are but a shadow, a
                        blast, a bubble, and things of no continuance. That we must rely on God
                        himself, and our whole dependance must be upon him. If trouble from smaller
                        matters begin to arise in me, I have something at hand to check my self
                        with, and say, why am I troubled? It was but the other day that if I had had
                        the world, I would have given it for my freedom, or to have been a Servant
                        to a Christian. I have learned to look beyond present and smaller troubles,
                        and to be quieted under them, as <hi rend="italic">Moses</hi> said, <hi
                            rend="italic">Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi rend="italic">Stand still and see
                            the salvation of the Lord.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
