<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="behn-oroonoko">


   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="statusBar">Oroonoko, or, The royal slave: A True History</title>

            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Aphra</forename>
                  <surname>Behn</surname>
               </persName>
               <date when="1640-12-14">Birth: 1640 December 14?</date>
               <date when="1689-04-16">Death: 1689 April 16</date>
            </author>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name>Students of The University of Virginia</name>
               <name>Malcolm Bare</name>
               <name>Ankita Chakrabarti</name>
               <name>Neal Curtis</name>
               <name>Alison Glassie</name>
               <name>Robert Hoile</name>
               <name>Rebeccca Rosenblatt</name>
               <name>Simon Sarkodie</name>
               <name>Kristian Smith</name>
               <name>Michael Van Hoose</name>
               <name>Alissa Winn</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <orgName>Literature in Context</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of English, The University of Virginia</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
            </distributor>
            <authority>
               <idno>behn-oroonoko</idno>
            </authority>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
               <p>This text is incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme;
                  also, page images of the first edition would be a nice thing to have, but have not
                  been sourced yet.</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2018</date>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>This edition has been prepared from the edition undertaken by the Oxford Text
               Archive, which reproduces the copy of the first edition in the Huntington Library,
               San Marino, California. This is Oxford Text Archive record number A27305. We
               corrected errors in the Oxford Text Archive against the Google Books digitized page
               images of the first edition: <extent>[14], 239 [i.e. 223] p.</extent>
            </bibl>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName type="lastFirst" key="behnA"> Behn, Aphra; 1640-1689 </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main">Oroonoko</title>
                  <title type="sub">; or, The Royal Slave; a True History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="city" key="lon">London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed for Will. Canning</publisher>
                     <date when="1688">1688</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which
               provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources
               relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the
               17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for
               the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
               University.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                  lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCCN">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCC">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="ESTC">
               <bibl>English Short Title Catalogue Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>

            <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="ORCID">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="SNAC">
               <bibl>Social Network in Archival Context ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <div type="title_page">
               <p>OROONOKO: OR, THE Royal Slave. A TRUE HISTORY.</p>
               <p>By Mrs. A. BEHN.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Canning,</hi> at his Shop in the
                     <hi>Temple-Cloysters.</hi> 1688.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="dedication">
               <head>TO THE Right Honourable THE Lord <hi>MAITLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Since the World is grown so Nice and Critical upon Dedications, and will Needs be
                  Judging the Book, by the Wit of the Patron; we ought, with a great deal of
                  Circumspection, to chuse a Person against whom there can be no <pb/>Exception; and
                  whose Wit, and Worth, truly Merits all that one is capable of saying upon that
                  Occasion.</p>
               <p>The most part of Dedications are charg'd with Flattery; and if the World knows a
                  Man has some Vices, they will not allow one to speak of his Virtues. This, my
                  Lord, is for want of thinking Rightly; if Men wou'd consider with Reason, they
                  wou'd have another sort of Opinion, and Esteem of Dedications; and wou'd believe
                  almost every Great Man has enough to make him Worthy of all that can be said of
                  him there. My Lord, a Picture-drawer, when he intends to make a good Picture,
                  essays the Face many Ways, and in <pb/>many Lights, before he begins; that he may
                  chuse, from the several turns of it, which is most Agreeable, and gives it the
                  best Grace; and if there be a Scar, an ungrateful Mole, or any little Defect, they
                  leave it out; and yet make the Picture extreamly like: But he who has the good
                  Fortune to draw a Face that is exactly Charming in all its Parts and Features,
                  what Colours or Agreements can be added to make it Finer? All that he can give is
                  but its due; and Glories in a Piece whose Original alone gives it its Perfection.
                  An ill Hand may diminish, but a good Hand cannot augment its Beauty. A Poet is a
                  Painter <pb/>in his way; he draws to the Life, but in another kind; we draw the
                  Nobler part, the Soul and Mind; the Pictures of the Pen shall out-last those of
                  the Pencil, and even Worlds themselves. 'Tis a short Chronicle of those Lives that
                  possibly wou'd be forgotten by other Historians, or lye neglected there, however
                  deserving an immortal Fame; for Men of eminent Parts are as Exemplary as even
                  Monarchs themselves; and Virtue is a noble Lesson to be learn'd, and 'tis by
                  Comparison we can Judge and Chuse. 'Tis by such illustrious <ref
                        target="#n002" xml:id="a002">Presidents</ref> , as your Lordship, the
                  World can be Better'd and Refin'd; when a great part of the lazy Nobi<pb/>lity
                  shall, with Shame, behold the admirable Accomplishments of a Man so Great, and so
                  Young.</p>
               <p>Your Lordship has Read innumerable Volumes of Men, and Books; not Vainly for the
                  gust of Novelty, but Knowledge, excellent Knowledge: Like the industrious Bee,
                  from every Flower you return Laden with the precious Dew, which you are sure to
                  turn to the Publick Good. You hoard no one Perfection, but lay it all out in the
                  Glorious Service of your Religion and Country; to both which you are a useful and
                  necessary Honour: They both want such Supporters; and 'tis only Men of so elevated
                  Parts,<pb/> and fine Knowledge; such noble Principles of Loyalty and Religion this
                  Nation Sighs for. Where shall we find a Man so Young, like St. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
                  in the midst of all his Youth and Gaiety, Teaching the World divine Precepts, true
                  Notions of Faith, and Excellent Morality, and, at the same time, be also a perfect
                  Pattern of all that accomplish a Great Man? You have, my Lord, all that refin'd
                  Wit that Charms, and the Affability that Obliges; a Generosity that gives a Lustre
                  to your Nobility; that Hospitality, and Greatness of Mind, that ingages the World;
                  and that admirable Conduct, that so <pb/>well Instructs it. Our Nation ought to
                  regret and bemoan their Misfortunes, for not being able to claim the Honour of the
                  Birth of a Man who is so fit to serve his Majesty, and his Kingdoms, in all Great
                  and Publick Affairs: And to the Glory of your Nation be it spoken, it produces
                  more considerable Men, for all fine Sence, Wit, Wisdom, Breeding, and Generosity
                  (for the generality of the Nobility) than all other Nations can Boast; and the
                  Fruitfulness of your Virtues sufficiently make amends for the Barrenness of your
                  Soil: Which however cannot be incommode to your Lordship; since your Quality, and
                  the <pb/>Veneration that the Commonalty naturally pay their Lords, creates a
                  flowing Plenty there—that makes you Happy. And to compleat your Happiness, my
                  Lord, Heaven has blest you with a Lady, to whom it has given all the Graces,
                  Beauties, and Virtues of her Sex; all the Youth, Sweetness of Nature; of a most
                  illustrious Family; and who is a most rare Example to all Wives of Quality, for
                  her eminent Piety, Easiness, and Condescention; and as absolutely merits Respect
                  from all the World, as she does that Passion and Resignation she receives from
                  your Lordship; and which is, on her part, with so much Ten<pb/>derness return'd.
                  Methinks your tranquil Lives are an Image of the new Made and Beautiful Pair in
                  Paradise: And 'tis the Prayers and Wishes of all, who have the Honour to know you,
                  that it may Eternally so continue, with Additions of all the Blessings this World
                  can give you.</p>
               <p>My Lord, the Obligations I have to some of the Great Men of your Nation,
                  particularly to your Lordship, gives me an Ambition of making my Acknowledgments,
                  by all the Opportunities I can; and such humble Fruits, as my Industry produces, I
                  lay at your Lordships Feet. This is a <pb/>true Story, of a Man Gallant enough to
                  merit your Protection; and, had he always been so Fortunate, he had not made so
                  Inglorious an end: The Royal Slave I had the Honour to know in my Travels to the
                  other World; and though I had none above me in that Country, yet I wanted power to
                  preserve this Great Man. If there be any thing that seems Romantick, I beseech
                  your Lordship to consider, these Countries do, in all things, so far differ from
                  ours, that they produce unconceivable Wonders; at least, they appear so to us,
                  because New and Strange. What I have mention'd I have taken-care shou'd <pb/>be
                  Truth, let the Critical Reader judge as he pleases. 'Twill be no Commendation to
                  the Book, to assure your Lordship I writ it in a few Hours, though it may serve to
                  Excuse some of its Faults of Connexion; for I never rested my Pen a Moment for
                  Thought: 'Tis purely the Merit of my Slave that must render it worthy of the
                  Honour it begs; and the Author of that of Subscribing herself,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> Your Lordship's most oblig'd and obedient Servant,
                     <signed>A. BEHN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </titlePage>
      </front>

      <pb/>
      <body>
         <div type="audio">
            <p><ref
                  target="https://soundcloud.com/aya-rashaideh/sets/novel-oroonoko-the-royal-slave"
                  >LIBRIVOX RECORDING</ref></p>
            <!--[soundcloud url="https://api.soundcloud.com/playlists/232039842" params="auto_play=false&hide_related=false&show_comments=true&show_user=true&show_reposts=false&visual=true" width="100%" height="450" iframe="true" /] -->
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THE HISTORY OF THE <hi>Royal Slave.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I do not pretend, in giving you the History of this <hi>Royal Slave,</hi> to
               entertain my Reader with the Adventures of a feign'd <hi>Hero,</hi> whose Life and
               Fortunes Fancy may manage at the Poets Pleasure; nor in relating the Truth, design to
               adorn it with any Accidents, but such as arriv'd in earnest to him: And it shall come
                  <pb n="2"/>simply into the World, recommended by its own proper Merits, and
               natural Intrigues; there being enough of Reality to support it, and to render it
               diverting, without the Addition of Invention.</p>
            <p>I was my self an <ref target="#n003" xml:id="a003">Eye-Witness</ref> , to a
               great part, of what you will find here set down; and what I cou'd not be Witness of,
               I receiv'd from the Mouth of the chief Actor in this History, the <hi>Hero</hi>
               himself, who gave us the whole Transactions of his Youth; and though I shall omit,
               for Brevity's sake, a thousand little Accidents of his Life, which, however pleasant
               to us, where History was scarce, and Adventures very rare; yet might prove tedious
               and heavy to my Reader, in a World where he finds Diversions for every Minute,<pb
                  n="3"/> new and strange: But we who were perfectly charm'd with the Character of
               this great Man, were curious to gather every Circumstance of his Life.</p>
            <p>The Scene of the last part of his Adventures lies in a Colony in <hi>America,</hi>
               called <ref target="#n004" xml:id="a004">Surinam,</ref> in the
                  <hi>West-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I give you the Story of this <hi>Gallant Slave,</hi> 'tis fit I tell you
               the manner of bringing them to these new <hi>Colonies;</hi> for those they make use
               of there, are not <hi>Natives</hi> of the place; for those we live with in perfect
               Amity, without daring to command 'em; but on the contrary, caress 'em with all the
               brotherly and friendly Affection in the World; trading with 'em for their Fish,
               Venison, Buffilo's, Skins, and little Rarities; as <ref target="#n005"
                     xml:id="a005">Marmosets</ref> , a sort of <hi>Monkey</hi> as <pb n="4"
               />big as a Rat or Weesel, but of a marvellous and delicate shape, and has Face and
               Hands like an Humane Creature: and <ref target="#n006" xml:id="a006"
                     >Cousheries,</ref> a little Beast in the form and fashion of a Lion, as
               big as a Kitten; but so exactly made in all parts like that noble Beast, that it is
               it in <hi>Minature.</hi> Then for little <hi>Parakeetoes,</hi> great Parrots,
                  <hi>Muckaws,</hi> and a thousand other Birds and Beasts of wonderful and
               surprizing Forms, Shapes, and Colours. For Skins of prodigious Snakes, of which there
               are some threescore Yards in length; as is the Skin of one that may be seen at His
               Majesty's <ref target="#n007" xml:id="a007">Antiquaries:</ref> Where are
               also some rare Flies, of amazing Forms and Colours, presented to 'em by my self; some
               as big as my Fist, some less; and all of various Excellencies, such as Art <pb n="5"
               />cannot imitate. Then we trade for Feathers, which they order into all Shapes, make
               themselves little short Habits of 'em, and glorious Wreaths for their Heads, Necks,
               Arms and Legs, whose Tinctures are unconceivable. I had a Set of these presented to
               me, and I gave 'em to the King's Theatre, and it was the Dress of the <ref
                     target="#n008" xml:id="a008">Indian Queen</ref> infinitely admir'd by
               Persons of Quality; and were unimitable. Besides these, a thousand little Knacks, and
               Rarities in Nature, and some of Art; as their Baskets, Weapons, Aprons,
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We dealt with 'em with Beads of all Colours, Knives, Axes, Pins
               and Needles; which they us'd only as Tools to drill <ref target="#n009"
                     xml:id="a009">Holes</ref> with in their Ears, Noses and Lips, where they
               hang a great many little things; as long Beads, bits of Tin,<pb n="6"/>Brass, or
               Silver, beat thin; and any shining Trincket. The Beads they weave into Aprons about a
               quarter of an Ell long, and of the same breadth; working them very prettily in
               Flowers of several Colours of Beads; which Apron they wear just before 'em, as
                  <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did the Fig-leaves; the Men wearing a long Stripe
               of Linen, which they deal with us for. They thread these Beads also on long
               Cotton-threads, and make Girdles to tie their Aprons to, which come twenty times, or
               more, about the Waste; and then cross, like a Shoulder-belt, both ways, and round
               their Necks, Arms and Legs. This Adornment, with their long black Hair, and the Face
               painted in little Specks or Flowers here and there, makes 'em a wonderful Figure
                  to<pb n="7"/> behold. Some of the Beauties which indeed are finely shap'd, as
               almost all are, and who have pretty Features, are very charming and novel; for they
               have all that is called Beauty, except the Colour, which is a reddish Yellow; or
               after a new Oiling, which they often use to themselves, they are of the colour of a
               new Brick, but smooth, soft and sleek. They are extream modest and bashful, very shy,
               and nice of being touch'd. And though they are all thus naked, if one lives for ever
               among 'em, there is not to be seen an indecent Action, or Glance; and being
               continually us'd to see one another so unadorn'd, so like our first Parents before
               the Fall, it seems as if they had no Wishes; there being nothing to heighten
               Curiosity, but all you can see, you<pb n="8"/> see at once, and every Moment see; and
               where there is no Novelty, there can be no Curiosity. Not but I have seen a handsom
               young <hi>Indian,</hi> dying for Love of a very beautiful young <hi>Indian</hi> Maid;
               but all his Courtship was, to fold his Arms, pursue her with his Eyes, and Sighs were
               all his Language: While she, as if no such Lover were present; or rather, as if she
               desired none such, carefully guarded her Eyes from beholding him; and never
               approach'd him, but she look'd down with all the blushing Modesty I have seen in the
               most severe and cautious of our World. And these People represented to me an absolute
                  <hi>Idea</hi> of the first State of Innocence, before Man knew how to sin: And
               'tis most evident and plain, that simple Nature is the most harmless, inoffen<pb
                  n="9"/>sive and vertuous Mistress. 'Tis she alone, if she were permitted, that
               better instructs the World, than all the Inventions of Man: Religion wou'd here but
               destroy that Tranquillity, they possess by Ignorance; and Laws wou'd but teach 'em to
               know Offence, of which now they have no Notion. They once made Mourning and Fasting
               for the Death of the <hi>English</hi> Governor, who had given his Hand to come on
               such a Day to 'em, and neither came, nor sent; believing, when once a Man's Word was
               past, nothing but Death cou'd or shou'd prevent his keeping it: And when they saw he
               was not dead, they ask'd him, what Name they had for a Man who promis'd a thing he
               did not do? The Governor told them, Such a man was a <hi>Lyar,</hi> which<pb n="10"/>
               was a Word of Infamy to a Gentleman. Then one of 'em reply'd, <hi>Governor, you are a
                  Lyar, and guilty of that Infamy.</hi> They have a Native Justice, which knows no
               Fraud; and they understand no Vice, or Cunning, but when they are taught by the
                  <hi>White Men.</hi> They have Plurality of Wives, which, when they grow old, they
               serve those that succeed 'em, who are young; but with a Servitude easie and
               respected; and unless they take Slaves in War, they have no other Attendants.</p>
            <p>Those on that <hi>Continent</hi> where I was, had no King; but the oldest War-Captain
               was obey'd with great Resignation.</p>
            <p>A War-Captain is a Man who has lead them on to Battel with Conduct, and Success; of
               whom I shall have Occasion to speak<pb n="11"/> more hereafter, and of some other of
               their Customs and Manners, as they fall in my way.</p>
            <p>With these People, as I said, we live in perfect Tranquillity, and good
               Understanding, as it behooves us to do; they knowing all the places where to seek the
               best Food of the Country, and the Means of getting it; and for very small and
               unvaluable Trifles, supply us with what 'tis impossible for us to get; for they do
               not only in the Wood, and over the <hi>Sevana's,</hi> in Hunting, supply the parts of
               Hounds, by swiftly scouring through those almost impassable places; and by the meer
               Activity of their Feet, run down the nimblest Deer, and other eatable Beasts: But in
               the water, one wou'd think they were Gods of the Rivers, or Fellow-Citizens of the
                  <pb n="12"/>Deep; so rare an Art they have in Swimming, Diving, and almost Living
               in Water; by which they command the less swift Inhabitants of the Floods. And then
               for Shooting; what they cannot take, or reach with their Hands, they do with Arrows;
               and have so admirable an Aim, that they will split almost an Hair; and at any
               distance that an Arrow can reach, they will shoot down Oranges, and other Fruit, and
               only touch the Stalk with the Dart's Points, that they may not hurt the Fruit. So
               that they being, on all Occasions, very useful to us, we find it absolutely necessary
               to caress 'em as Friends, and not to treat 'em as Slaves; nor dare we do other, their
               Numbers so far surpassing ours in that <hi>Continent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><pb n="13"/>Those then whom we make use of to work in our Plantations of Sugar, are
                  <hi>Negro's, Black-</hi>Slaves altogether; which are transported thither in this
               manner.</p>
            <p>Those who want Slaves, make a Bargain with a Master, or Captain of a Ship, and
               contract to pay him so much a-piece, a matter of twenty Pound a Head for as many as
               he agrees for, and to pay for 'em when they shall be deliver'd on such a Plantation:
               So that when there arrives a Ship laden with Slaves, they who have so contracted, go
               a-board, and receive their Number by Lot; and perhaps in one Lot that may be for ten,
               there may happen to be three or four Men; the rest, Women and Children: Or be there
               more or less of either Sex, you are oblig'd to be contented with your Lot.</p>
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p><ref target="#n010" xml:id="a010">Coramantien,</ref> a Country of
                  <hi>Blacks</hi> so called, was one of those places in which they found the most
               advantageous Trading for these Slaves; and thither most of our great Traders in that
               Merchandice traffick'd; for that Nation is very war-like and brave; and having a
               continual Campaign, being always in Hostility with one neighbouring Prince or other,
               they had the fortune to take a great many Captives; for all they took in Battel, were
               sold as Slaves; at least, those common Men who cou'd not ransom themselves. Of these
               Slaves so taken, the General only has all the profit; and of these Generals, our
               Captains and Masters of Ships buy all their Freights.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Coramantien</hi> was himself a Man of a Hundred and<pb n="15"/> odd
               Years old, and had no Son, though he had many beautiful <hi>Black-</hi>Wives; for
               most certainly, there are Beauties that can charm of that Colour. In his younger
               Years he had had many gallant Men to his Sons, thirteen of which died in Battel,
               conquering when they fell; and he had only left him for his Successor, one
               Grand-Child, Son to one of these dead Victors; who, as soon as he cou'd bear a Bow in
               his Hand, and a Quiver at his Back, was sent into the Field, to be trained up by one
               of the oldest Generals, to War; where, from his natural Inclination to Arms, and the
               Occasions given him, with the good Conduct of the old General, he became, at the Age
               of Seventeen, one of the most expert Captains, and bravest Soldiers, that ever saw
                  <pb n="16"/>the Field of <hi>Mars:</hi> So that he was ador'd as the Wonder of all
               that World, and the Darling of the Soldiers. Besides, he was adorn'd with a native
               Beauty so transcending all those of his gloomy Race, that he strook an Awe and
               Reverence, even in those that knew not his Quality; as he did in me, who beheld him
               with Surprize and Wonder, when afterwards he arriv'd in our World.</p>
            <p>He had scarce arriv'd at his Seventeenth Year, when fighting by his Side, the General
               was kill'd with an Arrow in his Eye, which the Prince <hi>Oroonoko</hi> (for so was
               this gallant <hi>Moor</hi> call'd) very narrowly avoided; nor had he, if the General,
               who saw the Arrow shot, and perceiving it aim'd at the Prince, had not bow'd his Head
               between, on purpose to receive it in his own <pb n="17"/>Body rather than it shou'd
               touch that of the Prince, and so saved him.</p>
            <p>'Twas then, afflicted as <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was, that he was proclaim'd Genéral in the
               old Man's place; and then it was, at the finishing of that War, which had continu'd
               for two Years, that the Prince came to Court; where he had hardly been a Month
               together, from the time of his fifth Year, to that of Seventeen; and 'twas amazing to
               imagine where it was he learn'd so much Humanity; or, to give his Accomplishments a
               juster Name, where 'twas he got that real Greatness of Soul, those refin'd Notions of
               true Honour, that absolute Generosity, and that Softness that was capable of the
               highest Passions of Love and Gallantry, whose Objects were almost<pb n="18"/>
               continually fighting Men, or those mangl'd, or dead; who heard no Sounds, but those
               of War and Groans: Some part of it we may attribute to the Care of a
               <hi>French-</hi>Man of Wit and Learning; who finding it turn to very good Account to
               be a sort of Royal Tutor to this young <hi>Black,</hi> &amp; perceiving him very
               ready, apt, and quick of Apprehension, took a great pleasure to teach him Morals,
               Language and Science; and was for it extreamly belov'd and valu'd by him. Another
               Reason was, He lov'd, when he came from War, to see all the <hi>English</hi>
               Gentlemen that traded thither; and did not only learn their Language, but that of the
                  <hi>Spaniards</hi> also, with whom he traded afterwards for Slaves.</p>
            <p>I have often seen and convers'd with this great Man, and been a Witness to many of
               his mighty Actions; and do assure my Reader, the most Illustrious Courts cou'd not
               have produc'd a braver Man, both for Greatness of Courage and Mind, a Judgment more
               solid, a Wit more quick, and a Conversation more sweet and diverting. He knew almost
               as much as if he had read much: He had heard of, and admir'd the <hi>Romans;</hi> he
               had heard of the late <ref target="#n011" xml:id="a011">Civil Wars</ref> in
                  <hi>England,</hi> and the deplorable Death of our great Monarch; and wou'd
               discourse of it with all the Sense, and Abhorrence of the Injustice imaginable. He
               had an extream good and graceful Mien, and all the Civility of a well-bred great Man.
               He had nothing of Barbarity in his Nature, but in all Points address'd himself, as if
               his Education had been in some <hi>European</hi> Court.</p>
            <p> This great and just Character of <hi>Oroonoko</hi> gave me an extream Curiosity to
               see him, especially when I knew he spoke <ref target="#n012" xml:id="a012"
                     >French</ref> and <ref target="#n013" xml:id="a013"
                  >English,</ref> and that I cou'd talk with him. But though I had heard so
               much of him, I was as greatly surpriz'd when I saw him, as if I had heard nothing of
               him; so beyond all Report I found him. He came into the Room, and address'd himself
               to me, and some other Women, with the best Grace in the World. He was pretty tall,
               but of a Shape the most exact that can be fansy'd: The most famous <ref
                     target="#n014" xml:id="a014">Statuary</ref> cou'd not form the Figure of a
               Man more admirably turn'd from Head to Foot. His Face was not of that brown, rusty
               Black which most of that Nation are, but a perfect Ebony, or polish'd Jett. His Eyes
               were the most <ref target="#n015" xml:id="a015">awful</ref> that cou'd be
               seen, and very piercing; the White of 'em being like Snow, as were his Teeth. His
               Nose was rising and <hi>Roman,</hi> instead of <hi>African</hi> and flat. His Mouth,
               the finest shap'd that cou'd be seen; far from those great turn'd Lips, which are so
               natural to the rest of the <hi>Negroes.</hi> The whole Proportion and Air of his Face
               was so noble, and exactly form'd, that, <ref target="#n016" xml:id="a016"
                     >bating</ref> his Colour, there cou'd be nothing in Nature more beautiful,
               agreeable and handsome. There was no one Grace wanting, that bears the Standard of
               true Beauty: His Hair came down to his Shoulders, by the Aids of Art; which was, by
               pulling it out with a Quill, and keeping it comb'd; of which he took particular Care.
               Nor did the Perfections of his Mind come short of those of his Person; for his
               Discourse was admirable upon almost any Subject; and who-ever had heard him speak,
               wou'd have been convinc'd of their Errors, that all fine Wit is confin'd to the
                  <hi>White</hi> Men, especially to those of <hi>Christendom;</hi> and wou'd have
               confess'd that <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was as capable even of reigning well, and of
               governing as wisely, had as great a Soul, as <ref target="#n017" xml:id="a017"
                     >politick</ref> Maxims, and was as sensible of Power as any Prince
               civiliz'd in the most refin'd Schools of Humanity and Learning, or the most
               Illustrious Courts.</p>

            <p>This Prince, such as I have describ'd him, whose Soul and Body were so admirably
               adorn'd, was (while yet he was in the Court of his Grandfather) as I said, as capable
               of Love, as 'twas possible for a brave and gallant Man to be;and in saying that, I
               have nam'd the highest Degree of Love; for sure, great Souls are most capable of that
               Passion.</p>
            <p>I have already said, the old General was kill'd by the shot of an Arrow, by the Side
               of this Prince, in Battel; and that <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was made General. This old dead
                  <hi>Hero</hi> had one only Daughter left of his Race; a Beauty that, to describe
               her truly, one need say only, she was Female to the noble Male; the beautiful
                  <hi>Black Venus,</hi> to our young <hi>Mars;</hi> as charming in her Person as he,
               and of delicate Vertues. I have seen an hundred <hi>White</hi> Men sighing after her,
               and making a thousand Vows at her Feet, all vain, and unsuccessful: And she was,
               indeed, too great for any, but a Prince of her own Nation to adore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko</hi> coming from the Wars, (which were now ended) after he had made his
               Court to his Grandfather, he thought in Honour he ought to make a Visit to
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> the Daughter of his Foster-father, the dead General; and to make
               some Excuses to her, because his Preservation was the Occasion of her Father's Death;
               and to present her with those Slaves that had been taken in this last Battel, as the
               Trophies of her Father's Victories. When he came, attended by all the young Soldiers
               of any Merit, he was infinitely surpriz'd at the Beauty of this fair Queen of Night,
               whose Face and Person was so exceeding all he had ever beheld, that lovely Modesty
               with which she receiv'd him, that Softness in her Look, and Sighs, upon the
               melancholy Occasion of this Honour that was done by so great a Man as
                  <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> and a Prince of whom she had heard such admirable things; the
               Awfulness wherewith she receiv'd him, and the Sweetness of her Words and Behaviour
               while he stay'd, gain'd a perfect Conquest over his fierce Heart, and made him feel,
               the Victor cou'd be subdu'd. So that having made his first Complements, and presented
               her an hundred and fifty Slaves in Fetters, he told her with his Eyes, that he was
               not insensible of her Charms; while <hi>Imoinda,</hi> who wish'd for nothing more
               than so glorious a Conquest, was pleas'd to believe, she understood that silent
               Language of new-born Love; and from that Moment, put on all her Additions to
               Beauty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26"/> The Prince return'd to Court with quite another Humour than before; and
               though he did not speak much of the fair <hi>Imoinda,</hi> he had the pleasure to
               hear all his Followers speak of nothing but the Charms of that Maid; insomuch that,
               even in the Presence of the old King, they were extolling her, and heightning, if
               possible, the Beauties they had found in her: So that nothing else was talk'd of, no
               other Sound was heard in every Corner where there were Whisperers, but <hi>Imoinda!
                  Imoinda!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twill be imagin'd <hi>Oroonoko</hi> stay'd not long before he made his second Visit;
               nor, considering his Quality, not much longer before he told her, he ador'd her. I
               have often heard him say, that he admir'd by what strange Inspiration he came to talk
               things so soft, and<pb n="27"/> so passionate, who never knew Love, nor was us'd to
               the Conversation of Women; but (to use his own Words) he said, Most happily, some
               new, and till then unknown Power instructed his Heart and Tongue in the Language of
               Love, and at the same time, in favour of him, inspir'd <hi>Imoinda</hi> with a Sense
               of his Passion. She was touch'd with what he said, and return'd it all in such
               Answers as went to his very Heart, with a Pleasure unknown before: Nor did he use
               those Obligations ill, that Love had done him; but turn'd all his happy Moments to
               the best advantage; and as he knew no Vice, his Flame aim'd at nothing but Honour, if
               such a distinction may be made in Love; and especially in that Country, where Men
               take to themselves as many<pb n="28"/> as they can maintain; and where the only Crime
               and Sin with Woman is, to turn her off, to abandon her to Want, Shame and Misery:
               Such ill Morals are only practis'd in <hi>Christian-</hi>Countries, where they prefer
               the bare Name of Religion; and, without Vertue or Morality, think that's sufficient.
               But <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was none of those Professors; but as he had right Notions of
               Honour, so he made her such Propositions as were not only and barely such; but,
               contrary to the Custom of his Country, he made her Vows, she shou'd be the only woman
               he wou'd possess while he liv'd; that no Age or Wrinkles shou'd incline him to
               change, for her Soul wou'd be always fine, and always young; and he shou'd have an
               eternal <hi>Idea</hi> in his Mind of the Charms she now <pb n="29"/>bore, and shou'd
               look into his Heart for that <hi>Idea,</hi> when he cou'd find it no longer in her
               Face.</p>
            <p>After a thousand Assurances of his lasting Flame, and her eternal Empire over him,
               she condescended to receive him for her Husband; or rather, receiv'd him, as the
               greatest Honour the God's cou'd do her.</p>
            <p>There is a certain Ceremony in these Cases to be observ'd, which I forgot to ask him
               how perform'd; but 'twas concluded on both sides, that, in Obedience to him, the
               Grand-father was to be first made acquainted with the Design: for they pay a most
               absolute Resignation to the Monarch, especially when he is a Parent also.</p>
            <p>On the other side, the old King, who had many Wives, and many<pb n="30"/> Concubines,
               wanted not Court-Flatterers to insinuate in his Heart a thousand tender Thoughts for
               this young Beauty; and who represented her to his Fancy, as the most charming he had
               ever possess'd in all the long Race of his numerous Years. At this Character his old
               Heart, like an extinguish'd Brand, most apt to take Fire, felt new Sparks of Love,
               and began to kindle; and now grown to his second Childhood, long'd with Impatience to
               behold this gay thing, with whom, alas! he cou'd but innocently play. But how he
               shou'd be confirm'd she was this <hi>Wonder,</hi> before he us'd his Power to call
               her to Court (where Maidens never came, unless for the King's private Use) he was
               next to consider; and while he was so doing, he had Intelligence <pb n="31"/>brought
               him, that <hi>Imoinda</hi> was most certainly Mistress to the Prince
                  <hi>Oroonoko.</hi> This gave him some <hi>Shagrien;</hi> however, it gave him also
               an Opportunity, one Day, when the Prince was a-hunting, to wait on a Man of Quality,
               as his Slave and Attendant, who shou'd go and make a Present to <hi>Imoinda,</hi> as
               from the Prince; he shou'd then, unknown, see this fair Maid, and have an Opportunity
               to hear what Message she wou'd return the Prince for his Present; and from thence
               gather the state of her Heart, and degree of her Inclination. This was put in
               Execution, and the old Monarch saw, and burnt: He found her all he had heard, and
               wou'd not delay his Happiness, but found he shou'd have some Obstacle to overcome her
               Heart; for she express'd <pb n="32"/>her Sense of the Present the Prince had sent
               her, in terms so sweet, so soft and pretty, with an Air of Love and Joy that cou'd
               not be dissembl'd; insomuch that 'twas past doubt whether she lov'd <hi>Oroonoko</hi>
               entirely. This gave the old King some Affliction; but he salv'd it with this, that
               the Obedience the People pay their King, was not at all inferior to what they pay'd
               their Gods: And what Love wou'd not oblige <hi>Imoinda</hi> to do, Duty wou'd compel
               her to.</p>
            <p>He was therefore no sooner got to his Apartment, but he sent the Royal Veil to
                  <hi>Imoinda;</hi> that is, the Ceremony of Invitation; he sends the Lady, he has a
               Mind to honour with his Bed, a Veil, with which she is cover'd, and secur'd for the
               King's Use; and 'tis Death to disobey; besides, held a most impious Disobedience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33"/> 'Tis not to be imagin'd the Surprize and Grief that seiz'd this lovely
               Maid at this News and Sight. However, as Delays in these Cases are dangerous, and
               Pleading worse than Treason; trembling, and almost fainting, she was oblig'd to
               suffer her self to be cover'd, and led away.</p>
            <p>They brought her thus to Court; and the King, who had caus'd a very rich Bath to be
               prepar'd, was led into it, where he sate under a Canopy, in State, to receive this
               long'd for Virgin; whom he having commanded shou'd be brought to him, they (after
               dis-robing her) led her to the Bath, and making fast the Doors, left her to descend.
               The King, without more Courtship, bad her throw off her Mantle, and come to his Arms.
               But <hi>Imoinda,</hi> all in <pb n="34"/> Tears, threw her self on the Marble, on the
               Brink of the Bath, and besought him to hear her. She told him, as she was a Maid, how
               proud of the Divine Glory she should have been of having it in her power to oblige
               her King: but as by the Laws, he cou'd not; and from his Royal Goodness, wou'd not
               take from any Man his wedded Wife: So she believ'd she shou'd be the Occasion of
               making him commit a great Sin, if she did not reveal her State and Condition; and
               tell him, she was anothers, and cou'd not be so happy to be his.</p>
            <p>The King, enrag'd at this Delay, hastily demanded the Name of the bold Man, that had
               marry'd a Woman of her Degree, without his Consent. <hi>Imoinda,</hi> seeing his Eyes
               fierce, and his Hands tremble; <pb n="35"/>whether with Age, or Anger, I know not;
               but she fansy'd the last, almost repented she had said so much, for now she fear'd
               the Storm wou'd fall on the Prince; she therefore said a thousand things to appease
               the raging of his Flame, and to prepare him to hear who it was with Calmness; but
               before she spoke, he imagin'd who she meant, but wou'd not seem to do so, but
               commanded her to lay aside her <ref target="#n018" xml:id="a018"
                  >Mantle</ref> , and suffer her self to receive his Caresses; or, by his Gods,
               he swore, that happy Man whom she was going to name shou'd die, though it were even
                  <hi>Oroonoko</hi> himself. <hi>Therefore</hi> (said he) <hi>deny this Marriage,
                  and swear thy self a Maid. That</hi> (reply'd <hi>Imoinda) by all our Powers I do;
                  for I am not yet known to my Husband. 'Tis enough</hi> (said the King:) <hi>'tis
                  enough</hi><pb n="36"/>
               <hi>to satisfie both my Conscience, and my Heart.</hi> And rising from his Seat, he
               went, and led her into the Bath; it being in vain for her to resist.</p>
            <p>In this time the Prince, who was return'd from Hunting, went to visit his
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> but found her gone; and not only so, but heard she had receiv'd
               the <ref target="#n019" xml:id="a019">Royal Veil</ref> . This rais'd him to
               a Storm; and in his Madness, they had much ado to save him from laying violent Hands
               on himself. Force first prevail'd, and then Reason: They urg'd all to him, that might
               oppose his Rage; but nothing weigh'd so greatly with him as the King's Old Age
               uncapable of <ref target="#n020" xml:id="a020">injuring him</ref> with
                  <hi>Imoinda.</hi> He wou'd give way to that Hope, because it pleas'd him most, and
               flatter'd best his Heart. Yet this <pb n="37"/>serv'd not altogether to make him
               cease his different Passions, which sometimes rag'd within him, and sometimes softned
               into Showers. 'Twas not enough to appease him, to tell him, his Grand-father was old,
               and cou'd not that way injure him, while he retain'd that awful Duty which the young
               Men are us'd there to pay to their grave Relations. He cou'd not be convinc'd he had
               no Cause to sigh and mourn for the Loss of a Mistress, he cou'd not with all his
               Strength and Courage retrieve. And he wou'd often cry, <hi>O my Friends! were she in
                  wall'd Cities, or confin'd from me in Fortifications of the greatest Strength; did
                  Inchantments or Monsters detain her from me, I wou'd venture through any Hazard to
                  free her: Buthere, in the Arms of a feeble old Man, my Youth, my violent Love, my
                  Trade</hi><pb n="38"/><hi>in Arms, and all my vast Desire of Glory, avail me
                  nothing:</hi> Imoinda <hi>is as irrecoverably lost to me, as if she were snatch'd
                  by the cold Arms of Death: Oh! she is never to be retriev'd. If I wou'd wait
                  tedious Years, till Fate shou'd bow the old King to his Grave; even that wou'd not
                  leave me</hi> Imoinda <hi>free; but still that Custom that makes it so vile a
                  Crime for a Son to marry his Father's Wives or Mistresses, wou'd hinder my
                  Happiness; unless I wou'd either ignobly set an ill President to my Successors, or
                  abandon my Country, and fly with her to some unknown World, who never heard our
                  Story.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it was objected to him, that his Case was not the same; for <hi>Imoinda</hi>
               being his lawful Wife, by solemn Contract, 'twas he was the injur'd Man, and might,
               if he so pleas'd, take <hi>Imoinda</hi> back, the <pb n="39"/>Breach of the Law being
               on his Grand-father's side; and that if he cou'd circumvent him, and redeem her from
               the <ref target="#n021" xml:id="a021">Otan</ref> , which is the Palace of
               the King's Women, a sort of <hi>Seraglio,</hi> it was both just and lawful for him so
               to do.</p>
            <p>This Reasoning had some force upon him, and he shou'd have been entirely comforted,
               but for the Thought that she was possess'd by his Grand-father. However, he lov'd so
               well, that he was resolv'd to believe what most favour'd his Hope; and to endeavour
               to learn from <hi>Imoinda</hi>'s own Mouth, what only she cou'd satisfie him in;
               whether she was robb'd of that Blessing, which was only due to his Faith and Love.
               But as it was very hard to get a Sight of the Women, for no Men ever enter'd into the
                  <hi>Otan,</hi> but when<pb n="40"/> the King went to entertain himself with some
               one of his Wives, or Mistresses; and 'twas Death at any other time, for any other to
               go in; so he knew not how to contrive to get a Sight of her.</p>

            <p>While <hi>Oroonoko</hi> felt all the Agonies of Love, and suffer'd under a Torment
               the most painful in the World, the old King was not exempted from his share of
               Affliction. He was troubl'd for having been forc'd by an irresistable Passion, to rob
               his <ref target="#n022" xml:id="a022">Son</ref> of a Treasure, he knew,
               cou'd not but be extreamly dear to him, since she was the most beautiful that ever
               had been seen; and had besides, all the Sweetness and Innocence of Youth and Modesty,
               with a Charm of Wit surpassing all. He found that, however she was forc'd to expose
               her lovely Person to his wither'd Arms, she <pb n="41"/>cou'd only sigh and weep
               there, and think of <hi>Oroonoko;</hi> and oftentimes cou'd not forbear speaking of
               him, though her Life were, by Custom, forfeited by owning her Passion. But she spoke
               not of a Lover only, but of a Prince dear to him, to whom she spoke; and of the
               Praises of a Man, who, till now, fill'd the old Man's Soul with Joy at every Recital
               of his Bravery, or even his Name. And 'twas this Dotage on our young <hi>Hero,</hi>
               that gave <hi>Imoinda</hi> a thousand Privileges to speak of him, without offending;
               and this Condescention in the old King, that made her take the Satisfaction of
               speaking of him so very often.</p>
            <p>Besides, he many times enquir'd how the Prince bore himself; and those of whom he
               ask'd, being entirely Slaves to the Merits and Vertues <pb n="42"/> of the Prince,
               still answer'd what they thought conduc'd best to his Service; which was, to make the
               old King fansy that the Prince had no more Interest in <hi>Imoinda,</hi> and had
               resign'd her willingly to the Pleasure of the King; that he diverted himself with his
               Mathematicians, his Fortifications, his Officers, and his Hunting.</p>
            <p>This pleas'd the old Lover, who fail'd not to report these things again to
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> that she might, by the Example of her young Lover, withdraw her
               Heart, and rest better contented in his Arms. But however she was forc'd to receive
               this unwelcome News, in all Appearance, with Unconcern, and Content, her Heart was
               bursting within, and she was only happy when she cou'd get alone, to vent her Griefs
               and Moans with Sighs and Tears.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43"/> What Reports of the Prince's Conduct were made to the King, he thought
               good to justifie as far as possibly he cou'd by his Actions; and when he appear'd in
               the Presence of the King, he shew'd a Face not at all betraying his Heart: So that in
               a little time the old Man, being entirely convinc'd that he was no longer a Lover of
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> he carry'd him with him, in his Train, to the <hi>Otan,</hi>
               often to banquet with his Mistress. But as soon as he enter'd, one Day, into the
               Apartment of <hi>Imoinda,</hi> with the King, at the first Glance from her Eyes,
               notwithstanding all his determin d Resolution, he was ready to sink in the place
               where he stood; and had certainly done so, but for the Support of <hi>Aboan,</hi> a
               young Man, who was next to him; which, with his Change of Countenance,<pb n="44"/>
               had betray'd him, had the King chanc'd to look that way. And I have observ'd, 'tis a
               very great Error in those, who laugh when one says, <hi>A</hi> Negro <hi>can change
                  Colour;</hi> for I have seen 'em as frequently blush, and look pale, and that as
               visibly as ever I saw in the most beautiful <hi>White.</hi> And 'tis certain that
               both these Changes were evident, this Day, in both these Lovers. And
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> who saw with some Joy the Change in the Prince's Face, and found
               it in her own, strove to divert the King from beholding either, by a forc'd Caress,
               with which she met him; which was a new Wound in the Heart of the poor dying Prince.
               But as soon as the King was busy'd in looking on some fine thing of
               <hi>Imoinda</hi>'s making, she had time to tell the Prince with her angry,<pb n="45"
               /> but Love-darting Eyes, that she resented his Coldness, and bemoan'd her own
               miserable Captivity. Nor were his Eyes silent, but answer'd hers again, as much as
               Eyes cou'd do, instructed by the most tender, and most passionate Heart that ever
               lov'd: And they spoke so well, and so effectually, as <hi>Imoinda</hi> no longer
               doubted, but she was the only Delight, and the Darling of that Soul she found
               pleading in 'em its Right of Love, which none was more willing to resign than she.
               And 'twas this powerful Language alone that in an Instant convey'd all the Thoughts
               of their Souls to each other; that they both found, there wanted but Opportunity to
               make them both entirely happy. But when he saw another Door open'd by
                  <hi>Onahal,</hi> a former old Wife of <pb n="46"/>the King's, who now had Charge
               of <hi>Imoinda;</hi> and saw the Prospect of a Bed of State made ready, with Sweets
               and Flowers for the Dalliance of the King; who immediately lead the trembling Victim
               from his Sight, into that prepar'd Repose. What Rage! what wild Frenzies seiz'd his
               Heart! which forcing to keep within Bounds, and to suffer without Noise, it became
               the more insupportable, and rent his Soul with ten thousand Pains. He was forc'd to
               retire, to vent his Groans; where he fell down on a Carpet, and lay struggling a long
               time, and only breathing now and then,—<hi>O Imoinda!</hi> When <hi>Onahal</hi> had
               finish'd her necessary Affair within, shutting the Door, she came forth to wait, till
               the King call'd; and hearing some one sighing in the other<pb n="47"/> Room, she
               pass'd on, and found the Prince in that deplorable Condition, which she thought
               needed her Aid: She gave him Cordials, but all in vain; till finding the nature of
               his Disease, by his Sighs, and naming <hi>Imoinda.</hi> She told him, he had not so
               much Cause as he imagin'd, to afflict himself; for if he knew the King so well as she
               did, he wou'd not lose a Moment in Jealousie, and that she was confident that
                  <hi>Imoinda</hi> bore, at this Minute, part in his Affliction. <hi>Aboan</hi> was
               of the same Opinion; and both together, perswaded him to re-assume his Courage; and
               all sitting down on the Carpet, the Prince said so many obliging things to
                  <hi>Onahal,</hi> that he half perswaded her to be of his Party. And she promis'd
               him, she wou'd thus far comply with his just Desires, that she<pb n="48"/> wou'd let
                  <hi>Imoinda</hi> know how faithful he was, what he suffer'd, and what he said.</p>
            <p>This Discourse lasted till the King call'd, which gave <hi>Oroonoko</hi> a certain
               Satisfaction; and with the Hope <hi>Onahal</hi> had made him conceive, he assum'd a
               Look as gay as 'twas possible a Man in his Circumstances cou'd do; and presently
               after, he was call'd in with the rest who waited without. The King commanded Musick
               to be brought, and several of his young Wives and Mistresses came all together by his
               Command, to dance before him; where <hi>Imoinda</hi> perform'd her Part with an Air
               and Grace so passing all the rest, as her Beauty was above 'em; and receiv'd the
               Present, ordain'd as a Prize. The Prince was every Moment more charm'd with the <pb
                  n="49"/> new Beauties and Graces he beheld in this fair One: And while he gaz'd,
               and she danc'd, <hi>Onahal</hi> was retir'd to a Window with <hi>Aboan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Onahal,</hi> as I said, was one of the <ref target="#n023" xml:id="a023"
                     >Cast-Mistresses</ref> of the old King; and 'twas these (now past their
               Beauty) that were made Guardians, or Governants to the new, and the young Ones; and
               whose Business it was, to teach them all those wanton Arts of Love, with which they
               prevail'd and charm'd heretofore in their Turn; and who now treated the triumphing
               happy Ones with all the Severity, as to Liberty and Freedom, that was possible, in
               revenge of those Honours they rob them of; envying them those Satisfactions, those
               Gallantries and Presents, that were once made to themselves, while Youth and <pb
                  n="50"/>Beauty lasted, and which they now saw pass were regardless by, and pay'd
               only to the Bloomings. And certainly, nothing is more afflicting to a decay'd Beauty,
               than to behold in it self declining Charms, that were once ador'd; and to find those
               Caresses paid to new Beauties, to which once she laid a Claim; to hear 'em whisper as
               she passes by, <hi>That once was a delicate Woman.</hi> These abandon'd Ladies
               therefore endeavour to revenge all the Despights, and Decays of Time, on these
               flourishing happy Ones. And 'twas this Severity, that gave <hi>Oroonoko</hi> a
               thousand Fears he shou'd never prevail with <hi>Onahal,</hi> to see <hi>Imoinda.</hi>
               But, as I said, she was now retir'd to a Window with <hi>Aboan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This young Man was not only one of the best Quality, but a Man <pb n="51"/>extreamly
               well made, and beautiful; and coming often to attend the King to the <hi>Otan,</hi>
               he had subdu'd the Heart of the antiquated <hi>Onahal,</hi> which had not forgot how
               pleasant it was to be in Love: And though she had some Decays in her Face, she had
               none in her Sence and Wit; she was there agreeable still, even to <hi>Aboan</hi>'s
               Youth; so that he took pleasure in entertaining her with Discourses of Love: He knew
               also, that to make his Court to these She-Favourites, was the way to be great; these
               being the Persons that do all Affairs and Business at Court. He had also observ'd
               that she had given him Glances more tender and inviting, than she had done to others
               of his Quality: And now, when he saw that her Favour cou'd so absolutely oblige the
               Prince, he<pb n="52"/> fail'd not to sigh in her Ear, and to look with Eyes all soft
               upon her, and give her Hope that she had made some Impressions on his Heart. He found
               her pleas'd at this, and making a thousand Advances to him; but the Ceremony ending,
               and the King departing, broke up the Company for that Day, and his Conversation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aboan</hi> fail'd not that Night to tell the Prince of his Success, and how
               advantageous the Service of <hi>Onahal</hi> might be to his Amour with
                  <hi>Imoinda.</hi> The Prince was overjoy'd with this good News, and besought him,
               if it were possible, to caress her so, as to engage her entirely; which he cou'd not
               fail to do, if he comply'd with her Desires: <hi>For then</hi> (said the Prince)
                  <hi>her Life lying at your Mercy, she must grant you the Request you make in
                  my</hi><pb n="53"/><hi>Behalf. Aboan</hi> understood him; and assur'd him, he
               would make Love so effectually, that he wou'd defie the most expert Mistress of the
               Art, to find out whether he dissembl'd it, or had it really. And 'twas with
               Impatience they waited the next Opportunity of going to the <hi>Otan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Wars came on, the Time of taking the Field approach'd, and 'twas impossible for
               the Prince to delay his going at the Head of his Army, to encounter the Enemy: So
               that every Day seem'd a tedious Year, till he saw his <hi>Imoinda;</hi> for he
               believ'd he cou'd not live, if he were forc'd away without being so happy. 'Twas with
               Impatience therefore, that he expected the next Visit the King wou'd make; and,
               according to his Wish, it was not long.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54"/> The Parley of the Eyes of these two Lovers had not pass'd so secretly,
               but an old jealous Lover cou'd spy it; or rather, he wanted not Flatterers, who told
               him, they observ'd it: So that the Prince was hasten'd to the Camp, and this was the
               last Visit he found he shou'd make to the <hi>Otan;</hi> he therefore urg'd
                  <hi>Aboan</hi> to make the best of this last Effort, and to explain himself so to
                  <hi>Onahal,</hi> that she, deferring her Enjoyment of her young Lover no longer,
               might make way for the Prince to speak to <hi>Imoinda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Affair being agreed on between the Prince and <hi>Aboan,</hi> they attended
               the King, as the Custom was, to the <hi>Otan;</hi> where, while the whole Company was
               taken up in beholding the Dancing, and antick Postures the Women<pb n="55"/> Royal
               made, to divert the King, <hi>Onahal</hi> singl'd out <hi>Aboan,</hi> whom she found
               most pliable to her Wish. When she had him where she believ'd she cou'd not be heard,
               she sigh'd to him, and softly cry'd, <hi>Ah,</hi> Aboan! <hi>When will you be
                  sensible of my Passion? I confess it with my Mouth, because I wou'd not give my
                  Eyes the Lye; and you have but too much already perceiv'd they have confess'd my
                  Flame: Nor wou'd I have you believe, that because I am the abandon'd Mistress of a
                  King, I esteem my self altogether divested of Charms. No,</hi> Aboan; <hi>I have
                  still a Rest of Beauty enough engaging, and have learn'd to please too well, not
                  to be desirable. I can have Lovers still, but will have none but</hi> Aboan.
                  <hi>Madam</hi> (reply'd the half-feigning Youth) <hi>you have already, by my Eyes,
                  found, you can still conquer; and I believe 'tis in pity of me,</hi><pb n="56"
                  /><hi>you condescend to this kind Confession. But, Madam, Words are us'd to be so
                  small a part of our Country-Courtship, that 'tis rare one can get so happy an
                  Opportunity as to tell one's Heart; and those few Minutes we have are forc'd to be
                  snatch'd for more certain Proofs of Love, than speaking and sighing; and such I
                  languish for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He spoke this with such a Tone, that she hop'd it true, and cou'd not forbear
               believing it; and being wholly transported with Joy, for having subdu'd the finest of
               all the King's Subjects to her Desires, she took from her Ears two large Pearls, and
               commanded him to wear 'em in his. He wou'd have refus'd 'em, crying, <hi>Madam, these
                  are not the Proofs of your Love that I expect; 'tis Opportunity, 'tis a Lonehour
                  only, that can make me happy.</hi> But forcing the Pearls into his<pb n="57"/>
               Hand, she whisper'd softly to him, <hi>Oh! Do not fear a Woman's Invention, when Love
                  sets her a-thinking.</hi> And pressing his Hand, she cry'd, <hi>This Night you
                  shall be happy. Come to the Gate of the Orange-Groves, behind the</hi> Otan;
                  <hi>and I will be ready, about Mid-night, to receive you.</hi> 'Twas thus agreed,
               and she left him, that no notice might be taken of their speaking together.</p>
            <p>The Ladies were still dancing, and the King, laid on a Carpet, with a great deal of
               pleasure, was beholding them, especially <hi>Imoinda;</hi> who that Day appear'd more
               lovely than ever, being enliven'd with the good Tidings <hi>Onahal</hi> had brought
               her of the constant Passion the Prince had for her. The Prince was laid on another
               Carpet, at the other end of the Room, with his Eyes fix'd on the Object <pb n="58"/>
               of his Soul; and as she turn'd, or mov'd, so did they; and she alone gave his Eyes
               and Soul their Motions: Nor did <hi>Imoinda</hi> employ her Eyes to any other Use,
               than in beholding with infinite Pleasure the Joy she produc'd in those of the Prince.
               But while she was more regarding him, than the Steps she took, she chanc'd to fall;
               and so near him, as that leaping with extream force from the Carpet, he caught her in
               his Arms as she fell; and 'twas visible to the whole Presence, the Joy wherewith he
               receiv'd her: He clasp'd her close to his Bosom, and quite forgot that Reverence that
               was due to the Mistress of a King, and that Punishment that is the Reward of a
               Boldness of this nature; and had not the Presence of Mind of <hi>Imoinda</hi> (fonder
               of his Safety, than her<pb n="59"/> own) befriended him, in making her spring from
               his Arms, and fall into her Dance again, he had, at that Instant, met his Death; for
               the old King, jealous to the last degree, rose up in Rage, broke all the Diversion,
               and led <hi>Imoinda</hi> to her Apartment, and sent out Word to the Prince, to go
               immediately to the Camp; and that if he were found another Night in Court, he shou'd
               suffer the Death ordain'd for disobedient Offenders.</p>
            <p>You may imagine how welcome this News was to <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> whose unseasonable
               Transport and Caress of <hi>Imoinda</hi> was blam'd by all Men that lov'd him; and
               now he perceiv'd his Fault, yet cry'd, <hi>That for such another Moment, he wou'd be
                  content to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the <hi>Otan</hi> was in disorder about this Accident; and <hi>Onahal</hi><pb
                  n="60"/> was particularly concern'd, because on the Prince's Stay depended her
               Happiness; for she cou'd no longer expect that of <hi>Aboan.</hi> So that, e'er they
               departed, they contriv'd it so, that the Prince and he shou'd come both that Night to
               the Grove of the <hi>Otan,</hi> which was all of Oranges and Citrons; and that there
               they shou'd wait her Orders.</p>
            <p>They parted thus, with Grief enough, till Night; leaving the King in possession of
               the lovely Maid. But nothing cou'd appease the Jealousie of the old Lover: He wou'd
               not be impos'd on, but wou'd have it, that <hi>Imoinda</hi> made a false Step on
               purpose to fall into <hi>Oroonoko</hi>'s Bosom, and that all things look'd like a
               Design on both sides, and 'twas in vain she protested her Innocence: He was old and
               obstinate, and left her more <pb n="61"/> than half assur'd that his Fear was
               true.</p>
            <p>The King going to his Apartment, sent to know where the Prince was, and if he
               intended to obey his Command. The Messenger return'd, and told him, he found the
               Prince pensive, and altogether unpreparing for the Campaign; that he lay negligently
               on the Ground, and answer'd very little. This confirm'd the Jealousie of the King,
               and he commanded that they shou'd very narrowly and privately watch his Motions; and
               that he shou'd not stir from his Apartment, but one Spy or other shou'd be employ'd
               to watch him: So that the Hour approaching, wherein he was to go to the Citron-Grove;
               and taking only <hi>Aboan</hi> along with him, he leaves his Apartment, and was
               watch'd to the<pb n="62"/> very Gate of the <hi>Otan;</hi> where he was seen to
               enter, and where they left him, to carry back the Tidings to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko</hi> and <hi>Aboan</hi> were no sooner enter'd, but <hi>Onahal</hi> led
               the Prince to the Apartment of <hi>Imoinda;</hi> who, not knowing any thing of her
               Happiness, was laid in Bed. But <hi>Onahal</hi> only left him in her Chamber, to make
               the best of his Opportunity, and took her dear <hi>Aboan</hi> to her own; where he
               shew'd the heighth of Complaisance for his Prince, when, to give him an Opportunity,
               he suffer'd himself to be caress'd in Bed by <hi>Onahal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince softly waken'd <hi>Imoinda,</hi> who was not a little surpriz'd with Joy
               to find him there; and yet she trembl'd with a thousand Fears. I believe, he omitted
               saying nothing to this young Maid, <pb n="63"/>that might perswade her to suffer him
               to seize his own, and take the Rights of Love; and I believe she was not long
               resisting those Arms, where she so long'd to be; and having Opportunity, Night and
               Silence, Youth, Love and Desire, he soon prevail'd; and ravish'd in a Moment, what
               his old Grand-father had been endeavouring for so many Months.</p>

            <p>'Tis not to be imagin'd the Satisfaction of these two young Lovers; nor the Vows she
               made him, that she remain'd a spotless Maid, till that Night; and that what she did
               with his Grand-father, had robb'd him of no part of her Virgin-Honour, the Gods, in
               Mercy and Justice, having reserv'd that for her plighted Lord, to whom of Right it
               belong'd. And 'tis impossible to express the Transports<pb n="64"/> he suffer'd,
               while he listen'd to a Discourse so charming, from her lov'd Lips; and clasp'd that
               Body in his Arms, for whom he had so long languish'd; and nothing now afflicted him,
               but his suddain Departure from her; for he told her the Necessity, and his Commands;
               but shou'd depart satisfy'd in this, That since the old King had hitherto not been
               able to deprive him of those Enjoyments which only belong'd to him, he believ'd for
               the future he wou'd be less able to injure him; so that, abating the Scandal of the
               Veil, which was no otherwise so, than that she was Wife to another: He believ'd her
               safe, even in the Arms of the King, and innocent; yet wou'd he have ventur'd at the
               Conquest of the World, and have given it all, to have had her avoided that Honour <pb
                  n="65"/>of receiving the <hi>Royal Veil.</hi> 'Twas thus, between a thousand
               Caresses, that both bemoan'd the hard Fate of Youth and Beauty, so liable to that
               cruel Promotion: 'Twas a Glory that cou'd well have been spar'd here, though desir'd,
               and aim'd at by all the young Females of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But while they were thus fondly employ'd, forgetting how Time ran on, and that the
               Dawn must conduct him far away from his only Happiness, they heard a great Noise in
               the <hi>Otan,</hi> and unusual Voices of Men; at which the Prince, starting from the
               Arms of the frighted <hi>Imoinda,</hi> ran to a little Battel-Ax he us'd to wear by
               his Side; and having not so much leisure, as to put on his Habit, he oppos'd himself
               against some who were already opening the Door; <pb n="66"/>which they did with so
               much Violence, that <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was not able to defend it; but was forc'd to
               cry out with a commanding Voice, <hi>Whoever ye are that have the Boldness to attempt
                  to approach this Apartment thus rudely, know, that I, the Prince</hi> Oroonoko,
                  <hi>will revenge it with the certain Death of him that first enters: Therefore
                  stand back, and know, this place is sacred to Love, and me this Night; to Morrow
                  'tis the King's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he spoke with a Voice so resolv'd and assur'd, that they soon retir'd from the
               Door, but cry'd, <hi>'Tis by the King's Command we are come; and being satisfy'd by
                  thy Voice, O Prince, as much as if we had enter'd, we can report to the King the
                  Truth of all his Fears, and leave thee to provide for thy own Safety, as thou art
                  advis'd by thy Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67"/> At these Words they departed, and left the Prince to take a short and
               sad Leave of his <hi>Imoinda;</hi> who trusting in the strength of her Charms,
               believ'd she shou'd appease the Fury of a jealous King, by saying, She was surpriz'd,
               and that it was by force of Arms he got into her Apartment. All her Concern now was
               for his Life, and therefore she hasten'd him to the Camp; and with much a-do,
               prevail'd on him to go: Nor was it she alone that prevail'd, <hi>Aboan</hi> and
                  <hi>Onahal</hi> both pleaded, and both assur'd him of a Lye that shou'd be well
               enough contriv'd to secure <hi>Imoinda.</hi> So that, at last, with a Heart sad as
               Death, dying Eyes, and sighing Soul, <hi>Oroonoko</hi> departed, and took his way to
               the Camp.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68"/> It was not long after the King in Person came to the <hi>Otan;</hi>
               where beholding <hi>Imoinda</hi> with Rage in his Eyes, he upbraided her Wickedness
               and Perfidy, and threatning her Royal Lover, she fell on her Face at his Feet,
               bedewing the Floor with her Tears, and imploring his Pardon for a Fault which she had
               not with her Will committed; as <hi>Onahal,</hi> who was also prostrate with her,
               cou'd testifie: That, unknown to her, he had broke into her Apartment, and ravish'd
               her. She spoke this much against her Conscience; but to save her own Life, 'twas
               absolutely necessary she shou'd feign this Falsity. She knew it cou'd not injure the
               Prince, he being fled to-an-Army that wou'd stand by him, against any Injuries that
               shou'd assault him. However, <pb n="69"/>this last Thought of <hi>Imoinda</hi>'s
               being ravish'd, chang'd the Measures of his Revenge; and whereas before he design'd
               to be himself her Executioner, he now resolv'd she shou'd not die. But as it is the
               greatest Crime in nature amongst 'em to touch a Woman, after having been possess'd by
               a Son, a Father, or a Brother; so now he look'd on <hi>Imoinda</hi> as a polluted
               thing, wholly unfit for his Embrace; nor wou'd he resign her to his Grand-son,
               because she had receiv'd the <hi>Royal Veil.</hi> He therefore removes her from the
                  <hi>Otan,</hi> with <hi>Onahal;</hi> whom he put into safe Hands, with Order they
               shou'd be both sold off, as Slaves, to another Country, either <hi>Christian,</hi> or
                  <hi>Heathen;</hi> 'twas no matter where.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70"/> This cruel Sentence, worse than Death, they implor'd, might be revers'd;
               but their Prayers were vain, and it was put in Execution accordingly, and that with
               so much Secrecy, that none, either without, or within the <hi>Otan,</hi> knew any
               thing of their Absence, or their Destiny.</p>
            <p>The old King, nevertheless, executed this with a great deal of Reluctancy; but he
               believ'd he had made a very great Conquest over himself, when he had once resolv'd,
               and had perform'd what he resolv'd. He believ'd now, that his Love had been unjust;
               and that he cou'd not expect the Gods, or <ref target="#n024" xml:id="a024"
                     >Captain of the Clouds</ref> , (as they call the unknown Power) shou'd
               suffer a better Consequence from so ill a Cause. He now begins to hold
                  <hi>Oroonoko</hi> excus'd; and <pb n="71"/>to say, he had Reason for what he did:
               And now every Body cou'd assure the King, how passionately <hi>Imoinda</hi> was
               belov'd by the Prince; even those confess'd it now, who said the contrary before his
               Flame was abated. So that the King being old, and not able to defend himself in War,
               and having no Sons of all his Race remaining alive, but only this, to maintain him on
               his Throne; and looking on this as a Man disoblig'd, first by the Rape of his
               Mistress, or rather, Wife; and now by depriving of him wholly of her, he fear'd,
               might make him desperate, and do some cruel thing, either to himself, or his old
               Grand-father, the Offender; he began to repent him extreamly of the Contempt he had,
               in his Rage, put on <hi>Imoinda.</hi> Besides, he consider'd he ought in<pb n="72"/>
               Honour to have kill'd her, for this Offence, if it had been one: He ought to have had
               so much Value and Consideration for a Maid of her Quality, as to have nobly put her
               to death; and not to have sold her like a common Slave, the greatest Revenge, and the
               most disgraceful of any; and to which they a thousand times prefer Death, and implore
               it; as <hi>Imoinda</hi> did, but cou'd not obtain that Honour. Seeing therefore it
               was certain that <hi>Oroonoko</hi> wou'd highly resent this Affront, he thought good
               to make some Excuse for his Rashness to him; and to that End he sent a Messenger to
               the Camp, with Orders to treat with him about the Master, to gain his Pardon, and to
               endeavour to mitigate his Grief; but that by no means he shou'd tell him, she was
               sold, but secretly put to death; <pb n="73"/> for he knew he shou'd. never obtain his
               Pardon for the other.</p>
            <p>When the Messenger came, he found the Prince upon the point of Engaging with the
               Enemy; but as soon as he heard of the Arrival of the Messenger, he commanded him to
               his Tent, where he embrac'd him, and receiv'd him with Joy; which was soon abated, by
               the down-cast Looks of the Messenger, who was instantly demanded the Cause by
                  <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> who, impatient of Delay, ask'd a thousand Questions in a
               Breath; and all concerning <hi>Imoinda:</hi> But there needed little Return, for he
               cou'd almost answer himself of all he demanded, from his Sighs and Eyes. At last, the
               Messenger casting himself at the Prince's Feet, and kissing them, with all the
               Submission of a Man that had something to implore<pb n="74"/> which he dreaded to
               utter, he besought him to hear with Calmness what he had to deliver to him, and to
               call up all his noble and Heroick Courage, to encounter with his Words, and defend
               himself against the ungrateful things he must relate. <hi>Oroonoko</hi> reply'd, with
               a deep Sigh, and a languishing Voice,—<hi>I am arm'd against their worst Efforts—;
                  for I know they will tell me,</hi> Imoinda <hi>is no more—; and after that, you
                  may spare the rest.</hi> Then, commanding him to rise, he laid himself on a
               Carpet, under a rich Pavillion, and remain'd a good while silent, and was hardly
               heard to sigh. When he was come a little to himself, the Messenger ask'd him leave to
               deliver that part of his Embassy, which the Prince had not yet devin'd: And the
               Prince cry'd, <hi>I permit thee—</hi>Then he told him the Affliction <pb n="75"/> the
               old King was in, for the Rashness he had committed in his Cruelty to
                  <hi>Imoinda;</hi> and how he daign'd to ask Pardon for his Offence, and to implore
               the Prince wou'd not suffer that Loss to touch his Heart too sensibly, which now all
               the Gods cou'd not restore him, but might recompence him in Glory, which he begg'd he
               wou'd pursue; and that Death, that common Revenger of all Injuries, wou'd soon even
               the Account between him, and a feeble old Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko</hi> bad him return his Duty to his Lord and Master; and to assure him,
               there was no Account of Revenge to be adjusted between them; if there were, 'twas he
               was the Agressor, and that Death wou'd be just, and, <ref target="#n025"
                     xml:id="a025">maugre</ref> his Age, wou'd see him righted; and he was
               contented to leave his Share of <pb n="76"/>Glory to Youths more fortunate, and
               worthy of that Favour from the Gods. That henceforth he wou'd never lift a Weapon, or
               draw a Bow; but abandon the small Remains of his Life to Sighs and Tears, and the
               continual Thoughts of what his Lord and Grand-father had thought good to send out of
               the World, with all that Youth, that Innocence, and Beauty.</p>
            <p>After having spoken this, whatever his greatest Officers, and Men of the best Rank
               could do, they cou'd not raise him from the Carpet, or perswade him to Action, and
               Resolutions of Life; but commanding all to retire, he shut himself into his Pavillion
               all that Day, while the Enemy was ready to engage; and wondring at the Delay, the
               whole Body of the chief<pb n="77"/>of the Army then address'd themselves to him, and
               to whom they had much a-do to get Admittance. They fell on their Faces at the Foot of
               his Carpet; where they lay, and besought him with earnest Prayers and Tears, to lead
               'em forth to Battel, and not let the Enemy take Advantages of them; and implor'd him
               to have regard to his Glory, and to the World, that depended on his Courage and
               Conduct. But he made no other Reply to all their Supplications but this, That he had
               now no more Business for Glory; and for the World, it was a Trifle not worth his
               Care. <hi>Go,</hi> (continu'd he, sighing) <hi>and divide it amongst you; and reap
                  with Joy what you so vainly prize, and leave me to my more welcome Destiny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They then demanded what they shou'd do, and whom he <pb n="78"/> wou'd constitute in
               his Room, that the Confusion of ambitious Youth and Power might not ruin their Order,
               and make them a Prey to the Enemy. He reply'd, He wou'd not give himself the
               Trouble—; but wish'd 'em to chuse the bravest Man amongst 'em, let his Quality or
               Birth be what it wou'd: <hi>For, O my Friends</hi> (said he!) <hi>it is not Titles
                  make Men brave, or good; or Birth that bestows Courage and Generosity, or makes
                  the Owner happy. Believe this, when you behold</hi> Oroonoko, <hi>the most
                  wretched, and abandon'd by Fortune, of all the Creation of the Gods.</hi> So
               turning himself about, he wou'd make no more Reply to all they cou'd urge or
               implore.</p>
            <p>The Army beholding their Officers return unsuccessful, with sad Faces, and ominous
               Looks, that <pb n="79"/> presag'd no good Luck, suffer'd a thousand Fears to take
               Possession of their Hearts, and the Enemy to come even upon 'em, before they wou'd
               provide for their Safety, by any Defence; and though they were assur'd by some, who
               had a mind to animate 'em, that they shou'd be immediately headed by the Prince, and
               that in the mean time <hi>Aboan</hi> had Orders to command as General; yet they were
               so dismay'd for want of that great Example of Bravery, that they cou'd make but a
               very feeble Resistance; and at last, down-right, fled before the Enemy, who pursu'd
               'em to the very Tents, killing 'em: Nor cou'd all <hi>Aboan</hi>'s Courage, which
               that Day gain'd him immortal Glory, shame 'em into a Manly Defence of themselves. The
               Guards that were left behind, <pb n="80"/>about the Prince's Tent, seeing the
               Soldiers flee before the Enemy, and scatter themselves all over the Plain, in great
               Disorder, made such Out-cries as rouz'd the Prince from his amorous Slumber, in which
               he had remain'd bury'd for two Days, without permitting any Sustenance to approach
               him: But, in spight of all his Resolutions, he had not the Constancy of Grief to that
               Degree, as to make him insensible of the Danger of his Army; and in that Instant he
               leap'd from his Couch, and cry'd,—<hi>Come, if we must die, let us meet Death the
                  noblest Way; and 'twill be more like</hi> Oroonoko <hi>to encounter him at an
                  Army's Head, opposing the Torrent of a conquering Foe, than lazily, on a Couch, to
                  wait his lingering Pleasure, and die every Moment by a thousand wrecking Thought;
                  or be tamely taken by an</hi>
               <pb n="81"/><hi>Enemy, and led a whining, Love-sick Slave, to adorn the Triumphs
                  of</hi> Jamoan, <hi>that young Victor, who already is enter'd beyond the Limits I
                  had prescrib d him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While he was speaking, he suffer'd his People to dress him for the Field; and
               sallying out of his Pavillion, with more Life and Vigour in his Countenance than ever
               he shew'd, he appear'd like some Divine Power descended to save his Country from
               Destruction; and his People had purposely put him on all things that might make him
               shine with most Splendor, to strike a reverend Awe into the Beholders. He flew into
               the thickest of those that were pursuing his Men; and being animated with Despair, he
               fought as if he came on purpose to die, and did such things as will not be believ'd
               that Humane <pb n="82"/> Strength cou'd perform; and such as soon inspir'd all the
               rest with new Courage, and new Order: And now it was, that they began to fight
               indeed; and so, as if they wou'd not be out-done, even by their ador'd <hi>Hero;</hi>
               who turning the Tide of the Victory, changing absolutely the Fate of the Day, gain'd
               an entire Conquest; and <hi>Oroonoko</hi> having the good Fortune to single out
                  <hi>Jamoan,</hi> he took him Prisoner with his own Hand, having wounded him almost
               to death.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Jamoan</hi> afterwards became very dear to him, being a Man very gallant,
               and of excellent Graces, and fine Parts; so that he never put him amongst the Rank of
               Captives, as they us'd to do, without distinction, for the common Sale, or Market;
               but kept him<pb n="83"/> in his own Court, where he retain'd nothing of the Prisoner,
               but the Name, and return'd no more into his own Country, so great an Affection he
               took for <hi>Oroonoko;</hi> and by a thousand Tales and Adventures of Love and
               Gallantry, flatter'd his Disease of Melancholy and Languishment; which I have often
               heard him say, had certainly kill'd him, but for the Conversation of this Prince and
                  <hi>Aboan,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Governor he had from his Childhood, of whom I
               have spoken before, and who was a Man of admirable Wit, great Ingenuity and Learning;
               all which he had infus'd into his young Pupil. This <hi>French-</hi>Man was banish'd
               out of his own Country, for some Heretical Notions he held; and though he was a Man
               of very little Religion, he <pb n="84"/> had admirable Morals, and a brave Soul.</p>
            <p>After the total Defeat of <hi>Jamoan</hi>'s Army, which all fled, or were left dead
               upon the Place, they spent some time in the Camp; <hi>Oroonoko</hi> chusing rather to
               remain a while there in his Tents, than enter into a Place, or live in a Court where
               he had so lately suffer d so great a Loss. The Officers therefore, who saw and knew
               his Cause of Discontent, invented all sorts of Diversions and Sports, to entertain
               their Prince: So that what with those Amuzements abroad, and others at home, that is,
               within their Tents, with the Perswasions, Arguments and Care of his Friends and
               Servants that he more peculiarly priz'd, he wore off in time a great part of that
                     <ref target="#n026" xml:id="a026">Shagrien</ref>, and Torture of
                  Despair,<pb n="85"/> which the first Efforts of <hi>Imoinda</hi>'s Death had given
               him: Insomuch as having receiv'd a thousand kind Embassies from the King, and
               Invitations to return to Court, he obey'd, though with no little Reluctancy; and when
               he did so, there was a visible Change in him, and for a long time he was much more
               melancholy than before. But Time lessens all Extreams, and reduces 'em to
                  <hi>Mediums</hi> and Unconcern; but no Motives or Beauties, though all endeavour'd
               it, cou'd engage him in any sort of Amour, though he had all the Invitations to it,
               both from his own Youth, and others Ambitions and Designs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was no sooner return'd from this last Conquest, and receiv'd at
               Court with all the Joy <pb n="86"/> and Magnificence that cou'd be express'd to a
               young Victor, who was not only return'd triumphant, but belov'd like a Deity, when
               there arriv'd in the Port an <hi>English</hi> Ship.</p>
            <p><ref target="#n027" xml:id="a027">This Person</ref> had often before been in
               these Countries, and was very well known to <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> with whom he had
               traffick'd for Slaves, and had us'd to do the same with his Predecessors.</p>
            <p>This Commander was a Man of a finer sort of Address, and Conversation, better bred,
               and more engaging, than most of that sort of Men are; so that he seem'd rather never
               to have been bred out of a Court, than almost all his Life at Sea. This Captain
               therefore was always better receiv'd at Court, than most of the Traders to those
               Countries were; and <pb n="87"/>especially by <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> who was more
               civiliz'd, according to the <hi>European</hi> Mode, than any other had been, and took
               more Delight in the <hi>White</hi> Nations; and, above all, Men of Parts and Wit. To
               this Captain he sold abundance of his Slaves; and for the Favour and Esteem he had
               for him, made him many Presents, and oblig'd him to stay at Court as long as possibly
               he cou'd. Which the Captain seem'd to take as a very great Honour done him,
               entertaining the Prince every Day with Globes and Maps, and Mathematical Discourses
               and Instruments; eating, drinking, hunting and living with him with so much
               Familiarity, that it was not to be doubted, but he had gain'd very greatly upon the
               Heart of this gallant young Man. And the Captain,<pb n="88"/>in Return of all these
               mighty Favours, besought the Prince to honour his Vessel with his Presence, some Day
               or other, to Dinner, before he shou'd set Sail; which he condescended to accept, and
               appointed his Day. The Captain, on his part, fail'd not to have all things in a
               Readiness, in the most magnificent Order he cou'd possibly: And the Day being come,
               the Captain, in his Boat, richly adorn'd with Carpets and Velvet-Cushions, row'd to
               the Shoar to receive the Prince; with another Long-Boat, where was plac'd all his
               Musick and Trumpets, with which <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was extreamly delighted; who met
               him on the Shoar, attended by his <hi>French</hi> Governor, <hi>Jamoan, Aboan,</hi>
               and about an hundred of the noblest of the Youths of the<pb n="89"/>Court: And after
               they had first carry'd the Prince on Board, the Boats fetch'd the rest off; where
               they found a very splendid Treat, with all sorts of fine Wines; and were as well
               entertain'd, as 'twas possible in such a place to be.</p>
            <p>The Prince having drunk hard of Punch, and several Sorts of Wine, as did all the rest
               (for great Care was taken, they shou'd want nothing of that part of the
               Entertainment) was very merry, and in great Admiration of the Ship, for he had never
               been in one before; so that he was curious of beholding every place, where he
               decently might descend. The rest, no less curious, who were not quite overcome with
               Drinking, rambl'd at their pleasure <hi>Fore</hi> and <hi>Aft,</hi> as their Fancies
               guided 'em: So that the Captain, who had<pb n="90"/> well laid his Design before,
               gave the Word, and seiz'd on all his Guests; they clapping great Irons suddenly on
               the Prince, when he was leap'd down in the Hold, to view that part of the Vessel; and
               locking him fast down, secur'd him. The same Treachery was us'd to all the rest; and
               all in one Instant, in several places of the Ship, were lash'd fast in Irons, and
               betray'd to Slavery. That great Design over, they set all Hands to work to hoise
               Sail; and with as treacherous and fair a Wind, they made from the Shoar with this
               innocent and glorious Prize, who thought of nothing less than such an
               Entertainment.</p>
            <p>Some have commended this Act, as brave, in the Captain; but I will spare my Sence of
               it, and leave it to my Reader, to judge as he pleases.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91"/> It may be easily guess'd, in what manner the Prince resented this
               Indignity, who may be best resembl'd to a Lion taken in a Toil; so he rag'd, so he
               struggl'd for Liberty, but all in vain; and they had so wisely manag'd his Fetters,
               that he cou'd not use a Hand in his Defence, to quit himself of a Life that wou'd by
               no Means endure Slavery; nor cou'd he move from the Place, where he was ty'd, to any
               solid part of the Ship, against which he might have beat his Head, and have finish'd
               his Disgrace that way: So that being deprived of all other means, he resolved to
               perish for want of Food: And pleased at last with that Thought, and toil'd and tired
               by Rage and Indignation, he laid himself down, and sullenly resolved upon dying,<pb
                  n="92"/> and refused all things that were brought him.</p>
            <p>This did not a little vex the Captain, and the more so, because, he found almost all
               of 'em of the same Humour; so that the loss of so many brave Slaves, so tall and
               goodly to behold, wou'd have been very considerable: He therefore order'd one to go
               from him (for he wou'd not be seen himself) to <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> and to assure him
               he was afflicted for having rashly done so unhospitable a Deed, and which cou'd not
               be now remedied, since they were far from shore; but since he resented it in so high
               a nature, he assur'd him he wou'd revoke his Resolution, and set both him and his
               Friends a-shore on the next Land they shou'd touch at; and of this the Messenger gave
                  <pb n="93"/> him his Oath, provided he wou'd resolve to live: And
                  <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> whose Honour was such as he never had violated a Word in his
               Life himself, much less a solemn Asseveration; believ'd in an instant what this Man
               said, but reply'd, He expected for a Confirmation of this, to have his shameful
               Fetters dismiss'd. This Demand was carried to the <hi>Captain,</hi> who return'd him
               answer, That the Offence had been so great which he had put upon the Prince, that he
               durst not trust him with Liberty while he remained in the Ship, for fear lest by a
               Valour natural to him, and a Revenge that would animate that Valour, he might commit
               some Outrage fatal to himself and the <hi>King</hi> his Master, to whom his Vessel
               did belong. To this <hi>Oroonoko</hi> replied,<pb n="94"/> he would engage his Honour
               to behave himself in all friendly Order and Manner, and obey the Command of the
                  <hi>Captain,</hi> as he was Lord of the <hi>King</hi>'s Vessel, and General of
               those Men under his Command.</p>
            <p>This was deliver'd to the still doubting <hi>Captain,</hi> who could not resolve to
               trust a <hi>Heathen</hi> he said, upon his <ref target="#n028" xml:id="a028"
                     >Parole</ref>, a Man that had no sence or notion of the God that he
               Worshipp'd. <hi>Oroonoko</hi> then replied, He was very sorry to hear that the
                  <hi>Captain</hi> pretended to the Knowledge and Worship of any <hi>Gods,</hi> who
               had taught him no better Principles, than not to Credit as he would be Credited: but
               they told him the Difference of their Faith occasion'd that Distrust: For the
                  <hi>Captain</hi> had protested to him upon the Word of a <hi>Christian,</hi><pb
                  n="95"/> and sworn in the Name of a Great <hi>GOD;</hi> which if he shou'd
               violate, he would expect eternal Torment in the World to come. <hi>Is that all the
                  Obligation he has to be Just to his Oath,</hi> replied <hi>Oroonoko? Let him know
                  I Swear by my Honour, which to violate, wou'd not only render me contemptible and
                  despised by all brave and honest Men, and so give my self perpetual pain, but it
                  wou'd be eternally offending and diseasing all Mankind, harming, betraying,
                  circumventing and outraging all Men; but Punishments hereafter are suffer'd by
                  ones self; and the World takes no cognizances whether this</hi> God <hi>have
                  revenged em, or not, tis done so secretly, and deferr'd so long: While the Man of
                  no Honour, suffers every moment the scorn and contempt of the honester World, and
                  dies every day ignominiously in his Fame, which</hi><pb n="96"/>
               <hi>is more valuable than Life: I speak not this to move Belief, but to shew you how
                  you mistake, when you imagine, That he who will violate his Honour, will keep his
                  Word with his</hi> Gods. So turning from him with a disdainful smile, he refused
               to answer him, when he urg'd him to know what Answer he shou'd carry back to his
                  <hi>Captain;</hi> so that he departed without saying any more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Captain</hi> pondering and consulting what to do, it was concluded that
               nothing but <hi>Oroonoko</hi>'s Liberty wou'd encourage any of the rest to eat,
               except the <hi>French-</hi>man, whom the <hi>Captain</hi> cou'd not pretend to keep
               Prisoner, but only told him he was secured because he might act something in favour
               of the Prince, but that he shou'd be freed as soon <pb n="97"/> as they came to Land.
               So that they concluded it wholly necessary to free the Prince from his Irons, that he
               might show himself to the rest; that they might have an Eye upon him, and that they
               cou'd not fear a single Man.</p>
            <p>This being resolv'd, to make the Obligation the greater, the Captain himself went to
                  <hi>Oroonoko;</hi> where, after many Complements, and Assurances of what he had
               already promis'd, he receiving from the Prince his <hi>Parole,</hi> and his Hand, for
               his good Behaviour, dismiss'd his Irons, and brought him to his own Cabin; where,
               after having treated and repos'd him a while, for he had neither eat nor slept in
               four Days before, he besought him to visit those obstinate People in Chains, who
               refus'd all manner <pb n="98"/> of Sustenance; and intreated him to oblige 'em to
               eat, and assure 'em of their Liberty the first Opportunity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> who was too generous, not to give Credit to his Words, shew'd
               himself to his People, who were transported with Excess of Joy at the sight of their
               Darling Prince; falling at his Feet, and kissing and embracing 'em; believing, as
               some Divine Oracle, all he assur'd 'em. But he besought 'em to bear their Chains with
               that Bravery that became those whom he had seen act so nobly in Arms; and that they
               cou'd not give him greater Proofs of their Love and Friendship, since 'twas all the
               Security the Captain (his Friend) cou'd have, against the Revenge, he said, they
               might possibly justly take, for the <pb n="99"/> Injuries sustain'd by him. And they
               all, with one Accord, assur'd him, they cou'd not suffer enough, when it was for his
               Repose and Safety.</p>
            <p>After this they no longer refus'd to eat, but took what was brought 'em, and were
               pleas'd with their Captivity, since by it they hop'd to redeem the Prince, who, all
               the rest of the Voyage, was treated with all the Respect due to his Birth, though
               nothing cou'd divert his Melancholy; and he wou'd often sigh for <hi>Imoinda,</hi>
               and think this a Punishment due to his Misfortune, in having left that noble Maid
               behind him, that fatal Night, in the <hi>Otan,</hi> when he fled to the Camp.</p>
            <p>Possess'd with a thousand Thoughts of past Joys with this fair young Person, and a
               thousand <pb n="100"/> Griefs for her eternal Loss, he endur'd a tedious Voyage, and
               at last arriv'd at the Mouth of the River of <hi>Surinam,</hi> a Colony belonging to
               the King of <hi>England,</hi> and where they were to deliver some part of their
               Slaves. There the Merchants and Gentlemen of the Country going on Board, to demand
               those Lots of Slaves they had already agreed on; and, amongst those, the Over-seers
               of those Plantations where I then chanc'd to be, the Captain, who had given the Word,
               order'd his Men to bring up those noble Slaves in Fetters, whom I have spoken of; and
               having put 'em, some in one, and some in other Lots, with Women and Children (which
               they call <ref target="#n029" xml:id="a029">Pickaninies</ref>,) they sold
               'em off, as Slaves, to several Merchants and Gentlemen; not <pb n="101"/>putting any
               two in one Lot, because they wou'd separate 'em far from each other; not daring to
               trust 'em together, lest Rage and Courage shou'd put 'em upon contriving some great
               Action, to the Ruin of the Colony.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was first seiz'd on, and sold to our Over-seer, who had the first
               Lot, with seventeen more of all sorts and sizes; but not one of Quality with him.
               When he saw this, he found what they meant; for, as I said, he understood
                  <hi>English</hi> pretty well; and being wholly unarm'd and defenceless, so as it
               was in vain to make any Resistance, he only beheld the Captain with a Look all fierce
               and disdainful, upbraiding him with Eyes, that forc'd Blushes on his guilty Cheeks,
               he only cry'd, in passing over the Side of the Ship, <pb n="102"/><hi>Farewel, Sir:
                  'Tis worth my Suffering, to gain so true a Knowledge both of you, and of your Gods
                  by whom you swear.</hi> And desiring those that held him to forbear their pains,
               and telling 'em he wou'd make no Resistance, he cry'd, <hi>Come, my Fellow-Slaves;
                  let as descend, and see if we can meet with more Honour and Honesty in the next
                  World we shall touch upon.</hi> So he nimbly leap'd into the Boat, and shewing no
               more Concern, suffer'd himself to be row'd up the River, with his seventeen
               Companions.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman that bought him was a young <hi>Cornish</hi> Gentleman, whose Name was
                  <hi>Trefry;</hi> a Man of great Wit, and fine Learning, and was carry'd into those
               Parts by the <ref target="#n030" xml:id="a030">Lord—Governor</ref>, to
               manage all his Affairs. He reflecting on the last Words of <hi>Oroonoko</hi> to the
                  <pb n="103"/>Captain, and beholding the Richness of his <ref target="#n031"
                     xml:id="a031">Vest</ref>, no sooner came into the Boat, but he fix'd his
               Eyes on him; and finding something so extraordinary in his Face, his Shape and Mien,
               a Greatness of Look, and Haughtiness in his Air, and finding he spoke
                  <hi>English,</hi> had a great mind to be enquiring into his Quality and Fortune;
               which, though <hi>Oroonoko</hi> endeavour'd to hide, by only confessing he was above
               the Rank of common Slaves, <hi>Trefry</hi> soon found he was yet something greater
               than he confess'd; and from that Moment began to conceive so vast an Esteem for him,
               that he ever after lov'd him as his dearest Brother, and shew'd him all the
               Civilities due to so great a Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trefry</hi> was a very good Mathematician, and a Linguist; cou'd<pb n="104"/>
               speak <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spanish;</hi> and in the three Days they remain'd in
               the Boat (for so long were they going from the Ship, to the Plantation) he
               entertain'd <hi>Oroonoko</hi> so agreeably with his Art and Discourse, that he was no
               less pleas'd with <hi>Trefry,</hi> than he was with the Prince; and he thought
               himself, at least, fortunate in this, that since he was a Slave, as long as he wou'd
               suffer himself to remain so, he had a Man of so excellent Wit and Parts for a Master:
               So that before they had finish'd their Voyage up the River, he made no scruple of
               declaring to <hi>Trefry</hi> all his Fortunes, and most part of what I have here
               related, and put himself wholly into the Hands of his new Friend, whom he found
               resenting all the Injuries were done him, and was charm'd with all the Greatnesses of
               his Actions; <pb n="105"/>which were recited with that Modesty, and delicate Sence,
               as wholly vanquish'd him, and subdu'd him to his Interest. And he promis'd him on his
               Word and Honour, he wou'd find the Means to re-conduct him to his own Country again:
               assuring him, he had a perfect Abhorrence of so dishonourable an Action; and that he
               wou'd sooner have dy'd, than have been the Author of such a Perfidy. He found the
               Prince was very much concern'd to know what became of his Friends, and how they took
               their Slavery; and <hi>Trefry</hi> promis'd to take care about the enquiring after
               their Condition, and that he shou'd have an Account of 'em.</p>
            <p>Though, as <hi>Oroonoko</hi> afterwards said, he had little Reason to credit the
               Words of a <ref target="#n032" xml:id="a032">Backearary</ref>, yet he knew
               not why; but he saw a kind<pb n="106"/> of Sincerity, and awful Truth in the Face of
                  <hi>Trefry;</hi> he saw an Honesty in his Eyes, and he found him wise and witty
               enough to understand Honour; for it was one of his Maxims, <hi>A Man of Wit cou'd not
                  be a Knave or Villain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In their passage up the <ref target="#n033" xml:id="a033">River</ref>, they
               put in at several Houses for Refreshment; and ever when they landed, numbers of
               People wou'd flock to behold this Man; not but their Eyes were daily entertain'd with
               the sight of Slaves, but the Fame of <hi>Oroonoko</hi> was gone before him, and all
               People were in Admiration of his Beauty. Besides, he had a rich Habit on, in which he
               was taken, so different from the rest, and which the Captain cou'd not strip him of,
               because he was forc'd to surprize his Person in the Minute he sold him. When he found
                  his<pb n="107"/> Habit made him liable, as he thought, to be gaz'd at the more, he
               begg'd <hi>Trefry</hi> to give him something more befitting a Slave; which he did,
               and took off his Robes. Nevertheless, he shone through all; and his <ref
                     target="#n034" xml:id="a034">Osenbrigs</ref> (a sort of brown
                  <hi>Holland</hi> Suit he had on) cou'd not conceal the Graces of his Looks and
               Mien; and he had no less Admirers, than when he had his dazeling Habit on: The Royal
               Youth appear'd in spight of the Slave, and People cou'd not help treating him after a
               different manner, without designing it: As soon as they approach'd him, they
               venerated and esteem'd him; his Eyes insensibly commanded Respect, and his Behaviour
               insinuated it into every Soul. So that there was nothing talk'd of but this young and
               gallant Slave, even by those who yet knew not that he was a Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108"/> I ought to tell you, that the <hi>Christians</hi> never buy any Slaves
               but they give 'em some Name of their own, their native ones being likely very
               barbarous, and hard to pronounce; so that Mr. <hi>Trefry</hi> gave <hi>Oroonoko</hi>
               that of <ref target="#n035" xml:id="a035">Caesar;</ref> which Name will live
               in that Country as long as that (scarce more) glorious one of the great
                  <hi>Roman;</hi> for 'tis most evident, he wanted no part of the Personal Courage
               of that <hi>Caesar,</hi> and acted things as memorable, had they been done in some
               part of the World replenish'd with People, and Historians, that might have given him
               his due. But his Misfortune was, to fall in an obscure World, that afforded only a
               Female Pen to celebrate his Fame; though I doubt not but it had liv'd from others
               Endeavours, if the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who, immediately after his <pb n="109"/>Time, took
               that <ref target="#n036" xml:id="a036">Country</ref>, had not kill'd,
               banish'd and dispers'd all those that were capable of giving the World this great
               Man's Life, much better than I have done. And Mr. <hi>Trefry,</hi> who design'd it,
               dy'd before he began it; and bemoan'd himself for not having undertook it in
               time.</p>
            <p>For the future therefore, I must call <hi>Oroonoko, Caesar,</hi> since by that Name
               only he was known in our Western World, and by that Name he was receiv'd on Shoar at
                  <ref target="#n037" xml:id="a037">Parham-House</ref>, where he was destin'd a
               Slave. But if the King himself (God bless him) had come a-shore, there cou'd not have
               been greater Expectations by all the whole Plantation, and those neighbouring ones,
               than was on ours at that time; and he was receiv'd more like a Governor, than <pb
                  n="110"/> a Slave. Notwithstanding, as the Custom was, they assign'd him his
               Portion of Land, his House, and his Business, up in the Plantation. But as it was
               more for Form, than any Design, to put him to his Task, he endur'd no more of the
               Slave but the Name, and remain'd some Days in the House, receiving all Visits that
               were made him, without stirring towards that part of the Plantation where the
                  <hi>Negroes</hi> were.</p>
            <p>At last, he wou'd needs go view his Land, his House, and the Business assign'd him.
               But he no sooner came to the Houses of the Slaves, which are like a little Town by it
               self, the <hi>Negroes</hi> all having left Work, but they all came forth to behold
               him, and found he was that Prince who had, at several times, sold most of 'em to
               these <pb n="111"/> Parts; and, from a Veneration they pay to great Men, especially
               if they know 'em, and from the Surprize and Awe they had at the sight of him, they
               all cast themselves at his Feet, crying out, in their Language, <hi>Live, O King!
                  Long live, O King!</hi> And kissing his Feet, paid him even Divine Homage.</p>
            <p>Several <hi>English</hi> Gentlemen were with him; and what Mr. <hi>Trefry</hi> had
               told 'em, was here confirm'd; of which he himself before had no other Witness than
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> himself: But he was infinitely glad to find his Grandure confirm'd
               by the Adoration of all the Slaves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caesar</hi> troubl'd with their Over-Joy, and Over-Ceremony, besought 'em to
               rise, and to receive him as their Fellow-Slave; assuring them, he was no better. At
               which <pb n="112"/> they set up with one Accord a most terrible and hidious Mourning
               and condoling, which he and the <hi>English</hi> had much a-do to appease; but at
               last they prevail'd with 'em, and they prepar'd all their barbarous Musick, and every
               one kill'd and dress'd something of his own Stock (for every Family has their Land
               apart, on which, at their leisuretimes, they breed all eatable things;) and clubbing
               it together, made a most magnificent Supper, inviting their <ref target="#n038"
                  xml:id="a038">Grandee</ref> Captain, their <hi>Prince,</hi> to honour it with his
               Presence; which he did, and several <hi>English</hi> with him; where they all waited
               on him, some playing, others dancing before him all the time, according to the
               Manners of their several Nations; and with unwearied Industry, endeavouring to please
               and delight him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb id="a039" xml:id="a039" n="129"/> While they sat at Meat Mr. <hi>Trefry</hi>
               told <hi>Caesar,</hi> that most of these young <hi>Slaves</hi> were undon in Love,
               with a fine she <hi>Slave,</hi> whom they had had about Six Months on their Land; the
                  <hi>Prince,</hi> who never heard the Name of <hi>Love</hi> without a Sigh, nor any
               mention of it without the Curiosity of examining further into that tale, which of all
               Discourses was most agreeable to him, asked, how they came to be so Unhappy, as to be
               all Undon for one fair <hi>Slave? Trefry,</hi> who was naturally Amorous, and lov'd
               to talk of Love as well as any body, proceeded to tell him, they had the most
               charming Black that ever was beheld on their <hi>Plantation,</hi> about Fifteen or
               Sixteen Years old, as he guest; that, for his part, he had done nothing but Sigh for
               her <pb n="130"/>ever since she came; and that all the white Beautys he had seen,
               never charm'd him so absolutely as this fine Creature had done; and that no Man, of
               any Nation, ever beheld her, that did not fall in Love with her; and that she had all
               the <hi>Slaves</hi> perpetually at her Feet; and the whole Country resounded with the
               Fame of <hi>Clemene,</hi> for so, said he, we have Christ'ned her: But she denys us
               all with such a noble Disdain, that 'tis a Miracle to see, that she, who can give
               such eternal Desires, shou'd herself be all Ice, and all Unconcern. She is adorn'd
               with the most Graceful Modesty that ever beautifyed Youth; the softest Sigher—that,
               if she were capable of Love, one would swear she languish'd for some absent happy
               Man; and<pb n="131"/> so retir'd, as if she fear'd a Rape even from the God of Day;
               or that the Breezes would steal Kisses from her delicate Mouth. Her Task of Work some
               sighing Lover every day makes it his Petition to perform for her, which she excepts
               blushing, and with reluctancy, for fear he will ask her a Look for a Recompence,
               which he dares not presume to hope; so great an Awe she strikes into the Hearts of
               her Admirers. <hi>I do not wonder,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>that</hi> Clemene
                  <hi>shou'd refuse Slaves, being as you say so Beautiful, but wonder how she
                  escapes those who can entertain her as you can do; or why, being your Slave, you
                  do not oblige her to yield. I confess,</hi> said <hi>Trefry, when I have, against
                  her will, entertain'd her with Love so long, as to be transported</hi><pb n="132"/>
               <hi>with my Passion; even above Decency, I have been ready to make use of those
                  advantages of Strength and Force Nature has given me. But oh! she disarms me, with
                  that Modesty and Weeping so tender and so moving, that I retire, and thank my
                  Stars she overcame me.</hi> The Company laught at his Civility to a
                  <hi>Slave,</hi> and <hi>Caesar</hi> only applauded the nobleness of his Passion
               and Nature; since that Slave might be Noble, or, what was better, have true Notions
               of Honour and Vertue in her. Thus past they this Night, after having received, from
               the <hi>Slaves,</hi> all imaginable Respect and Obedience.</p>
            <p>The next Day <hi>Trefry</hi> ask'd <hi>Caesar</hi> to walk, when the heat was
               allay'd, and designedly carried him by the Cottage of the <hi>fair Slave;</hi> and
                  <pb n="133"/>told him, she whom he spoke of last Night liv'd there retir'd.
                  <hi>But,</hi> says he, <hi>I would not wish you to approach, for, I am sure, you
                  will be in Love as soon as you behold her. Caesar</hi> assur'd him, he was proof
               against all the Charms of that Sex; and that if he imagin'd his Heart cou'd be so
               perfidious to Love again, after <hi>Imoinda,</hi> he believ'd he shou'd tear it from
               his Bosom: They had no sooner spoke, but a little shock Dog, that <hi>Clemene</hi>
               had presented her, which she took great Delight in, ran out; and she, not knowing any
               body was there, ran to get it in again, and bolted out on those who were just
               Speaking of her: When seeing them, she wou'd have run in again; but <hi>Trefry</hi>
               caught her by the Hand, and cry'd, Clemene, <hi>however you</hi><pb n="134"/>
               <hi>fly a Lover, you ought to pay some Respect to this Stranger:</hi> (pointing to
                  <hi>Caesar)</hi> But she, as if she had resolv'd never to raise her Eyes to the
               Face of a Man again, bent 'em the more to the Earth, when he spoke, and gave the
                  <hi>Prince</hi> the Leasure to look the more at her. There needed no long Gazing,
               or Consideration, to examin who this fair Creature was; he soon saw <hi>Imoinda</hi>
               all over her; in a Minute he saw her Face, her Shape, her Air, her Modesty, and all
               that call'd forth his Soul with Joy at his Eyes, and left his Body destitute of
               almost Life; it stood without Motion, and, for a Minute, knew not that it had a
               Being; and, I believe, he had never come to himself, so opprest he was with over-Joy,
               if he had not met <pb n="135"/> with this Allay, that he perceiv'd <hi>Imoinda</hi>
               fall dead in the Hands of <hi>Trefry:</hi> this awaken'd him, and he ran to her aid,
               and caught her in his Arms, where, by degrees, she came to herself; and 'tis needless
               to tell with what transports, what extasies of Joy, they both a while beheld each
               other, without Speaking; then Snatcht each other to their Arms; then Gaze again, as
               if they still doubted whether they possess'd the Blessing: They Graspt, but when they
               recovered their Speech, 'tis not to be imagin'd, what tender things they exprest to
               each other; wondering what strange Fate had brought 'em again together. They soon
               inform'd each other of their Fortunes, and equally bewail'd their Fate; but, at the
                  same<pb n="136"/> time, they mutually protested, that even Fetters and Slavery
               were Soft and Easy; and wou'd be supported with Joy and Pleasure, while they cou'd be
               so happy to possess each other, and to be able to make good their Vows.
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> swore he disdain'd the Empire of the World, while he cou'd behold
               his <hi>Imoinda;</hi> and she despis'd Grandure and Pomp, those Vanities of her Sex,
               when she cou'd Gaze on <hi>Oroonoko.</hi> He ador'd the very Cottage where she
               resided, and said, That little Inch of the World wou'd give him more Happiness than
               all the Universe cou'd do; and she vow'd, It was a Pallace, while adorn'd with the
               Presence of <hi>Oroonoko.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trefry</hi> was infinitely pleas'd with this <ref target="#n040" xml:id="a040"
                  >Novel</ref><hi>Clemene</hi><pb n="137"/> was the Fair Mistress of whom
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> had before spoke; and was not a little satisfied, that Heaven was
               so kind to the <hi>Prince,</hi> as to sweeten his Misfortunes by so lucky an
               Accident; and leaving the Lovers to themselves, was impatient to come down to
                  <hi>Parham House,</hi> (which was on the same <hi>Plantation)</hi> to give me an
               Account of what had hapned. I was as impatient to make these Lovers a Visit, having
               already made a Friendship with <hi>Caesar;</hi> and from his own Mouth learn'd what I
               have related, which was confirmed by his French-man, who was set on Shore to seek his
               Fortunes; and of whom they cou'd not make a Slave, because a Christian; and he came
               daily to <hi>Parham Hill</hi> to see and pay his Respects<pb n="138"/> to his Purple
                  <hi>Prince:</hi> So that concerning and intresting my self, in all that related to
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> whom I had assur'd of Liberty, as soon as the Governor arriv'd, I
               hasted presently to the Place where the Lovers were, and was infinitely glad to find
               this Beautiful young <hi>Slave</hi> (who had already gain'd all our Esteems, for her
               Modesty and her extraordinary Prettyness) to be the same I had heard <hi>Caesar</hi>
               speak so much off. One may imagine then, we paid her a treble Respect; and though
               from her being carv'd in fine Flowers and Birds all over her Body, we took her to be
               of Quality before, yet, when we knew <hi>Clemene</hi> was <hi>Imoinda,</hi> we cou'd
               not enough admire her.</p>
            <p>I had forgot to tell you, that <pb n="139"/> those who are Nobly born of that
               Country, are so delicately <ref target="#n041" xml:id="a041">Cut and Rac'd</ref> all
               over the fore-part of the Trunk of their Bodies, that it looks as if it were <ref
                  target="#n042" xml:id="a042">Japan'd</ref>; the Works being raised like high
               Poynt round the Edges of the Flowers: Some are only Carv'd with a little Flower, or
               Bird, at the Sides of the Temples, as was <hi>Caesar;</hi> and those who are so
               Carv'd over the Body, resemble our Ancient <ref target="#n043" xml:id="a043"
                  >Picts,</ref> that are figur'd in the Chronicles, but these Carvings are more
               delicate.</p>
            <p>From that happy Day <hi>Caesar</hi> took <hi>Clemene</hi> for his Wife, to the
               general Joy of all People; and there was as much Magnificence as the Country wou'd
               afford at the Celebration of this Wedding: and in a very short time after she <pb
                  n="140"/>conceiv'd with Child; which made <hi>Caesar</hi> even adore her, knowing
               he was the last of his Great Race. This new Accident made him more Impatient of
               Liberty, and he was every Day treating with <hi>Trefry</hi> for his and
                  <hi>Clemene's</hi> Liberty; and offer'd either Gold, or a vast quantity of Slaves,
               which shou'd be paid before they let him go, provided he cou'd have any Security that
               he shou'd go when his Ransom was paid: They fed him from Day to Day with Promises,
               and delay'd him, till the Lord Governor shou'd come; so that he began to suspect them
               of falshood, and that they wou'd delay him till the time of his Wives delivery, and
               make a Slave of that too, For all the Breed is<pb n="141"/> theirs to whom the
               Parents belong: This Thought made him very uneasy, and his Sullenness gave them some
               Jealousies of him; so that I was oblig'd, by some Persons, who fear'd a Mutiny (which
               is very Fatal sometimes in those Colonies, that abound so with Slaves, that they
               exceed the Whites in vast Numbers) to discourse with <hi>Caesar,</hi> and to give him
               all the Satisfaction I possibly cou'd; they knew he and <hi>Clemene</hi> were scarce
               an Hour in a Day from my Lodgings; that they eat with me, and that I oblig'd 'em in
               all things I was capable of: I entertain'd him with the Lives of the Romans, and
               great Men, which charm'd him to my Company; and her, with teaching her all the pretty
               Works that I was Mistress <pb n="142"/>of; and telling her Stories of Nuns, and
               endeavoring to bring her to the knowledge of the true God. But of all Discourses
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> lik'd that the worst, and wou'd never be reconcil'd to our Notions
               of the Trinity, of which he ever made a Jest; it was a Riddle, he said, wou'd turn
               his Brain to conceive, and one cou'd not make him understand what Faith was. However,
               these Conversations fail'd not altogether so well to divert him, that he lik'd the
               Company of us Women much above the Men; for he cou'd not Drink; and he is but an ill
               Companion in that Country that cannot: So that obliging him to love us very well, we
               had all the Liberty of Speech with him, especially my self, whom he call'd <pb
                  n="143"/> his <hi>Great Mistress;</hi> and indeed my Word wou'd go a great way
               with him. For these Reasons, I had Opportunity to take notice to him, that he was not
               well pleasd of late, as he us'd to be; was more retir'd and thoughtful; and told him,
               I took it Ill he shou'd Suspect we wou'd break our Words with him, and not permit
               both him and <hi>Clemene</hi> to return to his own Kingdom, which was not so long a
               way, but when he was once on his Voyage he wou'd quickly arrive there. He made me
               some Answers that shew'd a doubt in him, which made me ask him, what advantage it
               wou'd be to doubt? it would but give us a Fear of him, and possibly compel us to
               treat him so as I shou'd be<pb n="144"/> very loath to behold: that is, it might
               occasion his Confinement. Perhaps this was not so Luckily spoke of me, for I
               perceiv'd he resented that Word, which I strove to Soften again in vain: However, he
               assur'd me, that whatsoever Resolutions he shou'd take, he wou'd Act nothing upon the
               White-People; and as for my self, and those upon that <hi>Plantation</hi> where he
               was, he wou'd sooner forfeit his eternal Liberty, and Life it self, than lift his
               Hand against his greatest Enemy on that Place: He besought me to suffer no Fears upon
               his Account, for he cou'd do nothing that Honour shou'd not dictate; but he accus'd
               himself for having suffer'd Slavery so long; yet he charg'd that weakness on Love
               alone, who<pb n="145"/> was capable of making him neglect even Glory it self; and,
               for which, now he reproches himself every moment of the Day. Much more to this effect
               he spoke, with an Air impatient enough to make me know he wou'd not be long in
               Bondage; and though he suffer'd only the Name of a Slave, and had nothing of the Toil
               and Labour of one, yet that was sufficient to render him Uneasy; and he had been too
               long Idle, who us'd to be always in Action, and in Arms: He had a Spirit all Rough
               and Fierce, and that cou'd not be tam'd to lazy Rest; and though all endeavors were
               us'd to exercise himself in such Actions and Sports as this World afforded, as
               Running, Wrastling, Pitching the Bar, Hunting and Fishing,<pb n="146"/> Chasing and
               Killing <hi>Tigers</hi> of a monstrous Size, which this Continent affords in
               abundance; and wonderful <hi>Snakes,</hi> such as <ref target="#n044" xml:id="a044"
                  >Alexander</ref> is reported to have incounter'd at the River of <hi>Amazons,</hi>
               and which <hi>Caesar</hi> took great Delight to overcome; yet these were not Actions
               great enough for his large Soul, which was still panting after more renown'd
               Action.</p>
            <p>Before I parted that Day with him, I got, with much ado, a Promise from him to rest
               yet a little longer with Patience, and wait the coming of the Lord Governor, who was
               every Day expected on our Shore; he assur'd me he wou'd, and this Promise he desired
               me to know was given perfectly in Complaisance to me,<pb n="147"/>in whom he had an
               intire Confidence.</p>
            <p>After this, I neither thought it convenient to trust him much out of our View, nor
               did the Country who fear'd him; but with one accord it was advis'd to treat him
               Fairly, and oblige him to remain within such a compass, and that he shou'd be
               permitted, as seldom as cou'd be, to go up to the Plantations of the Negroes; or, if
               he did, to be accompany'd by some that shou'd be rather in appearance Attendants than
               Spys. This Care was for some time taken, and <hi>Caesar</hi> look'd upon it as a Mark
               of extraordinary Respect, and was glad his discontent had oblig'd 'em to be more
               observant to him; he received new assurance from <pb n="148"/>the Overseer, which was
               confirmed to him by the Opinion of all the Gentlemen of the Country, who made their
               court to him: During this time that we had his Company more frequently than hitherto
               we had had, it may not be unpleasant to relate to you the Diversions we entertain'd
               him with, or rather he us.</p>
            <p>My stay was to be short in that Country, because my Father dy'd at Sea, and never
               arriv'd to possess the Honour was design'd him, (which was Lieutenant-General of Six
               and thirty Islands, besides the Continent of <hi>Surinam)</hi> nor the advantages he
               hop'd to reap by them; so that though we were oblig'd to continue on our Voyage, we
               did not <pb n="149"/>intend to stay upon the Place: Though, in a Word, I must say
               thus much of it, That certainly had his late Majesty, of sacred Memory, but seen and
               known what a vast and charming World he had been Master off in that Continent, he
               would never have parted so Easily with it to the <hi>Dutch.</hi> 'Tis a Continent
               whose vast Extent was never yet known, and may contain more Noble Earth than all the
               Universe besides; for, they say, it reaches from East to West; one Way as far as
                  <hi>China,</hi> and another to <hi>Peru:</hi> It affords all things both for
               Beauty and Use; 'tis there Eternal Spring, always the very Months of <hi>April,
                  May</hi> and <hi>June;</hi> the Shades are perpetual, the Trees, bearing at once
               all degrees of Leaves and Fruit,<pb n="150"/> from blooming Buds to ripe Autumn;
               Groves of Oranges, Limons, Citrons, Figs, Nutmegs, and noble Aromaticks, continually
               bearing their Fragrancies. The Trees appearing all like <ref target="#n045"
                  xml:id="a045">Nosegays</ref> adorn'd with Flowers of different kind; some are all
               White, some Purple, some Scarlet, some Blew, some Yellow; bearing, at the same time,
               Ripe Fruit and Blooming Young, or producing every Day new. The very Wood of all these
               Trees have an intrinsick Value above common Timber; for they are, when cut, of
               different Colours, glorious to behold; and bear a Price considerable, to inlay
               withal. Besides this, they yield rich Balm, and Gums; so that we make our Candles of
               such an Aromatick Substance, as<pb n="151"/> does not only give a sufficient Light,
               but, as they Burn, they cast their Perfumes all about. Cedar is the common Firing,
               and all the Houses are built with it. The very Meat we eat, when set on the Table, if
               it be Native, I mean of the Country, perfumes the whole Room; especially a little
               Beast call'd an <hi>Armadilly,</hi> a thing which I can liken to nothing so well as a
                  <hi>Rhinoceros;</hi> 'tis all in white Armor so joynted, that it moves as well in
               it, as if it had nothing on; this Beast is about the bigness of a Pig of Six Weeks
               old. But it were endless to give an Account of all the divers Wonderfull and Strange
               things that Country affords, and which we took a very great Delight to go in search
               of; though <pb n="152"/>those adventures are oftentimes Fatal and at least Dangerous:
               But while we had <hi>Caesar</hi> in our Company on these Designs we fear'd no harm,
               nor suffer'd any.</p>
            <p>As soon as I came into the Country, the best House in it was presented me, call'd St.
                  <hi>John's Hill.</hi> It stood on a vast Rock of white Marble, at the Foot of
               which the River ran a vast depth down, and not to be descended on that side; the
               little Waves still dashing and washing the foot of this Rock, made the softest
               Murmurs and Purlings in the World; and the Oposite Bank was adorn'd with such vast
               quantities of different Flowers eternally Blowing, and every Day and Hour new, fenc'd
               behind 'em with lofty Trees of a Thousand rare<pb n="153"/> Forms and Colours, that
               the Prospect was the most raving that Sands can create. On the Edge of this white
               Rock, towards the River, was a Walk or Grove of Orange and Limon Trees, about half
               the length of the <ref target="#n046" xml:id="a046">Mall</ref> here, whose Flowery
               and Fruity bear Branches meet at the top, and hinder'd the Sun, whose Rays are very
               fierce there, from entering a Beam into the Grove; and the cool Air that came from
               the River made it not only fit to entertain People in, at all the hottest Hours of
               the Day, but refresh'd the sweet Blossoms, and made it always Sweet and harming; and
               sure the whole Globe of the World cannot show so delightful a Place as this Grove
               was: Not all the Gardens of boasted<pb n="154"/>
               <hi>Italy</hi> can produce a Shade to outvie this, which Nature had joyn'd with Art
               to render so exceeding Fine; and 'tis a marvel to see how such vast Trees, as big as
               English Oaks, cou'd take footing on so solid a Rock, and in so little Earth, as
               cover'd that Rock but all things by Nature there are Rare, Delightful and Wonderful.
               But to our Sports;</p>
            <p>Sometimes we wou'd go surprizing, and in search of young <ref target="#n047"
                  xml:id="a047">Tigers</ref> in their Dens, watching when the old Ones went forth
               to forage for Prey; and oftentimes we have been in great Danger, and have fled apace
               for our Lives, when surpriz'd by the <ref target="#n048" xml:id="a048">Dams</ref>.
               But once, above all other times, we went on this Design, and <hi>Caesar</hi> was with
               us, who had no sooner<pb n="155"/>stol'n a young <hi>Tiger</hi> from her Nest, but
               going off, we incounter'd the Dam, bearing a Buttock of a Cow, which he had torn off
               with his mighty Paw, and going with it towards his <hi>Den;</hi> we had only four
               Women, <hi>Caesar,</hi> and an English Gentleman, Brother to <hi>Harry Martin,</hi>
               the great <ref target="#n049" xml:id="a049">Oliverian;</ref> we found there was no
               escaping this inrag'd and ravenous Beast. However, we Women fled as fast as we cou'd
               from it; but our Heels had not sav'd our Lives, if <hi>Caesar</hi> had not laid down
               his <hi>Cub,</hi> when he found the <hi>Tiger</hi> quit her Prey to make the more
               speed towards him; and taking Mr. <hi>Martin</hi>'s Sword desir'd him to stand aside,
               or follow the Ladies. He obey'd him, and <hi>Caesar</hi> met this monstrous<pb
                  n="156"/> Beast of might, size, and vast Limbs, who came with open Jaws upon him;
               and fixing his Awful stern Eyes full upon those of the Beast, and putting himself
               into a very steddy and good aiming posture of Defence, ran his Sword quite through
               his Breast down to his very Heart, home to the Hilt of the Sword; the dying Beast
               stretch'd forth her Paw, and going to grasp his Thigh, surpris'd with Death in that
               very moment, did him no other harm than fixing her long Nails in his Flesh very deep,
               feebly wounded him, but cou'd not grasp the Flesh to tear off any. When he had done
               this, he hollow'd to us to return; which, after some assurance of his Victory, we
               did, and found him lugging<pb n="157"/> out the Sword from the Bosom of the
                  <hi>Tiger,</hi> who was laid in her Bloud on the Ground; he took up the
                  <hi>Cub,</hi> and with an unconcern, that had nothing of the Joy or Gladness of a
               Victory, he came and laid the Whelp at my Feet: We all extreamly wonder'd at his
               Daring, and at the Bigness of the Beast, which was about the highth of an Heifer, but
               of mighty, great, and strong Limbs.</p>
            <p>Another time, being in the Woods, he kill'd a <hi>Tiger,</hi> which had long infested
               that part, and born away abundance of Sheep and Oxen, and other things, that were for
               the support of those to whom they belong'd; abundance of People assail'd this Beast,
               some affirming they had shot her<pb n="158"/> with several Bullets quite through the
               Body, at several times; and some swearing they shot her through the very Heart, and
               they believ'd she was a Devil rather than a Mortal thing. <hi>Caesar,</hi> had often
               said, he had a mind to encounter this Monster, and spoke with several Gentlemen who
               had attempted her; one crying, I shot her with so many poyson'd Arrows, another with
               his Gun in this part of her, and another in that; so that he remarking all these
               Places where she was shot, fancy'd still he shou'd overcome her, by giving her
               another sort of a Wound than any had yet done; and one day said (at the Table)
                  <hi>What Trophies and Garlands Ladies will you make me, if I bring you home the
                  Heart of</hi>
               <pb n="159"/>
               <hi>this Ravenous Beast, that eats up all your Lambs and Pigs?</hi> We all promis'd
               he shou'd be rewarded at all our Hands. So taking a Bow, which he chus'd out of a
               great many, he went up in the Wood with two Gentlemen, where he imagin'd this
               Devourer to be; they had not past very far in it, but they heard her Voice, growling
               and grumbling, as if she were pleas'd with something she was doing. When they came in
               view, they found her muzzling in the Belly of a new ravish'd Sheep, which she had
               torn open; and seeing herself approach'd, she took fast hold of her Prey, with her
               fore Paws, and set a very fierce raging Look on <hi>Caesar,</hi> without offering to
               approach him; for fear, at the<pb n="160"/> same time, of loosing what she had in
               Possession. So that <hi>Caesar</hi> remain'd a good while, only taking aim, and
               getting an opportunity to shoot her where he design'd; 'twas some time before he
               cou'd accomplish it, and to wound her, and not kill her, wou'd but have enrag'd her
               more, and indanger'd him: He had a Quiver of Arrows at his side, so that if one
               fail'd he cou'd be supply'd; at last, retiring a little, he gave her opportunity to
               eat, for he found she was Ravenous, and fell too as soon as she saw him retire; being
               more eager of her Prey than of doing new Mischiefs. When he going softly to one side
               of her, and hiding his Person behind certain Herbage that grew high and thick, <pb
                  n="161"/>he took so good aim, that, as he intended, he shot her just into the Eye,
               and the Arrow was sent with so good a will, and so sure a hand, that it stuck in her
               Brain, and made her caper, and become mad for a moment or two; but being seconded by
               another Arrow, he fell dead upon the Prey: <hi>Caesar</hi> cut him Open with a Knife,
               to see where those Wounds were that had been reported to him, and why he did not Die
               of 'em. But I shall now relate a thing that possibly will find no Credit among Men,
               because 'tis a Notion commonly receiv'd with us, That nothing can receive a Wound in
               the Heart and Live; but when the Heart of this courageous Animal was taken out, there
               were Seven<pb n="162"/> Bullets of Lead in it, and the Wounds seam'd up with great
               Scars, and she liv'd with the Bullets a great while, for it was long since they were
               shot: This Heart the Conqueror brought up to us, and 'twas a very great Curiosity,
               which all the Country came to see; and which gave <hi>Caesar</hi> occasion of many
               fine Discourses; of Accidents in War, and Strange Escapes.</p>
            <p>At other times he wou'd go a Fishing; and discoursing on that Diversion, he found we
               had in that Country a very Strange Fish, call'd, a <ref target="#n050" xml:id="a050"
                  >Numb Eel,</ref> (an <hi>Eel</hi> of which I have eaten) that while it is alive,
               it has a quality so Cold, that those who are Angling, though with a Line of never so
               great a length, with a Rod <pb n="163"/>at the end of it, it shall, in the same
               minute the Bait is touched by this <hi>Eel,</hi> seize him or her that holds the Rod
               with benumb'dness, that shall deprive 'em of Sense, for a while; and some have fall'n
               into the Water, and others drop'd as dead on the Banks of the Rivers where they
               stood, as soon as this Fish touches the Bait. <hi>Caesar</hi> us'd to laugh at this,
               and believ'd it impossible a Man cou'd loose his Force at the touch of a Fish; and
               cou'd not understand that Philosophy, that a cold Quality should be of that Nature:
               However, he had a great Curiosity to try whether it wou'd have the same effect on him
               it had on others, and often try'd, but in vain; at last, the sought for<pb n="164"/>
               Fish came to the Bait, as he stood Angling on the Bank; and instead of throwing away
               the Rod, or giving it a sudden twitch out of the Water, whereby he might have caught
               both the <hi>Eel,</hi> and have dismist the Rod, before it cou'd have too much Power
               over him; for Experiment sake, he grasp'd it but the harder, and fainting fell into
               the River; and being still possest of the Rod, the Tide carry'd him senseless as he
               was a great way, till an <hi>Indian</hi> Boat took him up; and perceiv'd, when they
               touch'd him, a Numbness seize them, and by that knew the Rod was in his Hand; which,
               with a Paddle (that is, a short Oar) they struck away, and snatch'd it into the Boat,
                  <pb n="165"/><hi>Eel</hi> and all. If <hi>Caesar</hi> were almost Dead, with the
               effect of this Fish, he was more so with that of the Water, where he had remain'd the
               space of going a League; and they found they had much a-do to bring him back to Life:
               But, at last, they did, and brought him home, where he was in a few Hours well
               Recover'd and Refresh'd; and not a little Asham'd to find he shou'd be overcome by an
                  <hi>Eel;</hi> and that all the People, who heard his Defiance, wou'd Laugh at him.
               But we cheared him up; and he, being convinc'd, we had the <hi>Eel</hi> at Supper;
               which was a quarter of an <ref target="#n051" xml:id="a051">Ell</ref> about, and
               most delicate Meat; and was of the more Value, since it cost so<pb n="166"/>Dear, as
               almost the Life of so gallant a Man.</p>
            <p>About this time we were in many mortal Fears, about some Disputes the
                  <hi>English</hi> had with the <hi>Indians;</hi> so that we cou'd scarce trust our
               selves, without great Numbers, to go to any <hi>Indian</hi> Towns, or Place, where
               they abode; for fear they shou'd fall upon us, as they did immediately after my
               coming away; and that it was in the possession of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who us'd 'em
               not so civilly as the <hi>English;</hi> so that they cut in pieces all they cou'd
               take, getting into Houses, and hanging up the Mother, and all her Children about her;
               and cut a Footman, I left behind me, all in Joynts, and nail'd him to Trees.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="167"/> This feud began while I was there; so that I lost half the satisfaction
               I propos'd, in not seeing and visiting the <hi>Indian</hi> Towns. But one Day,
               bemoaning of our Misfortunes upon this account, <hi>Caesar</hi> told us, we need not
               Fear; for if we had a mind to go, he wou'd undertake to be our Guard: Some wou'd, but
               most wou'd not venture; about Eighteen of us resolv'd, and took Barge; and, after
               Eight Days, arriv'd near an <hi>Indian</hi> Town: But approaching it, the Hearts of
               some of our Company fail'd, and they wou'd not venture on Shore; so we Poll'd who
               wou'd, and who wou'd not: For my part, I said, If <hi>Caesar</hi> wou'd, I wou'd go;
               he resolv'd, so did my Brother, and<pb n="168"/> my Woman, a Maid of good Courage.
               Now none of us speaking the Language of the People, and imagining we shou'd have a
               half Diversion in Gazing only; and not knowing what they said, we took a Fisherman
               that liv'd at the Mouth of the River, who had been a long Inhabitant there, and
               oblig'd him to go with us: But because he was known to the <hi>Indians,</hi> as
               trading among 'em; and being, by long Living there, become a perfect <hi>Indian</hi>
               in Colour, we, who resolv'd to surprize 'em, by making 'em see something they never
               had seen, (that is, White People) resolv'd only my self, my Brother, and Woman shou'd
               go; so <hi>Caesar,</hi> the Fisherman, and the rest, hiding behind some<pb n="169"/>
               thick Reeds and Flowers, that grew on the Banks, let us pass on towards the Town,
               which was on the Bank of the River all along. A little distant from the Houses, or
               Hutts; we saw some Dancing, others busy'd in fetching and carrying of Water from the
               River: They had no sooner spy'd us, but they set up a loud Cry, that frighted us at
               first; we thought it had been for those that should Kill us, but it seems it was of
               Wonder and Amazement. They were all Naked, and we were Dress'd, so as is most comode
               for the hot Countries, very Glittering and Rich; so that we appear'd extreamly fine;
               my own Hair was cut short, and I had a Taffaty Cap, with Black Feathers, on my<pb
                  n="170"/> Head; my Brother was in a Stuff Sute, with Silver Loops and Buttons, and
               abundance of Green Ribon; this was all infinitely surprising to them, and because we
               saw them stand still, till we approach'd 'em, we took Heart and advanc'd; came up to
               'em, and offer'd 'em our Hands; which they took, and look'd on us round about,
               calling still for more Company; who came swarming out, all wondering, and crying out
                  <hi>Tepeeme;</hi> taking their Hair up in their Hands, and spreading it wide to
               those they call'd out too; as if they would say (as indeed it signify'd)
                  <hi>Numberless Wonders,</hi> or not to be recounted, no more than to number the
               Hair of their Heads. By degrees they grew<pb n="171"/> more bold, and from gazing
               upon us round, they touch'd us; laying their Hands upon all the Features of our
               Faces, feeling our Breasts and Arms, taking up one Petticoat, then wondering to see
               another; admiring our Shooes and Stockings, but more our Garters, which we gave 'em;
               and they ty'd about their Legs, being Lac'd with Silver Lace at the ends, for they
               much Esteem any <ref target="#n052" xml:id="a052">shining things</ref>: In fine, we
               suffer'd 'em to survey us as they pleas'd, and we thought they wou'd never have done
               admiring us. When <hi>Caesar,</hi> and the rest, saw we were receiv'd with such
               wonder, they came up to us; and finding the <hi>Indian</hi> Trader whom they knew,
               (for 'tis <pb n="172"/> by these Fishermen, call'd <hi>Indian</hi> Traders, we hold a
               Commerce with 'em; for they love not to go far from home, and we never go to them)
               when they saw him therefore they set up a new Joy; and cry'd, in their Language,
                  <hi>Oh! here's our</hi>
               <ref target="#n053" xml:id="a053">Tiguamy</ref>, <hi>and we shall now know whether
                  those things can speak:</hi> So advancing to him, some of 'em gave him their
               Hands, and cry'd, <hi>Amora Tiguamy,</hi> which is as much as, <hi>How do you,</hi>
               or <hi>Welcome Friend;</hi> and all, with one din, began to gabble to him, and ask'd,
               If we had Sense, and Wit? if we cou'd talk of affairs of Life, and War, as they cou'd
               do? if we cou'd Hunt, Swim, and do a thousand things they use? He answer'd 'em, We
               cou'd. Then <pb n="173"/>they invited us into their Houses, and dress'd Venison and
               Buffelo for us; and, going out, gathered a Leaf of a Tree, call'd a <ref
                  target="#n054" xml:id="a054">Sarumbo</ref> Leaf, of Six Yards long, and spread it
               on the Ground for a Table-Cloth; and cutting another in pieces instead of Plates,
               setting us on little bow <hi>Indian</hi> Stools, which they cut out of one intire
               piece of Wood, and Paint, in a sort of Japan Work: They serve every one their <ref
                  target="#n055" xml:id="a055">Mess</ref> on these pieces of Leaves, and it was
               very good, but too high season'd with Pepper. When we had eat, my Brother, and I,
               took out our Flutes, and play'd to 'em, which gave 'em new Wonder; and I soon
               perceiv'd, by an admiration, that is natural to these<pb n="174"/> People; and by the
               extream Ignorance and Simplicity of 'em, it were not difficult to establish any
               unknown or extravagant Religion among them; and to impose any Notions or Fictions
               upon 'em. For seeing a Kinsman of mine set some Paper a Fire, with a <ref
                  target="#n056" xml:id="a056">Burning-glass</ref>, a Trick they had never before
               seen, they were like to have Ador'd him for a God; and beg'd he wou'd give them the
               Characters or Figures of his Name, that they might oppose it against Winds and
               Storms; which he did, and they held it up in those Seasons, and fancy'd it had a
               Charm to conquer them; and kept it like a Holy Relique. They are very Superstitious,
               and call'd him the<pb n="175"/> Great <hi>Peeie,</hi> that is, <hi>Prophet</hi> They
               show d us their <hi>Indian Peeie</hi> a Youth of about Sixteen Years old, as handsom
               as Nature cou'd make a Man. They consecrate a beautiful Youth from his Infancy, and
               all Arts are us'd to compleat him in the finest manner, both in Beauty and Shape: He
               is bred to all the little Arts and cunning they are capable of; to all the <ref
                  target="#n057" xml:id="a057">Legerdemain</ref> Tricks, and Slight of Hand,
               whereby he imposes upon the Rabble; and is both a Doctor in Physick and Divinity. And
               by these Tricks makes the Sick believe he sometimes eases their Pains; by drawing
               from the afflicted part little Serpents, or odd Flies, or Worms, or any Strange
               thing; and though<pb n="176"/>they have besides undoubted good Remedies, for almost
               all their Diseases, they cure the Patient more by Fancy than by Medicines; and make
               themselves Fear'd, Lov'd, and <ref target="#n058" xml:id="a058">Reverenc'd</ref>.
               This young <hi>Peeie</hi> had a very young Wife, who seeing my Bròther kiss her, came
               running and kiss'd me; after this, they kiss'd one another, and made it a very great
               Jest, it being so Novel; and new Admiration and Laughing went round the Multitude,
               that they never will forget that Ceremony, never before us'd or known.
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> had a mind to see and talk with their War <hi>Captains,</hi> and
               we were conducted to one of their Houses; where we beheld several of the <pb n="177"
               />great <hi>Captains,</hi> who had been at Councel: But so frightful a Vision it was
               to see 'em no Fancy can create; no such Dreams can represent so dreadful a Spectacle.
               For my part I took 'em for Hobgoblins, or Fiends, rather than Men; but however their
               Shapes appear'd, their Souls were very Humane and Noble; but some wanted their Noses,
               some their Lips, some both Noses and Lips, some their Ears, and others Cut through
               each Cheek, with long Slashes, through which their Teeth appear'd; they had other
               several formidable Wounds and Scars, or rather Dismemberings; they had <ref
                  target="#n059" xml:id="a059">Comitias,</ref> or little Aprons before 'em; and
               Girdles of Cotton, with their Knives naked,<pb n="178"/> stuck in it; a Bow at their
               Backs, and a Quiver of Arrows on their Thighs; and most had Feathers on their Heads
               of divers Colours. They cry'd, <hi>Amora Tigame</hi> to us, at our entrance, and were
               pleas'd we said as much to em; they seated us, and gave us Drink of the best Sort;
               and wonder'd, as much as the others had done before, to see us. <hi>Caesar</hi> was
               marvelling as much at their Faces, wondering how they shou'd all be so Wounded in
               War; he was Impatient to know how they all came by those frightful Marks of Rage or
               Malice, rather than Wounds got in Noble Battel: They told us, by our Interpreter,
               That when any War was waging, two<pb n="179"/> Men chosen out by some old
                  <hi>Captain,</hi> whose Fighting was past, and who cou'd only teach the Theory of
               War, these two Men were to stand in Competition for the Generalship, or Great War
               Captain; and being brought before the old Judges, now past Labour, they are ask'd,
               What they dare do to shew they are worthy to lead an Army? When he, who is first
               ask'd, making no Reply, Cuts of his Nose, and throws it contemptably on the Ground;
               and the other does something to himself that he thinks surpasses him, and perhaps
               deprives himself of Lips and an Eye; so they Slash on till one gives out, and many
               have dy'd in this Debate. And 'its by a passive Valour they <pb n="180"/>shew and
               prove their Activity; a sort of Courage too Brutal to be applauded by our Black Hero;
               nevertheless he express'd his Esteem of 'em.</p>
            <p>In this Voyage <hi>Caesar</hi> begot so good an understanding between the
                  <hi>Indians</hi> and the <hi>English,</hi> that there were no more Fears, or <ref
                  target="#n060" xml:id="a060">Heart-burnings</ref> during our stay; but we had a
               perfect, open, and free Trade with 'em: Many things Remarkable, and worthy Reciting,
               we met with in this short Voyage; because <hi>Caesar</hi> made it his Business to
               search out and provide for our Entertainment, especially to please his dearly Ador'd
                  <hi>Imoinda,</hi> who was a sharer in all our Adventures; we being resolv'd to
               make her Chains as easy as we cou'd, and<pb n="181"/> to Compliment the Prince in
               that manner that most oblig'd him.</p>
            <p>As we were coming up again, we met with some <hi>Indians</hi> of strange Aspects;
               that is, of a larger Size, and other sort of Features, than those of our Country: Our
                  <hi>Indian Slaves,</hi> that Row'd us, ask'd 'em some Questions, but they cou'd
               not understand us; but shew'd us a long Cotton String, with several Knots on it; and
               told us, they had been coming from the Mountains so many <ref target="#n061"
                  xml:id="a061">Moons</ref> as there were Knots; they were habited in Skins of a
               strange Beast, and brought along with 'em Bags of Gold Dust; which, as well as they
               cou'd give us to understand, came streaming in<pb n="182"/> little small Chanels down
               the high Mountains, when the Rains fell; and offer'd to be the Convoy to any Body, or
               Persons, that wou'd go to the <ref target="#n062" xml:id="a062">Mountains</ref>. We
               carry'd these Men up to <hi>Parham,</hi> where they were kept till the Lord Governour
               came: And because all the Country was mad to be going on this Golden Adventure, the
               Governour, by his Letters, commanded (for they sent some of the Gold to him) that a
               Guard shou'd be set at the Mouth of the River of <ref target="#n063" xml:id="a063"
                  >Amazons</ref>, (a River so call'd, almost as broad as the River of
                  <hi>Thames)</hi> and prohibited all People from going up that River, it conducting
               to those Mountains of Gold. But we going off for <hi>England</hi> before <pb n="183"
               />the Project was further prosecuted, and the Governour being drown'd in a Hurricane,
               either the Design dy'd, or the <hi>Dutch</hi> have the Advantage of it: And 'tis to
               be bemoan'd what his Majesty lost by loosing that part of <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this digression is a little from my Story, however since it contains some
               Proofs of the Curiosity and Daring of this great Man, I was content to omit nothing
               of his Character.</p>
            <p>It was thus, for sometime we diverted him; but now <hi>Imoinda</hi> began to shew she
               was with Child, and did nothing but Sigh and Weep for the Captivity of her Lord, her
               Self, and the Infant yet Unborn; and believ'd,<pb n="184"/> if it were so hard to
               gain the Liberty of Two, 'twou'd be more difficult to get that for Three. Her Griefs
               were so many Darts in the great Heart of <hi>Caesar;</hi> and taking his Opportunity
               one <hi>Sunday,</hi> when all the Whites were overtaken in Drink, as there were
               abundance of several Trades, and <hi>Slaves</hi> for Four Years, that Inhabited among
               the <hi>Negro</hi> Houses; and <hi>Sunday</hi> was their Day of Debauch, (otherwise
               they were a sort of Spys upon <hi>Caesar;)</hi> he went pretending out of Goodness to
               'em, to Feast amongst 'em; and sent all his Musick, and order'd a great Treat for the
               whole Gang, about Three Hundred <hi>Negros;</hi> and about a Hundred and Fifty were
               able to bear Arms, such as <pb n="185"/>they had, which were sufficient to do
               Execution with Spirits accordingly: For the <hi>English</hi> had none but rusty
               Swords, that no Strength cou'd draw from a Scabbard; except the People of particular
               Quality, who took care to Oyl 'em and keep 'em in good Order: The Guns also, unless
               here and there one, or those newly carri'd from <hi>England,</hi> wou'd do no good or
               harm; for 'tis the Nature of that County to Rust and Eat up Iron, or any Metals, but
               Gold and Silver. And they are very Unexpert at the Bow, which the <hi>Negros</hi> and
                  <hi>Indians</hi> are perfect Masters off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caesar,</hi> having singl'd out these Men from the Women and Children, made an
                  <ref target="#n064" xml:id="a064">Harangue</ref><pb n="186"/> to 'em of the
               Miseries, and Ignominies of Slavery; counting up all their Toyls and Sufferings,
               under such Loads, Burdens, and Drudgeries, as were fitter for Beasts than Men;
               Senseless Brutes, than Humane Souls. He told 'em it was not for Days, Months, or
               Years, but for Eternity; there was no end to be of their Misfortunes: They suffer'd
               not like Men who might find a Glory, and Fortitude in Oppression; but like Dogs that
               lov'd the Whip and Bell, and fawn'd the more they were beaten: That they had lost the
               Divine Quality of Men, and were become insensible Asses, fit only to bear; nay worse:
               an Ass, or Dog, or Horse having done his Duty, cou'd lye down<pb n="187"/> in
               Retreat, and rise to Work again, and while he did his Duty indur'd no Stripes; but
               Men, Villanous, Senseless Men, such as they, Toyl'd on all the tedious Week till
               Black <ref target="#n065" xml:id="a065">Friday</ref>; and then, whether they Work'd
               or not, whether they were Faulty or Meriting, they promiscuously, the Innocent with
               the Guilty, suffer'd the infamous Whip, the sordid Stripes, from their Fellow
                  <hi>Slaves</hi> till their Blood trickled from all Parts of their Body; Blood,
               whose every drop ought to be Reveng'd with a Life of some of those Tyrants, that
               impose it; <hi>And why,</hi> said he, <hi>my dear Friends and Fellow-sufferers,
                  shou'd we be Slaves to an unknown People? Have they Vanquish'd us Nobly in Fight?
                  Have they Won</hi><pb n="188"/><hi> us in Honourable Battel? And are we, by the
                  chance of War, become their <ref target="#n066" xml:id="a066">Slaves</ref>? This
                  wou'd not anger a Noble Heart, this wou'd not animate a Souldiers Soul; no, but we
                  are Bought and Sold like Apes, or Monkeys, to be the Sport of Women, Fools and
                  Cowards; and the Support of Rogues, <ref target="#n067" xml:id="a067"
                     >Runagades</ref>, that have abandon'd their own Countries, for Rapin, Murders,
                  Thefts and Villanies: Do you not hear every Day how they upbraid each other with
                  infamy of Life, below the Wildest Salvages; and shall we render Obedience to such
                  a degenerate Race, who have no one Humane Vertue left, to distinguish 'em from the
                  vilest Creatures? Will you, I say, suffer the Lash from such Hands?</hi> They all
               Reply'd, with one accord,<pb n="189"/>
               <hi>No, no, no;</hi> Caesar <hi>has spoke like a Great Captain; like a Great
                  King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this he wou'd have proceeded, but was interrupted by a tall <hi>Negro</hi> of
               some more Quality than the rest, his Name was <ref target="#n068" xml:id="a068"
                  >Tuscan;</ref> who Bowing at the Feet of <hi>Caesar,</hi> cry'd, <hi>My Lord, we
                  have listen'd with Joy and Attention to what you have said; and, were we only Men,
                  wou'd follow so great a Leader through the World: But oh! consider, we are
                  Husbands and Parents too, and have things more dear to us than Life; our Wives and
                  Children unfit for Travel, in these unpassable Woods, Mountains and Bogs; we have
                  not only difficult Lands to overcome, but Rivers to Wade, and Monsters to
                  Incounter;</hi><pb n="190"/>
               <hi>Ravenous Beasts of Prey—</hi>To this, <hi>Caesar</hi> Reply'd, <hi>That Honour
                  was the First Principle in Nature, that was to be Obey'd; but as no Man wou'd
                  pretend to that, without all the Acts of Vertue, Compassion, Charity, Love,
                  Justice and Reason; he found it not inconsistent with that, to take an equal Care
                  of their Wives and Children, as they wou'd of themselves; and that he did not
                  Design, when he led them to Freedom, and Glorious Liberty, that they shou'd leave
                  that better part of themselves to Perish by the Hand of the Tyrant's Whip: But if
                  there were a Woman among them so degenerate from Love and Vertue to chuse Slavery
                  before the pursuit of her Husband, and with the hazard of her Life, to share with
                  him in</hi>
               <pb n="191"/><hi>his Fortunes; that such an one ought to be Abandon'd, and left as a
                  Prey to the common Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which they all Agreed,—and Bowed. After this, he spoke of the Impassable Woods and
               Rivers; and convinc'd 'em, the more Danger, the more Glory. He told them that he had
               heard of one <hi>Hannibal</hi> a great Captain, had <ref target="#n069"
                  xml:id="a069">Cut his Way</ref> through Mountains of solid Rocks; and shou'd a
               few Shrubs oppose them; which they cou'd Fire before 'em? No, 'twas a trifling Excuse
               to Men resolv'd to die, or overcome. As for Bogs, they are with a little Labour
               fill'd and harden'd; and the Rivers cou'd be no Obstacle, since they Swam by Nature;
               at least by<pb n="192"/>Custom, from their First Hour of their Birth: That when the
               Children were Weary they must carry them by turns, and the Woods and their own
               Industry wou'd afford them Food. To this they all assented with Joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tuscan</hi> then demanded, What he wou'd do? He said, they wou'd Travel towards
               the Sea; Plant a New Colony, and Defend it by their Valour; and when they cou'd find
               a Ship, either driven by stress of Weather, or guided by Providence that way, they
               wou'd Sieze it, and make it a Prize, till it had Transported them to their own
               Countries; at least, they shou'd be made Free in his Kingdom, and be Esteem'd as his
               Fellowsufferers, and Men that had<pb n="193"/> the Courage, and the Bravery to
               attempt, at least, for Liberty; and if they Dy'd in the attempt it wou'd be more
               brave, than to Live in perpetual Slavery.</p>
            <p>They bow'd and kiss'd his Feet at this Resolution, and with one accord Vow'd to
               follow him to Death. And that Night was appointed to begin their March; they made it
               known to their Wives, and directed them to tie their Hamaca about their Shoulder, and
               under their Arm like a Scarf; and to lead their Children that cou'd go, and carry
               those that cou'd not. The Wives who pay an intire Obedience to their Husbands obey'd,
               and stay'd for 'em, where they were appointed: The Men <pb n="194"/>stay'd but to
               furnish themselves with what defensive Arms they cou'd get; and All met at the
               Rendezvous, where <hi>Caesar</hi> made a new incouraging Speech to 'em, and led 'em
               out.</p>
            <p>But, as they cou'd not march far that Night, on Monday early, when the Overseers went
               to call 'em all together, to go to Work, they were extreamly surpris'd, to find not
               one upon the Place, but all fled with what Baggage they had. You may imagine this
               News was not only suddenly spread all over the <hi>Plantation,</hi> but soon reach'd
               the Neighbouring ones; and we had by Noon about Six hundred Men, they call the
                  <hi>Militia</hi> of the County, that came to assist us in the persute of the
                  Fugitives:<pb n="195"/> But never did one see so comical an Army march forth to
               War. The Men, of any <ref target="#n070" xml:id="a070">fashion</ref>, wou'd not
               concern themselves, though it were almost the common Cause; for such Revoltings are
               very ill Examples, and have very fatal Consequences oftentimes in many Colonies: But
               they had a Respect for <hi>Caesar,</hi> and all hands were against the
                  <hi>Parhamites,</hi> as they call'd those of <hi>Parham Plantation;</hi> because
               they did not, in the first place, love the Lord Governor; and secondly, they wou'd
               have it, that <hi>Caesar</hi> was <ref target="#n071" xml:id="a071">Ill us'd</ref>,
               and <ref target="#n072" xml:id="a072">Baffl'd with</ref>; and 'tis not impossible
               but some of the best in the Country was of his Council in this Flight, and depriving
               us of all the<hi>Slaves;</hi> so that they<pb n="196"/>of the better sort wou'd not
               meddle in the matter. The <ref target="#n074" corresp="a074">Deputy Governor</ref>,
               of whom I have had no great occasion to speak, and who was the most Fawning
               fair-tongu'd Fellow in the World, and one that pretended the most Friendship to
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> was now the only violent Man against him; and though he had
               nothing, and so need fear nothing, yet talk'd and look'd bigger than any Man: He was
               a Fellow, whose Character is not fit to be mention'd with the worst of the
                  <hi>Slaves.</hi> This Fellow wou'd lead his Army forth to meet <hi>Caesar;</hi> or
               rather to persue him; most of their Arms were of those sort of cruel Whips they call
                  <ref target="#n075" xml:id="a075">Cat with Nine Tayls</ref>; some had rusty<pb
                  n="197"/> useless Guns for show; others old <ref target="#n076" xml:id="a076"
                  >Basket-hilts</ref>, whose Blades had never seen the Light in this Age; and others
               had long Staffs, and Clubs. Mr. <hi>Trefry</hi> went a long, rather to be a Mediator
               than a Conqueror, in such a Batail; for he foresaw, and knew, if by fighting they put
               the <hi>Negroes</hi> into dispair, they were a sort of sullen Fellows, that wou'd
               drown, or kill themselves, before they wou'd yield; and he advis'd that fair means
               was best: But <hi>Byam</hi> was one that abounded in his own <ref target="#n077"
                  xml:id="a077">Wit</ref>, and wou'd take his own Measures.</p>
            <p>It was not hard to find these Fugitives; for as they fled they were forc'd to fire
               and cut the Woods before 'em, so that Night<pb n="198"/> or Day they persu'd 'em by
               the light they made, and by the path they had clear'd: But as soon as <hi>Caesar</hi>
               found he was persu'd, he put himself in a Posture of Defence, placing all the Women
               and Children in the Reer; and himself, with <hi>Tuscan</hi> by his side, or next to
               him, all promising to Dye or Conquer. Incourag'd thus, they never stood to Parley,
               but fell on Pell-mell upon the <hi>English,</hi> and kill'd some, and wounded a good
               many; they having recourse to their Whips, as the best of their Weapons: And as they
               observ'd no Order, they perplex'd the Enemy so sorely, with Lashing 'em in the Eyes;
               and the Women and Children, seeing their Husbands so treated, being of <pb n="199"
               />fearful Cowardly Dispositions, and hearing the <hi>English</hi> cry out, <hi>Yield
                  and Live, Yield and be Pardon'd;</hi> they all run in amongst their Husbands and
               Fathers, and hung about 'em, crying out, <hi>Yield, yield; and leave</hi> Caesar
                  <hi>to their Revenge;</hi> that by degrees the <hi>Slaves</hi> abandon'd
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> and left him only <hi>Tuscan</hi> and his Heroick
                  <hi>Imoinda;</hi> who, grown big as she was, did nevertheless press near her Lord,
               having a Bow, and a Quiver full of poyson'd Arrows, which she manag'd with such
               dexterity, that she wounded several, and shot the <hi>Governor</hi> into the
               Shoulder; of which Wound he had like to have Dy'd, but that an <hi>Indian</hi> Woman,
               his Mistress, suck'd the Wound, and cleans'd it from<pb n="200"/> the Venom: But
               however, he stir'd not from the Place till he had Parly'd with <hi>Caesar,</hi> who
               he found was resolv'd to dye Fighting, and wou'd not be Taken; no more wou'd
                  <hi>Tuscan,</hi> or <hi>Imoinda.</hi> But he, more thirsting after Revenge of
               another sort, than that of depriving him of Life, now made use of all his Art of
               talking, and dissembling; and besought <hi>Caesar</hi> to yield himself upon Terms,
               which he himself should propose, and should be Sacredly assented to and kept by him:
               He told him, It was not that he any longer fear'd him, or cou'd believe the force of
               Two Men, and a young Heroin, cou'd overcome all them, with all the Slaves now on
               their side also; but it was the vast Esteem<pb n="201"/> he had for his Person; the
               desire he had to serve so Gallant a Man; and to hinder himself from the Reproach
               hereafter, of having been the occasion of the Death of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whose
               Valour and Magnanimity deserv'd the Empire of the World. He protested to him, he
               look'd upon this Action, as Gallant and Brave; however tending to the prejudice of
               his Lord and Master, who wou'd by it have lost so considerable a number of
                  <hi>Slaves;</hi> that this Flight of his shou'd be look'd on as a heat of Youth,
               and rashness of a too forward Courage, and an <ref target="#n078" xml:id="a078"
                  >unconsider'd</ref> impatience of Liberty, and no more; and that he labour'd in
               vain to accomplish that which they wou'd effectually perform,<pb n="202"/>as soon as
               any Ship arriv'd that wou'd <ref target="#n079" xml:id="a079">touch on</ref> his
               Coast. <hi>So that if you will be pleas'd,</hi> continued he, <hi>to surrender your
                  self, all imaginable Respect shall be paid you; and your Self, your Wife, and
                  Child, if it be here born, shall depart free out of our Land.</hi> But
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> wou'd hear of no Composition; though <hi>Byam</hi> urg'd, If he
               persu'd, and went on in his Design, he wou'd inevitably Perish, either by great
                  <hi>Snakes,</hi> wild Beasts, or Hunger; and he ought to have regard to his Wife,
               whose Condition required ease, and not the fatigues of <ref target="#n080"
                  xml:id="a080">tedious</ref> Travel; where she cou'd not be secur'd from being
               devoured. But <hi>Caesar</hi> told him, there was no Faith in the White Men, or the
               Gods they Ador'd;<pb n="203"/> who instructed 'em in Principles so false, that honest
               Men cou'd not live amongst 'em; though no People profess'd so much, none perform'd so
               little; that he knew what he had to do, when he dealt with Men of Honour; but with
               them a Man ought to be eternally on his Guard, and never to Eat and Drink with
                  <hi>Christians</hi> without his Weapon of Defence in his Hand; and, for his own
               Security, never to credit one Word they spoke. As for the rashness and
               inconsiderateness of his Action he wou'd confess the Governor is in the right; and
               that he was asham'd of what he had done, in endeavoring to make those Free, who were
               by Nature <hi>Slaves,</hi> poor wretched Rogues, fit to be us'd as<pb n="204"/>
               <hi>Christians</hi> Tools; Dogs, treacherous and cowardly, fit for such Masters; and
               they wanted only but to be whipt into the knowledge of the <hi>Christian Gods</hi> to
               be the vilest of all creeping things; to learn to Worship such Deities as had not
               Power to make 'em Just, Brave, or Honest. In fine, after a thousand things of this
               Nature, not fit here to be recited, he told <hi>Byam,</hi> he had rather Dye than
               Live upon the same Earth with such Dogs. But <hi>Trefry</hi> and <hi>Byam</hi>
               pleaded and protested together so much, that <hi>Trefry</hi> believing the
                  <hi>Governor</hi> to mean what he said; and speaking very cordially himself,
               generously put himself into <hi>Caesar</hi>'s Hands, and took him aside, and
               perswaded him, even with Tears,<pb n="205"/> to Live, by Surrendring himself, and to
               name his Conditions. <hi>Caesar</hi> was overcome by his Wit and Reasons, and in
               consideration of <hi>Imoinda;</hi> and demanding what he desir'd, and that it shou'd
               be ratify'd by their Hands in Writing, because he had perceiv'd that was the common
               way of contract between Man and Man, amongst the Whites: All this was perform'd, and
                  <hi>Tuscan</hi>'s Pardon was put in, and they Surrender to the Governor, who
               walked peaceably down into the <hi>Plantation</hi> with 'em, after giving order to
               bury their dead. <hi>Caesar</hi> was very much toyl'd with the bustle of the Day; for
               he had fought like a <ref target="#n081" xml:id="a081">Fury</ref>, and what Mischief
               was done he and <hi>Tuscan</hi> perform'd <pb n="206"/>alone; and gave their Enemies
               a fatal Proof that they durst do any thing, and fear'd no mortal Force.</p>
            <p>But they were no sooner arriv'd at the Place, where all the Slaves receive their
               Punishments of Whipping, but they laid Hands on <hi>Caesar</hi> and <hi>Tuscan,</hi>
               faint with heat and toyl; and, surprising them, Bound them to two several Stakes, and
               Whipt them in a most deplorable and inhumane Manner, rending the very Flesh from
               their Bones; especially <hi>Caesar,</hi> who was not perceiv'd to make any Mone, or
               to alter his Face, only to roul his Eyes on the Faithless <hi>Governor,</hi> and
               those he believ'd Guilty, with Fierceness and Indignation; and, to compleat his Rage,
               he <pb n="207"/>saw every one of those <hi>Slaves,</hi> who, but a few Davs before,
               Ador'd him as something more than Mortal, now had a Whip to give him some Lashes,
               while he strove not to break his Fetters; though, if he had, it were impossible: But
               he pronounced a Woe and Revenge from his Eyes, that darted Fire, that 'twas at once
               both Awful and Terrible to behold.</p>
            <p>When they thought they were sufficiently Reveng'd on him, they unty'd him, almost
               Fainting, with loss of Blood, from a thousand Wounds all over his Body; from which
               they had rent his Cloaths, and led him Bleeding and Naked as he was; and loaded him
               all over with Irons; and then rubbed his<pb n="208"/> Wounds, to compleat their
               Cruelty, with <hi>Indian Pepper,</hi> which had like to have made him raving Mad;
               and, in this Condition, made him so fast to the Ground that he cou'd not stir, if his
               Pains and Wounds wou'd have given him leave. They spar'd <hi>Imoinda,</hi> and did
               not let her see this Barbarity committed towards her Lord, but carry'd her down to
                  <hi>Parham,</hi> and shut her up; which was not in kindness to her, but for fear
               she shou'd Dye with the Sight, or Miscarry; and then they shou'd loose a young
                  <hi>Slave,</hi> and perhaps the Mother.</p>
            <p>You must know, that when the News was brought on Monday Morning, that <hi>Caesar</hi>
               had betaken himself to the Woods,<pb n="209"/> and carry'd with him all the
                  <hi>Negroes.</hi> We were possess'd with extream Fear, which no perswasions cou'd
               Dissipate, that he wou'd secure himself till Night; and then, that he wou'd come down
               and Cut all our Throats. This apprehension made all the Females of us fly down the
               River, to be secur'd; and while we were away, they acted this Cruelty: For I suppose
               I had Authority and Interest enough there, had I suspected any such thing, to have
               prevented it; but we had not gon many Leagues, but the News overtook us that
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> was taken, and Whipt like a common <hi>Slave.</hi> We met on the
               River with Colonel <hi>Martin,</hi> a Man of great Gallantry, Wit, and<pb n="210"
               />Goodness, and whom I have celebrated in a Character of my New <hi>Comedy,</hi> by
               his own Name, in memory of so brave a <ref target="#n082" xml:id="a082">Man</ref> :
               He was Wise and Eloquent; and, from the fineness of his Parts, bore a great Sway over
               the Hearts of all the <hi>Colony:</hi> He was a Friend to <hi>Caesar,</hi> and
               resented this false Dealing with him very much. We carried him back to
                  <hi>Parham,</hi> thinking to have made an Accomodation; when we came, the First
               News we heard was, that the <hi>Governor</hi> was Dead of a Wound <hi>Imoinda</hi>
               had given him; but it was not so well: But it seems he wou'd have the Pleasure of
               beholding the Revenge he took on <hi>Caesar;</hi> and before the cruel Ceremony was
               finish'd, he drop'd<pb n="211"/> down; and then they perceiv'd the Wound he had on
               his Shoulder, was by a venom'd Arrow; which, as I said, his <hi>Indian</hi> Mistress
               heal'd, by Sucking the Wound.</p>
            <p>We were no sooner Arriv'd, but we went up to the <hi>Plantation</hi> to see
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> whom we found in a very Miserable and Unexpressable Condition;
               and I have a Thousand times admired how he liv'd, in so much tormenting Pain. We said
               all things to him, that Trouble, Pitty, and Good Nature cou'd suggest; Protesting our
               Innocency of the Fact, and our Abhorance of such Cruelties. Making a Thousand
               Professions of Services to him, and Begging as many Pardons for the Offenders,<pb
                  n="212"/>till we said so much, that he believ'd we had no Hand in his ill
               Treatment; but told us, he cou'd never Pardon <hi>Byam;</hi> as for <hi>Trefry,</hi>
               he confess'd he saw his Grief and Sorrow, for his Suffering, which he cou'd not
               hinder, but was like to have been beaten down by the very <hi>Slaves,</hi> for
               Speaking in his Defence: But for <hi>Byam,</hi> who was their Leader, their Head;—and
               shou'd, by his Justice, and Honor, have been an Example to 'em.—For him, he wish'd to
               Live, to take a dire Revenge of him, and said, <hi>It had been well for him, if he
                  had Sacrific'd me, instead of giving me the contemptable Whip.</hi> He refus'd to
               Talk much, but Begging us to give him our Hands; he took<pb n="213"/> 'em, and
               Protested never to lift up his, to do us any Harm. He had a great Respect for Colonel
                  <hi>Martin,</hi> and always took his Counsel, like that of a Parent; and assur'd
               him, he wou'd obey him in any thing, but his Revenge on <hi>Byam. Therefore,</hi>
               said he, <hi>for his own Safety, let him speedily dispatch me; for if I cou'd
                  dispatch my self, I wou'd not, till that Justice were done to my injur'd Person,
                  and the contempt of a Souldier: No, I wou'd not kill my self, even after a
                  Whiping, but will be content to live with that Infamy, and be pointed at by every
                  grining Slave, till I have compleated my Revenge; and then you shall see that</hi>
               Oroonoko <hi>scorns to live with the Indignity that was put on</hi> Caesar. All we<pb
                  n="214"/> cou'd do cou'd get no more Words from him; and we took care to have him
               put immediately into a healing Bath, to rid him of his Pepper; and order'd a <ref
                  target="#n083" xml:id="a083">Chirurgeon</ref> to anoint him with healing Balm,
               which he suffer'd, and in some time he began to be able to Walk and Eat; we fail'd
               not to visit him every Day, and, to that end, had him brought to an <ref
                  target="#n084" xml:id="a084">apartment</ref> at <hi>Parham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Governor</hi> was no sooner recover'd, and had heard of the <ref
                  target="#n085" xml:id="a085">menaces</ref> of <hi>Caesar,</hi> but he call'd his
               Council; who (not to disgrace them, or <ref target="#n086" xml:id="a086"
                  >Burlesque</ref> the Government there) consisted of such notorious Villains as
                  <ref target="#n087" xml:id="a087">Newgate</ref> never <ref target="#n088"
                  xml:id="a088">transported</ref>; and possibly originally were such, who<pb
                  n="215"/> understood neither the Laws of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> and had no
               sort of Principles to make 'em worthy the Name of Men: But, at the very Council
               Table, wou'd Contradict and Fight with one another; and Swear so bloodily that 'twas
               terrible to hear, and see 'em. (Some of 'em were afterwards Hang'd, when the
                  <hi>Dutch</hi> took possession of the place; others sent off in Chains:) But
               calling these special Rulers of the Nation together, and requiring their Counsel in
               this weighty Affair, they all concluded, that (Damn 'em) it might be their own Cases;
               and that <hi>Caesar</hi> ought to be made an Example to all the <hi>Negroes,</hi> to
               fright 'em from daring to threaten their Betters, their Lords<pb n="216"/> and
               Masters; and, at this rate, no Man was safe from his own <hi>Slaves;</hi> and
               concluded, <ref target="#n089" xml:id="a089">nemine contradicente</ref> that
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> shou'd be Hang'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trefry</hi> then thought it time to use his Authority; and told <hi>Byam</hi> his
               Command did not extend to his Lord's <hi>Plantation;</hi> and that <hi>Parham</hi>
               was as much exempt from the Law as <ref target="#n090" xml:id="a090"
                  >White-hall;</ref> and that they ought no more to touch the Servants of the
               Lord—(who there represented the King's Person) than they cou'd those about the King
               himself; and that <hi>Parham</hi> was a Sanctuary; and though his Lord were absent in
               Person, his Power was still in Being there; which he had intrusted with him, as far
               as the Dominions of his particular<pb n="217"/>
               <hi>Plantations</hi> reach'd, and all that belong'd to it; the rest of the
                  <hi>Country,</hi> as <hi>Byam</hi> was Lieutenant to his Lord, he might exercise
               his Tyrany upon. <hi>Trefry</hi> had others as powerful, or more, that int'rested
               themselves in <hi>Caesar</hi>'s Life, and absolutely said, He shou'd be Defended. So
               turning the <hi>Governor,</hi> and his wise Council, out of Doors, (for they sate at
                  <hi>Parham-house)</hi> they set a Guard upon our Landing Place, and wou'd admit
               none but those we call'd Friends to us and <hi>Caesar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Governor</hi> having remain'd wounded at <hi>Parham,</hi> till his recovery
               was compleated, <hi>Caesar</hi> did not know but he was still there; and indeed, for
               the most part, his time was spent there;<pb n="218"/> for he was one that lov'd to
               Live at other Peoples Expence; and if he were a Day absent, he was Ten present there;
               and us'd to Play, and Walk, and Hunt, and Fish, with <hi>Caesar.</hi> So that
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> did not at all doubt, if he once recover'd Strength, but he shou'd
               find an opportunity of being Reveng'd on him: Though, after such a Revenge, he cou'd
               not hope to Live; for if he escap'd the Fury of the <hi>English</hi>
               <ref target="#n091" xml:id="a091">Mobile</ref>, who perhaps wou'd have been glad of
               the occasion to have kill'd him, he was resolv'd not to survive his Whiping; yet he
               had, some tender Hours, a repenting Softness, which he called his fits of Coward;
               wherein he struggl'd with Love for the Victory of his Heart,<pb n="219"/> which took
               part with his charming <hi>Imoinda</hi> there; but, for the most part, his time was
               past in melancholy Thought, and black Designs; he consider'd, if he shou'd do this
               Deed, and Dye, either in the Attempt, or after it, he left his lovely
                  <hi>Imoinda</hi> a Prey, or at best a <hi>Slave,</hi> to the inrag'd Multitude;
               his great Heart cou'd not indure that Thought. <hi>Perhaps,</hi> said he, <hi>she may
                  be first Ravished by every Brute; exposed first to their nasty Lusts, and then a
                  shameful Death.</hi> No; he could not Live a Moment under that Apprehension, too
               insupportable to be born. These were his Thoughts, and his silent Arguments with his
               Heart, as he told us afterwards; so that now resolving not only<pb n="220"/> to kill
                  <hi>Byam,</hi> but all those he thought had inrag'd him; pleasing his great Heart
               with the fancy'd Slaughter he shou'd make over the whole Face of the
                  <hi>Plantation.</hi> He first resolv'd on a Deed, that (however Horrid it at first
               appear'd to us all) when we had heard his Reasons, we thought it Brave and Just:
               Being able to Walk, and, as he believ'd, fit for the Execution of his great Design,
               he beg'd <hi>Trefry</hi> to trust him into the Air, believing a Walk wou'd do him
               good; which was granted him, and taking <hi>Imoinda</hi> with him, as he us'd to do
               in his more happy and calmer Days, he led her up into a Wood, where, after (with a
               thousand Sighs, and long Gazing silently on her Face, while<pb n="221"/> Tears gust,
               in spight of him, from his Eyes) he told her his Design first of Killing her, and
               then his Enemies, and next himself, and the impossibility of Escaping, and therefore
               he told her the necessity of Dying; he found the Heroick Wife faster pleading for
               Death than he was to propose it, when she found his fix'd Resolution; and, on her
               Knees, besought him, not to leave her a Prey to his Enemies. He (griev'd to Death)
               yet pleased at her noble Resolution, took her up, and imbracing her, with all the
               Passion and Languishment of a dying Lover, drew his Knife to kill this Treasure of
               his Soul, this Pleasure of his Eyes; while Tears trickl'd down his Cheeks, hers were
               Smiling with Joy she <pb n="222"/> shou'd dye by so noble a Hand, and be sent in her
               own Country, (for that's their Notion of the next World) by him she so tenderly
               Lov'd, and so truly Ador'd in this; for Wives have a respect for their Husbands equal
               to what any other People pay a Deity; and when a Man finds any occasion to quit his
               Wife, if he love her, she dyes by his Hand; if not, he sells her, or suffers some
               other to kill her. It being thus; you may believe the Deed was soon resolv'd on; and
               'tis not to be doubted, but the Parting, the eternal Leave taking of Two such Lovers,
               so greatly Born, so <ref target="#n092" xml:id="a092">Sensible</ref>, so Beautiful,
               so Young, and so Fond, must be very Moving, as the Relation of it was to me
               afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="223"/> All that Love cou'd say in such cases, being ended; and all the
               intermitting Irresolutions being adjusted, the Lovely, Young, and Ador'd Victim lays
               her self down, before the Sacrificer; while he, with a Hand resolv'd, and a Heart
               breaking within, gave the Fatal Stroke; first, cutting her Throat, and then severing
               her, yet Smiling, Face from that Delicate Body, pregnant as it was with Fruits of
               tend' rest Love. As soon as he had done, he laid the Body decently on Leaves and
               Flowers; of which he made a Bed, and conceal'd it under the same <ref target="#n093"
                  xml:id="a093">cover-lid</ref> of Nature; only her Face he left yet bare to look
               on: But when he found she was Dead, and past all Retrieve, never more<pb n="224"/> to
               bless him with her Eyes, and soft Language; his Grief swell'd up to Rage; he Tore, he
               Rav'd he Roar'd, like some Monster of the Wood, calling on the lov'd Name of
                  <hi>Imoinda;</hi> a thousand times he turn'd the Fatal Knife that did the Deed,
               toward his own Heart, with a Resolution to go immediately after her; but dire
               Revenge, which now was a thousand times more fierce in his Soul than before, prevents
               him; and he wou'd cry out, <hi>No; since I have sacrificed</hi> Imoinda <hi>to my
                  Revenge, shall I loose that Glory which I have purchas'd so dear, as at the Price
                  of the fairest, dearest, softest Creature that ever Nature made? No, no!</hi>
               Then, at her Name, Grief wou'd get the ascendant of Rage, and he wou'd<pb n="225"/>
               lye down by her side, and water her Face with showers of Tears, which never were wont
               to fall from those Eyes: And however bent he was on his intended Slaughter, he had
               not power to stir from the Sight of this dear Object, now more Belov'd, and more
               Ador'd than ever.</p>
            <p>He remain'd in this deploring Condition for two Days, and never rose from the Ground
               where he had made his sad Sacrifice; at last, rousing from her side, and accusing
               himself with living too long, now <hi>Imoinda</hi> was dead; and that the Deaths of
               those barbarous Enemies were deferr'd too long, he resolv'd now to finish the great
               Work; but offering to rise, he found his Strength so decay'd,<pb n="226"/> that he
               reel'd to and fro, like Boughs assail'd by contrary Winds; so that he was forced to
               lye down again, and try to summons all his Courage to his Aid; he found his Brains
               turn round, and his Eyes were dizzy; and Objects appear'd not the same to him they
               were wont to do; his Breath was short; and all his Limbs surprised with a Faintness
               he had never felt before: He had not Eat in two Days, which was one occasion of this
               Feebleness, but excess of Grief was the greatest; yet still he hop'd he shou'd
               recover Vigour to act his Design; and lay expecting it yet six Days longer; still
               mourning over the dead Idol of his Heart, and striving every Day to rise, but cou'd
               not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="227"/> In all this time you may believe we were in no little affliction for
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> and his Wife; some were of Opinion he was escap'd never to
               return; others thought some Accident had hap'ned to him: But however, we fail'd not
               to send out an hundred People several ways to search for him; a Party, of about
               forty, went that way he took; among whom was <hi>Tuscan,</hi> who was perfectly
               reconcil'd to <hi>Byam;</hi> they had not gon very far into the Wood, but they smelt
               an unusual Smell, as of a dead Body; for Stinks must be very noisom that can be
               distinguish'd among such a quantity of Natural Sweets, as every Inch of that Land
               produces. So that they concluded they shou'd find him dead, or somebody that<pb
                  n="228"/> was so; they past on towards it, as Loathsom as it was, and made such a
               rusling among the Leaves that lye thick on the Ground, by continual Falling, that
                  <hi>Caesar</hi> heard he was approach'd; and though he had, during the space of
               these eight Days, endeavor'd to rise, but found he wanted Strength, yet looking up,
               and seeing his Pursuers, he rose, and reel'd to a Neighbouring Tree, against which he
               fix'd his Back; and being within a dozen Yards of those that advanc'd, and saw him;
               he call'd out to them, and bid them approach no nearer, if they wou'd be safe: So
               that they stood still, and hardly believing their Eyes, that wou'd perswade them that
               it was <hi>Caesar</hi> that spoke to 'em, so much was he alter'd; <pb n="229"/>they
               ask'd him, What he had done with his Wife? for they smelt a Stink that almost struck
               them dead. He, pointing to the dead Body, sighing, cry'd, <hi>Behold her there;</hi>
               they put off the Flowers that cover'd her with their Sticks, and found she was
               kill'd; and cry'd out, <hi>Oh Monster! that hast murther'd thy Wife:</hi> Then asking
               him, Why he did so cruel a Deed? He replied, he had no leasure to answer impertinent
               Questions; <hi>You may go back,</hi> continued he, <hi>and tell the Faithless
                  Governor, he may thank Fortune that I am breathing my last; and that my Arm is too
                  feeble to obey my Heart, in what it had design'd him:</hi> But his Tongue
               faultering, and trembling, he cou'd scarce end what he was saying. The <pb n="230"
                  /><hi>English</hi> taking Advantage by his Weakness, cry'd, <hi>Let us take him
                  alive by all means:</hi> He heard 'em; and, as if he had reviv'd from a Fainting,
               or a Dream, he cry'd out, <hi>No, Gentlemen, you are deceiv'd; you will find no
                  more</hi> Caesars <hi>to be Whipt; no more find a Faith in me: Feeble as you think
                  me, I have Strength yet left to secure me from a second Indignity.</hi> They swore
               all a-new, and he only shook his Head, and beheld them with Scorn; then they cry'd
               out, <hi>Who will venture on this single Man? Will no body?</hi> They stood all
               silent while <hi>Caesar</hi> replied, <hi>Fatal will be the Attempt to the first
                  Adventurer; let him assure himself,</hi> and, at that Word, held up his Knife in a
               menacing Posture, <hi>Look ye, ye faithless Crew,</hi> said he,<pb n="231"/>
               <hi>'tis not Life I seek, nor am I afraid of Dying;</hi> and, at that Word, cut a
               piece of Flesh from his own Throat, and threw it at 'em, <hi>yet still I wou'd Live
                  if I cou'd, till I had perfected my Revenge. But oh! it cannot be; I feel Life
                  gliding from my Eyes and Heart; and, if I make not haste, I shall yet fall a
                  Victim to the shameful Whip.</hi> At that, he rip'd up his own Belly; and took his
               Bowels and pull'd 'em out, with what Strength he cou'd; while some, on their Knees
               imploring, besought him to hold his Hand. But when they saw him tottering, they cry'd
               out, <hi>Will none venture on him?</hi> A bold <hi>English</hi> cry'd, <hi>Yes, if he
                  were the Devil;</hi> (taking Courage when he saw him almost Dead) and swearing a
               horrid Oath for his farewell<pb n="232"/> to the World; he rush'd on <hi>Caesar,</hi>
               with his Arm'd Hand met him so fairly, as stuck him to the Heart, and he fell Dead at
               his Feet. <hi>Tuscan</hi> seeing that, cry'd out, <hi>I love thee, oh</hi> Caesar;
                  <hi>and therefore will not let thee Dye, if possible:</hi> And, running to him,
               took him in his Arms; but, at the same time, warding a Blow that <hi>Caesar</hi> made
               at his Bosom, he receiv'd it quite through his Arm; and <hi>Caesar</hi> having not
               the Strength to pluck the Knife forth, though he attempted it, <hi>Tuscan</hi>
               neither pull'd it out himself, nor suffer'd it to be pull'd out; but came down with
               it sticking in his Arm; and the reason he gave for it was, because the Air shou'd not
               get into the Wound: They put their Hands a-cross, and carried<pb n="233"/>
               <hi>Caesar</hi> between Six of 'em, fainted as he was; and they thought Dead, or just
               Dying; and they brought him to <hi>Parham,</hi> and laid him on a Couch, and had the
               Chirurgeon immediately to him, who drest his Wounds, and sow'd up his Belly, and us'd
               means to bring him to Life, which they effected. We ran all to see him; and, if
               before we thought him so beautiful a Sight, he was now so alter'd, that his Face was
               like a Death's Head black'd over; nothing but Teeth, and Eyeholes: For some Days we
               suffer'd no body to speak to him, but caused Cordials to be poured down his Throat,
               which sustained his Life; and in six or seven Days he recover'd his Senses: For, you
               must know, that <pb n="234"/> Wounds are almost to a Miracle cur'd in the
                  <hi>Indies;</hi> unless Wounds in the Legs, which rarely ever cure.</p>
            <p>When he was well enough to speak, we talk'd to him; and ask'd him some Questions
               about his Wife, and the Reasons why he kill'd her; and he then told us what I have
               related of that Resolution, and of his Parting; and he besought us, we would let him
               Dye, and was extreamly Afflicted to think it was possible he might Live; he assur'd
               us, if we did not Dispatch him, he wou'd prove very Fatal to a great many. We said
               all we cou'd to make him Live, and gave him new Assurances; but he begg'd we wou'd
               not think so poorly of him, or of his love to <hi>Imoinda,</hi> to <pb n="235"
               />imagine we cou'd Flatter him to Life again; but the Chirurgeon assur'd him, he
               cou'd not Live, and therefore he need not Fear. We were all (but <hi>Caesar)</hi>
               afflicted at this News; and the Sight was <ref target="#n094" xml:id="a094"
                  >gashly</ref>; his Discourse was sad; and the earthly Smell about him so strong,
               that I was perswaded to leave the Place for some time; (being my self-but Sickly, and
               very apt to fall into Fits of dangerous Illness upon any extraordinary Melancholy)
               the Servants, and <hi>Trefry,</hi> and the Chirurgeons, promis'd all to take what
               possible care they cou'd of the Life of <hi>Caesar;</hi> and I, taking Boat, went
               with other Company to Colonel <hi>Martin</hi>'s, about three Days Journy down the
               River; but I was no sooner gon, but the<pb n="236"/>
               <hi>Governor</hi> taking <hi>Trefry,</hi> about some pretended earnest Business, a
               Days Journy up the River; having communicated his Design to one <hi>Banister,</hi> a
               wild <hi>Irish</hi>
               <ref target="#n095" xml:id="a095">Man</ref>, and one of the Council; a Fellow of
               absolute Barbarity, and fit to execute any Villany, but was Rich. He came up to
                  <hi>Parham,</hi> and forcibly took <hi>Caesar,</hi> and had him carried to the
               same Post where he was Whip'd; and causing him to be ty'd to it, and a great Fire
               made before him, he told him, he shou'd Dye like a Dog, as he was. <hi>Caesar</hi>
               replied, this was the first piece of Bravery that ever <hi>Banister</hi> did; and he
               never spoke Sence till he pronounc'd that Word; and, if he wou'd keep it, he wou'd
               declare, in the other World, that he was<pb n="237"/> the only Man, of all the
               Whites, that ever he heard speak Truth. And turning to the Men that bound him, he
               said, <hi>My Friends, am I to Dye, or to be Whip'd?</hi> And they cry'd, <hi>Whip'd!
                  no; you shall not escape so well:</hi> And then he replied, smiling, <hi>A
                  Blessing on thee;</hi> and assur'd them, they need not tye him, for he wou'd stand
               fixt, like a Rock; and indure Death so as shou'd encourage them to Dye. <hi>But if
                  you Whip me,</hi> said he, <hi>be sure you tye me fast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had learn'd to take Tobaco; and when he was assur'd he should Dye, he desir'd they
               would give him a Pipe in his Mouth, ready Lighted, which they did; and the
               Executioner came, and first cut off his Members,<pb n="238"/> and threw them into the
               Fire; after that, with an ill-favoured Knife, they cut his Ears, and his Nose, and
               burn'd them; he still Smoak'd on, as if nothing had touch'd him; then they hack'd off
               one of his Arms, and still he bore up, and held his Pipe; but at the cutting off the
               other Arm, his Head sunk, and his Pipe drop'd; and he gave up the Ghost, without a
               Groan, or a Reproach. My Mother and Sister were by him all the while, but not
               suffer'd to save him; so rude and wild were the Rabble, and so inhumane were the
               Justices, who stood by to see the Execution, who after paid dearly enough for their
               Insolence. They cut <hi>Caesar</hi> in Quarters, and sent them to several of the
                  chief<pb n="239"/><hi>Plantations:</hi> One Quarter was sent to Colonel
                  <hi>Martin,</hi> who refus'd it; and swore, he had rather see the Quarters of
                  <hi>Banister,</hi> and the <hi>Governor</hi> himself, than those of
                  <hi>Caesar,</hi> on his <hi>Plantations;</hi> and that he cou'd govern his
                  <hi>Negroes</hi> without Terrifying and Grieving them with frightful Spectacles of
               a mangl'd King.</p>
            <p>Thus Dy'd this Great Man; worthy of a better Fate, and a more sublime Wit than mine
               to write his Praise; yet, I hope, the Reputation of my Pen is considerable enough to
               make his Glorious Name to survive to all Ages; with that of the Brave, the Beautiful,
               and the Constant <hi>Imoinda.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="annotations">
            <note xml:id="n002" target="a002" type="gloss"> Precedents </note>
            <note xml:id="n003" target="a003" type="gloss">Not only one who has observed something
               firsthand, but in a legal sense, one who is "able to describe or testify to it."
               (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n004" target="a004" type="gloss">A colony neighbored by Brazil to the
               south and Guiana to the West. At the time of the action of the story, the colony was
               in British control, but it was lost to the Dutch shortly thereafter</note>
            <note xml:id="n005" target="a005" type="gloss">A particularly tiny species of monkey
               that is, indeed, about the size of a mouse. Notably adorable.</note>
            <note xml:id="n006" target="a006" type="gloss">It is not clear what kind of animal Behn
               is referring to here, but it probably a species of feline.</note>
            <note xml:id="n007" target="a007" type="gloss">An "antiquary" was a collection of
               unusual and exotic items. Janet Todd suggests that this could be a reference to the
               museum of the Royal Society in London. The singular form "antiquary" could describe a
               collector of antiques or rare objects.</note>
            <note xml:id="n008" target="a008" type="gloss">Here is an image of Anne Bracegirdle,
               performing in John Dryden's play <hi>The Indian Queen,</hi> wearing the feathered
               headress referred to in this passage. Whether this headdress was the same one that
               Behn brought back to England from Surinam in the 1660s is impossible to know at this
               point. <graphic class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2005"
                  src="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Indianqueen.jpg"
                  alt="Indianqueen.jpg" width="220" height="300"/>(Folger Shakespeare
               Library)</note>
            <note xml:id="n009" target="a009" type="gloss">Behn is describing the process of
               piercing ears and other parts of the body</note>
            <note xml:id="n010" target="a010" type="gloss">Coramantien was the name both of
               slave-trading castle, depicted here, and of the coastal area of what is now the
               nation of Ghana where several such fortified trading posts were located. In the
               1660s, when this story is set, both English and Dutch slave traders used the fort at
               Coramantien. By the late seventeenth century, it was controlled by the Dutch, who
               renamed it Fort Amsterdam. Its ruins can still be visited today. <ref
                  target="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/FortAmsterdamCormantine.jpg"
                  rel="attachment wp-att-2408"><graphic
                     class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-2408"
                     url="http://virginia-anthology.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/FortAmsterdamCormantine-300x206.jpg"
                     alt="FortAmsterdamCormantine" width="300" height="206"/></ref></note>
            <note xml:id="n011" target="a011" type="gloss">The English Civil Wars of 1642 1649
               between the supporters of the Stuart monarchy and the supporters of Parliament, which
               led to the execution of Charles I in 1649.</note>
            <note xml:id="n012" target="a012 a013" type="gloss">Behn's emphasis on Oroonoko's
               knowledge of French and English associates him with civilized Europeans; eloquent
               Africans in European literature were often imagined as here, as more European than
               African.</note>
            <note xml:id="n014" target="a014" type="gloss">An artist who makes statues, a sculptor
               of statues. (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n015" target="a015" type="gloss">awe-inspiring</note>
            <note xml:id="n016" target="a016" type="gloss">excepting</note>
            <note xml:id="n017" target="a017" type="gloss">prudent, shrewd, sagacious (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n018" target="a018" type="gloss">a protective cloak or garment; a loose,
               sleeveless cloak. (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n019" target="a019" type="gloss">A veil delivered by the king as an
               invitation to his harem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n020" target="a020" type="gloss">That is, the King is impotent. It's
               notable that the narrator thinks first of the potential cost to Oroonoko rather than
               the cost to Imoinda.</note>
            <note xml:id="n021" target="a021" type="gloss">"Otan" seems to be derived from the
               Turkish word "odan," referring to a room or small enclosure in a harem. This is one
               of the moments when this part of the story, though set in Africa, feels more like an
               "Oriental" tale.</note>
            <note xml:id="n022" target="a022" type="gloss">Oroonoko is actually his grandson.</note>
            <note xml:id="n023" target="a023" type="gloss">Discarded, former mistresses</note>
            <note xml:id="n024" target="a024" type="gloss">Here Behn seems to be informed by
               knowledge of African religious traditions, as such references to a sky deity appear
               there, but we do not know her source for this term.</note>
            <note xml:id="n025" target="a025" type="gloss">In spite of</note>
            <note xml:id="n026" target="a026" type="gloss">Chagrin; that is, disappointment or
               vexation</note>
            <note xml:id="n027" target="a027" type="gloss">The commander of the ship</note>
            <note xml:id="n028" target="a028" type="gloss">Pledge, oath</note>
            <note xml:id="n029" target="a029" type="gloss">Dark-skinned children, usually of African
               descent. The term is likely a pidgin form of the Portuguese word pequenino.</note>
            <note xml:id="n030" target="a030" type="gloss">Lord Willoughby was the governor of
               Surinam and the owner of the Parham plantation. Trefy was there to oversee the
               plantation in Willoughby's absence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n031" target="a031" type="gloss">clothing</note>
            <note xml:id="n032" target="a032" type="gloss">An altered from of bakra, buckra, or
               buccra, a word used in Surinam for master.</note>
            <note xml:id="n033" target="a033" type="gloss">The Suriname River</note>
            <note xml:id="n034" target="a034" type="gloss">A kind of coarse linen used for
               hard-wearing clothing that was produced in Osnabruck, Germany. (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n035" target="a035" type="gloss">Slaves were often given the names of
               powerful Romans, which was often a way of mocking their profound lack of power. Here,
               too, as Janet Todd notes, Behn sometimes referred to James II as Caesar, so this
               forms another link between Oroonoko and the Stuart monarchy.</note>
            <note xml:id="n036" target="a036" type="gloss">Surinam was turned over to the Dutch in
               the Treaty of Breda in 1667, just after the action of this story takes place.</note>
            <note xml:id="n037" target="a037" type="gloss">The main house on the Parham
               plantation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n038" target="a038" type="gloss">A Spanish or Portugese nobleman of the
               highest rank (OED).</note>
            <note xml:id="n039" target="a039" type="gloss">In the first edition, there is a page
               number skip from page 112 to page 129. One possible explanation for this as that a
               sheet, which would have had exactly sixteen pages in the original octavo format of
               this book, was removed for corrections. When he returned the sheet with the corrected
               type, the printed continued with the original pagination of the preceding sheet,
               perhaps forgetting that sixteen page numbers would then be missing. No text is
               missing; it's simply an error in pagination.</note>
            <note xml:id="n040" target="a040" type="gloss">To Behn and her readers, the word "novel"
               would have been associated with short romantic stories set among the aristocracy; the
               story of Oroonoko and Imoinda that Trefry has just heard fits that definition.
               "Novel" only gained its modern sense decades later.</note>
            <note xml:id="n041" target="a041" type="gloss">To cut or slash (a shoe, item of
               clothing) for decorative purposes. Obs. (OED, “race”)</note>
            <note xml:id="n042" target="a042" type="gloss">Lacquered, or covered with a glossy
               material; in this period, highly-lacquered glossy black surfaces were associated with
               Japan, which exported such goods to Europe.</note>
            <note xml:id="n043" target="a043" type="gloss">The Picts were an ancient tribe in the
               northern part of Britain who painted and tattooed their bodies. The engravings of
               Picts in Thomas Hariot’s A Brief and True Report of the New Found Land of Virginia
               (1588) are accompanied by the comment that "the markings of the Picts were similar to
               those of the Native Americans in Virginia.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n044" target="a044" type="gloss">The reference here is to Alexander the
               Great, who by legend met Thallestris, the Queen of the Amazons, a race of female
               warriors, whose home was near the river Jaxartes, which reportedly had
               brightly-colored poisonous snakes. There is no historical evidence for this, but the
               stories were told over and over again in historical romances from antiquity onwards,
               which is the context that Behn is invoking here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n045" target="a045" type="gloss">Fragrant bouquets</note>
            <note xml:id="n046" target="a046" type="gloss">Pall Mall, one of the straightest avenues
               in London, well known in Behn's era as a place for the socially ambitious to
               promenade.</note>
            <note xml:id="n047" target="a047" type="gloss">There are, of course, no tigers in
               Surinam, so either Behn is thinking of some other kind of large carnivore such a
               jaguar (which does exist in Surinam), or is fancifully adding this detail.</note>
            <note xml:id="n048" target="a048" type="gloss">Mothers</note>
            <note xml:id="n049" target="a049" type="gloss">Follower of Oliver Cromwell, the leader
               of the Parliamentary forces in the Civil War and head of the Commonwealth government
               that ruled England in the 1650s.</note>
            <note xml:id="n050" target="a050" type="gloss">An electric eel</note>
            <note xml:id="n051" target="a051" type="gloss">An ell is a unit of measurement; it
               varied from place to place and at different times, but an English ell of this period
               would have been about 45 inches</note>
            <note xml:id="n052" target="a052" type="gloss">Behn’s description of Native American
               gentleness and fascination with European dress and trinkets is an exploitive theme
               common throughout early colonial American literature. In most of the colonial
               writings regarding Native Americans, the tribes encountered are often depicted as
               subservient and attracted to lustrous items rather than those things which might
               possess monetary value. Writers of the period employed instances of civil exchange,
               fascination, and amity between white Europeans and Native Americans to engender
               merchants to settle the New World as well as convince wealthy aristocrats and
               merchants to patron campaigns to westernize and impose dominion by means of Christian
               conversion.</note>
            <note xml:id="n053" target="a053" type="gloss">Janet Todd notes that the phrase Amora
               tiguamy appears in Antione Biet’s Voyage de la France équixonale en l’isle de Cayenne
               (1654, pp. 395-7). Todd argues that Behn records a traditional greeting and provides
               the translation herself; however, it should be noted that the term Amora has
               connection with the Latin Amore, suggesting that Behn plays with contemporary
               accounts and phonetics to further depict the indigenous characters as loving and
               peaceful. The phrase likely developed out of interactions between the natives and the
               Spanish.</note>
            <note xml:id="n054" target="a054" type="gloss">Todd notes that Behn borrowed the word
               sarumbo from Biet as well; Biet observes that these large leaves were used as
               napkins.</note>
            <note xml:id="n055" target="a055" type="gloss">A serving of food; a course; or a meal
               (OED).</note>
            <note xml:id="n056" target="a056" type="gloss">A lens, by which the rays of the sun may
               be concentrated on an object, so as to burn it if combustible (OED).</note>
            <note xml:id="n057" target="a057" type="gloss">Juggling or conjuring tricks. Deception,
               from the French leger de main, literally "light of hand."</note>
            <note xml:id="n058" target="a058" type="gloss">Behn describes the tribe as passing down
               its highest artistic and scientific knowledge to a select member who undergoes
               rigorous training from youth. This pattern relates to ideal models of aristocratic
               education in European society.</note>
            <note xml:id="n059" target="a059" type="gloss">Todd notes that Behn may have borrowed
               from Biet yet again. Biet claims Indians wore a small piece of clothing called a
               camison.</note>
            <note xml:id="n060" target="a060" type="gloss">Jealousy, resentment, or discontent.
               Grudges (OED).</note>
            <note xml:id="n061" target="a061" type="gloss">Months</note>
            <note xml:id="n062" target="a062" type="gloss">Europeans still believed that a golden
               city, or El Dorado, existed in the South American mountains</note>
            <note xml:id="n063" target="a063" type="gloss">Todd explains that this is a geographic
               blunder. The mouth of the Amazon is in Brazil, but cartographers had drawn it as the
               south-eastern border of “Guiana” throughout the seventeenth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n064" target="a064" type="gloss">A tirade. The term first appears c1450,
               but only in Scottish writings. It was not used in England until c1600. It derives
               from medieval Latin harenga, which shares the current definition, and the Italian
               aringo, a place of declamation, arena.</note>
            <note xml:id="n065" target="a065" type="gloss">The Day of Judgment.</note>
            <note xml:id="n066" target="a066" type="gloss">Oroonoko here is expressing what was
               known as the "just war" doctrine of slavery, that those who lost a war could rightly
               be enslaved. It is on this basis that Oroonoko himself owns slaves. The distinction
               he is making here is that, according to this doctrine, slaves gained through conquest
               are justified while slaves acquired through trickery or commerce are not.</note>
            <note xml:id="n067" target="a067" type="gloss">Renegades</note>
            <note xml:id="n068" target="a068" type="gloss">Tuscan’s name derives from the late Latin
               Tuscānus meaning “of or belonging to the Tuscī or Thuscī, a people of ancient Italy
               (called also Etruscī Etruscans)” (OED). The Etruscans inhabited ancient Etruria, so
               Tuscan’s name implies nobility and European origins.</note>
            <note xml:id="n069" target="a069" type="gloss">According to the Roman historian
               Plutarch, the Carthaginian general Hannibal used vinegar and fire to burn his way
               through the Alps to attack the Roman army.</note>
            <note xml:id="n070" target="a070" type="gloss">Of high social standing; the upper
               class</note>
            <note xml:id="n071" target="a071" type="gloss">Poorly treated</note>
            <note xml:id="n072" target="a072" type="gloss">Subjected to public disgrace (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n074" target="a074" type="gloss">William Byam is a real historical
               personage, noted both in Antione Biet’s Voyage de la France équixonale en l’isle de
               Cayenne (1654) and Henry Adis’s A Letter Sent from Syrrinam (1664). As deputy
               governor of Surinam, Byam ruled the colony in the absence of Lord Willoughby.
               According to Flannigan’s Antigua and the Antiguans. A Full Account of the Colony and
               its Inhabitants, after the Dutch takeover of Surinam, Byam led many of the British
               colonists to Antigua, where became governor and lived until c. 1670. Todd notes that
               both Biet and Adis, otherwise critical of the colony in Surinam, praise Byam: Adis
               refers to him as “that worthy person, whom your Lordship hath lately honoured with
               the Title and Power of your Lieutenant General of this Continent of Guinah”; while
               Biet describes him as brave, honorable, and civil (pp. 263, 279). Behn’s decision to
               portray him as cowardly and deceitful appears to have been her own. On the other
               hand, Byam did face accusations of unnecessary cruelty in his governance from an
               opposition group led by John Allin. Byam wrote a tract An Exact Relation of the Most
               Execrable Attempts of John Allin (1665) defending the need for harsh measures to
               govern the unruly colonists and accusing Allin of insurrection.</note>
            <note xml:id="n075" target="a075" type="gloss">More commonly cat-o'-nine-tails, a whip
               with nine knotted lashes, often used for corporal punishment in the British military
               until 1881. (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n076" target="a076" type="gloss">Defensive hilts on the handle of a sword
               consisting of narrow plates of steel curved into the shape of a basket</note>
            <note xml:id="n077" target="a077" type="gloss"><note xml:id="n078" target="a078"
                  type="gloss">Unpremeditated</note>Followed his own judgment</note>
            <note xml:id="n079" target="a079" type="gloss"><note xml:id="n080" target="a080"
                  type="gloss">Tiresome, exhausting</note>Draw near to</note>
            <note xml:id="n081" target="a081" type="gloss">An allusion to the Furies, three mythical
               Greek goddesses of vengeance and punishment, best known for punishing those who swear
               false oaths and, especially, those who kill their own kin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n082" target="a082" type="gloss">Todd notes that a Colonel Marten of the
               Surinam militia appears in multiple historical accounts of the colony, although the
               authority under which he was styled colonel is dubious. In contrast to Behn’s
               positive portrayal, Robert Sanford depicts Marten in Surinam Justice (1662) with many
               of the negative traits assigned to Byam and other colonists by Behn: he is eager to
               commit violent acts, cruel, ill-tempered, profane, and “so famous in nothing as his
               variety of councels: and it seems the whole bulk of Government must dance to the
               changes of his brain."Colonel Martin indeed appears as a character in Behn's play The
               Younger Brother, Or, The Amorous Jilt. Behn's self-promotion is premature, however,
               since the play was not produced until 1696, seven years after her death</note>
            <note xml:id="n083" target="a083" type="gloss">Surgeon</note>
            <note xml:id="n084" target="a084" type="gloss">A room in a house designed for the use of
               a particular person</note>
            <note xml:id="n085" target="a085" type="gloss">Threats</note>
            <note xml:id="n086" target="a086" type="gloss">imitate, deride, or amuse (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n087" target="a087" type="gloss">The central prison in London</note>
            <note xml:id="n088" target="a088" type="gloss">Throughout this period, many criminals
               found guilty of crimes against property in Britain were sentenced by being
               "transported" or exiled for a period of years to the colonies.</note>
            <note xml:id="n089" target="a089" type="gloss">With no one speaking to the
               contrary.</note>
            <note xml:id="n090" target="a090" type="gloss">Offices of government in Whitehall,
               London. Trefry's implication is that Byam, although governor of Surinam, remains as
               subordinate to the King as any civil servant back in Great Britain.</note>
            <note xml:id="n091" target="a091" type="gloss">The mob, the rabble; the common people,
               the populace (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n092" target="a092" type="gloss">Capable of or liable to mental emotion.
               Having sensibility; capable of delicate or tender feeling. (OED)</note>
            <note xml:id="n093" target="a093" type="gloss">Coverlet, blanket</note>
            <note xml:id="n094" target="a094" type="gloss">Ghastly</note>
            <note xml:id="n095" target="a095" type="gloss">Major James Bannister was responsible for
               negotiating with the Dutch when England ceded Surinam in 1667. According to Todd, in
               1671, he led “about a hundred families to Jamaica where he joined forces with
               governor Sir Thomas Lynch who was trying to suppress a rival, backed by other
               ex-Surinam settlers” (Saunders Webb, 97). Bannister then became major-general of
               Jamaica. Bannister was killed in 1673 by Mr. Burford, a surveyor-general, who was
               then hanged.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
