<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="julian-revelation">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Revelation of Divine Love</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="79089397">
                      <name>Julian of Norwich</name>  
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>      
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#StudStaff"
                        >Students and Staff of the University of Virginia</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                
            </titleStmt>
                   <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Department of English, University of Virginia</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22901-4121</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>      
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author><name>Julian of Norwich</name></author>
                        <title>A Revelation of Divine Love</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7012005">Norwich</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>np, manuscript</publisher>
                            <date when="c.1400">1400</date>
                            <note>Julian of Norwich's text, which has gone by the name <hi rend="italic">Revelations of Divine Love</hi>, exists in a number of different manuscript copies, none of which are by Julian herself, and most of which date to decades after her death in the early fifteenth century. The manuscripts are usually divided into what are known as the "Long Text" and the "Short Text" for obvious reasons. The Short Text is believed by scholars to have been written around the time that Julian reported having the mystical experience it recounts, which occurred in 1373. The Long Text was probably written much later, perhaps two or three decades after the Short Text. Various manuscript versions of both texts, produced in the fifteenth, sixteenth, and seventeenth centuries, largerly by nuns in England and France, exist; the Long Text was first published in 1670 by Serenus de Cressy, a priest who was associated with a group of English nuns in France. This edition, which is of the Long Text and preserves the Middle English that Julian wrote in, is based on the version edited by Marion Glasscoe and published by Exeter University in the 1970s as part of its Series in Medieval Literature and digitized by the Oxford Text Archive. </note>                       
                        </imprint>                   
                    </monogr>            
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
           <profileDesc> 
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
               <creation/>
            <textDesc n="vision">
                <channel mode="w">manuscript</channel>
                <constitution type="single">single vision</constitution>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="inapplicable"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="inspire" degree="high"/>
               </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>        
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7012005">Norwich, England</name>
                    <time from="1340" to="1420">Late Middle Ages</time>               
                </setting>           
            </settingDesc>
            </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, reliable, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is was initially funded by the National Endowment for the
                    Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount
                    University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section for more information.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgm">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
           
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2001-1-12" who="Colley, Greg">
         Header recomposed with TEIXML header
            </change>
            <change when="1997-12-18" who="Burnard, Lou">
                Header auto-generated from TOMES
            </change>
            <change when="2023-11-8" who="editors.xml#JOB">
                prepared text for Literature in Context edition
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Revelations to one who could not read a letter.</head> 
                <head> Anno Domini, 1373.</head>
                <div type="chapter">
<head>1. A particular of the chapters.</head>
                    <lb/>

<p>The first chapter - off the noumber of the revelations particularly.</p>
<p>This is a revelation of love that Iesus Christ, our endless blisse,
made in xvi sheweings or revelations particular; off the which
the first is of his pretious coroning with thornys; and therewith
was comprehended and specifyed the Trinite with the incarnation
and unite betwix God and man soule, with many faire sheweings
of endless wisedome and teacheing of love, in which all the
sheweings that follow be grounded and onyd. The iid is the discolloureing of his faire face in tokenyng of his deareworthy
passion. The iiid is that our lord God, almighty wisedome, all
love, right as verily as he hath made every thing that is, also
verily he doith and workeith all thing that is done. The iiiith
is the scourgeing of his tender body with plentious sheddyng of
his blood. The vth is that the fend is overcome by the pretious
passion of Christe. The vi is the worshippfull thankeing of our
lord God in which he rewardeth his blissed servants in hevyn.
The vii is often feeleing of wele and wo - feleing of wele is
gracious touching and lightening, with trew sekirness of endless
ioy; the feleing of wo is temptation be heavyness and irkehede of
our fleshly liveing - with ghostly understanding that we arn kept
aso sekirly in love, in wo as in wele, be the godeness of God.
The viii is the last paynes of Christ and his cruelle dyeing. The
ix is of the likeing which is in the blissefull Trinite of the
herde passion of Christe and his rewfull dyeing; in which ioy and
likeing he will wee be solacid and myrthid with him till whan we
come to the fullhede in heavyn. The xth is our lord lesus shewith
in love his blissefull herte even cloven on two enioyand. The xi
is an hey ghostly sheweing of his deareworthy moder. The xii is
that our lord is most worthy be ing. The xiii is that our lord God
wil we have gret regard to all the deeds that he hath done in the
gret nobleth of all things makyng, and of the excellency of man
makeyng, which is above ill his workes, and of the pretious asseth
that he hath made for ian synne, turneing'all our blame into end-
lesse worshippe; where also our lord seith: "Behold and see; for
be the same mightie wisedome and goodnesse I shall make w(e)le
all that is not wele and thou shalt see it.' And in this he will
we keepe us in the feith and trowthe of holy church, not willing
to wete his privityes now, but as it longyth to us in this life.
The xiiii is that our lord is ground of our beseekeing. Herein'
were seene ii properties: that one is rightfull prayer, that other
is sekir truste, which he will both be alike large; and thus our
prayers likyth him and he of his goodnesse fullfilleth it. The
xvth, that we shall sodenly be taken from al our peyne and from
all our wo and, of his goodnesse, we shall come up aboven where
we shall have our lord lesus to our mede and be fullfilled of ioy
and blisse in hevyn. The xvi is that the blissefull Trinite our
maker, in Christe Iesus our saviour, endlessely wonyth in our
soule, worshipfully reuland and geveand all things, us mightily
and wisely saveand and keepeand for love, and we shall not be
overcome of our enemy.</p>
 </div>
       <div type="chapter">
      
<head>2. The ii chapter - of the tyme of these revelations, and how she
    asked iii petitions.</head>
           <lb/>
<p>These revelations were shewed to a simple creature that cowde no
letter, the yeere of our lord 1373, the viiith day of May; which
creature desired afore iii gifts of God: the first was mende of his
passion, the ii was bodily sekenesse in youth at xxx yeeres of
age, the iii was to have of Gods gift iii wounds. As in the first
methought I had sume feleing in the passion of Christe but yet
I desired more be the grace of God. Methought I would have beene
that time with Mary Magdalen and with other that were Crists lovers,
and therefore I desired a bodily sight wherein I might have more
knowledge of the bodily peynes of our saviour, and of the compassion
(of) our lady and of all his trew lovers that seene that time his
peynes, for I would be one of them and suffer with him. Other sight
ner sheweing of God desired I never none till the soule was departid
fro the body. The cause of this petition was that after the sheweing
I should have the more trew minde in the passion of Christe. The
iid came to my mynde with contrition, frely desireing that seke-
nesse so herde as to deth that I might, in that sekeness, vnder-
fongyn all my rites of holy church, myselfe weneing that I should
dye, and that all creatures might suppose the same that seyen me;
for I would have no manner comfort of eardtly life. In this sike-
nesse I desired to have all manier peynes bodily and ghostly that
I should have if I should dye, with all the dreds and tempests of
the fends, except the outpassing of the soule. And this I ment
for I would be purged be the mercy of God and after lyven more
to the worshippe of God because of that sekenesse; and that for
the more speede in my deth, for I desired to be soone with my
God. These ii desires of the passion and the sekenesse I desired
with a condition, ssey(ing) thus: "Lord, thou wotith what I would -
if it be thy will that I have it; and if it be not thy will, good
lord, be not displeased, for I will nought but as thou wilt.' For
the iii, by the grace of God and teachyng of holy church, I con-
ceived a mighty desire to receive iii wounds in my life: that is
to sey the wound of very contrition, the wound of kinde compassion
and the wound of willfull longing to God. And all this last petition
I asked without any condition. These ii desires foresaid passid
fro my minde, and the iiid dwelled with me continually.</p>

                <div type="chapter">
<head>3. Of the sekenese opteyned of God be petition - iii chapter.</head>
                    <lb/>               
<p>And when I was thirty yers old and halfe God sent me a bodely
sekeness in which I lay iii dayes and iii nights; and on the fourth
night I tooke all my rites of holy church and wened not a levyd
till day. And after this I langorid forth ii dayes and ii nights.
And on the iii night I wened oftentimes to have passyd, and so
wened they that were with me. And in youngith yet, I thought great
sweeme to dye; but for nothing (that) was in earth that me lekid
to levin for, ne for no peyne that I was aferd of, for I trusted
in God of his mercy; but it was to have lyved that I might have
loved God better and longer tyme, that I might have the more knoweing
and lovyng of God in blisse of hevyn. For methought all the time
that I had lived here, so little and so short in reward of that
endlesse blisse - I thought nothing. Wherefore I thought: "Good
lord, may my living no longer be to thy worshippe!' And I under-
stood by my reason and be my feleing of my peynes that I should
dye. And I assented fully with all, with all the will of my herte,
to be at God will. Thus I durid till day, and be than my body was
dede fro the middis downewards as to my feleing. Then was I stered
to be sett upright, underlenand with helpe, for to have more fredam
of my herte to be at Gods will, and thinkeing on God while my life
would lest. My curate was sent for to be at my endeing, and by
than he cam I had sett my eyen and might not speke. He sett the
cross before my face and seid: "I have browte thee the image of
thy maker and saviour. Louke thereupon and comfort thee therewith.'
Methought I was wele, for my eyen were sett uprightward into hevyn
where I trusted to come be the mercy of God. But nevertheless I
assented to sett my eyen in the face of the crucifix if I might,
and so I dede, for methought I might longer duren to loke even-
forth than right up. After this my sight began to failen and it
was all derke about me in the chamber as it had be night, save
in the image of the cross wherein I beheld a comon light, and I
wiste not how. All that was beside the cross was uggely to me as
if it had be mekil occupyed with the fends. After this the other
party of my body began to dyen so ferforth that onethys I had
ony feleing, with shortness of onde. And than I went sothly to
have passid. And, in this, sodenly all my peyne was taken fro me
and I was as hele, and namely in the other party of my body, as
ever I was aforn. I mervalid at this soden change for methought
it was a privy workeing of God and not of kinde. And yet by the
feleing of this ease I trusted never the more to levyn; ne the
feleing of this ease was no full ease to me, for methought I had
lever a be deliveryd of this world. Than came suddenly to my minde
that I should desyre the second wounde, of our lords gracious gift,
that my body might be fullfilled with minde and felyng of his blissid
passion; for I would that his peynes were my peynes with compassion,
and afterward longeing to God. But in this I desired never bodily
sight nor sheweing of God, but compassion, as a kinde soule might
have with our lord Iesus, that for love would beene a dedely man;
and therefore I desired to suffer with him.</p>

                    <div type="chapter">
<head>4. Here begynnith the first revelation of the pretious crownyng of
Criste etc. in the first chapter; and how God fullfilleth the herrte
with most ioy, and of his greate meekenesse, and how the syght
of the passion of Criste is sufficient strength ageyn all temp-
tations of the fends, and of the gret excellency and mekenesse
of the blissid virgin Mary - the iiii chapter.</head>
                        <lb/>
<p>In this sodenly I saw the rede blode trekelyn downe fro under the
garlande, hote and freisly and ryth plenteously, as it were in
the time of his passion that the garlande of thornys was pressid
on his blissid hede, ryte so both God and man, the same that
sufferd thus for me. I conceived treuly and mightily that it was
himselfe shewed it me without ony mene. And in the same sheweing
sodenly the Trinite fullfilled the herte most of ioy. And so I
understood it shall be in hevyn withoute end to all that shall
come there. For the Trinite is God, God is the Trinite; the
Trinite is our maker and keeper, the Trinite is our everlasting
lover, everlasting ioy and blisse, be our lord Iesus Christ. And
this was shewed in the first and in all; for where Iesus appereith
the blissid Trinite is understond, as to my sight. And I said:
"Benedicite domine!' This I said, for reverence in my meneing
with a mighty voice; and full gretly was astonyed for wonder snd
mervel that I had that he that is so reverend and dredfull will
be so homely with a synfull creture liveing in wretched flesh.
This I tooke for the time of my temptation, for methowte by the
sufferance of God, I should be tempted of fends or I dyed. With
this sight of the blissid passion with the Godhede that I saw
in myne understonding, I knew wele that it was strength enow to
me, ya and to all creturers leving, ageyn all the fends of hell
and ghostly temptation. In this he browght our blissid lady to
my understonding. I saw hir ghostly in bodily likeness, a simple
mayde and a meke, young of age and little waxen above a child,
in the stature that she was wan she conceived with child. Also
God shewid in party the wisedam and the trueth of hir soule,
wherein I understood the reverend beholding that she beheld hir
God and maker, mervelyng with greate reverence that he would be
borne of hir that was a simple creature of his makeyng. And this
wisdam and trueth, knowyng the greteness of (her) maker and the
littlehede of hirselfe that is made, caused hir sey full mekely
to Gabriel: "Lo me, Gods handmayd.' In this sight I undestoode
sothly that she is mare than all that God made beneath hir in
worthyness and grace; for aboven hir is nothing that is made but
the blissid (manhood) of Criste, as to my sight.
</p></div>

<div type="chapter">
<head>5. How God is to us everything that is gode, tenderly wrappand us;
amd all thing that is made, in regard to almighty God, it is
nothing; and how man hath no rest till he nowteth himselfe and
all thing for the love of God - the v chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>In this same time our lord shewed to me a ghostly sight of his
homely loveing. I saw that he is to us everything that is good
and comfortable for us. He is our clotheine that for love wrappith us,(halseth)us and all beclosyth us for tender love, that hee map
never leave us, being to us althing that is gode, as to myne under-
stondyng. Also in this he shewed a littil thing, the quantitye
of an hesil nutt in the palme of my hand; and it was as round as
a balle. I lokid thereupon with eye of my understondyng and thowte:
"What may this be?' And it was generally answered thus: "It is
all that is made.' I mervellid how it might lesten, for methowte
it might suddenly have fallen to nowte for littil. And I was ans-
wered in my understondyng: "It lesteth and ever shall, for God
loveth it; and so allthing hath the being be the love of God.'
In this littil thing I saw iii properties: the first is that
God made it, the second is that God loveth it, the iiid, that
God kepith it. But what is to me sothly the maker, the keper, and
the lover I canot tell; for, till I am substantially onyd to him,
I may never have full rest ne very blisse; that is to sey, that
I be so festined to him that there is right nowte that is made
betwix my God and me. It needyth us to have kmoweing of the
littlehede of creatures and to nowtyn all thing that is made for
to love and have God that is unmade. For this is the cause why
we be not all in ease of herete and soule: for we sekyn here rest
in these things that is so littil, wherin is no rest, and know
not our God that is almighty, al wise, all gode; for he is the
very rest. God will be knowen, and him liketh that we rest in him;
for all that is beneth him sufficeth not us; and this is the cause
why that no soule is restid till it is nowted of all things that
is made. Whan he is willfully nowtid, for love to have him that is
all, then is he abyl to receive ghostly rest. Also our lord God
shewed that it is full gret plesance to him that a sily soule come
to him nakidly and pleynly and homely. For this is the kinde
yernings of the soule by the touching of the Holy Ghost, as be the
understondyng that I have in this sheweing: "God, of thy goodnesse,
give me thyselfe; for thou art enow to me and I may nothing aske
that is less that may be full worshippe to thee. And if I aske
anything that is lesse, ever me wantith, but only in thee I have
all.' And these words arn full lovesome to the soule and full nere
touchen the will of God and his goodness; for his goodness com-
prehendith all his creatures and all his blissid works, and over-
passith without end, for he is the endleshede. And he hath made
us only to himselfe and restorid us be his blissid passion and
kepith us in his blissid love. And all this is of his goodness.</p></div>


<div type="chapter">

<head>6. How we shold pray, of the gret tender love that our lord hath to
mannes soule willing us to be occupyed in knowing and loveing of
him - the vi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>This sheweing was made to lerne our soule wisely to clevyn to the
goodnes of God. And in that time the custome of our prayeing was
browte to mende: how we use, for lak of understonding and knowing
of love, to make many menys. Than saw I sothly that is more wor-
shippe to God, and more very delite, that we faithfully pray to
himselfe of his goodness and clevyn thereto be his grace, with
trew understondyng and stedfast be love, than if we made all the
menys that herte can thinke; for if we make all these menys, it
is to litil and not full worshippe to God, but in his goodnes is
all the hole, and there failith right nowte. For thus, as I shall
say, came to my minde in the same time: we pray to God for his
holy flesh and for his pretious blode, his holy passion, his deare-
worthy death and wounds, and all the blissid kindenes, the endles
life, that we have of all this is his goodnes; and we pray him
for his sweete moder love that him bare, and all the helpe we have
of her is of his (g)odeness; and we pray by his holy cross that
he dyed on, and all the vertue and the helpe that we have of the
cross, it is of his godeness. And on the same wise, all the helpe
that we have of special saints and all the blissed company of
hevyn, the dereworthy love and endles freindshippe that we have
of them, it is of his godenes; for God of his godenes hath ordeyned
meanys to helpe us, wole faire and fele, of which the chiefe and
principal mene is the blissid kinde that he toke of the mayd,
with all the menys that gone aforn and cum after which belongyn
to our redemption and to endless salvation. Wherefore it pleaseth
him that we seke him and worship be menys, understondyng and
knoweing that he is the goodness of all; for the goodness of God
is the heyest prayer and it comith downe to the lowest party of
our nede. It quickyth our soule and bringith it on life and mak-
yth it for to waxen in grace and vertue. It is merest in kind
and ridiest in grace; for it is the same grace that the soule
sekith, and evir shall, till we know verily that hath us all in
himselfe beclosyd; for he hath no dispite of that he hath made,
ne he hath no disdeyne to serve us at the simplest office that
(t)o our body longyth in kinde, for love of the soule that he
hath made to his owne likness; for as the body is cladde in the
cloth, and the flesh in the skyne, and the bonys in the flesh,
and the herte in the bouke, so arn we, soule and body, cladde
in the goodnes of God and inclosyd; ya, and more homley, for all
these may wasten and weren away, the godenes of God is ever hole,
snd more nere to us withoute any likenes; for treuly our lover
desireth that our soule cleve to hym with all the might and that
we be evermore clevand to his godenes; for of all thing that
herete may thinke, it plesyth most God and sonest spedyth; for
our soule is so specially lovid of him that is heiest that it
overpassyth the knoweing of all creatures - that is to seyen,
there is no creature that is made that may wetyn how mekyl and
how swetely and how tenderly our maker loveth us. And therefore
we may with his grace and his helpe stond in ghostly beholding,
with everlestyng merveyling in this hey, overpassing, onenestimable
love that almitie God hath to us of his godenes. And therefore
we may aske of our lover with reverence all that we willen; for
our kindly will is to have God and the gode will of God is to have
us. And we may never blyn of willing ne of longyng till we have
him in fullhede of ioy, and than may we no more willen; for he
will that we be occupyed in knoweing and loveing til the tyme
that we shall be fulfilled in hevyn. And therefore was this lesson
of love shewid, with all that followith, as ye shall se; for the
strength and the ground of all was shewed in the first sight; for
of all thing, the beholding and the lovyng of the maker makith the
soule to seeme lest in his owne sight, and most fillith it with
reverend drede and trew mekenes, with plenty of charitie to his
even cristen.</p></div>

                    <div type="chapter">

<head>7. How our lady beholdyng the gretenes of hir maker, thowte hirselfe
leste, and of the great droppys of blode renning from under the
garland, and how the most ioy to man is that God most hie and
mightie is holyest and curtesiest - vii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And to lerne us this, as to myne understondyng our lord God shewed
our lady Saint Mary in the same tyme; that is to mene (the) hey
wisedome and trewth she had in beholdine of hir maker so grete,
so hey, so mightie and so gode. This gretenes and this noblyth
of the beholdyng of God fulfilled her of reverend drede, and with
this she saw hirselfe so litil and so low, so simple and so pore,
in reward of hir lord God, that this reverend drede fulfillid hir
of mekenes. And thus, by this grounde, she was fulfillid of grace
and of al manner of vertues and overpassyth all creatures. In all
the tyme that he shewed this that I have said nov in ghostly sight,
I saw the bodyly sight lesting of the plentious bledeing of the
hede. The grete dropis of blode fel downe from under the garland
like pellots semand as it had cum out of the veynis; and in the
comeing out it were browne rede, for the blode was full thick;
and in the spredeing abrode it were bright rede; and whan it come
to the browes, than it vanyshid; notwithstondyng the bleding
continuid till many things were seene and understondyn. The faire-
hede and the livelyhede is like nothing but the same. The plen-
tioushede is like to the dropys of water that fallen of the evys
after a greate showre of reyne that fall so thick that no man may
numbre them with bodily witte. And for the roundhede, it were like
to the scale of heryng in the spreadeing on the forehead. These
iii come to my (mynde) in the tyme: pellots, for roundhede, in
the comynge out of the blode; the scale of herying, in the
spreadeing in the forehede, for roundhede; the dropys of evese,
for the plentioushede inumerable. This shewing was quick and
lively, and hidouse and dredfull, swete and lovely. And of all
the sight it was most comfort to me that our God and lord, that
is so reverent and dredefull, is so homley and curtes. And this
most fullfilled me with likeing and sekirnes of soule. And to the
understondyng of this he shewid this opyn example: it is the
most worshippe that a solemne king or a grete lord may doe a pore
servant if he will be homely with him, and namely if he shewith
it himselfe, of a full trew meneing and with a glad cheere, both
prive and partie. Than thinkyth this pore creature thus: "A! What "might this nobil lord doe more worshipp and ioy to
shew me, that am so simple, this mervelous homlyhede? Sothly it
is more ioy and likeing to me than he gave me grete gifts and
were himselfe strange in maner.' This bodily example was shewid
so hey that manys herete might be ravishid and almost forgettyng
himselfe for ioy of this grete homlyhede. Thus it fareith be our
lord Iesus and be us; for sothly it is the most ioy that may be,
as to my sight, that he that is heyest and migtyest, noblest and
worthyest, is lowest and mekest, homlyest and curteysest. And
treuly and sothly this mervelous ioy shall be shewne us all whan
we se him; and this will our lord, that we willen and trowen,
ioyen and liken, comfortyn us and solacyn us, as we may, with his
grace and with his helpe, into the tyme that we se it verily; for
the most fulhede of ioy that we shal have, as to my sight, is the
mervelous curtesie and homlyhede of our fader that is our maker,
in our lord Iesus Criste that is our brother and our saviour. But
this mervelous homlyhede may no man weten in this tyme of life,
but he have it of special shewing of our lord, or of grete plenty
of grace inwardly govyn of the Holy Ghost. But faith and beleve
with charite deservith the mede, and so it is had be grace; for
im faith with hope and charete our life is groundyd. The shewyng,
made to whome that God will, pleynly techith the same, openyd and
declarid with many privy points longing to our faith which be
worshipfull to knowen. And whan the shewyng, which is goven in a
tyme, is passyd and hid, than the feith kepyth be grace of the
Holy Ghost into our life end. And thus be the shewyng it is not
other than the faith, ne less ne more, as it may be seene be our
lords meneing in the same matter be than it come to the end.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">

<head>8. A recapitulation of that is seid and how it was shewid to hir
    generally for all - viii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And as longe as I saw this sight of the plentious bleding of the
hede I might never stinte of these words: "Benedicite domine!'.
In which sheweyng I understode vi things: the first is the toknys
of the blissid passion and the plentious sheddyng of his pretious
blode; the iid is the maiden that is derworthy moder; the iiid
is the blissfull Godhede that ever was, is and ever shal bene,
al mighty, al wisdam, al love; the iiiith is althing that he hath
hath made; for wele I wete that hevyn and erth and all that is
made is mekil and large, faire and gode, but the cause why it is
shewid so litil to my sight was for I saw it in the presence of
him that is the maker of all thing, for a soule that seith the
maker of all, all that is made semith Pull litil; the vth is he that
made all things for love; be the same love it is kept and shall
be withoute end; the vith is that God is al thing that is gode,
as to my sight, and the godenes that al thing hath, it is he;
and al these our lord shewid me in the first sight with time and
space to beholden it. And the bodily sight stinted and the gostly
sight dwellid in myne understondyng. And I abode with reverent
drede ioyand in that I saw. And I desired as I durst to se more,
if it were his will, or ell lenger time the same. In al this I
was mekil sterid in charite to mine evem cristen, that thei might
seen and knowyn the same that I saw; for I would it were comfort
to they, for al this sight was shewid general. Than said I to
them that were aboute me: "It is today domysday with me.' And
this I said for I went a deid; for that day that a man deith he
is demyd as he shal be without end, as to my understondyng. This
I seid for I would thei lovid God the better, for to make hem to
have mende that this life is shorte as thei might se in example;
for in al this time I went have deid and that was mervil to me
and sweeme in partie, for methowte this vision was shewid for hem
that should leven. And that I say of me I sey in the person of al
myn even cristen, for I am lernyd in the gostly shewing of our
lord God that he menyth so; and therefore I pray you al for Gods
sake and counsel you for your owne profitt that ye levyn the
beholding of a wretch that it was shewid to, and mightily, wisely
and mekely behold God, that of his curtes love and endles godenes
wolde shewyn it generally in comfort of us al; for it is Gods will
that ye take it with gret ioy and likyng as Iesus had shewid it
on to you all.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">

<head>9. Of the mekenes of this woman kepeing hir alway in the feith of
holy church, and how he that lovyth his evyn cristen for God
lovith allthing - ix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>For the shewing I am not goode but if I love God the better; and
in as much as ye love God the better it is more to you than to me-
I sey not this to hem that be wise, for thei wote it wele; but
I sey it to yow that be simple for ese and comfort, for we arn
al one in comfort; for sothly it was not shewid me that God lovid
me better than the lest soule that is in grace, for I am sekir that
there be many that never had shewing ner sight, but of the comon
techyng of holy church, that loven God better than I; for if I
loke singularly to myselfe I am right nowte; but in general I
am in hope, in onehede of charitie with al myn evyn cristen; for
in this onehede stond the life of all mankinde that shall be savid;
for God is all that is good, on to my sight, and God hat made
al that is made, and God lovith al that he hath made, and he that
generaly loveith al his evyn cristen for God, he lovith al that
is; for in mankynd that shall be savid is comprehendid al: that
is to sey, all that is made and the maker of al; for in man is
God, and God is in al. And I hope be the grace of God he that
beholdith it thus shal be truely taught and mightily comforted
if he nedith comforte. I speake of hem that shal be save, for
in this time God shewid me none other. But in althing I leve
as holy church levith, preachith and teachith; for the feith of
holy church the which I had aforn hand understonden and, as I
hope, by the grace of God wilfully kept in use and custome,
stode continualy in my sight, willing and meneing never to receive
onything that might be contrary therunto. And with this entent
I beheld the shewing with al my diligens; for in al this blissid
shewing I beheld it as ome in Gods meneyng. All this was shewid
by thre: that is to sey, be bodily sight and by word formyd in
my understonding and be gostly sight. But the gostly sight I
cannot ne may not shew it as hopinly ne as fully as I wolde. But
I truste in our lord God almightie that he shal of his godenes,
and for yowr love, make yow to take it more gostly and more
swetely than I can or may telle it.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">

<head>10. The iid revelation is of his discolouryng etc., of our redemption,
and the discolouring of the vernacle, and how it plesith God we
seke him besily, abiding him stedfastly and trusting hym
mightily - x chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after this I saw with bodily sight in the face of the crucifix
that henge before me, in the which I behelde continualy, a parte
of his passion: despite, spitting and sollowing and buffetting and
many lamgoryng peynes, mo than I can tel, and often chamging of
colour. And one time I saw how halfe the face, begyning at the
ere, overred with drie blode til it beclosid to the mid face,
and after that, the tuther halfe beclosyd on the same wise, and
therewhiles in this party even as it came. This saw I bodily,
swemely and derkely, and I desired more bodily sight to have sene
more clerely. And I was answered in my reason: " If God wil shew
thee more, he shal be thy light. Thee nedith none but him.' For
I saw him (and sought hym); for we arn now so blynd and so unwise
that we never sekyn God til he of his godenes shewith him to us;
and we ought se of him graciously, than arn we sterid by the same
grace to sekyn with gret desire to se him more blisfully; and
thus I saw him and sowte him, and I had him and I wantid hym.
And this is, and should be, our comon werkeyng in this, as to my
sight. One tyme mine understondyng was led downe into the see-
ground, and there I saw hill and dalis grene, semand as it were
mosse begrowne, with wrekke and gravel. Than I understode thus:
that if a man or a woman were under the broade watyr, if he might
have sight of God so, as God is with a man continually, he should
be save in body and soule and take no harme and, overpassing, he
should have mor solace and comfort than al this world can telle;
for he wille that we levyn that we se him continually, thowe that
us thinkeith that it be but litil, and in this beleve he makith
us evermore to getyn grace; for he will be sene and he wil be
sowte; he wil be abe dyn and he wil be trosted. This iid sheweing
was so low and so litil and so simple that my sprets were in grete
travel in the beholding, mornand, dredfull and longand; for I was
sumtime in doute whither it was a shewing. And than divers times
our gode lord gave me more sight whereby I understode treuly that
it was a shewing. It was a figure and likenes of our foule dede
hame that our faire, bright, blissid lord bare for our sins. It
made me to thinke of the holy vernacle of Rome which he hath
portrayed with his owne blissid face whan he was in his herd
passion, wilfully going to his deth, and often chongyng of colour.
Of the brownehede and blakehede, reulihede and lenehede of this
image, many mervel how it might be, stondyng he portraied it with
his blissid face which is the fairhede of heavyn, flowre of erth
and the fruite of the mayden wombe. Than how might this image be
so discolouring and so fer fro faire? I desire to sey like as I
have understond be the grace of God. We know in our faith and
beleve be the teaching and preching of holy church that the
blissed Trinite made mankinde to his image and to his likenes.
In the same maner wise we knowen that whan man felle so deepe
and so wretchidly be syne there was none other helpe to restore
man but throw him that made man. And that made man for love, be
the same love he would restore man to the same blisse, and over-
passing. And like as we were like made to the Trinite in our first
makyng, our maker would that we should be like Iesus Criste our
saviour, in hevyn without ende, be the vertue of our geynmakyng.
Than atwix these two he would, for love and worshippe of man, make
himselfe as like to man in this dedely life, in our foulehede and
our wratchidnes, as man myght be without gilte. Whereof it meneith
as it was aforseyd: it was the image and likenes of our foule blsk
dede hame wherein our faire, bryte, blissid lord God is hid. But
ful sekirly I dar sey, and we owen to trowen, that so faire a man
was never none but he till what tyme his faire colour was chongyd
with travel and sorrow and passion, deyeng. Of this it is spoken
in the viii revelation where it tretith more of the same likenes.
And there it seith of the vernacle of Rome, it mevyth be dyvers
chongyng of colour and chere, sometyme more comfortably and lively,
and sometime more reuly and dedely, as it may be seene in the
viii revelation. And this vision was a lernyng to myn vnderstondyng
that the continual sekyng of the soule plesith God ful mekyl; for
it may do no more than sekyn, suffrin and trosten, and this (is)
wrought in the soule that hath it be the Holy Ghost; and the
clernes of fyndyng is of his special grace whan it is his will.
The sekyng with feith, hope and charite plesyth our lord, and
the finding plesyth the soule and fulfillith it with ioy. And
thus was I lernyd to myn vnderstondyng that sekyng is as good as
beholdyng for the tyme that he will suffer the soule to be in
travel. It is God wille that we seke him to the beholdyng of him,
for be that he shall shew us himselfe of his special grace whan
he wil. And how a soule shall have him in his beholdyng he shal
teche himselfe; and that is most worshipp to him and profitt to
thyselfe, and most receivith of mekenes and vertues with the grace
and ledyng of the Holy Goste; for a soule that only festinith him
on to God with very troste, either be sekyng or in beholdyng,
it is the most worshipp that he may don to him, as to my sight.
These arn two werkyng that mown be seene in this vision: that
on is sekyng, the other is beholdyng. The sekyng is common;
that, every soule may have with his Brace, and owith to have that
discretion and techyng of the holy church. It is God wil that
we have thre things in our sekyng: the first is that we sekyn
wilfully and bisily, withouten slauth, as it may be throw his
grace, gladly and merili withoute onskilful hevynes and veyne
sorow; the second is that we abide him stedfastly for his love,
withoute gruching and striveing ageyns him, in our lives end,
for it shall lesten but awhile; the thred that we trosten in him
mightily of fulsekird feith, for it is his wil. We knowen he shall
appere sodenly and blisfully to al his lovers; for his werkyng
is privy, and he wil be perceivid, and his appering shal be swith
sodeyn, and he wil be trowid, for he is full hend and homley -
blissid mot he ben!</p>
</div>

                    <div type="chapter">
<head>11. The iiid revelation etc., how God doth althing except synne, never
chongyng his purpose without end, for he hath made althing in
fulhede of goodnes - xi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after this I saw God in a poynte, that is to sey, in myn
vnderstondyng, be which sight I saw that he is in al things.
I beheld with avisement, seing and knowing in sight with a soft
drede, and thought:'What is synne?' for I saw truly that God
doth althing be it never so litil. And I saw truly that nothing
is done be happe ne be aventure, but althing be the foreseing
wisedome of God. If it be happe or adventure in the sight of man,
our blindhede and our onforesight is the cause, for the things
that arn in the foreseing wisdam of God fro withoute beginning
(which rightfully and worshippfully and continualy he ledyth to
the best end as they comen aboute) fallyn to us sodenly, ourselfe
unwetyng; and thus, be our blindhede and our onforsighte, we seyen
these ben happis and aventures; but to our lord God thei be not
so. Wherefore me behovith nedes to grant that althing that is done,
it is wel done, for our lord God doth alle; for in this time the
werkyng of cretures was not shewid, but of our lord God in the
creature; for he is in the mydde poynt of allthyng and all he
doith, and I was sekir he doith no synne. And here I saw sothly
that synne is no dede, for in al this was not synne shewid. And
I wold no lenger mervel in this, but beheld our lord, what he
wold shewen. And thus, as it might be for the time, the rightful-
hede of Gods werkyng was shewid to the soule. Rightfulhede hath
ii faire properties: it is right and it is full; and so arn al
the works of our lord God; and thereto nedith neither the werkyng
of mercy ner grace, for it ben al rightfull, wherin feilith nougte.
And in another time he shewid for the beholdyng of synne nakidly,
as I shal sey, where he usith werkyng of mercy and grace. And
this vision was shewid to myne vnderstondeng, for our lord will
have the soule turnid truly into the beholdyng of him, and generally
of all his werks; for they arn full gode and al his doings be
easye and swete, and to gret ease bringing the soule that is
turnyd fro the beholdyng of the blind demyng of man onto the faire
swete demyng of our lord God; for a man beholdith some dedes wele
done and some dedes evil, but our lord beholdyth hem not so; for
as al that hath being in kinde is of Godds makyng, so is althing
that is done in propertie of Gods doing; for it is easye to under-
stonde that the best dede is wele done; and so wele as the best
dede is done and the heiest, so wele is the lest dede done; and
al in propertie and in the ordir that our lord hath it ordeynit
to fro withoute begynning, for ther is no doer but he. I saw ful
sekirly that he chongyth never his purpos in no manner thyng, nor
never shall, withoute end; for ther was nothyng onknowen to him
in his rightfull ordenance from without begynnyng, and therefore
althyng was sett in ordir, or anything was made, as it should
stonde withoute end; and no maner thyng shall failen of that poynt;
for he made althinge in fulhede of godenes; and therefore the
blissid Trinite is ever ful plesid in al his werks. And al this
shewid he ful blisfully, meneing thus: "Se I am God. Se I am in
althing. Se I doe althyng. Se I left never myne hands of myn werks,
ne never shall, withoute ende. Se I lede althing to the end I
ordeynd it to fro withoute beginnyng be the same might, wisdam
and love that I made it. how should anything be amysse?' Thus
migtily, wisely and lovinly was the soule examynyd in this vision.
Than saw I sothly that me behovyd nedis to assenten with gret
reverens, enioyand in God.</p></div>


                     <div type="chapter">

<head>12. The iiiith revelation etc., how it likith God rather and better
to wash us in his blode from synne than in water, for his blode
is most pretious - xii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after this I saw, beholding, the body plentiously bleding
in seming of the scorgyng, as thus: the faire skynne was brokyn
ful depe into the tender flesh with sharpe smyting al about the
sweete body; so plenteously the hote blode ran oute that there
was neither sene skynne ne wound, but as it were al blode. And
whan it come wher it should a fallen downe, than it vanyshid;
notwitstondyng, the bleding continued a while til it migt be sene
with avisement. And this was so plenteous to my sigt that methowte,
if it had be so in kind and in substance for that tyme, it should
have made the bed al on blode and a passid over aboute. And than
cam to my minde that God hath made waters plentivous in erthe to
our service amd to our bodily ease, for tender love that he hath
to us, but yet lekyth him better that we take full homely (h)is
blissid blode to washe us of synne; for there is no licor that is
made that he lekyth so wele to give us; for it is most plentivous
as it is most pretious, and that be the vertue of his blissid God-
hede. And it is our kinde and alblissfully beflowyth us be the
vertue of his pretious love. The dereworthy blode of our lord
Iesus Criste, as verily as it is most pretious, as verily it is
most plentivous. Beholde and se. The pretious plenty of his dere-
worthy blode descendid downe into helle and braste her bands and
deliveryd al that were there which longyd to the curte of hevyn.
The pretious plenty of his dereworthy blode overflowith al erth
and is redye to wash al creaturs of synne which be of gode will,
have ben and shal ben. The pretious plenty of his dereworthy blode
ascendid up into hevyn to the blissid body of our lord Iesus
Christe, and there is in him bleding and praying for us to the
Father - and is and shall be as long as it nedith. And evermore
it flowith in all hevyns enioying the salvation of al mankynde
that arn there and shal ben, fulfilling the noumber that failith.</p></div>

<div type="chapter">

<head>13. The vth revelation is that the temptation of the fend is overcome
be the passion of Criste, to the encres of ioy of us, and to his
peyne, everlestingly - xiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after, or God shewid ony words, he sufferd me to beholden in
him a conable tyme, and all that I had sene, and all intellecte
that was therein as the simplicite of the soule migte take it.
Than he, without voice and openyng of lippis, formys in my soule
these words: "Herewith is the fend overcome.' These words seyd
our lord menening his blissid passion as he shewid aforn. In this
shewid our lord that the passion of him is the overcomming of the
fend. God shewid that the fend hath now the same malice that he
had aforn the incarnation; and as sore he travilith and as con-
tinually he seeth that all sent of salvation ascappym him worshipply
be the vertue of Cristes pretious passion; and that is his sorow,
and ful evyl he is attemyd; for all that God sufferith him to doe
turnith into ioy and him to shame and wo; and he hath as mech
sorow whem God givith him leave to werkyn as when he werkyth
not; and that is for he may never doe as yvel as he would, for
his migte is al tokyn in Godds hand. But in God map be no wreth,
as to my syte, for our gode lord endlesly hath regarde to his
owne worshippe and to the profite of al that shall be savid. With
might and right he withstondith the reprovid, the which of mallice
and shrewidnes bysyen hem to contriven and to done agens Gods
wille. Also I saw our lord scorne his malice and nowten his
onmigte, and he wil that we doe so. for this sigte I lavhyd
migtily, and that made hem to lavhyn that were about me, and
ther lavhyng was a likeing to me. I thowte that I wold that al
myn evyn christen had ben as I saw, and than should thei al
lavhyn with me. But I saw not Criste lawhyn; for I understode
that we may lavhyn in comforting of ourselfe and ioying in God,
for the devil is overcome. And thenI saw him scorne his malice,
it was be ledyng of myn understondyng into our lord, that is to
sey, an inward sheweing of sothfastnes, withoute chongyng of chere;
for, as to my sight, it is a worshipfull property that is in God,
which is durabil. And after this I fel into a sadhede and seid:
"I se iii things: (g)ame,scorne and arneste. I se (g)ame that
the fend is overcome. I se scorne that God scornith him and he
shal be scornyd. And I se arneste that he is overcome be the bliss-
full passion and deth of our lord Iesus Criste that was done in
ful arnest and with sad travelle.' And I seid "He is scornid', I
mene that God scornith him: that is to sey, for he seeth him now
as he shall done withoute end; for in this God shewid that the
fend is dampnid; and this ment I when I seid "He shall be scornyd':
at domysday generally of all that shal be savyd, to hose con-
solation he hath gret invye; for than he shall seen that all the
wo and tribulation that he hath done to them shal be turnid to
encres of their ioy without ende, and al the peyne and tribulation
that he would a brougte hem to shal endlesly goe with him to helle.</p></div>

<div type="chapter">
      

<head>14. The vi revelation is of the worshippfull thanke with which he
    rewardith his serva(n)ts, and it hath iii ioyes - xiiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>After this our good lord seid: "I thanke thee of thy travel and
namely of thy youthe'. And in this myn understondyng was lifted
up into hevyn where I saw our lord as a lord in his owne house,
which hath clepid al his derworthy servants and freinds to a
solemne feste. Than I saw the lord take no place in his owne house,
but I saw him rialy regne in his hous, and fulfillid it with ioy
and mirth, hymselfe endlesly to gladen and to solacyn his derworthy
frends ful homeley and ful curtesly, with mervelous melody of
endles love in his owen faire blissid chere; which glorious chere
of the Godhede fulfillith hevyns of ioy and bliss. God shewid
iii degrees of blis that every soule shal have in hevyn that
wilfully hath servid God in any degre in erthe. The first is the
worshipful thanke of our lord God that he shal recevyn whan he is
deliverid of peyne; this thanke is so high and so worshipful that
him thinkith it fillith him thow there were no more; for methowte
that all the peyne and travel that might be suffryd of all liveing
men might not deserve the worshipfull thanke that one man shall
have that wilfully hath servid God. The iid, that all the blissid
creatures that arn in hevyn shall se that worshipfull thankyng,
and he makyth his service knowen to al that arn in hevyn. And in
this time this example was shewid: a king, if he thanke his
servants it is a gret worship to hem, and if he makyth it knowen
to all the reme, than is his worshippe mekil incresid. The iii
is that as new and as lekyng as it is underfongyn that tyme, rigte
so shall it lesten withoute ende. And I saw that homely and swetely
was this shewid: that the age of every man shal be knowen in hevyn,
amd shal be rewardid for his wilful service and for his time; and
namely the age of hem that wilfully and frely offir her yongith
to God passingly is rewardid and wonderly is thankyd; for I saw
that whan or what tyme a man or woman be truly turnid to God, for
on day service and for his endles wille, he shall have al these
iii degres of blisse. And the more that the lovand soule seeth
this curtesy of God, the lever he is to serve him al the dayes
of his life.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">

<head>15. The viith revelation is of oftentymes felyng of wele and wo etc.,
and how it is expedient that man sumtymes be left withoute comfort,
synne it not causeing - xv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after this he shewid a soveren gostly lekyng in my soule. I
was fulfillid of the everlesting sekirnes migtily susteinid with-
oute any peynful drede. This felyng was so gladd and so gostly
that I was in al peace and in reste that there was nothing in erth
that should a grevid me. This lestinid but a while and I was
turnyd and left to myselfe in hevynes and werines of my life and
irkenes of myselfe that onethis I coude have patience to leve.
There was no comfort nor none ease to me but feith, hope and
charite, and these I had in truthe, but litil in feling. And anone,
after this, our blissid lord gave me ageyne the comfort and the
rest in soule, in likyng and sekirnes so blisful and so mycti that
no drede, no sorow, ne peyne bodily that might be suffrid should
have desesid me. And than the peyne shewid ageyn to my feling,
and than the ioy and the lekyng, and now that one, and now that
other, dyvers tymes - I suppose aboute xx tymes. And in the same
tyme of ioy I migte have seid with Seynt Paul: "Nothing shal
depart me fro the charite of Criste'. And in the peyne I migte
have seid with Peter: "Lord, save me, I perish'. This vision was
shewid me, after myn vnderstondyng, that it is spedeful to some
soulis to fele on this wise, somtime to be in comfort, and
somtyme to faile and to be left to hemselfe. God wille we knowen
that he kepyth us even alike sekir in wo and in wele. And for
profitt of manys soule a man is sumtyme left to himselfe, althowe
synne is not ever the cause; for in this tyme I synned not wher-
fore I shulde be left to myselfe, for it was so soden. Also I
deservyd not to have this blissid felyng. But frely our lord
gevyth whan he wille, and suffrith us in wo sumtyme. And both is
one love; for it is Godds wil we hold us in comfort with al our
migte, for blisse is lestinge without ende, and peyne is passand
and shal be browte to nougte to hem that shall be savyd. And
therefore it is not Godds will that we folow the felynge of peyne
in sorow and mornyng for hem, but sodenly passing over and holden
us in endless likyng.</p></div>


                        <div type="chapter">

<head>16. The viiith revelation is of the last petivous peynes of Christe
deyeng, and discoloryng of his face and dreyeng of his flesh -
xvi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>After this Criste shewid a partie of his passion nere his deyeng.
I saw his swete face as it was drye and blodeles with pale deyeng;
and sithen more pale, dede, langoring, and than turnid more dede
into blew, and sithen more browne blew, as the flesh turnyd more
depe dede; for his passion shewid to me most propirly in his blissid
face, and namly in his lippis; there I saw these iiii colowres,
tho that were aforn freshe, redy and likyng to my sigte. This was
a swemful chonge to sene this depe deyeng, and also the nose clange
and dryed, to my sigte, and the swete body was brown and blak,
al turnyd oute of faire lifely colowr of hymselfe onto drye
deyeng; for that eche tyme that our lord and blissid savior deyid
upon the rode it was a dry, harre wynde and wond colde, as to my
sigte; and what tyme the pretious blode was blede oute of the
swete body that migte passe therfro, yet there dwellid a moysture
in the swete flesh of Criste, as it was shewyd. Blodeleshede and
peyne dryden within and blowyng of wynde and cold commyng fro
withouten metten togeder in the swete body of Criste. And these
iiii, tweyn withouten, and tweyn within, dryden the fleshe of
Criste be process of tyme. And thow this peyne was bitter and
sharpe, it was full longe lestyng, as to my sighte, and peynfully
dreyden up all the lively spirits of Crists fleshe. Thus I saw the
swete fleshe dey, in semyng be party after party, dryande with
mervelous peynys. And as longe as any spirit had life in Crists
fleshe, so longe sufferid he peyne. This longe pynyng semyd to
me as if he had bene seven night ded, deyand, at the poynt of
out passing away, sufferand the last peyne. And than I said it
semyd to me as if he had bene seven night dede, it menyth that
the swete body was so discoloryd, so drye, so clongen, so dedely
and so petevous as he had be seven night dede, continuly deyand.
And methowte the deyeng of Crists flesh was the most peyne, and
the last, of his passion.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">

<head>17. Of the grevous bodyly threst of Criste causyd iiii wysys, and
of his petovous coronyng, and of the most payne to a kinde
lover - xvii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And in this deyng was browte to my mynde the words of Criste:
"I threst'; for I saw in Criste a doble threst: one bodely,
another gostly the which I shal speke of in the xxxi chapter;
for this word was shewid for the bodyly threst the which I under-
stode was causid of failyng of moysture, for the blissid flesh
and bonys was left al alone without blode and moysture. The
blissid bodye dreid alone long tyme, with wryngyng of the naylys
and weyte of the bodye; for I understode that for tenderness of
the swete hands and of the swete fete, be the gretnes, hardhede
and grevoushed of the naylis, the wounds wexid wider and the body
saggid for weyte be long tyme hanging; and peircing and wrangyng
of the hede and byndyng of the crowne, al bakyn with drye blode,
with the swete heire clyngand, and the drye flesh, to the thornys,
and the thornys to the flesh deyand; and in the begynnyng, while
the flesh was fresh and bledand, the continuant sytyng of the
thornys made the wounds wyde. And ferthermore I saw that the swete
skyn and the tender flesh, with the heere and the blode, was al
rasyd and losyd abov from the bone with the thornys where thowe
it were daggyd on many pecys, as a clith that were saggand, as
it wold hastely have fallen of for hevy and lose while it had kynde
moysture; and that was grete sorow and drede to me, for methowte
I wold mot for my life a sen it fallen. How it was don I saw not,
but understode it was with the sharpe thornys and the boystrous
and grevous setting on of the garland onsparably and without pety.
This comtimuid a while and sone it began to chongyn, and I beheld
and merveled how it migt ben. And than I saw it was for it began
to dreyen and stynte a party of the weyte and sette abute the
garland. And thus it envyronyd al aboute, as it were garland upon
garland. The garland of the thornys was dyed with the blode, and
the tother garland and the hede, al was on colour, as cloderyd
blode whan it is drey. The skynne of the flesh that semyd of the
face and of the body was smal, ronkyllid, with a tannyd colour,
lyke a dry borde whan it is akynned; and the face more browme
than the body. I saw iiii maner of dryengs: the first was blode-
less; the secund was payne folowyng after; the thred, hangyng up
in the eyr as men hang a cloth to drye; the forth, that the bodily
kynd asky(d) licour and ther was no maner of comfort myn ystid to
hym in al his wo and disese. A! herd and grevous was his peyne,
but mech more hard and grevous it was whan the moysture faylid
and al beganne to drye thus clyngand. These were the paynys that
shewdyn in the blissful hede: the first wrought to the deyng why
it was moyst; and that other, slow, with clyngyng dryand, with
blowing of the wynde from withowten that dryed him more, and peynd
with cold, than myn herte can (thingke);and other paynys; for
which paynys I saw that all is to litil that I can sey, for it
may not be told. The which shewing of Cristes peynys fillid me
ful of payne, for I wiste wele he suffryd but onys, but, as he
wold shewn it me and fillen me with mynde as I had aforn desyryd.
And in al this tyme of Cristes paynys I felte no payn but for
Cristes paynys. Than thowte me "I knew but litil what payne it
was that I askyd', and as a wretch repentid me, thynkand if I had
Wiste what it had be, lothe me had be to have praydd it; for
methowte it passid bodely dethe, my paynes. I thowte: "Is any
payne like this?' And I was answered in my reason: "Helle is
another payne, for there is despeyr. But of al paynes that leden
to salvation, this is the most payne: to se thy love suffir.'
How might any payne be more to me than to se him that (is) al
my life, al my blisse and al my ioy suffren? Here felt I soth-
fastly that I lovyd Criste so mech above myselfe that there was
no payne that might be suffrid leke to that sorow that I had to
se him in payne.</p></div>

                    <div type="chapter">

<head>18. Of the spiritual martyrdam of our lady and other lovers of Criste,
    and how al things suffryd (with) hym, goode and ylle - xviii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Here I saw a part of the compassion of our lady Seynt Mary, for
Christe and she were so onyd in love that the gretnes of his lovyng
was cause of the mekylhede of hyr payne; for in thys I saw a sub-
stance of kynd love, continyyd be grace, that creatures have to
hym; which kynde love was most fulsomely shewyd in his swete moder,
and overpassyng, for so mech as she lovid him more than al others,
hir panys passyd al others; for ever the heyer, the myghtyer, the
sweter that the love be, the mor sorow it is to the lover to se
that body in payne that is lovid. And al his disciples and al his
trew lovers suffrid panys more than ther owne bodyly deyng; for
I am sekir, by myn owne felyng, that the lest of hem lovid hym so
far above hemself that it passyth al that I can sey. Here saw I
a gret onyng betwyx Christe and us, to myn understondyng; for whan
he was in payne, we were in peyne. And al cretures that might
suffre payne suffrid with hym, that is to sey, al cretures that
God hathe made to our service. The firmament, the erth faledyn
for sorow in hyr kynde in the tyme of Crists deyng; for longith
it kyndely to thir properte to know hym for ther God in whome al
ther vertue stondyth; whan he faylid, than behovyd it nedis to
them for kyndnes to faylen with hym as mech as thei myght, for
sorow of his penys. And thus thei that were his frends suffryd
peyne for love. And generaly, al - that is to sey, thei that knew
hym not - suffrid for feylyng of al manner of comfort save the
myghty privy kepyng of God. I mene of ii manner of folke, as it
may be understode by ii personys: that on was Pilate, that other
was Sain Dionyse of France, which was that tyme a paynym; for
whan he saw wonderous and mervelous sorowes and dreds that be-
fallen in that tyme, he sayd: "Either the world is now at an
end, or ell he that is maker of kynde suffryth.' Wherfor he did
write on an auter: "This is the auter of onknown God.' God of his
godenes that maketh the planets and the elements to werkyn of
kynd to the blissid man and the cursid, in that tyme it was with-
drawen from bothe; wherfore it was that thei that knew him not
were in sorow that tyme. Thus was our lord Iesus nawted for us,
amd we stond al in this manner nowtid with hym; and shal done
til we come to his blisse, as I shal sey after.</p> </div>

                    <div type="chapter">
                             
<head>19. Of the comfortable beholdyng of the crucifyx, and how the desyre
of the flesh without consent of the soule is no synne, and the
flesh must be in peyne, suffring, til bothe be onyd to Criste -
xix chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>In this I wold a lokyd up of the crosse, and I durst not, for I
weste wele whyl I beheld in the cross I was seker and save; there-
fore I wold not assenten to put my soule in perel, for beside the
crosse was no sekernes for vggyng of fends. Than had I a profir
in my reason as it had be frendly seyd to me: "Loke up to hevyn
to his Fader'. And than saw I wele with the feyth that I felte
that ther was nothyn betwix the crosse and hevyn that myght have
desesyd me. Either me behovyd to loke up, or else to answeren.
I answered inwardly with al the myghts of my soule and said: "Nay,
I may not, for thou art my hevyn'. This I seyd for I wold not;
for I had lever a ben in that peyne til domysday than to come
to hevyn otherwyse than by hym; for I wiste wele that he that
bonde me so sore, he sholde onbynde me whan that he wolde. Thus
was I lerid to chose Iesus to my hevyn, whome I saw only in payne
at that tyme. Me lekyd no other hevyn than Iesus, which shal be
my blisse whan I come there. And this hath ever be a comfort to
me, that I chose Iesus to my hevyn, be his grace, in al this tyme
of passion and sorow. And that hat be a lernyng to me that I should
evermor done so, chesyn only Iesus to my hevyn in wele and wo.
And thow I as a wretch had repentid me - I sayd aforn if I had
wiste what peyne it had be me had be loth to have prayed - here
saw I sothly that it was grutching and daming of the flesh without
assent of the soule, in whych God assignyth no blame. Repenting
and wilful choys be two contrarys which I felte both in one at
that tyme; and tho be two parties: that one outward, that other
inward. The outeward party is our dedely fleshede which is now
in peyne and wo, and shal be in this life, whereof I felt mech
in this tyme, and that party was that repented. The inward party
is an high, blissfull life which is al in pece and in love, and
this was more privily felte; and this party is in which mightyly,
wysly and wilfully I chase Iesus to my hevyn. And in this I saw
sothly that the inward party is master and soverayn to the oute-
ward, and not charging ne takyng hede to the will of that, but
al the entent and will is sett endlesly to be onyd into our lord
Iesus. That the outeward part should draw the inward to assent
was not shewid to me; but that the inward drawith the outeward
by grace, and bothe shal be onyd in blisse without end by the
vertue of Criste: this was shewid.</p></div>

                        <div type="chapter">

<head>20. Of the onspekabyl passion of Criste, and of iii things of the
    passion alway to be remembrid - xx chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And thus I saw our lord Iesus langring long tyme; for the onyng
of the Godhede gave strength to the manhode for love to suffre
more than al man myght suffryn. I mene not allonly more peyne
than al men myght suffre, but also that he suffrid more peyne
than al men of salvation that ever was from the first begynnyng
into the last day myght tellyn or ful thynkyn, havyng regard to
the worthynes of the heyest, worshipful kyng and the shamly,
dispitous, peynful dethe; for he that is heyest and worthyest
was fullyest nowtyd and utterlyest dispisid; for the hyest poynte
that may be sean in the passion is to thynkyn and knowen what he
is that suffryd. And in this he browte a part in mende the heyte
and noblyth of the glorias Godhede, and therwith the pretioushed
and the tendernes of the blisfull body, which be together onyd,
and also the lothhede that is in our kynd to suffre peyne; for
as mech as he was most tender and clene, ryght so he was most
strong and myghty to suffir; and for every manny synne that shall
be savid he suffrid; and every manys sorow and desolation he saw
and sorowid for kyndenes and love; for in as mekyl as our lady
sorowid for his peynes, as mekyl he suffrid sorrow for her sorow,
and more, in as mekyl as the swete manhode of hym was worthier in
kynd. For as long as he was passible he suffryd for us and sorowyd
for us; and now he is uprysyn and no more passibyl, yet he suffryt
with us . And I, beholdyng al this be his grace, saw that the
love of hym was so strong whych he hath to our soule that wilfully
he ches it with gret desyr and myldly he suffrid it with wel
payeyng; for the soule that beholdyth it thus, whan it is touchid
be grace, he shal veryly se that the peynys of Crists passion
passen al peynys: that is to sey, which peynys shal be turnyd into
everlestyng passyng ioyes by the vertue of Crists passion.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">

<head>21. Of iii beholdyngs in the passion of Criste, and how we be now
deyng in the crosse with Criste, but his chere puttyt away al
peyne - xxi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Tis Goddys wille, as to myn vnderstondyng, that we have iii manner
of beholdyngs in his blissid passion. The first is the herd peyn
that he suffrid, with contrition and compassion; and that shewid
our lord in this tyme and gave me myght and grace to se it. And
I loked after the departing with al my myght and (wende) have seen
the body al ded, but I saw hym not so. And ryth in the same tyme
that methowte, be semyng, the life myght ne lenger lesten and the
shewyng of the end behovyd nedis to be, sodenly, I beholdyng in
the same crosse, he chongyd his blissfull chere. The chongyng of
his blisful chere chongyd myn, and I was as glad and mery as it
was possible. Than browte our lord merily to my mynde: "Where
is now ony poynte of the peyne or of thin agreefe?' And I was
full merry. I understode that we be now, in our lords menyng,
in his crosse with hym in our peynys and our passion, deyng; and
we wilfully abydyng in the same cross with his helpe and his grace
into the last poynte, sodenly he shall chonge his chere to us,
and we shal be with hym in hevyn. Betwix that one and that other
shal be no tyme, and than shal al be browte to ioy; and so mente
he in this shewyng: "Where is now ony poynt of thy peyne or thyn
agreefe?' And we shal be full blissid. And here saw I sothfastly
that if he shewid now us his blissful chere ther is no peyne in
erth, nor in other place, that should us agrevyn, but al things
should be to us ioy and blisse. But for he shewith to us time
of passion as he bare in this life and his crosse, therefore we
arn in desese and travel with hym as our frelete askyth. And the
cause why he suffrith is for he wil of his godeness make us the
heyer with hym in his bliss; and for this litil peyne that we
suffre here we shal have an hey, endles knowyng in God, whych we
myght never have without that. And the harder our peynys have ben
with him in his cross, the more shall our worshippe be with hym
in his kyngdom.</p></div>

                              
    <div type="chapter">


<head>22. (T)he ix revelation is o(f) the lekyng etc., of iii hevyns and
the infinite love of Criste desiring everyday to suffre for us
if he myght, althow it is not nedeful - xxii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Than (seide) our good lord Iesus Christe, askyng: "Art thou wele
payd that I suffrid for thee?' I sayd: "Ya good lord, gramercy.
Ya good lord, blissid mot thou be!' Than seyd Iesus, our kinde
lord: "If thou art payde, I am payde. It is a ioy, a blis, an
endles lekyng to me that ever suffrid I passion for the; and if
I myht suffre more, I wold suffre more.' In this felyng my vnder-
stondyng was lifte up into hevyn, and there I saw thre hevyns, of
which syght I was gretly mervelyd. And thow I se thre hevyns, and
all in the blissid manhode of Criste, non is more, non is less,
non is heyer, non is lower, but evyn Iyke in blis. For the first
hevyn Christe shewyd mo his Fader, in no (b)odyly lyknes, but in
his properte and in his werkyng: that is to sey, I saw in Criste
that the Fader is. The werkyng of the Fader is this: that he
gevyth mede to his Son, Iesus Criste. This geft and this mede
is so blisful to Iesus that his Fader myht have goven hym no mede
that myght have lykyd hym better. The first hevyn, that is the
plesyng of the Fader, shewid to me as an hevyn, and it was ful
blisfull, for he is ful plesed with al the dedes that Iesus hath
done aboute our salvation; wherefore we be not only his be his
beying, but also by the curtes geft of his Fader we be his blis,
we be his mede, we be his worshippe, we be his corone - and this
was a singular mervel and a full delectable beholdyng, that we
be his corone. This that I sey is so grete blis to Iesus that he
settith at nowte al his travel and his herd passion and his cruel
and shamful deth. And in these words, "If that I might suffre
more, I would suffer more', I saw sothly that as often as he
myght deyen so often he wold, and love should neve(r) let him have
rest til he had don it. And I beheld with gret diligens for to
wetyn how often he would deyn if he myght, and sotly the noumbre
passid myn understondyng and my wittis so fer that my reson myghte
not, ne coude, comprehend it. And whan he had thus oft deyid,
or should, yet he would set it at nowte for love; for al thynkyth
him but litil in reward of his love; for thowe the swete manhood
of Criste might suffre but onys, the godenes in him may never
sesin of profir; everyday he is redy to the same if it myght be;
for if he seyd he wold for my love make new hevyns and new erth,
it were but litil in reward, for this might be done everyday if
he wold, withoute any travel; but for to dey for my love so often
that the noumbre passith creature reson, it is the heyest profir
that our lord God myght make to manys soule, as to my syte. Than
menyth he thiss: "How shold it than be that I shold not do for
thi love al that I myght - which dede grevyth me not sith I wold
for thi love dey so often having no reward to my herd peynys - ?'
And here saw I for the second beholdyne in this blissid passion
the love that made him to suffre passith as far al his peynes as
hevyn is above erth; for the peynes was a nobele, worshipfull
dede don in a tyme be the werkyng of love; and love was without
begynnyng, is, and shall be without endyng; for which love he seyd
ful swetely these words: "If I myght suffre more, I wold suffre
more. He seyd not "If it were nedeful to suffre more', for thow
it were not nedeful, if he myght suffre more, he wold. This dede
and this werke about our salvation was ordeynyd as wele as God
myght ordeyn it. And here I saw a full blisse in Criste; for his
blisse shold not a be full if it myte any better have be done.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">

<head>23. How Criste wil we ioyen with hym gretly in our redemption and to
    desire grace of hym that we may so doe - xxiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And in these iii words "It is a ioy, a blis, an endles lykyng
to me' were shewid iii hevyns, as thus: for the ioy I vnderstode
the plesance of the Fader; and for the blis, the worshippe of the
Son; and for the endles lykyng, the Holy Gost. The Fader is plesid,
the Son is worshippid, the Holy Gost lykith. And here saw I for the
thred beholdyng in his blisful passion: that is to sey, the ioy
and the blis that make hym to lekyn it; for our curtes lord shewid
his passion to me in v manners: of which the first is the bledyng
of the hede, the iid is discoloryng of his face, the iiid is the
plentivous bledyng of the body in semys of the scorgyng, the iiiith
is the depe deyng - these iiii are aforseyd for the peynys of the
passion - and the vth is that was shewid for the ioy and the bliss
of the passion; for it is Goddys wille that we have trew lekyng
with hym in our salvation, and therin he wil we be myghtyly com-
fortid and strengthnid, and thus wil he merily with his grace that
our soule be occupyed; for we arn his blisse; for in us he lekyth
without end and so shal we in hym with his grace. And al that he
hath done for us, and doth, and ever shal, was never coste ne charge
to hym, ne myte be; but only that he dede in our manhood, begynnyng
at the sweete incarnation and lesting to the blissid upriste on
Esterne morow, so long durid the cost and the charge aboute our
redemption in dede, of which dede he enioyeth endlesly, as it is
afornseyd. Iesus wil we takyn hede to the blis that is in the blis-
ful Trinite of our salvation and that we desiren to have as mech
gostly lykyng, with his grace, as it is afornseyd: that is to sey,
that the likyng of our salvation be like to the ioy that Criste
hath of our salvation as it may be whil we arn here. Al the Trinite
wroute in the passion of Criste, minystryng abundance of vertues
and plenty of grace to us be hym, but only the mayden son suffrid;
whereof all the blissid Trinite endlesly enioyeth. A(n)d this was
shewid in these words: "Art thou wel payd?' and be that other word
that Criste sayd, "If thou art payed, than am I paide', as if he
sayd: "It is ioy and likyng enow to me, and I aske nowte ell of
the for my travel but that I myght wel payen the.' And in this
he browte to mend the property of a glad gevere: a glad gever
takyth but litil hede of the thvng that he gevith, but al his
desire and al his intent is to plesyn hym and solacyn hym to
whome he gevyth it; and if the receiver take the geft heyly and
thankfully, than the curtes gever settith at nowte all his coste
and al his travel for ioy and delite that he hath for he hath
plesid and solacid hym that he lovyth. Plenteously and fully was
this shewid. Thynke also wisely of the gretnes of this word "ever';
for in that was shewid an high knowing of love that he hath in
our salvation, with manyfold ioyes that folow of the passion of
Criste; one is that he ioyeth that he hath don it in dede, and
he shal no more suffre; another, that he browte us up into hevyn
and made us for to be his corone and endles blisse; another is
that he hath therwith bawte us from endless peynys of helle.</p></div>


               
    <div type="chapter">
<head>24. The x revelation is that our lord Iesus shewith in love his blissid
    herte cloven in tw(o), enioyand - xxiiiith chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Than with a glad chere our lord loked into his syde and beheld,
enioyand; and with his swete lokyng he led forth the understondyng
of his creture be the same wound into his syde withinne. And than
he shewid a faire delectabil place, and large enow for al mankynd
that shal be save to resten in pece and in love. And therwith he
browte to mende his dereworthy blode and pretious water which he
lete poure al oute for love. And with the swete beholdyng he shewid
his blisful herte even cloven on two. And with this swete enioyyng
he shewid onto myn vnderstondyng, in party, the blissid Godhede,
steryng than the pure soule for to vnderstonde, as it may be said,
that is to mene, the endles love that was without begynnyng, and
is, and shal be ever. And with this our gode lord seyd ful blis-
fully "Lo how that I lovid the', as if he had seid: "My derling,
behold and se thy lord, thy God, that is thy maker and thyn endles
ioy. Se what likyng and bliss I have in thy salvation, and for
my love enioy now with me.' And also for more vnderstondyng this
blissid word was seyd: "Lo how I lovid the. Behold and se that I
lovid the so mekyl ere I deyd for the that I wold dey for the:
and now I hay deyd for the, and suffrid wilfuly that I may. And
now is al my bitter peyne and al my hard travel turnyd to endles joy and bliss to me and to thee. How should it now be that thou shouldst anything pray that pleaseth me but that I should full gladly grant it thee? For my pleasing is thy holiness and thine endless joy and bliss with me. This is the understanding, simply as I can say it, of this blessed word: Lo, how I loved thee. This shewed our good Lord for to make us glad and merry.</p>

    <div type="chapter">      
<head>26. The xi revelation is an hey gostly shewing of his moder - xxv
    chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And with this same chere of myrth and ioy our gode lord lokyd
downe on the ryte syde and browte to my mynde where our lord
stode in the tyme of his passion; and seid "Wilt th
and in this swete word, as if he had seyd: "I wote wele thou wold
se my blissid moder, for after myselfe she is the heyest ioy that
I myte shew the, and most lykyng and worshippe to me; and most
she is desyrid to be seene of my blissid cretures.' And for the
hey, mervelous, singular love that he hath to this swete mayden,
his blissid moder, our lady Seyt Mary, he shewid hir heyly enioyng,
as be the menyng of these swete words, as if he seyd: Wil thou
se how I love hir, that thou myte ioy with me in the love that
I have in her and she in me?' And also to more vnderstondyng this
swete word our lord God spekyth to al mankynde that shal be save
as it were al to one person, as if he seyd: "Wilt thou seen in
hir how thou art lovid? For thy love I made her so hey, so noble
and so worthy; and this likyth me, and so wil I that it doith the.'
For after hymselfe she is the most blisful syte. But herof am I
not lerid to longen to seen hir bodyly presense while I am here,
but the vertues of hir blissid soule: her truth, her wisdam, hir
charite; wherby I may leryn to know myselfe and reverently drede
my God. And whan our gode lord had shewid this and seid this word,
"Wilt thou seen hir?' I answerid and seyd: "Ya good lord, gramercy.
Ya good lord, if it be thy wille.' Oftentymes I prayd this and I
wend a seen hir in bodily presens, but I saw hir not so. And Iesus
in that word shewid me a gostly sigte of hir; ryte as I had seen
hir aforn litil and simple, so he shewid hir than hey and noble
and glorious and plesyng to hym above al creatures. And he wil
that it be knowen that al those that lyke in hym should lyken
in hir and in the lykyng that he hath in hir and she in him. And
to more understondyng he shewid this example: as, if a man love
a creature syngularly above al creatures, he wil make al creature
to loven and to lyken that creature that he lovith so mekyl. And
in this word that Iesus seid, "Wilt thou se hir?' methowte it was
the most likyng word that he might have gove me of hir with the
gostly shewyng that he gave me of hir; for our lord shewid me  nothyng in special but our lady Seynt Mary; and hir he shewid iii
tymys: the first was as she grevid,the iid was as she was in hir
sorows under the cross, the iii is as she is now in likyng, worshippe and ioye.</p></div>


             <div type="chapter">                    

         <head>27. The xii revelation is that the lord our God is al sovereyn beyng -
             xxvi chapter.</head><lb/>


         <p>And after this our (lorde) shewid hym more gloryfyed as to my syte,
         than I saw him beforne, wherin I was lernyd that our soule shal
         never have rest til it comith to hym knowing that he is fulhede
         of ioy, homely and curtesly blisful and very life. Our lord Iesus
         oftentymes seyd: "I it am, I it am; I it am that is heyest; I it
         am that thou lovist; I it am that thou lykyst; I it am that thou
         servist; I it am that thou longyst; I it am that thou desyrist; I
         it am that thou menyst; I it am that is al; I it am that holy church
         prechyth and teachyth the; I it am that shewed me here to thee.'
         The nombre of the words passyth my witte and al my vnderstondyng
         and al my mights, and it arn the heyest, as to my syte; for therin
         is comprehendid - I cannot tellyn; but the ioy that I saw in the
         shewyng of them passyth al that herte may willen and soule may
desire; and therefore the words be not declaryd here but every
         man after the grace that God gevyth him in vnderstondyng and
         lovyng receive hem in our lords menyng.</p></div>


             <div type="chapter">                     

   <head>   27. The xiiith revelation is that our lord God wil that we have grete
         regard to all his deds that he hav don in the gret noblyth of al
         of al things makyng and of etc., how synne is not knowin but by
         the peyn - xxvii  chapter.</head><lb/>   


         <p>After this the lord browte to my mynd the longyng that I had to hym
         aforn; and I saw that nothyng letted me but synne, and so I beheld
         generally in us al. And methowte if synne had not a ben, we should
         al a ben clene and like to our lord as he made us; and thus, in my
         foly, aforn this tyme often I wondrid whi by the gret forseyng vys-
         dam of God the begynnyng of synne was not lettid; for than, thowte
 =shuld a be wele. This steryng was mikel to forsakyn, and
         nevertheless mornyng and sorow I made therefor without reason and
         discretion. But Iesus, that in this vision enformid me of all that
         me neydyth, answerid by this worde and seyd: "Synne is behovabil,
         but al shal be wel, and al shal be wel, and al manner of thyng
shal be wele.' In this nakid word "synne' our lord browte to my
mynd generally al that is not good, and the shamfull dispite and
the utter nowtyng that he bare for us in this life, and his dyeng,
and al the peynys and passions of al his creatures, gostly and
and bodyly - for we be all in party nowtid, and we shall be nowtid
followyng our master Iesus till we be full purgyd: that is to sey,
till we be fully nowtid of our dedly flesh and of al our inward
affections which arn not very good - , and the beholdyng of this,
with al peynys that ever wern or ever shal be; and with al these
I understond the passion of Criste for most peyne and overpassyng.
And al this was shewid in a touch and redily passid over into com-
forte; for our good lord wold not that the soule were afferd of
this uggly sigte. But I saw not synne; for I beleve it hath no
maner of substance ne party of being, ne it myght not be knowin
but by the peyne that it is cause of; and thus peyne, it is some-
thyng, as to my syte, for a tyme, for it purgith and makyth us to
knowen ourselfe and askyn mercy; for the passion of our lord is
comforte to us agens al this, and so is his blissid wille. And for
the tender love that our good lord hath to all that shal be save
he comfortith redyly and swetely, menyng thus: "It is sothe that
synne is cause of all this peyne, but al shal be wele, and al shall
be wele, and all manner thing shal be wele.' These words were seyd
full tenderly, shewyng no manner of blame to me ne to non that
shall be safe. Than were it a gret unkindness to blame or wonder
on God for my synne, seith he blamyth not me for synne. And in
these same words I saw a mervelous hey privitye hid in God, which
privity he shall openly make knowen to us in hevyn; in which
knowyng we shal verily see the cause why he suffrid synne to come;
in which syte we shall endlesly ioyen in our lord God.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">     

<head>28.How the children of salvation shal be shakyn in sorowis, but Criste
enioyth wyth compassion; and a remedye agayn tribulation - xxviiith
chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Thus I saw how Criste hath compassion on us for the cause of synne.
And ryte as I was aforn in the passion of Criste fulfillid with
peyne and compassion, like in this I was fulfilld a party with
compassion of al myn even Cristen; for that wel, wel belovid
people that shal be savid: that is to sey, Gods servants, holy
church, shal be shakyn in sorows and anguis and tribulation in
this world as men shakyn a cloth in the wynde. And as to this
our lord answerid in this manner: "A gret thing shall I makyn
hereof in hevyn, of endles worshipps and everlestyng ioyes.' Ya,
so ferforth I saw that our lord ioyth of the tribulations of his
servants with reuth and compassion, to ech person that he lovyth
to his bliss for to bringen, he levyth upon them something that
is no lak in hys syte, wherby thei are lakid and dispisyd in thys
world, scornyd, rapyd and outcasten; and this he doith for to
lettyn the harme that thei shuld take of the pompe and the veyn
glory of this wrechid lif, and mak ther way redy to come to
hevyn, and heynen them in his bliss without end lestyng; for he
seith: "I shall al tobreke you for your veyn affections and
your vicious pryde; and after that I shal togeder gader you and
make you mylde and meke, clene and holy, by onyng to me.' And
than I saw that ech kynde compassion that man hath on his even
cristen with charite, it is Criste in him. That same nowtyng that
was shewid in his passion, it was shewid ageyn here in this com-
passion wherein were ii maner of vnderstondyngs in our lords
menyng: the one was the bliss that we arn bowte to wherin he will
be enioyen; that other is for comforte in our peyne; for he will
that we wettyn that it shal al be turnyd to worshippe and profite
be vertue of his passion, and that we wetyn that we suffir not
alone but with him, and seen hym our grounde, and that we seen
his penys and his nowtyng passith so fer al that we may sufre
that it may not be ful thowte. And the beholdyng of this will
save us from gruching and dispeir in the felyng of our peynys;
and if we se sothly that our synne deservyth it, yet his love
excusith us, and of his gret curtesye he doith awey al our blame,
and he holdyth us with ruth and pite as childer, inocentes and
vnlothfull.</p></div>



        <div type="chapter">                     
<head>29. Adam synne was gretest, but the satisfaction for it is more
    plesyng to God than ever was the synne harmfull - xxix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>But in this I stode beholdyng generally, swemly and mournyng,
seyng thus to our lord in my menyng with ful grete drede: "A!
good lord, how myte al ben wele for the grete hurte that is come
by synne to the creatures?' And here I desirid, as I durst, to
have sum more open declaryng wherwith I myte be esyd in this.
And to this our blisfull lord answerd full mekely,and with ful
lovely chere, and shewid that Adams synne was the most harme that
ever was don, or ever shal, to the world ende; and also he shewid
that this is openly knowen in al holy church in erth. furthermore
he leryd that I should behold the glorious asyeth; for this asyeth
makyng is more plesyng to God and more worshipfull for manys sal-
vation, without comparison, than ever was the synne of Adam harm-
full. Than menyth our blissid lord thus in this techyng, that we
should take hede to this: "For sythe I have made wele the most
harme, than it is my wil that thou knowe thereby that I shal make
wel al that less.'</p></div>

            <div type="chapter">                       


<head>30. How we shuld ioye and trusten in our savior Iesus, not presumyng
    to know his privy counsell - xxx chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>He gave me understondyng of ii parties. That one party is our
savior and our salvation; this blissid parte is hopyn and clere
and faire and lite and plentivous, for al manky(n)d that is of
good wille and shal be is comprehendid in this parte; herto arn
we bounden of God and drawen and coun(c)ellid and lerid inwardly
be the Holy Gost and outwardly be holy church in the same grace;
in this will our lord we be occupyed, ioyeng in him for he on-
ioyeth in us; and the more plentivously that we take of this with
reverens and mekenes, the more thanke we deserven of hym and the
more spede to ourselfe; and thus, may we sey, enioyeng our part
is our lord. That other is hid and sperid from us: that is to sey,
al that is besiden our salvation; for it is our lords privy
councell, and it longyth to the ryal lordhip of God to have his
privy councell in pece, and it longyth to his servant, for
obedience and reverens, not to wel wetyn his conselye. Our lord
hath pety and compassion on us for that sum creatures make them
so besy therin; and I am sekir if we wisten how mekil we shuld
plese hym and ese ourselfe to leven it, we wolden. The seynts that
be in hevyn, thei wil nothyng wetym but that our lord will shewen
hem, and also their charite and their desire is rulid after the
wil of our lord; and thus owen we to willen like to hem: than shal
we nothyng willen ne desiren but the wille of our lord like as
thei do; for we arn al on in Goddis menyng. And here was I lernyd
that we shal trosten and enioyen only in our savior blisful Iesus
for althynge.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">     

<head>31. Off the longyng and the spiritual threst of Criste, which lestyth
and shall lesten til domysday; and be the reason of his body he
is not yet full gloryfyed ne al unpassible - xxxi chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>And thus our good lord answerid to al the question and doubts that
I myte makyn, sayeing ful comfortably: 'I may makyn althing wele;
I can make althing wele and I wil make althyng wele and I shall
make althyng wele; and thoug shal se thiself that al manner of thyng
shal be wele.' That he seyth 'I may', I understond for the Fader;
and he seith 'I can', I understond for the Son; and where he seith
'I will', I understond for the Holy Gost; and wher he seith 'I
shall', I understond for the unite of the blissid Trinite, iii
persons and one trouthe; and where he seith "Thou shal se thi-
selfe', I understond the onyng of al mankynd that (shalle) be save
into the blisful Trinite. And in thes v words God wil be onclosid
in rest and pece; and thus shal the gostly threst of Criste have
an end; for this is the gostly thrist of Criste: the luflongyng
that lestith and ever shal, til we se that syte on domysday. For
we that shal be save, and shal be Crists ioye and his blis, some
be yet here, and some be to cum; and so shal sum be in to that day.
Therefore this is his thirst: a love longyng to have us al togeder
hole in him to his blis, as to my syte; for we be not now as f(u)lly 
hole in him as we shal be then. For we knowen in our feith, and
also it was shewid in alle, that Criste Iesus is both God and man.
And arnernst the Godhede, he is hymselfe heyest blis, and was from
without begynnyng and shall be from withoute end; which endles
blis may never be heyned ne Iownyd in the seIfe. for this plentivously sen in every shewyng, and namely in the twelfth
wher he seith: "I am that is heyest.' And anernst Crists manhood,
it is knowen in our feith, and also shewyd, that he, with the
vertue of Godhede, for love to bring us to his blis, suffrid
peynys and passions, and deid; and these be the werks of Crists
manhode wherin he enioyeth, and that shewid he in the ix rev-
elation wher he seith: "It is a ioye, a blis, an endles lykyng
to me that ever I suffrid passion for the.' And this is the
blis of Crists werks and thus he menyth where he seith in the
selfe shewing: we be his blis, we be his mede, we be his worship,
we be his corone. For anernst that Criste is our hede, he is glori-
fyed and onpassible, and anernst his body in which al his members
be knitt, he is not yet ful gloryfyed ne al onpassible; for the
same desire and threst that he had upon the cross, which desire,
longyng and thrist, as to my syte, was in him fro withoute be-
gynnyng, the same hath he yet, and shal into the tyme that the
last soule that shal be savid is cum up to his bliss; for as
verily as there is a properte in God of ruth and pity, as veryly
there is a property in God of threst and longyng. And of the
vertue of this longyng in Criste we have to longen ageyn to him,
withoute which no soule comyth to hevyn. And this propertye of
longyng and threst comyth of the endles goodnes of God, ryte as
the property of pite comith of his endles goodnes, and thow lon-
gyng and pite arn two sundry properties, as to my syte; and in
this stondyth the poynt of the gostly thrist, which is lestyng in
hym as long as we be in nede, us drawing up to his blis; and al
this was sen in the shewyng of compassion, for that sha
domysday. Thus he hath ruth and comapssion on us, and he hath
longyng to have us, but his wisdam and his love suffrith not the
end to cum til the best tyme.</p></div>

         
    <div type="chapter">             


<head>32. How althyng shal be wele and scripture fulfillid, and we must
stedfastly holdyn us in the faith of holy chirch, as is Crists
wille - xxxii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>On tyme our good lord seid: "Althyng shal be wele'; and another
tyme he seid: "Thou shalt sen thiself that al manner thyng shal
be wele'; and in these ii the soule toke sundry vnderstondyng.
On was this: that he wil we wetyn that not only he takith hede
to noble thyngs and to grete, but also to litil and to smale,
to low and to simple, to on and to other; and so menyth he in
that he seith "Al manner thyngs shal be wele'; for he will we
wetyn the leste thyng shal not be forgotten. Another vnderstondyng
is this: that there be dedes evyl done in our syte and so grete
harm(es) takyn that it semyth to us that it were impossibil that
ever it shuld cum to gode end; and upon this we loke, sorowyng
and morning therefore, so that we cannot restyn us in the blisful
beholdyng of God as we shuld doe; and the cause is this: that the
use of our reason is now so blynd, so low and so symple that we
cannot know that hey, mervelous wisdam, the myte and the goodness
of the blisful Trinite; and thus menyth he wher he seith "Thou
shalt se thiself that al maner thyng shal be wele', as if he seid:
"Take now hede faithfully and trostily, and at the last end thou
shalt verily sen it in fulhede of ioye.'  And thus in these same
v wordis afornseid: "I may make al thyngs wele etc.', I vnderstond
a myty comforte of al the works of our lord God that arn for to
comen. Ther is a dede the which the blisful Trinite shal don in
the last day, as to my syte, and whan the dede shall be, and how
it shal be done, it is onknown of all creatures that are beneath
Criste, and shal be till whan it is don. And the cause he wil we
know is for he wil we be the more esyd in our soule and pesid in
love, levyng the beholdyng of al tempests that myte lettyn us of
trewth, enioyeng in him. This is the grete dede ordeynyd of our
lord God from without begynnyng, treasured and hid in his blissid
breast, only knowen to hymself, be which dede he shal make al thyngs
wele; for like as the blisful Trinite made al thyngs of nowte, ryte
so the same blissid Trinite shal make wele al that is not wele. And
in this syte I mervelid gretely and beheld our feith, merveland
thus: our feith is g(r)owndid in Goddys word, and it longyth to
our feith that we levyn that Goddys word shal be savid in al things;
and one peynt of our feith is that many creatures shal be dampnyd -
as angells that fellyn out of hevyn for pride, which be now fends;
and man in herth that deyth oute of the feith of holy church, that
is to say, thei that be ethen men and also man that hath receyvid
christendam and livith uncristen life and so deyth out of charite -
all these shall be dampnyd to hel without end, as holy church
techyth me to belevyn. And stondyng al this, methowte it was im-
possibil that al manner thyng should be wele as our lord shewid
in this tyme; and as to this I had no other answere in shewyng
of our lord God but this: "That is impossible to the is not im-
possible to me. I shal save my worde in al things and I shal
make althing wele.' Thus I was tawte by the grace of God that I
should stedfasty hold me in the faith as I had afornehand vnder-
stonden, and therewith that I should sadly levyn that althyng
shal be wele as our lord shewid in the same tyme; for this is
the great dede that our lord shal done, in which dede he shal
save his word in althing and he shal make wele al that is not
wele. And how it shal be don, there is no creature benethe Criste
that wot it ne shal wetyn it till it is don, as to the vnder-
stondyng that I toke of our lords menyng in this tyme.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">              

<head>33. Al dampnyd soule be dispisid in the syte of God as the devil;
and these revelations withdraw not the feith of holy church,
but comfortith; and the more we besy to know Gods privites
the less we knowen - xxxiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And yet in this I desired, as I durst, that I myte have had ful
syte of helle and purgatory. put it was not my mening to maken
privy of anythyng that longyth to the feith - for I levyd soth-
fastly that hel and purgatory is for the same end that holy
church techith - but my menyng was that I myte have seen for
leryng in althyng that longyth to my feith wherby I myte liven
the more to Gods worship and to my profit. And for my desire I
coude of this ryte nowte, but as it is aforseid in the v shewing
wher that I saw that the devil is reprovid of God and endlesly
dampned; in which syte I understode that al creatures that arn of
the devils condition in this life and therin enden, there is no
more mention made of hem aforn God and al his holy than of the
devil, notwithstondyng that thei be of mankynd, whether they have
be cristenyd or not. For thow the revelation was made of goodnes,
in which was made litil mention of evil, yet I was not drawne ther-
by from any poynt of the feith that holy church techyth me to
levyn; for I had syte of the passion of Criste in dyvers shewyngs -
in the first, in the iid, in the v and in the viii - as it is
seid aforn, wheras I had in party a felyng of the sorow of our
lady and of his trew frends that sen hym in peyne, but I saw not
so propirly specyfyed the lewes that deden hym to ded; notwith-
stondyn, I knew in my feith that thei wer accursid and dampny(d) 
without end, savyng those that converten be grace. And I was
strengthyd and lered generaly to kepe me in the feith in every
pointe, and in al as I had afore vnderstoden, hopyng that I was
therin with the mercy and the grace of God, desyring and prayng
in my menyng that I myte continue therin onto my lifs end. And it
is Gods will that we have gret regard to al his dedes that he hath
don,but evermore it us nedyth levyn the beholdyng what the dede
shal be. And desir we to be leke our brethren which be seynts in
hevyn that wille ryth nowte but God wille, than shal we only
enioyen in God and ben wel payd both with hyding and with shewyng;
for I saw sothly in our lordis menyng: the more we besyn us to
knowen his privities in this or any other thyng, the ferther
 shal we be from the knowing therof.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">
<head>34. God shewyth the privityes necessarye to his lovers, and how they
plese God mekyl that receive diligently the prechyng of holy
church - xxxiiii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>Our lord God shewid to manner of privityes: on is this gret pri-
vyte with al the prive peynts that longen therto, and these pri-
vites he wil we knowen hid into the tyme that he wil clerly she-
wen hem to us; that other arn the privytes that he wil maken opyn
and knowen to us; for he wil we wetyn that it is his wil we knowen
hem. It arn privytes to us not only that he wil it ben privytes
to us, but it arn privytes to us for our blyndnes and our on-
knowyng; and therof hath he gret ruthe, and therfore he wil hym-
self maken hem more opyn to us wherby (w)e (m)ay knowen hym and
loven hym and clevyn to him; for al that is spedeful to us to
wetyn and to knowen, ful curtesly our lord will shewen us- and
that is this - with al the prechyng and techyng of holy church.
God shewid ful gret plesance that he hath in al men and women
that mytyly and mekely and wilfully taken the prechyng and tech-
yng of holy church; for it is his holy church; he is the ground,
he is the substance, he is the techyng, he is the techer, he is
the leryd, he is the mede wherfor every kynd soule travellith;
and this is knowen and shall be knowen to every soule to which
the Holy Gost declarith it. And hope sothly that al those that
seke this he shal spedyn, for they seky God. Al this that I have
now seid, and more that I shall sey after, is comfortyng ageyn
synne; for in the thred shewyng when I saw that God doith al that
is don, I saw no synne, and than saw I that al is wele. But whan
God shewid me for synne, than seid he: "Al shal be wele.'</p></div>
        
        <div type="chapter">

<head>35.How God doith al that is good, and suffrith worshipfully al by
his mercy, the which shal secyn whan synne is no longer suffrid -
xxxv chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>And whan God almyty had shewid so plentevously and so fully of
h(y)s godenes, I desired to wetyn a certeyn creature that I lovid
if it shuld continu in good lyvyng, which I hopid be the grace of
God was begonne. And in this syngular desire it semyd that I let-
tyd myselfe, for I was not taught in this tyme. And than was I
answerid in my reson, as it were be a freindful mene: "Take it
generally, and behold the curtesy of the lord God as he shewith
to the; for it is mor worship to God to behold hym in al than in
any special thyng.' I asentid and therewith I leryd that it is
more worship to God to knowen al things in general than to lyken
in onythyng in special. And if I shuld do wysely after this tech-
yng I shuld not only be glad for nothyng in special, ne gretly
disesid for no manner of thyng, for "Al shal be wele'; for the
fulhede of ioy is to beholden God in al; for be the same blissid
myte, wisdam and love that he made althyng, to the same end our
good lord ledyth it continually, and therto hymse(l)fe shal bryng
it; and whan it is tyme we shal sen it. And the grounde of this
was shewid in the first, and more openly in the iii wher it seyth,
"I saw God in a peynte'. Al that our lord doeth is rythful, and
that he suffrith is worshipful; and in these ii is comprehendid
good and ille; for al that is good our lord doith, and that is
evil our lord suffrrith. I sey not that ony evil is worshipful,
but I sey the sufferance of our lord God is worshipfull, wherby
his goodnes shal be know withoute end in his mervelous mekeness
and myldehede, by the werkyng of mercy and grace. Rythfulhede is
that thyng that is so goode that may not be better than it is; for
God hymselfe is very rythfulhede and al his werkes arn don ryth-
fully as they arn ordeynid from without begynnyng (by) his hey
myte, his hey wisdom, his hey goodnes. And ryth as he ordeyned
onto the best, ryth so he werkyth continualy and ledyth it to
the same end; and he is ever ful plesid with hymse(l)f and with al
his werks. And the beholdyng of this blisful accord is ful swete
to the soule (that) seith by grace. Al the sowlys that shal be
savid in hevyn without ende be mad rythful in the syte of God, and
be his owen goodnes; in which rythfulhede we arn endlesly kept and
mervelously, aboven al creatures. And mercy is a werkyng that com-
ith of the goodnes of God, and it shal lestyn in werkyng al along
as synne is suffrid to pursue rythful soule; and whan synne hath
no longer leve to pursue, than shal the werkyng of mercy secyn;
and than shal al be browte to rythfulhede and therein stondin
withoute ende. And by his suffranc we fallyn; and in his blisful
love with his myte and his wisdom we are kept; and be mercy and
grace we arn reysid to manyfold more ioyes. And thus in rythful-
hede and in mercy he wil be knowen and lovid now without ende.
And the soul that wisely beholdyth it in grace, it is wel plesyd
 with bothen, and endlesly enioyeth.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">                  

<head>36. Of another excellent dede that our lord shal don, which be grace
may be k(n)owena party here, and how we shuld enioyen in the same; and how God yet doith myracles - xxxvi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Our lord God shewid that a dede shall be done and hymsef shal don
it; and I shal do nothyng but synne, and my synne shal not lettyn
his goodnes werkyng. And I saw that the beholdyng of this is an
heyly ioy in a dredful soule which evermore kyndly be grace des-
irith Godds wille. This dede shal be begonne here, and it shal
be worshipful to God and plentously profitable to his lovers in
erth; and ever as we come to heyvyn we sha(lle) sen it in mer-
velous ioye, and it shal lestyn thus in werkyng onto the last day;
and the worship and the bliss of that shal lestyn in hevyn aforn
God and al his holy without end. Thus was this dede sene and un-
derstond in our lords menyng, and the cause why he shewid it is
to maken us enioyen in hym and al his werks. Whan I saw his shew-
ing continuid, I understod that it was shewid for a grete thyng
that was for to come; which thyng God shewid that hymselfe should
don it; which dede hath these properties afornseid; and this
shewid wel blisfully, menand that I should take it wysely, feith-
fully and trostily. hut what this dede shuld be, it was kepid
privy to me. And in this I saw that he wil not we dredyn to know
the thyngs that he shewith; he shewith hem for he will we know hem,
be which knowing he will we love hym and lekyn and endlesly en-
ioyen in hym. And for the grete love that he hat to us he shewith
us al that is worshipfull and profitable for the tyme; and the
thyngs that he will now hav privy, yet of his grete goodness he
shewith hem close, in which shewyng he will we leven and under-
stonden that we shal sen it verily in his endles bliss. Than owe
we to enioyen in hym for al that he shewith and al that he hidyth;
and if we wilfully and mekely doe thus, we shal fynd therin gret
ese; and endles thanks we shall have of hym therfore. And thus is
the understondyng of this word: that it shal be don by me - that
is the general man, that is to sey, al that shal be save - it
sha(lle) be worshipful and mervelous and plentevous and God hym-
self shal don it. And this shal be the heyest ioye that may ben,
to beholden the dede that God hymselfe shal don, and man shal do
ryte nowte but synne. Than menyth our lord God thus, as if he seid:
"Behold and se. Here hast thou matter of mekenes; here hast thou
matter of love; here hast thou matter to nowten thyself; her hast
thou matter to enioyen in me; and for my love enioye in me, for
of al thyngs, therwith myte thou most plese me.' And as long as
we arn in this lif, what tyme that we be our folly turne us to the
beholdyng of the reprovyd, tenderly our lord God toucht us and blig-
fully clepyth us, seyand in our soule: 'Lete be al thi love my
dereworthy child. Entend to me, I am enow to the, and enioye in
thi savior and in thi salvation.' And that this is our lo(r)ds
werkyng in us I am sekir; the soule that is aperceyvid therein be
grace shal sen it and felen it. And thow it be so that this dede
be truly taken for the general man, yet it excludith not the spe-
cial; for what our good lord will do be his pore creatures, it is
now onknowen to me. But this dede and the tother afornseid, they
arn not both on but ii sundry. But this dede shal be don sooner,
and that shal be as (we) come to hevyn; and to whom our lord
gevyth it it may be knowen her in party; but the gret dede aforn-
seid shal nether be knowen in hevyn ner erth till it is don. And
moreover he gave special vnderstondyng and techyng of werkyng of
miracles, as thus: "It is knowen that I have done miracles her any and fele, heygh and mervelous, worshipful and grete;
and so as I have don I do now continualy, and shal don in coming
of tyme.' It is know that afor miracles comen sorow and anguish
and tribulation; and that is that we showld know our owne febilnes
and our myschevis that we arn fallen in by synne to mekin us and
maken us to dreden God, cryen for helpe and grace. Myracles commen
after that, and that of the hey myte, wisdam and goodnes of God,
shewand his vertue and the ioyes of hevyn so as it may be in this
passand life, and that for to strength our feith and to encresyn
our hope, in charite; wherfor it plesyth hym to be knowen and wor-
shippid in miracles. Than menyth he thus: he wil that we be not
born over low (for) sorrow and tempests that fallen to us; for it
hath ever so ben aforn myracle comyng.</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">


<head>37. God kepyth his chosen ful sekirly althowe thei synne, for in these
is a godly will that never assayed to synne - xxxvii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>God browte to my mynd that I shuld synne; and for lykyng that I
had in beholdyng of hym I entended not redily to that shewyng.
And our lord full mercifully abode and gave me grace to entendyn.
And thys shewyng I toke singularly to myselfe, but be al the gra-
cious comforte tha(t) folowyth, as ye shal seen, I was leryd to
take it to al my even cristen, al in general and nothing in spe-
cial; thowe our lord shewid me I should synne, by me alone is
vnderstode al. And in this I concyvid a soft drede, and to this
our lord answerid: "I kepe the ful sekirly.' This word was seid
with more love and sekirness and gostly kepyng than I can or may
telle; for as it was shewid that I should synne, ryth so was the
comforte shewid: sekirnes and kepyng for al myn evyn cristen.
What may make me more to love myn evyn cristen than to seen in
God that he lovyth all that shal be savid as it wer al on soule?
For in every soule that shal be savid is a godly wil that never
assentid to synne ne never shal; ryth as there is a bestly will
in the lower party that may (w)illen no good, ryth so ther is a
godly will in the heyer party, which will is so good that it may
never willen yll but ever good; and therfore we arn that he lovith,
and endlesly we do that that hym lykyt. And this shewid our lord in
the holehede of love that we stonden in in his syght: ya, that
he lovith us now a(s) wele whil we arn here as he shal don whan
we arn there afore his blissid face. But for faylyng of love on
our party, therefore is al our travel.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">                   

<head>38.synne of the chosen shall be turnyd to ioye and worship; exemple
    of David, Peter and lohn of Beverley - xxxviii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Also God shewid that synne shal be no shame, but worship to man;
for ryth as to every synne is answeryng a peyne be trewth, ryth
so, for every synne, to the same soule is goven a bliss by love.
Ryth as dyvers synnes arn punyshid with dyvers peynes after that
thei be grevous, ryth so shal thei be rewardid with dyvers ioyes
in hevyn after thei have be peynful and sorowful to the soule in
erthe; for the soule that shal come to hevyn is pretious to God
and the place so worshipful that the goodnes of God suffrith never
that soul to synne that shal come there, but which synne shal be
rewardid; and it is made knowen without end, and blisfully res-
torid be over passyng worshipps; for in thys syte myn vnderstondyng
was lift up into hevyn; and than God browte merily to my minde
David and other in the old law without numbre, and in the new law
he browte to my mynd first Mary Magdalen, Peter and Paul, and those
of Inde and Seynt lohn of Beverley, and other also without noumbre:
how thei are knowen in the church in erth with ther synnes and it
is to hem no shame, but al is turnyd hem to worship. And therfore
our curtes lord shewith for them here in parte like as it is
there in fulhede; for ther the token of synne is turnyd to wor-
shippe. And Seynt lohn of Beverley, our lord shewid hym ful
heyly in comfort to us for homlyhed and browte to my mynde how
he is an hende neybor and of our knowyng; and God called hym Seynt
lohn of Beverly pleynly as we doe, and that with a full glad, swete
chere shewyng that he is a ful hey seynt in hevyn in his syght, and
a blisfull; and with this he made mention that in his youngth and
in his tendyr age he was a derworthy servant to God, mekyl God
lovand and dredand, and nevertheless God suffrid him to fall,
hym mercyfully kepand that he perishid not ne lost no tyme; and
afterward God reysyd hym to manyfold more grace, and be the con-
trition and mekenes that he had in his living God hat goven hym
in hevyn manyfold ioyes overpassing that he shuld hav had if he
had not fallen. And that thys is soth God shewith in erth with
plentivous miracles doyng aboute his body continuly. And al was
this to make us glad and mery in love.</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">  
<head>39. Of the sharpnes of synne and the godenes of contrition, and how
our kynd lord will not we dispair for often fallyng - xxxix chapter-</head><lb/>


<p>Synne is the sharpest scorge that any chousyn soule may be smyten
with; which scorge al forbetyth man and woman and noyith him in
his owne syte so ferforth that otherwhile he thynkyth hymself he
is not worthy but as to synken in helle til whan contrition takyth
hym be touchyng of the Holy Gost and turnyth the bitternes in hopes
of Gods mercy; and than he begynnyth his woundis to helyn and the
soule to quickkyn tur(n)yd sinto the life of holy chirch. The Holy
Gost ledyth hym to confession wilfully to shewyn his synnes, nak-
idly and truely, with grete sorow and grete shame that he hath de-
foulyd the fair ymage of God. Than underfo(n)gyth he penance for
every synne, enioynid by his domysman; that is groundid in holy
church be the teaching of the Holy Ghost. And this is on mekenes
that mekyl plesyt God; and also bodely sekenes of Gods sendyng,
and also sorow and shame from withoute, and reprove and dispyte
of this world with al manner grevance and temptations that wil 
be cast in, bodily and gostly. Ful pretiously our lord kepyth us
whan it semyth to us that we arn nere forsakyn and cast away for
our synne and because we have deservyd it. And because of mekenes
that we gettyn hereby we arn reysyd wol hey in Godds syte, be his
grace, swith so grete contrition, also with compassion and trew lon-
gyng to God. Than thei be sodenly delyveryd of synne and of peyne
and taken up to bliss and made even hey seynts. Be contrition we
arn made clene, be compassion we arn made redy and be trew longyng
to God we arn made worthy. Thes arn iii menys, as I understond,
wherby that al soulis come to hevyn - that is to seyn, that have
ben synners in erth and shal be save - for be these medycines be-
hovyth that every soule be helyd. Thow he be helyd his wounds arn
seen aforn God, not as wounds, but as worships. And so on the con-
trarye wise, as we ben ponishid here with sorow and with penance,
we shal be rewardid in hevyn be the curtes love of our lord God
almigty that wil that non that come there lose his travel in no
degre; for he holdyth synne as sorow and peyne to his lovers in
whome he assigneth no blame for love. The mede that we shall
underfongyn shal not be litil, but it shal be hey, glorious and
worshipfull. And so shal shame be turnyd to worship and more ioye;
for our curtes lord wil not that his servants dispeir for often
ne for grevous fallyng; for our fallyng lettyth not hym to love
us. Peas and love arn ever in us, beand and werkand, but we be not
alway in pese and in love; but he wil that we taken hede thus:
that he is ground of al our hole life in love, and furthermore
that he is our everlestyng keper and mytyly defendith us ageyn
our enemys that ben ful fel and fers upon us; and so mech our
nede is the more for we gyven hym occasion be our fallyng.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">  
<head>40. Us nedyth to longyn in love with Iesus, eschewyng synne for love;
the vyleness of synne passith al peynes, and God lovith wol ten-
derly us while (we) be in synne, and so us nedyth to doe our neybor - xl chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>This is a severayn frendshyp of our curtes lord that he kepyth
us so tenderly whil we be in synne; and furthermore he touchyth
us ful privily and shewyth us our synne be the swete lyte of mercy
and grace. Gut whan we seen ourselfe so foule, than wene we that
God were wroth with us for our synne, and than aren we steryd of
the Holy Gost be contrition into prayers and desire to amendyng
of our life with al our mytes, to slakyn the wreth of God, onto
the tyme we fynd a rest in soule and softnes in consciens; and
than hope we that God hath forgoven us our synnes; and it is soth.
And than shewith our curtes lord hymselfe to the soul, wol merily
and with glad cher, with frendful welcummyng, as if he had ben
in peyn and in prison, sayand swetely thus: "My derlyng I am glad
thou art comen to me. In al thi wo I have ever be with the and
now seist thou my lovyng and we be onyd in bliss.' Thus arn synnes
forgoven be mercy and grace and our soule worshipfully receivid
in ioye, like as it shal be whan it comyth to hevyn, as oftentymes
as it comys be the gracious werkyng of the Holy Gost and the ver-
tue of Crists passion. Here vnderstond I sothly that al manner
thyng is made redy to us be the grete goodnes of God so ferforth
that what tyme we ben ourselfe in peas and charite we be verily
save. But for we may not have this in fulhede whil we arn here,
therefore it befallyth us evermore to leven in swete prayor and
in lovely longyng with our lord Iesus; for he longyth ever to
bryng us to the fulhede of ioy, as it is afornseid where he shew-
ith the gostly threst. But now, because of al this gostly comfort
that is afornseyd, if ony man or woman be sterid be foly to seyn
or to thinken "If this be soth, than were it good to synne to have
the more mede', or ell to chargyn the less to synne, beware of this
steryng, for sothly, if it come it is ontrew and of the enemy of
the same trew love that techith us all this comforte. The same
blissid love techith us that we should haten synne only for love.
And I am sekir, by myn owen felyng, the more that every kinde soul
seith this in the curtes love of our lord God, the lother is hym
to synne and the more he is ashamid; for if afor us were layd al
the peynes in helle and in purgatory and in erth, deth and other,
and synne, we shuld rather chose al that peyne than synne; for
synne is so vile and so mekyl to haten that it may be liken to
no payne - which peyne is not synne. And to me was shewid no her-
der helle than synne, for a kynde soule hath non helle but synne.
And we govyn our intent to love and mekenes, be the werkyng of
mercy and grace we arn mad al fair and clene. And as mygty and
as wyse as God is to save man, as willy(ng) he is; for Criste hym-
selfe is ground of all the lawis of Cristen men, and he tawth us
to doe good ageyn ille. Here may we se that he is hymselfe this
charite, and doith to us as he techith us to don; for he will we
be like hym in holehede of endless love to ourselfe and to our
even cristen. No more than his love is broken to us for our synne,
no more will he that our love be broken to ourselfe and to our
evyn cristen; but nakidly haten by synne and endlesly loven the
soule as God lovith it. Than shal we haten synne lyke as God
hatith it, and love the soule as God lovyth it; for this word that
(God) seid is an endless comfort: "I kepe the sekirly.'</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">  
<head>41. The xiiiith revelation is as afornseyd etc., it is impossible we
shuld pray for mercy and want it; and how God will we alway pray
thow we be drey and barryn, for that prayer is to him acceptabil
and plesante - xli chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>After this our lord shewid for prayers; in which shewing I se ii
conditions in our lordis menyng: on is rytfulnes, another is sekir
troste. But yet oftentymes our troste is not full, for we arn not
sekir that God herith us, as us thynkith, for our onworthyness and
for we felyn ryth nowte; for we arn as barren and dry oftentymes
after our prayors as we wer aforn; and this, in our felyng, our
foly, is cause of our wekenes; for thus have I felt in myselfe.
And al this browte our lord sodenly to my mend and s(h)ewid these
words and seid: "I am ground of thi besekyng: first it is my wille
that thou have it, and sythen I make the to willen it, and sithen
I make the to besekyn it and thou besekyst it; how shuld it than
be that thou shuld not have thyn besekyng?' And thus in the first
reason, with the iii that followen, our good lord shewith a mytye
comforte, as it may be seen in the same words. And in the first
reason thus he seith: "And thou besekyst it'; there he shewith ful
grete plesance and endles mede that he will gevyn us for our be-
sekyng. And in the vit reason, there he seith "How shuld it than
be? etc.' this was seid for an impossible; for it is most impossible
that we shuld besekyn mercy and grace and not have it; for of all
thyng that our good lord makyth us to besekyn, hymselfe hath or-
deynid it to us from withoute begynnyng. here may we seen that our
besekyng is not cause of Godis goodness; and that shewid he soth-
fastly in al these swete words when he seith "I am grounde'. And
our good lord wille that this be knowen of his lovers in erth; and
the more that we knowen the more shuld we besekyn, if it be wisely
taken; and so is our lords menyng. Besekyng is a new, gracious,
lestyng will of the soule ony(d) and festenyd into the will of our
lord be the swete, privy werke of the Holy Gost. Our lord hymselfe,
he is the first receyvor of our prayors, as to my syte, and takyth
it ful thankfully and heyly enioyand; and he sendyth it up aboven
and settith it in tresour wher it shal never perishen. It is ther
aforn God with al his holy, continuly recyvyd, ever spedand our
nedys; and whan we shal underfongyn our bliss it shal be gevyn us
for a degre of ioye with endles worshipful thankyng of hym. Full
glad and mery is our lord of our prayors, and he lokyth therafter
and he wil have it; for with his grace he makyth us lyke to hym-
self in condition as we arn in kynd; and so is his blisful will;
for he seith thus: "Pray inderly thow the thynkyth it savowr the
nott, for it is profitable thow thou fele it not, thow thou se
nowte, ya, thow thou thynke thou myghte nowte; for in dryhede and
in barrenhede, in sekenes and in febi(l)hede, than is thyn prayers
wel plesant to me, thow the thynkyth it savowr the nowte but litil.
And so is al thy levyng prayers in my syte.' For the mede and the
endles thanke that he wil gevyn us, therfore he is covetous to have
us pray continuly in his syhte. God acceptith the good will and
the travel of his servant, howsoever we felen; wherfore it plesyth
hym that we werkyn and in our prayors and in good levyng, be hys
helpe and his grace, resonably with discr(e)tion kepand our myght
to hym til whan that we have hym that we sekyn in fulhede of ioy:
that is, Iesus. And that shewid he in the (xv),for aforn, this
word:  "Thou shalt have me to thy mede.' And also to prayors lon-
gyth tha(n)kyng. Thankyng is a new, inward knowing, with gret
reverens and lovely drede turnyng ourselfe with all our myghts
into the werkyng that our good lord steryth us to, enioyng and
thankyng inwardly. And sometyme, for plenteoushede, it brekyth
out with voyce and seith: "Good lord, grante mercy; blissid mot
thou be!' And sumtyme whan the herte is drey and felyth not, or
ell be temptation of our enemy, than it is dreven by reason and
be grece to cryen upon our lord with voyce, rehersyng his blissid
passion and his gret goodnes. And the vertue of our lords word
turnyth into the soule and quicknith the herte and entrith it be
his grace into trew werkyng, and makyth it prayen wel blisfully
and trewly to enioyen our lord; it is a ful blisful thankyng in
his syte.</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">  

<head>42. Off iii thyngs that longyn to prayor, and how we shuld pray; and
of the goodnes of God that supplyeth alwey our imperfection and
febilnes whan we do that longyth to us to do - xlii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Our lord God wille we have trew understondyng, and namely in iii
thyngs that longyn to our prayors. The first is be whom and how
that our prayors springyth; be whome he shewith when he seith "I
am ground'; and how, be his goodness, for he seith "First it is
my wille'. For the secund, in what manner and how we should usen
our prayors; and that is that our wil be turnyd into the will of
our lord, enioyand: and so menith he whan he seith "I mak the to
willen it'. For the thred, that we knowen the frute and the end
of our prayors: that is, to be onyd and lyk to our lord in al-
thyng. And to this menyng and for this end was al this lovely les-
son shewid; and he wil helpyn us and we shall make it so as he
seith hymselfe - blissid mot he ben! For this is our lords wille,
that our prayors and our troste ben both alyk large; for if we
trost not as mekyl as we preyen, we doe not ful worship to our
lord in our prayors and also we taryen and peyn ourselfe; and the
cause is, as I leve, for we know not truly that our lord is ground
on whom our prayors springith, and also that we know not that it
is goven us be the grace of his love; for if we knew this it would
maken us to trosten to hav, of our lords gyfte, al that we desire;
for I am sekir that no man askyth mercy and grace with trew menyng,
but mercy and grace be first geyvin to hym. But sumtyme it cumyth
to our mynd that we have prayd long tyme, and yet, thynkyth us,
that we have not our askyng; but herfor should we not be hevy;
for I am sekir, be our lords menyng, that eyther we abyden a bet-
ter tyme, or more grace, or a better gyfte. He will we have trow
knowyng in hymself that he is beyng; and in this knowyng he will
that our vnderstondyng be growndid with al our mytys and al our
entent and al our menyng; and in this grownd he will that we taken
our stede and our wonynge. And be the gracious ligte of hymself he
will we have understondyng of the thyngs that folow: the first is
our noble and excellent makyng; the second, our pretious and der-
worthy agen byeing; the thred, althyng that he hath made benethen
us to serven us and, for our love, kepith it. Than menyth he thus,
as if he seyd: "Behold and se that I have don al this beforn thi
prayors, and now thou art and prayest me.' And thus he menyth that
it longyth to us (to) wetyn that the gretest deds be don, as holy
church techyth. And in the beholdyng of thys with thankyng we owte
to pray for the dede that is now in doyng: and that is that he
reule us and gyde us to his worshippe in thys lif and bryng us to
his bliss; and therfore he hath don all. Than menyth he thus: that
we sen that he doth it and we prayen therfor; for that on is not
enow; for if we prayen and sen not that he doth it, it makyth us
hevy and doutful, and that is not his worshippe. And if we sen
that he doth, and we pray not, we do not our dette; and so may
it not ben, that is to seyen, so is it not in his beholdyng; but
to sen that he doth it and to pray forthwith, so is he worshippid
and we sped. Althyng that our lord hath ordeynyd to don, it is
his will that we prayen therfor, other in specyal or in generall;
and the ioy and the bliss that it is to hym, and the thanke and
the worshippe that we shall have therfore, it passyth the vnder-
stondyng of cretures, as to my syte; for prayor is a rythwis
vnderstondyng of that fulhede of ioye that is for to cume, with
wel longyng and sekir troste. Faylyng of our bliss that we ben
kyndly ordeynid to makyth us for to longen; trew vnderstondyng
and love, with swete mynd in our savior, graciously makyth us for
to trosten. And in these ii werkyngs our lord beholdyth us con-
tinuly; for it is our dett, and his goodnes may no less assignen
in us. Than longyth it to us to don our diligens; and whan we
have don it, than shal us yet thinken that is nowte - and soth
it is. But do we as we may, and sothly aske mercy and grace, al
that us faylyth we shal fynd in hym; and thus menyth he wher he
seith: "I am grounde of thy besekyng.' And thus in this blisful
word, with the shewing, I saw a full overcomyng agens al our wek-
enes and al our douteful dredis.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">

<head>43. What prayor doth, ordeynyd to God will; and how the goodnes of
God hath gret lekyng in the deds that he doth be us, as he wer
beholden to us, werkyng althyng ful swetely - xliii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Prayor onyth the soule to God; for thow the soule be ever lyke
to God in kynde and substance, restorid be grace, it is often
onlyke in condition be synne on manys partye. Than is prayor a
wittnes that the soule will as God will, and comfortith the con-
science and ablith man to grace. And thus he techith us to prayen,
and mytyly to trosten that we shal have it; for he beholdith us in
love and wil makyn us partyner of his gode dede, and therfore he
steryth us to prayen that that likyth hym to don; for which prayors
and gode will that he wil have of his gyft he wil reward us and
gevyn us endless mede. And this was shewid in this word: "And thou
besekyst it.' In this word God shewid so gret plesance and so gret
lykyng, as he were mekyl beholden to us for every god dede that we
don - and yet it is he that doth it - and for that we besekyn hym
mytyly to don althyng that hym lekyt; as if he seid: "What myte
then plese me more than to besekyn mytyly, wisely and wilfully to
do that thyng that I shal don?' And thus the soule be prayor
accordyth to God. But whan our curtes lord of his grace shewith
hymse(l)fe to our soule, we have that we desire; and than we se not
for the tyme what we shuld pray, but al our entent with al our myte
is sett holy to the beholdyng of hym; and this is an hey, onper-
c(ey)vable prayor, as to my syte; for al the cause wherfor we
prayen, it is onyd into the syte and beholdyng of hym to whome we
prayen, mervelously enioyand with reverent drede and so grete
sweteness and delite in hym that we can pray ryth nowte but as
he steryth us for the tyme. And wel I wote the mor the soule seeth
of God the more it desyrith hym be his grace. Gut whan we sen hym
not soi than fele we nede and cause to pray - for faylyng - for
ablyng of ourselfe to Iesus; for whan the soule is tempested,
troublid and left to hymself be onreste, than it is tyme to prayen
to maken hymselfe supple and buxum to God. But he be no manner of
prayor makyth God supple to hym, for he is ever alyke in love. And
thus I saw that what tyme we se nedys wherfore we prayen, than
our good lord folowyth us, helpand our desire. And whan we of his
special grace planely beholden hym, seying non other nedys, than
we folowen hym and he drawith us into hym be love; for I saw and
felt that his mervelous and fulsome goodnes fulfillith al our mytys;
and then I saw that his continuate werkyng in al manner thing is
don so godely, so wysely and so mytyly that it overpassyt al our
imagyning and all that we can wenyn and thynken; and than we can
do no more but behold hym, enioyeng, with an hey migty desire to
be al onyd into hym, centred to his wonyng, and enioy in hys lov-
yng and deliten in his godeness. And then shal we, with his swete
grace, in our owen meke continuat prayors, come into hym now in
thys life be many privy tuchyngs of swete gostly syghts and fel-
yng, mesurid to us as our simplehede may bere it; and this (is) 
wrewte, and shal be, be the grace of the Holy Gost, so long til
we shal dey in longyng for love. And than shal we all come into
our lord, ourselfe clerely knowand and God fulsomely havyng; and
we endlesly ben al had in God, hym verily seand and fu(l)sumly 
feland, hym gostly heryng, and hym delectably smellyng and hym
swetely swelowyng; and than shal we sen God face to face, homly
and fulsumly; the creature, that is made, shal sen and endlesly
beholden God, which is the maker; for thus may no man sen God and
leven after, that is to sey, in this dedly life; but whan he of
his special grace wil shewn him here, he st(r)engtneththe crea-
ture above the selfe, and he mesurith the shewing after his own
wille, as it is profitable for the tyme.</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">  

<head>44. Of the properties of the Trinite; and how mannys soule, a creature,
hath the same properties, doyng that that it was made for, seyng,
beholdyng and mervelyng his God; so, by that, it semyth as nowte
to the selfe - xliiii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>God shewid in al the revelations oftentymes that man werkyth
evermore his will and his wership lestyngly withoute ony styn-
tyng. And what this worke is was shewid in the first, and that
in a mervelous grounde, for it was shewid in the werkyng of the
soule of our blisfull lady Seynt Mary, treuth and wisdam; and
how, I hope be the grace of the Holy Gost I shal say as I saw.
Treuth seith God, and wisedam beholdyth God, and of these ii
comyth the thred: that is an holy mervelous delyte in God, which
is love. Wher treuth and wisdam is verily, there is love verily
commond of hem bothyn, and al of God makyng; for he is endles
soverain trueth, endles severeyn wisdam, endles sovereyn love,
onmade; and man soule is a creature in God, which hath the same
propertyes made; and evermore it doith that it was made for: it
seith God, it beholdyth God and it lovyth God; wherof God enioyith
in the creature, and the creature in God, endlesly mervelyng; in
which mervelyng he seith his God, his lord, his maker, so hey, so
gret and so good in reward of hym that is made, that onethys the
creature semyth owte to the selfe; but the clertye and the clenes
of treuth and wisdam makyth hym to sen and to beknowen that he is
made for love; in which God endlesly kepyth him.</p></div>


        <div type="chapter">

<head>45. Of the ferme and deepe iugement of God and the variant iugement
    of man - xlv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>45. God demyth us upon our kynde substance which is ever kept on in
hym, hoole and save without end; and this dome is of his rythful-
hede. And man iugith upon our changeabil sensualyte which semyth
now on, now other, after that it takyth of the parties, and she-
wyth outward. And this wisdam is medyllid; for sumtyme it is good
and esye, and sumtyme it (is) herd and grevous. And in as mekil
as it is good and esy it longyth to the rythfulhede; and in as
mekyl as it is herd and grevous, our good lord Iesus reformyth it
be mercy and grace throw the vertue of his blissid passion, and so
bryngith into the rythfulhede. And thow these ii be thus accordid
and onyd, yet it shal be knowen, both, in hevyn without end. The
first dome, which is of God rythfulhed, and that is of his hey,
endless life; and this is that faire swete dome that was shewid
in al the fair revelation in which I saw him assigne to us no
manner of blame. And thow this was swete and delectabil, yet only
in the beholdyng of this I cowd nowte be full esyd, and that was
for the dome of holy church which I had aforn vnderstond and was
continuly in my syte. And therfore be this dome methowte me behovyd
neds to know me a synner, and be the same dome I understode that
synners arn worthy sumtime blame and wreth; and these ii cowth I
not se in God, and there my desir was more than I can or may tell;
for the heyer dome God shewid hymself in the same tyme, and ther-
fore me behovyd neds to taken it; and the lower dome was lern me
aforn in holy church, and therfore I myte in no way levyn the lower
dome. Than was this my desire: that I myte sen in God in what man-
ner that the dome of holy church herin techyth is trew in his syte,
and how it longyth to me sothly to knoyn it; wherby thei myte both
be savid, so as it wer worshipfull to God and ryte way to me. And
to al this I had non other answere but a mervelous example of a
lord and of a servant, as I shal seyn after, and that ful mytyly 
shewid. And yet I stond in desire, and will into my end, that I
myte be grace knowen these ii domys as it longyth to me; for al
hevynly and al erthly things that longyn to hevyn, arn comprehendid
in thes ii domys. And the more vnderstondyng be the gracious ledyng
of the Holy Gost that we have of these ii domys, the more we shal
sen and known our faylyngs. And ever the more that we sen hem, the
more kynd(l)y be grace we shal longen to be fulfillid of endles
ioye and bliss; for we arn made therto, and our kindly substance
is now blisful in God, and hath ben sithen it was made, and shall
without end.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter"> 

<head>46. We cannot knowen ourself in this life but be feith and grace, but
we must know ourself synners; and how God is never wreth, being
most nere the soule, it kepyng - xlvi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>But our passand lif that we have here in our sensualite knowith
not what ourself is; than shal we verily and clerly sen and knowen
our lord God in fulhede of ioy. And therfore it behovyth neds to
be that the nerer we be our bliss, the more we shall longen, and
that both be kynd and be grace. we may have knowing of ourselfe
in this life be continuant helpe and vertue of our hey kynd, in
which knowing we may encrecin and wexen be (fortheryng) and spe-
ding of mercy and grace, but we may never full know ourselfe into
the laste poynte; in which poynte this passend life and manner of
peyne and wo shall have an end. And therfore it longyth properly
to us, both be kynd and be grace, to longen and desiren with al
our myghts to knowen ourselfe in fulhede of endles ioye. And yet
in al this tyme, from the begynnyng to the end, I had ii manner
of beholdyng: that one was endless continuant love with sekirnes
of kepyng and blisful salvation, for of this was al the shewing;
that other was the common techyng of holy church in which I was
aforn enformyd and growndid, and wilfully haveing in use and under-
stondyng. And the beholdyng of this come not from me; for be the
shewing I was not sterid ne led therfrom in no manner poynte, but
I had therin teching to loven it and liken it, wherby I myte, be
the helpe of our lord and his grace, encrecy and resyn to more
hevynly knowyng and heyer lovyng. And thus in al this beholdyng
methowte it behovyd nedys to sen and to knowen that we arn synners,
and don many evill that we owten to leven, and levyn many good dedes
ondon that we owten to don, wherfore we deserve peyne and wreth.
And notwithstondyng al this I saw sothfastly that our lord was
never wreth ne never shall, for he is God: good, life, trueth,
love, peas; his charite and his unite suffrith hym not to be wroth;
for I saw trewly that it is agens the properte of myte to be wroth,
and agens the properte of his wisdam and agens the properte of his
goodnes. God is the goodnes that may not be wroth for he is not but
goodnes; our soule (is) vnyd to hym, onchangable goodnes, and bet-
wix God and our soule is neyther wroth nor forgifenes in his syte;
for our soule is fulsomly onyd to God of his owen goodnes, that
atwix God and soule may ben ryth nowte. And to this vnderstondyng
was the soul led by love and drawne be mygte in every shewing; that
it is thus our good lord shewid and how it is thus sothly of his
gret goodnes; and he will we desire to wetyn, that is to seyn, as
it longyth to his creature to wetyn it; for althyng that the simple
soule understode God will that it be shewid and knowen; for the
thyngs that he will have privy, mytyly and wisely hymselfe he hydeth
hem for love; for I saw in the same shewing that mech privity is
hid which may never be knowen into the tyme that God of his good-
nes hath made us worthy to sen it. And therwith I am wele paid,
abyding our lords will in this hey mervel. And now I yeele me to
my moder holy church as a simple child owyth.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter">

<head>47. We must reverently mervelyn and mekly suffren, ever enioyand in
God; and how our blyndhede in that we se not God is cause of
syne - xlvii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Tweyn poynts longen to our soule be dett: on is that we reverently
mervelyn, that other is that we mekely suffryn, ever enioyand in
God; for he will we wetyn that we shal in short tyme se clerly
in hymself al that we desire. And notwithstondyng al this I beheld
and mervelyd gretly what is the mercy and forgivenes of God; for
be the techyng that I had aforn, I understode that the mercy of
God shuld be the forgevenes of his wreth after the tyme that we
have synned; for methowte, to a soule whose menyng and desire is
to loven, that the wreth of God wer herder than any other peyne,
and therfor I toke that the forgevness of his wreth shuld be one
of the principal poynts of his mercy. Rut for nowte that I myte
beholden and desyrin I could no se this poynte in al the shewyng.
But how I understode and saw of the werks of mercy I shal sey sum-
del, as God wil geve me grace. I understode this man is chongeable
in this lif, and be frelte and overcummyng fallith into synne; he
is onmytye and onwise of hymself, and also his wil is overleyd;
and in this tyme he is in tempest and in sorow and wo, and the
cause is blindhede, for he seith not God; for if he sey God con-
tinuly he shuld have no mischevous felyng, ne no manner steryng
the yernyng that servyth to synne. Thus saw I and felt in the same
tyme; and methowte that the syte and the felyng was hey and plen-
tivous and gracious in reward that our commen felyng is in this
lif; but yet I thowte it was but smal and low in reward of the
great desire that the soule hath to sen God. For I felt in me v
manner of werkyngs which be these: enioying, morning, desir, drede
and sekir hope; enioyeng, for God gave me vnderstondyng and knowing
that it was hymself that I saw; morning, and that was for faylyng;
desir, and that was that I myte sen hym ever more and more, vnder-
stondyng and knowyng that we shal never have ful rest til we sen
hym verily and clerly in hevyn; drede was for it semyd to me in al
that tyme that that syte shuld fayle and I ben left to myselfe;
sekir hope was in the endles love, that I saw I shuld be kept be
his mercy and browte to his bliss. And the ioyeing in his syte
with this sekir hope of his mercyful kepyng made me to have felyng
and comforte so that morneing and drede were not gretly peynfull.
And yet in al this I beheld in the shewing of God that this manner
syte of him may not be continuant in this lif, and that for his
owen worship and for encreas of our endles ioy. And therefore we
failen oftentymes of the syte of hym, and anon we fallen into our-
self, and than fynde we no felyng of ryth - nowte but contrarioust
that is in ourselfe, and that of the elder rote of our first synne
with all that followyn of our contrivans, and in this we arn tra-
veylid and tempestid with felyng of synnys and of peynes in many
dyvers manner, gostly and bodyly, as it (is) knowen to us in this
lif.</p></div>


        <div type="chapter"> 

<head>48. Off mercy and grace and their propertyes; and how we shall enioy
    that ever we suffrid wo patiently - xlviii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>But our good lord the Holy Gost, which is endles lif wonnyng in
our soule, ful sekirly kepyth us, and werkyth therin a peas and
bryngith it to ese be grace and accordith it to God and makyth it
buxum. And this is the mercy and the wey that our lord continuly
ledyth us in as longe as we ben here in this lif which is chonge-
abile; for I sow no wreth but in mannys partie, and that forgevyth
he in us; for wreth is not ell but a frowardness and a contrarioste
to peace and to love, and eyther it commyth of faylyng of myte or
of faylyng of wisdam, or of faylyng of goodnes, which faylyng is
not in God, but it is on our partie; for we be synne and wretchid-
nes have in us a wretchid and continuant contrariuste to peace and
to love, and that shewid he full often in his lovely chere of
ruth and pety; for the ground of mercy is love, and the werkyng
of mercy is our kepyng in love; and this was shewid in swich man-
ner that I cowth not aperceyven of the partye of mercy otherwise
but as it were alone in love, that is to sey, as to my syte. Mercy
is a swete gracious werkyng in love medilyd with plentevous pitte;
for mercy werkith, us kepand, and mercy werkyth turnyng to us al-
thyng to good. Percy be love suffrith us to faylen be mesur; and
in as mech as we faylen, in so mekyl we fallen, and in as mekyl
as we fallen, so mekyl we dyen; for us behovyth nedes to deyen
in as mech as we failen syght and felyng of God that is our lif.
Our faylyng is dredful, ovr falling is shamefull and our deyng
is sorowfull; but in al this the swete eye of pite and love cum-
myth never of us, ne the werkyng of mercy cessyth not. For I be-
held the properte of mercy and I beheld the properte of grace,
which have ii manner werkyng in one love; mercy is a pitifull
propirte which longyth to the moderid in tendyr love, and grace
is a worshipful propirte which longith to the ryal lordshipp in
the same love; mercy werkyth: kepyng, suffring, quecknyng and
helyng, and al is of tendernes of love; and grace werkyth: rey-
sing, rewardyng and endlessly overpassyng that our lovyng and our
travel deservyth, spreding abrode and shewyng the hey, plentivous
largess of Godds ryal lordship in his mervelous curtesye; and this
is of the abundance of love; for grace werkyth our dredfull fay-
lyng into plentivous endles solace, and grace werkyth our shame-
full fallyng into hey worship reysyng, and grace werkyth our
sorowfull deying into holy blisfull lif; for I saw full sekirly
that ever as our contrarioust werkyth to us here in erth peyne,
shame and sorow, ryth so on the contrariewise, grace werkyth to
us in hevyn, solace, worship and bliss; and overpassyng so fer-
forth that whan we cum up and receivyn the swete reward which
grace hath wrowte to us, than we shal thankyn and blissyn our
lord, endlesly enioyand that ever we suffrid wo. And that shal
be for a properte of blissid love that we shall know in God, which
we myte never a knowen withoute wo goeing afore. And whan I saw
all this, me behovid nedis to granten that the mercy of God and
the forgiveness is to slaken and wasten our wreth.</p></div>

            <div type="chapter">  

<head>49. Our lif is growndid in love, withoute the which we perish; but
yet God is never wroth, but in our wreth and synne he mercifully
kepith us and tretith us to peace, rewarding our tribulations -
xlix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>For this was an hey mervel to the soule, which was continuly she-
wid in al, and with gret diligens beholden: that our lord God,
anempts hymself, may not forgevyn, for he may not be wroth - it
were impossible. For this was shewid: that our lif is all groun-
did and rotid in love, and without love we may not levyn; and
therfore to the soule that of his special grace seyth so fer-
forth of the hey mervelous godenes of God, and that we arn end-
lesly onyd to hym in love, it is the most impossible that may
ben that God shuld be wreth, for wreth and frendship be ii con-
traries; for he that westeth and destroyith our wreth and makyth
us meke and mylde, it behovyth neds to ben that he be ever on in
love, meke and myld, which is contrarious to wreth; for I saw ful
sekirly that wher our lord apperith peas is taken and wreth hath
no place; for I saw no manner of wreth in God, neyther for short
tyme ne for longe, for sothly, as to my syte, if God myte be
wroth a touch we shuld never have lif ne stede ne beyng; for
verily as we have our beyng of the endles myte of God and of the
endless wisdam and of the endless godeness, as verily we have our
kepyng in the endles myte of God in the endles wisdom and in the
endless goodnes; for thow we felyn in us wretches, debates and
strives, yet arn we al mannerfullbeclosyd in the mildhede of God
and in his mekehede in his benignite and in his buxumhede; for I
saw full sekirly that al our endles frendship, our stede, our lif
and our beyng is in God; for that same endles goodnes that kepith
us whan we synne that we perish not, the same endles goodnes con-
tinuly tretyth in us a peace (agaynst) our wreth and our contra-
rious fallyng and makyth us to sen our nede with a trew drede
mytyly to sekyn into God to have forgivenes with a gracious des-
ire of our salvation, for we may not be blisfully save til we be
verily in peace and in love; for that is our salvation. And thow
we, be the wreth and the contrariouste that is in us, be now in
tribulation, desese and wo, as fallyth to our blindnes and frelte,
yet arn we sekirly safe be the mercifull kepyng of God that we
perish not. But we arn not blisfully saf in havyng of our endles
ioy till we ben al in peace and in love: that is to sey, ful ple-
sid with God and with al his werks and with al his domys, and
lovand and pessible with ourselfe and with our even cristen and
with al that God lovith, as love likyth. And this doeth Gods
goodnes in us. Thus saw I that God is our very peace and he is
our sekir keper whan we arn ourse(l)fe at onpeace, and he con-
tinuly werkith to bring us into endles peas. And thus whan we,
be the werkyng of mercy and grace, be made meke and mylde, we
arn ful safe. sodenly is the soule onyd to God whan it is trewly
pesid in the selfe, for in him is fonden no wreth. And thus I
saw, whan we arn all in peace and in love we fynde no contra-
riouste ne no manner of lettyng of that contrariouste which is
now in us. Our lord of his goodnes makyth it to us ful profit-
able; for that contrarioust is cause of our tribulations and al
our wo, and our lord Iesus takyth hem and send hem up to hevyn,
and there arn thei made more swete and delectable than herte may
thynken or tongue may tellen and whan we cu(m) thither we shal
fynd hem redy, al turnyd into very faire and endless worships.
Thus is God our stedfast ground, and he shal be our full bliss
and make us onchongeable as he is, whan we arn there.</p></div>


    <div type="chapter"> 

<head>50. How the chosen soule was never ded in the syte of God, and of a
nervel upon the same; and iii things boldid hir to aske of God
 the vnderstondyng of it - 1 chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And in this dedly lif mercy and forgivenes is our wey and ever-
more ledyth us to grace. And be the tempest and the sorow that
we fallen in on our parte, we be often dede, as to manys dome
in erth, but in the syte of God the soule that shal be save was
never dede ne never shall. But yet here I wondrid and mervelid
with al the diligens of my soul memand thus: "Good lord, I se the
that art very truth and I know sothly that we synne grevously al
day and ben mekyl blameworthy; and I ne may neyther levyn the
k(n)owyng of this sothe, ner I ne se the shewyn to us no manner
of blame. How may this be?' For I knew be the common techyng of
holy church and be myne owne felyng that the blame of our synne
continuly hangith upon us, from the first man into the tyme that
we come up into hevyn; than was this my mervel, that I saw our
lord God shewand to us no more blame than if we were as clene
as holy as angelys be in hevyn. And atwix these ii contraries my
reason was gretly traveylid by my blyndhede, and cowde have no
rest for drede that his blyssid presens shuld passyn from my syte
and I to be left in onknowyng how he beholdyth us in our synne;
for either behovid me to sen in God that synne were al don awey,
or ell me behovid to sen in God how he seith it, wherby I myte
trewly knowen how it longyth to me to se synne and the manner of
our blame. Hy longyn indurid, hym continuly beholding, and yet I
cowde have no patience for great awer and perplexitie, thynkand:
"If I take it thus, that we be not synners ne no blameworthy, it
semyth as I shuld eryn and faile of knoweing of this soth. And
if it be so that we be synners and blameworthy, good lord, how
may it than ben that I cannot sen this sothnes in the, which art
my God, my maker, in whom I desire to sen al trueths? For iii
poynts makyn me herdy to ask it: the first is for it is so low
a thyng, for if it wer an hey I should ben adred; the ii is that
it is so common, for if it were special and privye, also I shuld
ben adred; the iii is that it nedyth me to wetyn it, as me thynk-
yth, if I shall levyn here, for knowyng of good and evill, wherby
I may be reason and grace the more depart hem on sundre, and loven
goodnes and haten evill as holy church techyth.' I cryed inwardly
with al my myte, sekyng into God for helpe, menand thus: "A! lord
Iesus, king of bliss, how shall I ben esyd? Ho that shal techyn me
and tellen me that me nedyth to wetyn, if I may not at this tyme
sen it in the?'</p></div>


        <div type="chapter">  

<head>51. The answere to the doute afor by a mervelous example of a lord
and a servant; and God will be abidyn, for it was nere xx yeres
after ere she fully vnderstode this example; and how it is vnder-
stod that Crist syttith on the ryth hand of the Father - li chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And than our curtes lord answerd in shewing full mystily a wonder-
ful example of a lord that hath a servant, and gave me syte to my
vnderstondyng of botyrn; which syte was shewid double in the lord,
and the syte was shewid dowble in the servant: than on partie was
shewid gostly in bodily lyknes, and the other partie was shewid
more gostly without bodyly lyknes. For the first thus: I saw ii
persons in bodyly likenes, that is to sey, a lord and a servant;
and therewith God gave me gostly understondyng. The lord sittith
solemnly in rest and in peace, the servant standyth by, aforn his
lord reverently, redy to don his lords will. The lord lookyth up-
on his servant ful lovely and swetely, and mekely he sendyth hym
to a certain place to don his will. The servant, not only he goeth,
but suddenly he stirtith and rynnith in grete haste for love to
don his lords will. And anon he fallith in a slade and takith ful
grete sore. And than he gronith and monith and waylith and writh-
ith, but he ne may rysen ne helpyn hymself be no manner wey. And
of all this the most myscheif that I saw him in was faylyng of
comforte; for he cowde not turne his face to loke upon his loving
lord, which was to hym ful nere, in whom is ful comfort; but as
a man that was febil and onwise for the tyme, he entended to his
felyng, and induryd in wo, in which wo he suffrid vii grete peynes.
The first was the sore brosyng (that) he toke in hys fallyng, which
was to hym felable peyne. The ii was the hevynes of his body. The
iii was febilnes folowyng of these twe. The iiii, that he was
blinded in his reason and stonyed in his mend so ferforth that
almost he had forgotten his owne luf. The v was that he myte not
rysen. The vi was most mervelous to me, and that was that he lay
alone; I lokid al aboute and beheld, and fer ne nere, hey ne low,
I saw to him no helpe. The vii was that the place which he lay on
was a lang, herd and grevous. I merveled how this servant myte
mekely suffren there al this wo. And I beheld with avisement to
wetyn if I cowth perceyve in hym any defaute, or if the lord shuld
assigne in hym any blame, and sothly ther was non seen; for only
his good will and his grete desire was cause of his fallyng; and
he was as onlothful and as good inwardly as whan he stode afor his
lord redy to don his wille. And ryth thus continualy his lovand
lord ful tenderly beholdyth him; and now with a double cher; on
outward, ful mekely and myldely with grete ruth and pety, and this
was of the first; another inward, more gostly, and this was shewid
with a ledyng of my vnderstondyng into the lord, which I saw hym
heyly enioyen, for the worshipful resting and nobleth that he will
and shall bryng his servant to be his plentevous grace, and this
was of that other shewyng; and now my vnderstondyng led agen into
the first, both kepand in mynd. Than seith this curtes lord in
his menyng: "Lo, lo, my lovid servant. What harme and disese he
hath takeyn in my service for my love, ya, and for his good will!
Is it not skyl that I award hym his afray and his drede, his hurt
and his mai(m)e and al his wo? And not only this, but fallith it
not to me to gevyn a geft that be better to hym and more worship-
full than his own hole shuld have ben? And ell me thynkyth I dede
hym no grace.' And in this an inward gostly shewing of the lords
menyng descendid into my soule, in which I saw that it behovith
neds to ben, stondyng his grete and his own worship, that his
dereworthy servant which he lovid so mech shuld ben verily and
blisfully rewardid without end aboven that he shuld a ben if he
had not fallen; ya, and so ferforth that his fallyng and his wo
that he hath taken therby shall be turnyd into hey and overpassing
worship and endles bliss. And at this poynte the shewing of the
example vanishid, and our good lord led forth myn vnderstondyng
in syte and in shewing of the revelation to the end. But notwith-
stondymg al this forthledyng, the mervelymg of the example cam
never from me; for methowth it was goven me for an answere to my
desir, and yet cowth I not taken therin ful vnderstondyng to myn
ese at that tyme; for in the servant that was shewid for Adam,
as I shal seyn, I saw many dyvers properties that myten be no
manner way ben aret to single Adam. And thus in that tyme I stode
mekyl in onknowyng; for the full vnderstondyng of this mervelous
example was not goven me in that tyme; in which mystye example
iii propertes of the revelation be yet mekyl hidde, and notwith-
stondyng this I saw and understode that every shewing is full of
privities, and therfore me behovith now to tellen iii propertes
in which I am sumdele esyd. The frest is the begynnyng of techyng
that I understod therein in the same tyme; the ii is the inward
lernyng that I have vnderstodyn therein sithen; the iii al the
hole revelation from the begynnyng to the end, that is to sey,
of this boke, which our lord God of his goodnes bryngeth often-
tymes frely to the syte of myn vnderstondyng. And these iii arn
so onyd, as to my vnderstondyng, that I cannot, ner may, depart
them. And be these iii as on I have techyng wherby I owe to ley-
vyn and trostyn in our lord God, that of the same godenes that
he shewed it, and for the same end, ryth so of the same goodnes
and for the same end he shal declaryn it to us whan it is his
wille. For xx yeres after the tyme of the shewing, save iii mone-
this, I had techyng inwardly, as I shal seyen: "It longyth to
the to taken hede to all the propertes and condition that weryn
shewid in the example thow thou thynke that they ben mysty and
indifferent to thy syte.' I assend wilfully with grete desire
(seeing) inwardly with avisement al the poynts and propertes that
wer shewid in the same tyme, as ferforth as my witt and vnder-
stondyng wold servyn; begynning myn beholdyng at the lord and
at the servant, and the manner of sytting of the lord, and the
place that he sate on, and tho color of his clothyng and the
manner of shapp, and his cher withouten, and his nobleth and his
godeness within; at the manner of stondyng of the servant and the
place wher and how, at his manner of clothyng, the color and the
shappe,'at his outward havyng and at his inward goodnes and his
onlothfulhede. The lord that sate solemnly in rest and in peace,
I understond that he is God. The servant that stode aforn the
lord, I understode that it was shewid for Adam, that is to seyen,
on man was shewid that tyme, and his fallyng to maken that therby
understonden how God beholdith a man and his fallyng; for in the
syte of God al man is on man and on man is all man. This man was
hurte in hys myte and made ful febil; and he was stonyed in his
vnderstondyng, for he turnyd from the beholdyng of his lord. But
his will was kept hole in God sygte; for his will I saw our lord
commenden and approven, but hymselfe was lettid and blindhed of
the knowing of this will, and this is to him grete sorow and gre-
vous disese; for neither he seith clerly his lovyng lord, which
is to him ful meke and mylde, ne he seith trewly what himself is
in the sygte of his lovyng lord. And wel I wote, when these ii
are wysely and treuly seyn, we shall gettyn rest and peas her in
parte, and the fulhede of the bliss of hevyn, be his plentivous
grace. And this was a begynnyng of techyng which I saw in the same
tyme wherby I myte com to k(n)owing in what manner he beholdyth
us in our synne. And than I saw that only paynys blamith and pun-
ishith, and our curtis lord comfortith and sorowith, ever he is
to the soule in glad cher, lovand and longand to brynen us to
bliss. The place that our lord sat on was symple, on the erth
barren and desert, alone in wildernes. His clothyng was wide and
syde, and ful semely as fallyth to a lord; the color of his cloth
was blew as asure, most sad and fair. His cher was merciful, the
color of his face was faire browne with fulsomely featours; his
eyen were blak, most faire and semely, shewand ful of lovely pety;
and within him an hey ward, longe and brode, all full of endles
hevyns. And the lovely lokeing that he loked upon his servant
continuly, and namely in his fallyng, methowte it myte molten
our herts for love and bresten hem on to for ioy. The fair lokyng
shewid of a semely medlur which was mervelous to beholden: that
on was ruth and pety, that other was ioye and bliss. The ioy and
bliss passith as fer reuth and pite as hevyn is aboven erth. The
rite was erthly and the blis was hevenly. The ruth in the pite
of (the) Fadir was of the falling of Adam, which is his most lovyd
creatur: the ioy and the bliss was of his dereworthy Son, which is
evyn with the Fadir. The merciful beholdyng of his lofly cher
fulfilled al erth and descendid downe with Adam into helle, with
which continuant pite Adam was kept from endles deth. And this
mercy and pite dwellyth with mankind into the tyme we com up into
hevyn. But man is blindid in this life, and therfore we may not
sen our Fader, God, as he is. And what tyme that he of his good-
nes will shewin hym to man, he shewith him homley as man; notwith-
stonding I ne saw sothly, we owen to knowen and levyn that the
Fader is not man. But his sitting on the erth barreyn and desert
is this to menyn: he made mans soule to ben his owen cyte and his
dwellyng place, which is most plesyng to hym of al his werks; and
what tyme that man was fallen into sorow and peyne he was not al
semly to servyn of that noble office; and therfore our kind Fader
wold adyten him no other place but sitten upon the erth abeydand
mankynd, which is medlid with erth, till what time be his grace
his derworthy Son had bowte ageyn his cyte into the noble fayrhede
with his herd travel. The blewhede of the clothing betokinith his
stedfastnes. The brownhede of his fair face with the semely blak-
hede of the eyen was most accordyng to shew his holy sobirnes.
The larghede of his clothyng, which were fair, flamand abowten,
betokenith that he hath beclesid in hym a(ll) hevyns and al ioy
and blis. And this was shewid in a touch wher I sey "Myn vnder-
stondyng was led into the lord', in which I saw him heyly enioyen
for the worshipful restoring that he wil and shal bring his ser-
vant to be his plenteous grace. And yet I mervellyd, beholdyng
the lord and the servant afornseid. I saw the lord sitten solemnly,
and the servant stondand reverently aforn his lord, in which ser-
vant is double understondyng: on withouten, another within. Out-
ward, he was clad simply as a labourer which wer disposid to travel,
and he stode ful nere the lord, not even fornempts hym, but in
partie asyd, that on the lift. His clothyng was a white kirtle,
sengil, old and al defacid, died with swete of his body, streyte
fittyng to hym and short, as it were an handful benethe the knee,
bar, semand as it shuld sone be weryd up, redy to be raggid and
rent. And in this I mervelid gretly thynkand: "This is now an on-
semely clothyng for the servant that is so heyly lovid to stondyn
afor so worship lord.' And inward, in him was shewid a ground of
love, which love he had to the lord was even like to the love that
the lord had to hym. The wisdam of the servant saw inwardly that
ther was on thing to don which shuld be to the worshipp of the
lord. And the servant for love, haveing no reward to hymselfe ne
to nothing that might fallen on him, hastely he stirt and ran at
the sendyng of his lord to don that thing which was his will and
his worship. For it semyd be his outward clothyng as he had ben
a continuant labourer of leng tyme; and be the inward syte that
I had, both in the lord and in the servant, it semyd that he was
anew, tha(t) is to sey, new begynnyng to travellyn, which servant
was never sent out aforn. Ther was a tresor in the erth which the
lord lovid. I mervelid and thowte what it myte ben. And I was ans-
wered in myn vnderstondyng: "It is a mete which is lovesome and
plesant to the lord.' For I saw the lord sitten as a man, and I
saw neither mete ner drynke wherwith to servyn hym; this was on
mervel. Another mervel was that this solemn lord had no servant
but on, and hyn he sent owte. I beheld, thynkyng what manner lab-
our it myte ben that the servant shud don. And than I understode
that he shuld don the gretest labor and herdest travel that is
he shuld ben a gardiner; delvyn and dykyn, swinkin and swetyn,
and turne the earth upsodowne, and sekyn the depnes, and wattir
the plants in tyme. And in this he shuld continu his travel and
make swete flods to rennen, and noble and plenteous fruits to
springen, which he shuld bryng aforn the lord and servyn hym ther-
with to his lykyng. And he shuld never turne agen till he had
dygte this mete al redye as he knew that it lekyd the lord, and
than he shuld take this mete, with the drinke in the mete, and
beryn it ful worshipfully aforn the lord. And al this tyme the
lord shuld sytten on the same place abydand his servant whome
he sent out. And yet I merveylid from whens the servant came;
for I saw in the lord that he hath wythyn hymselfe endles lif
and al manner of goodnes, save that tresor that was in the erth -
and that was groun(dy)d in the lord in mervelous depenes of end-
les love - but it was not all to the worship till this servant
had dygte thus nobly it, and browte it aforn him, in hymself pre-
sent; and without the lord was nothing but wildernes. And I
understod not all what this example ment, and therfore I mer-
veylid whens the servant cam. In the servant is comprehendid the
second person in the Trinite; and in the servant is comprehendid
Adam, that is to sey, al man. And therfore whan I say "the Son',
it menyth the Godhede which is even with the Fadir, and whan I
sey "the servant', it menyth Christs manhood which is rythful
Adam. Be the nerehede of the servant is understode the Son, and
be the stondyng on the left syde is vnderstod Adam. The lord is
the Fadir, God. The servant is the Son, Christ Iesus. The Holy
Gost is even love which is in them both. Whan Adam fell, God Son
fell; for the rythfull onyng which was made in hevyn, God Son
myte not fro Adam, for by Adam I understond all man. Adam fell
fro lif to deth into the slade of this wretchid world and after
that into hell. Gods Son fell with Adam into the slade of the
mayden wombe, which was the fairest dauter of Adam, and therfor
to excuse Adam from blame in hevyn and in erth; and mytyly he
fetchid him out of hell. Be the wisdam and goodnes that was in
the servant is vnderstode Godds Son. Be the por clothyng as a
laborer standand nere the left syde is vnderstode the manhood
and Adam, with al the mischef and febilnes tha(t) folowith; for
in al this our good lord shewid his owne Son and Adam but one man.
The vertu and the goodnes that we have is of Iesus Criste, the
febilnes and the blindnes that we have is of Adam; which ii wer
shewid in the servant. And thus hath our good lo(r)d Iesus taken
upon him al our blame; and therfore our Fadir may, ne will, no
nore blame assigne to us than to his owen Son, derworthy Criste.
Thus was he the servant aforne his comeing into the erth, stond-
and redy aforne the Fader in purposs till what tyme he would send
hym to don that worshipfull dede be which mankynde was browte
ageyn into hevyn; that is to seyn, notwithstondyng that he is God,
evyn with the Fadir as anempts the Godhede, but in his forseeing
purpose that he wold be man to saven man in fulfilling of his
Faders will, so he stode afore his Fader as a servant, wilfully
takyng upon hym al our charge. And than he stirt full redily at
the Faders will, and anon he fell full low in the maydens womb,
haveing no reward to himselfe ne to his herd peyns. The (wyth) 
kirtle is the flesh; the syngulhede is that there was ryte
(noght) atwix the Godhod and manhede; the steytehede is povertye;
the eld is of Adams waring; the defaceing of swete, of Adams tra-
vel; the shorthede shewith the servant labour. And thus I saw the
Son stonding, sayeing in his menyng: "Lo, my der Fader, I stond
befor the in Adams kirtle al redy to sterten and to rennen. I wold
ben in the erth to don thy worship whan it is thy will to send me.
How long shal I desiren?' Ful sothfastly wist the Son whan it was
the Fader will and how long he shal desiren; that is to sey, ane-
mpt the Godhede, for he is the wisdam of the Fader. Wherfor this
mening was shewid in vnderstondyng of the manhode of Criste; for
all mankynd that shal be savid be the swete incarnation and blis-
ful passion of Criste, al is the manhood of Criste; for he is the
hede and we be his members; to which members the day and the tyme
is onknown whan every passand wo and sorow shal have an end, and
the everlestyng ioy and bliss sha(ll) be fulfyled; which day and
time for to se al the company of hevyn longyth. And al that shall
ben under hevyn that shal come thider, ther wey is be longynge and
desire; which desir and longing was shewid in the servant stondyng
aforen the lord, or ell thus, in the Sons stondyng aforn the Fadir
in Adams kirtle; for the langor and desire of al mankynd that shal
be savid aperid in Iesus; for Iesus is al that shal be savid ana
al that shal be savid is Iesus; and al of the charite of God, with
obediens, mekeness and patience, and vertues that longyn to us.
Also in this mervelous example I have techyng with me, as it were
the begynnyng of an ABC, wherby I may have sum vnderstondyng of
our lo(r)dis menyng; for the privities of the revelation ben hidd
therin, notwithstondyng that al the shewing arn ful of privityes.
The syttyng of the Fadir betokynyth his Godhede, that is to sey,
for shewyng of rest and peas; for in the Godhede may be no travel.
And that he shewid hymselfe as lord betokynith to our manhode.
The stondyng of the servant betokynyth travel; on syde and on the
left betokynyth that he was not al worthy to stonden ever ryth
aforn the lord. His stertyng was the Godhede, and the rennyng was
the manhede; for the Godhede sterte from the Fadir into the may-
dens wombe, falling into the taking of our kynde; and in this fal-
ling he toke gret sore; the sore that he toke was our flesh in
which he had also swithe felyng of dedly peynis. Be that he stod
dredfully aforn the lord, and not even ryth, betokynith that his
clothyng was not honest to stond in eve(n) ryth aforn the lord;
ne that myte not, ne shuld not, ben his office whil he was a lab-
orer; ne also he myte not sitten in rest and peace with the lord
till he had woon his peace rythfully with his herd travel; and be
the left syde, that the Fadir left his owne Son wilfully in the
manhode to suffre all mannys paynys without sparing of him. Be
that his kirtle was in poynte to be raggid and rent is vnderstonden
the sweppys and the scorgis, the thornys and the naylys, the draw-
yng and the draggyng, his tender flesh rendyng; as I saw in sum
partie, the flesh was rent from the hedepanne, falland in (pecys) 
into the tyme the bledyng failyd; and than it began to dryand
agen, clyngand to the bone. And be the wallowyng and wrythyng,
groning and monyng is vnderstonden that he myte never rysen al
mytyly from the tyme that he was fallen into the maydens wombe
till his body was slaine and ded, he yeldyng the soule in the
Fadirs hands with al mankynd for whom he was sent. And at this
poynte he began first to shewen his myte; for he went into helle,
and whan he was there he reysid up the grit rote out of the depe
depenes which rythfully was knit to hym in hey hevyn. The body
was in the grave till Estern morow, and from that tyme he lay never
more; for then was rythfully endid the walowyng and the wrythyng,
the groning and the monyng; and our foule dedly flesh that Gods
Son toke on hym, which was Adams old kirtle, steyte, bare and
short, than be our saviour was made fair now, white and bryte and
of endles cleness, wyde and syde, fairer and richer than was than
the clothyng which I saw on the Fadir; for that clothyng was blew,
and Christs clothyng is now of a fair, semely medlur which is so
mervelous that I can it not discrien; for it is al of very worshipps.
Now sittith not the lord on erth in wilderness, but he sittith in
his noblest sete which he made in hevyn most to his lekyng. how
stondith not the Son aforn the Fadir as a servant dredfully, un-
orn ely clad, in party nakid but he stondith aforn the Fadir ever
rythe, rechely clad in blissfull largess, with a corone upon his
hede of pretious richess; for it was shewid that we be his corone,
which corone is the Fadirs ioye, tho Sonys worshippe, the Holy
Gost lekyng, and endless mervelous bliss to all that be in hevyn.
Now stondith not the Son aforn the Fadir on the left syde as a
laborer, but he sittith on his Fadirs ryte hand in endles rest
and peace. But it is not ment that the Son syttith on the ryte
hond, syde be syde, as on man sittith be another in this lif; for
ther is no such syttyng, as to my syte, in the Trinite; but he
sittith on his Fadirs ryte hand, that is to sey, in the heyest
noblyth of the Fadirs ioyes. how is the spouse, Gods Son, in peace
with his lowid wife, which is the fair mayden of endles ioye. Now
sittith the Son, very God and man, in his cety in rest and peace,
which his Fadir hath adyte to him of his endles purpose; and the
Fadir in the Son, and tho Holy Gost in the Fadir and in the Son.</p></div>


            <div type="chapter">     

<head>52. God enioyeth that he is our fadir, bother and spouse; and how the
chosen have here a medlur of wele and wo, but God is with us in
iii manner; and how we may eschew synne but never (perfectly as
in heaven)  - lii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And thus I saw that God enioyeth that he is our fader, God enioyeth
that he is our moder, and God enioyeth that he is our very spouse,
and our soule is his lovid wife. And Criste enioyeth that he is
our broder, and Iesus enioyeth that he is our savior. Ther arn v
hey ioyes, as I vnderstond, in which he wil that we enioyen, hym
praysyng, him thankyng, him loveing, him endlesly blissand. Al
that shal be savid, for the tyme of this life, we have in us a
mervelous medlur bothen of wele and wo. We have in us our lord
Iesus uprysen; we have in us the wretchidnes of the mischefe of
Adams fallyng, deyand. Be Criste we are stedfastly kept, and be
his grace touchyng we are reysid into sekir troste of salvation.
And be Adams fallyng we arn so broken in our felyng on divers man-
ner, be synes and be sondry peynes, in which we arn made derke
and so blinde that onethys we can taken ony comfort. But in our
menyng we abiden God and faithfully trosten to have mercy and
grace; and this is his owen werkyng in us. And of his godeness he
opynyth the eye of our vnderstondyng be which we have syte, sum-
tyme more and sumtyme less, after that God gevyth abilite to takyn.
And now we arn reysid into that on, and now we are suffrid to fal-
len into that other. And thus is this medle so mervelous in us
that onethys we knowen of our selfe or of our evyn Cristen in what
way we stonden, for the merveloushede of this sundry felyng; but
that ilke holy assent that we assenten to God whan we felyn hym,
truly willand to be with him with al our herte with al our soule
snd with all our myte; and than we haten and dispisen our evil
sterings and all that myte be occasion of synne gostly and bodily.
And yet nevertheles whan this sweteness is hidde, we falyn ageyn
into blindhede, and so into wo and tribulation on divers manner.
But than is this our comfort, that we knowen in our feith that
be the vertue of Criste, which is our keper, we assenten never
therto, but we grutchin theragen, and duryin in peyne and wo,
prayand into that tyme that he shewith him agen to us. And thus
we stonden in this medlur all the dayes of our life. Cut he will
we trosten that he is lestyngly with us, and that in iii manner:
he is with us in hevyn, very man in his owne person us updrawand,
and that was shewid in the gostly thrist; and he is with us in
erth us ledand, and that was shewid in the thrid, wher I saw God
in a poynte; and he is with us in our soule endlesly wonand, us
reuland and yemand, and that was shewid in the xvith, as I shal
sey. And thus in the servant was shewid the mischefe and blynd-
hede of Adams fallyng; and in the servant was shewid the wisdam
and godeness of God Son. And in the lord was shewid the ruth
and pite of Adams wo; and in the lord was shewid the hey noblyth
and the endles worship that mankynde is cum to be the vertue
of the passion and the deth of his derworthy Son; and therfore
mytyly he enioyeth in his fallyng, for the hey reysing and full-
hede of bliss that mankynde is cum to, overpassing that we shuld
have had if he had not fallen; and thus to se this overpassing
nobleth was myn vnderstondyng led into God in the same tyme that
I saw the servant fallen. And thus we have now matter of morneing
for our synne is cause of Crists paynes; and we haive lestingly
matter of ioy, for endles love made hym to suffir. And therfore
the creature that seith and felith the werkyng of love be grace
hatith nowte but synne; for of althyng, to my syte, love and hate
arn herdest and most onmesurable contraries. And notwithstondyng
all this, I saw and understode in our lord menyng that we may not
in this life kepe us from synne as holy in ful clenes as we shal
ben in hevyn. But we may wele be grace kepe us from the synnes
which will ledyn us to endles pay(n)es, as holy church techith
us, and eschewen venal, resonable upon our myte; and if we be our
blyndhede and our wretchedness ony tyme fallen, that we redily
risen, knowand the swete touching of grace, and wilfully amenden
us upon the techyng of holy chuirch after that the synne is gre-
vous, and gon forwith to God in love; and neither on the on syd
fallen over low, enclynand to despeyr, ne on that other syd ben
over rekles as if we gove no fors, but nakidly knowing our feble-
hede, witeand that we may not stond a twincklyng of an eye but be
keping of grace, and reverently cleven to God, on him only trostyng;
for otherwise is the beholdyng of God, and otherwise is the be-
holdyng of man; for it longyth to man mekely to accusen hymselfe,
and it longith to the propir goodnes of our lord God curtesly to
excusen man. And these be ii parties that were shewid in the double
chere in which the lord beheld the fallyng of his lovid servant.
That one was shewid outward, wel mekely and myldly with gret ruth
and pite, and that of endless love. And ryth thus will our lord
that we accusen ourselfe, wilfully and sothly seand and knowand
our fallyng and all the harmes that cum thereof, seand and witand
that we may neve(r) restoren it, and therwith that we wilfully
and truly sen and knowen his everlasting love that he hath  us,
and his plenteous mercy. And thus graciously to sen and knowen
both togeder is the meke accusyng that our lord askyth of us, and
hymselfe werkith it then it is. And this is the lowor parte of
manys life and it was shewed in the outward chere; in which
shewing I saw tw(o) partes: that on is the reufull falling of man,
that other is the worshipfull asseth that our lord hath made for
man. The other cher was shewid inward, and that was mor heyly and
al on; for the life and the vertue that we have in the lower parte
is of the heyer, and it cummith downe to us of the kinde love of
the selfe be grace. Atwixen that on and that other is ryte nowte,
for it is all one love; which on blissid love hath now in us double
werking; for in the lower part arn peynes and passions, ruthes and
pites, mercies and forgevenes and swich other that arn profitable;
but in the higer parte are none of these, but al on hey love and
mervelous ioye, in which mervelous ioy all peynis are heyly re-
storid. And in this our good lord shewid not only our excusung,
but also the worshipfull nobleth that he shall bring us to, turnand
al our blame into endles worshippe. </p></div>


            <div type="chapter">          

<head>53. The kindness of God assingneth no blame to his chosen, for in these
is a godly will that never consent to synne; for it behovyth the
ruthfulhede so to be knitt to these that ther be a substance kept
that may never be departid from hym - liii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And I saw that he will we wetyin he takith not herder the fallyng
of any creatur that shall be save than he to toke the fallyng of
Adam, which we knowen was endlesly lovid and sekirly kept in the
tyme of all his nede, and now is blisfully restorid in hey over-
passing ioyes; for our lord God is so good, so gentill and so
curtes that he may never assigne defaute in whom he shall ever
be blissid and praysid. And in this that I have now seyd was my
desire in partie answerid, and myn gre(te) awer sumdele esid be the
lovely, gracious shewing of our good lord; in which shewing I saw
and understode ful sekirly that in every soule that shal be save
is a godly wille that never assent to synne, ne never shall; which
wille is so good that it may never willen ylle, but eve(r)
continuly it will good and werkyth good in the syte of God There-
fore our lord will we knowen it in the feith and the beleve, and
namly and truly that we have all this blissid will hole and safe
in our lo(r)d  Iesus Christe; for that ilke kind that hevyn shall
be fulfillid with behoveth nedes, of Gods rythfulhede so to be
knitt and onyd to him that therin were kept a substance which
myte never, ne shuld be, partid from him; and that throw his owne
good will in his endles forseing purpos. And notwithstonding
this rythfull knitting and this endles onyng, yet the redemption
and the ageyn byeng of mankynd is nedefull and spedefull in every-
thing, as it is don for the same entent and to the same end that
holy church in our feith us techith; for I saw that God began never
to loven mankynd; for ryte the same that mankynde shal ben in end-
les bliss fulfilland the ioye of God as anempts his werks, ryte
so the same mankynd hath ben, in the forsyte of God, knowen and
lovid from without begynnyng in his rytefull entent. And be the
endles assent of the full accord of al the Trinite, the mid person
would be ground and hede of this fair kinde, out of whom we be
al cum, in whom we be all inclosid, into whome we shall all wyndyn;
in him fyndyng our full hevyn in everlestand ioye be the forseing
purpos of all the blissid Trinite from without begynnyng; for er
that he mad us he lovid us; and whan we were made we lovid hym;
and this is a love made of the kindly substantial goodnes of the
Holy Gost, mytye in reson of the myte of the Fadir, and wise in
mend of the wisdam of the Son; and thus is man soule made of God
and in the same poynts knitt to God. And thus I vnderstond that
mannys soule is made of nought, that is to sey, it is made, but
of nought that is made, as thus: whan God shuld make mans body
he tooke the slyppe of erth, which is a matter medlid and gaderid
of all bodily things, and therof he made mannys bodye; but to the
makyng of manys soule he wold take ryte nought, but made it. And
thus is the kynd made rytefully onyd to the maker, which is sub-
stantial kynd onmade: that is, God. And therefore it is that ther
may, ne shall, be ryte nowte atwix God and mannys soule. And in
this endles love mans soule is kept hole as the matter of the rev-
elations menyth and shewith; in which endless love we be led and
kept of God and never shall be lost; for he will we wetyn that
our soule is a lif, which lif, of his goodnes and his grace, shall
lestin in hevyn without end, him loveand, him thankand, him pray-
sand. And ryte the same we shall be withoute end, the same we
were tresurid in God, and hidde, knowen and lovid from withoute
begynning. Wherfore he will we wettyn that the noblest thing that
eve(r) he made is ma(n)kynd, and the fullest substance and the
heyest vertue is the blissid soule of Criste. And furthermore he
will we wettyn that his derworthy soule was preciousley knitt to
him in the makeing; which knott is sotil and so myty that is onyd
into God; in which onyng it is made endlesly holy. Furthermore, he
will we wettyn that al the soules that shall be savid in hevyn with-
out end ar knitt and onyd in this onyng, and made holy in this
holyhede.</p></div>

        <div type="chapter"> 

<head>54. We ought to enioye that God wonyth in our soule and our soule in
God, so that atwix God and our soule is nothing, but as it were
al God; and how feith is ground of al vertue in our soule be the
Holy Gost - liiii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>And for the grete endless love that God hath to al mankynde, he
makith no departing in love betwix the blissid soule of Crist and
the lest soule that shal be savid; for it is full hesy to leven
and to trowen that the wonyng of the blissid soule of Criste is
full hey in the glorious Godhede, and sothly, as I vnderstond in
our lord menyng, wher the blissid soule of Crist is, ther is the
substans of al the soules that shal be savid be Crist. Heyly owe
we to enioyen that God wonyth in our soule, and mekil more heyly
owe enioyen that our soule wonyth in God. Our soule is made to be
Gods wonyng place, and the wonyng place of the soule is God, which
is onmade. And hey vnderstondyng it is inwardly to sen and to kno-
wen that God which is our maker wonyth in our soule; and an heyer
vnderstondyng it is inwardly to sen and to knowen our soule, that
is made, wonyth in Gods substance; of which substance, God, we
arn that we arn. And I saw no difference atwix God and our sub-
stance, but as it were al God, and yet myn vnderstondyng toke
that our substance is in God: that is to sey, that God is God,
and our substance is a creture in God; for the almyty truth of
the Trinite is our fader, for he made us and kepith us in him;
and the depe wisdam of the Trinite is our moder in whom we arn
al beclosid; the hey goodnes of the Trinite is our lord and in
him we arn beclosid and he in us. We arn beclosid in the Fadir,
and we arn beclosid in the Son, and we arn beclosid in the Holy
Gost; and the Fader is beclosid in us, and the Son is beclosid
in us, and the Holy Gost is beclosid in us: almytyhede, al wisdam,
al goodnes, on God, on lord. And our feith is a vertue that
comith of our kynd substance into our sensual soule be the Holy
Gost, in which al our vertuys comith to us - for without that
no man may receive vertue - for it is not ell but a rythe vnder-
stondyng with trew beleve and sekir troste of our beyng that we
arn in God, and God in us, which we se not. And this vertue with
al other that God hat ordeynid to us command therin, werkith in
us grete things; for Crists mercifull werking is in us, and we
graciosly accordand to him throw the gefts and the vertues of the
Holy Gost; this werkyng makith that we arn Crists children and
cristen in liveing.</p></div>

            <div type="chapter">                

<head>55. Christ is our wey, ledand and presenting us to the Fader; and
forwith as the soule is infusid in the body mercy and grace
werkyn; and how the second person toke our sensualite to deliver
us from duble deth - Iv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And thus Criste is our wey, us sekirly ledand in his lawes, and
Criste in his body mytyly berith up into hevyn; for I saw that
Crist, us al havand in him that shal be savid be him, worship-
fully presentith his Fader in hevyn with us; which present ful
thankfully his Fader receivith and curtesly gevith to his Son,
Iesus Criste; which geft and werkyng is ioye to the Fader and
bliss to the Son and likyng to the Holy Gost. And of althyng that
to us longith, it is most likyng to our lord that we enioyen in
this ioy which is in the blisfull Trinite of our salvation. And
this was sen in the ninth shewing wher it spekith more of this
matter. And notwithstanding al our feling, wo or wele, God will
we vnderstond and feithyn that we arn more verily in hevyin than
in erth. Our feith cummith of the kynd love of our soule and of
the cler lyte of our reson and of the stedfast mend which we have
of God in our first makyng. And what tyme that our soule is in-
spirid into our body, in which we arn made sensual, also swithe
mercy and grace begynyth to werkyng, haveing of us cure and kepyng
with pite and love; in which werkyng the Holy Gost formyth in our
feith hope that we shal cum agen up aboven to our substance, into
the vertue of Criste, incresid and fulfillid throw the Holy Gost.
Thus I vnderstond that the sensualite is groundid in kind, in mercy,
and in grace; which ground abylith us to receive gefts that leden
us to endles life; for I saw full sekirly that our substance is in
God, and also I saw that in our sensualite God is; for the selfe
poynte that our soule is mad sensual, in the selfe poynt is the
cite of God, ordeynid to him from withouten begynnyng; in which
se he commith and never shal remove it, for God is never out of
the soule in which he wonen blisfully without end. And this was
sen in the xvi shewing wer it seith: "The place that Iesus takith
in our soule he shal never remov it.' And all the gefts that God
may geve to cretures he hath geven to his Son Iesus for us; which
gefts he, wonand in us, hath beclosid in him into the time that
we be waxen and growne, our soule with our body and our body with
our soule, neyther of hem takeing help of other, till we be browte
up into stature as kynd werkyth; and than, in the ground of kind
with werkyng of mercy, the Holy Gost graciously inspirith into
us gifts ledand to endless life. And thus was my vnderstondyng
led of God to sen in him and to vnderstonden, to weten and to knowen,
that our soule is made trinite, like to the onmade blisfull Trinite,
knowen and lovid fro without begynnyng; and in the makyng vnyd
to the maker as it is afornseid. This syte was full swete and
mervelous to beholden, pesible and restfull, sekir and delectabil.
And for the worshipfull onyng that was thus made of God betwix
the soule and body, it behovith needs to ben that mankynd shal
be restorid from duble deth; which restoring might neve(r) be into
the time that the second person in the Trinite had takyn the lower
party of mankynde, to whom the heyest was onyd in the first makyng;
and these ii partes were in Criste, the heyer and the lower, which
is but on soule. The heyer part was on in peace with God in full
loy and bliss; the lower partie, which is sensualite, suffrid for
the salvation of mankynd. And these ii partes were seene and felt
in the viii shewing, in which my body was fulfillid of feling and
mynd of Crists passion and his deth. And ferthermore, with this
was a sotil feling and privy inward syte of the hey parte that I
was shewid in the same tyme, wher I myte not, for the mene profir,
lokyn up onto hevyn; and that was for that mytye beholdyng of the
inward lif; which inward lif is that hey substance. that pretious
soule, which is endlesly enioyand in the Godhede.</p>
            </div>


                <div type="chapter">            

<head>56. It is esier to know God than our soule, for God is to us nerer
than that, and therfore if we will have knowing of it we must
seke into God; and he will we desir to have knowledge of kynde
mercy and grace - Ivi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And thuss I saw full sekirly that it is ridier to us to cum to the
knowyng of God than to knowen our owne soule; for our soule is so
deepe groundid in God, and so endlesly tresorid, that we may not
cum to the knowing therof till we have first knowing of God, which
is the maker to whom it is onyd. But notwithstondyng, I saw that
we have of fulhede to desiren wisely and treuly to knowen our owne
soule, wherby we are lernid to sekyn it wher it is, and that is in
God. And thus be gracious ledyng of the Holy Gost we should knowen
hem both in on, whither we be sterid to knowen God or our soule;
they arn both good and trew. God is nerer to us than our owen
soule; for he is ground in whom our soule stondith and he is mene
that kepith the substance and the sensualite to God so that thai
shall never departyn; for our soule sittith in God in very rest
and our soule stondith in God in very strength and our soule is
kindly rotid in God in endles love. And therfore if we wil have
knowlidge of our soule and comenyng and daliance therwith, it be-
hovith to sekyn into our lord God in whom it is inclosid. And of
this inclos I saw and understode more in the xvi shewing, as I
shall sey. And anempts our substan(c)e and sensualite, it may
rytely be clepid our soule; and that is be the onyng that it hath
in God. The worshipfull cyte that our lord Iesus sittith in, it
is our sensualite in which he is inclosid; and our kindly sub-
stance is beclosid in Iesus with the blissid soule of Criste
sitting in rest in the Godhede. And I saw full sekirly that it
behovith neds to be that we shuld ben in longyng and in penance
into the time that we be led so depe into God that we verily and
trewly knowen our own soule. And sothly I saw that into this hey
depenes our good lord himselfe ledith us in the same love that he
made us, and in the same love that he bowte us be mercy and grace
throw vertue of his blissid passion. And notwithstondyng al this,
we may never come to full knowyng of God till we know first clerely
our owne soule; for into the tyme that it is in the full myts we
may not be al ful holy; and that is that our sensualite be the
vertue of Crists passion be browte up to the substan(c)e, with al
the profitts of our tribulation that our lord shall make us to
gettyn be mercy and grace. I had in partie touching, and it is
grounded in kynde; that is to sey, our reson is groundid in God
which is substantial heyhede. Of this substantial kindhede mercy
and grace springith and spredith into us, werking al things in
fulfilling of our ioy. These arn our grounds in which we have our
incres and our fulfilling; for in kind we have our life and our
beyng, and in mercy and grace we have our incres and our ful-
filling; these be iii propertes in on goodnes, and wher on werkith
all werkyn in the things which be now longyng to us. God will we
onderstond, desirand of al our hert and al our strength to have
knoing of hem more and mor into the time that we ben fulfillid;
for fully to knowen hem and clerely to sen hem is not ell but end-
less ioy and bliss that we shall have in hevyn; which God will
they ben begun here in knowing of his love; for only be our reson
we may not profitteyn, but if we have verily therwith mynd and
love; ne only in our kindly ground that we have in God we may not
be savid, but if we have connyng of the same ground, mercy and
grace; for of these iii we(r)kyng  altogeder we receive all our
goodnes; of the which the first arn goods of kynd; for in our first
makyng God gaf us as ful goods and also greter godes as we myte
receivin only in our spirite, but his forseing purpos in his endles wisdam wold that we wern duble.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">         

<head>57. In our subs(t)ance we aren full, in our sensualite we faylyn, which
God will restore be mercy and grace; and how our kinde which is the
heyer part is knitt to God in the makyng, and God, Iesus, is knitt
to our kind in the lower part in our flesh takyng; and of feith
spryngyn other vertues; and Mary is our moder - Ivii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And anempts our substance, he made us nobil and so rich that ever-
more we werkyn his will and his worship. There (l) say "we', it
menith man that shall be savid; for sothly I saw that we arn that
he lovith and don that he lekyth lestingly withouten ony styntyng;
and of the gret riches and of the hey noble, vertues be mesur
come to our soule what tyme it is knitt to our body; in which
knitting we arn made sensual. And thus in our substance we arn
full, and in our sensualite we faylyn; which faylyng God will re-
store and fulfill be werkyng mercy and grace plentiously flowand
into us of his owne kynd godhede. And thus his kinde godhede mak-
ith that mercy and grace werkyn in us; and the kind godhede that
we have of him abilith us to receive the werking of mercy and
grace. I saw that our kind is in God hole, in which he makyth
diverssetis flowand out of him to werkyn his will, whom kind kep-
ith, and mercy and grace restorith and fulfillith; and of these
non shall perishen; for our kind which is the heyer part is knitt
to God in the makyng; and God is knitt to our kinde which is the
lower partie in our flesh takyng; and thus in Christ our ii kinds
are onyd; for the Trinite is comprehendid (in) Criste in whome our
heyer partie is groundid and rotid, and our lower partie the second
person hath taken, which kynd first to him was adyte; for I saw
full sekirly that all the workes that God hath done or ever shall,
wer ful knowen to him and afornseen from without begynning; and
for love he made mankynd and for the same love himself wold be
man. The next good that we receive is our feith in which our
profittyng begynnyth; and it commith of the hey riches of our
kinde substance into our sensual soule; and it is groundid in us
and we in that throw the kynde goodness of God be the werkyng of
mercy and grace. And therof commen al othir goods be which we arn
led and savid; for the commandements of God commen therein in which
we owe to have ii manner of vnderstondyng which are: his bidding to
love them and to kepyn; that other is that we owe to knowen his
forbyddings, to haten and to refusen; for in these ii is all our
werkyn comprehendid. Also in our feith commen the seven sacraments
ech folowing other in order as God hath ordeyned hem to us, and
al nanner of vertues; for the same vertues that we have receivid
of our substance, gevyn to us in kinde, be the goodness of God the
same vertues, be the werkyng of mercy, arn geven to us in grace,
throw the Holy Gost renued; which vertues and gyfts are tresurd
to us in Iesus Christ; for in that ilk tyme that God knitted him
to our body in the maydens womb he toke our sensual soule; in which
takyng, he us al haveyng beclosid in him, he onyd it to our sub-
stance, in which onyng he was perfect man; for Criste havyng knitt
in him ilk man that shall be savid, is perfit man. Thus our lady
is our moder in whome we are all beclosid and of hir borne in
Christe; for she that is moder of our savior is moder of all that
shall be savid in our savior. And our savior is our very moder
in whom we be endlesly borne and neve(r) shall come out of him.
Plenteously and fully and swetely was this shewid; and it is spoken
of in the first wher he seith we arn all in him beclosid and he
is beclosid in us; and that is spoken of in the xvi shewing wher
it seith he sittith in our soule; for it is his likeyng to reygne
in our vnderstonding blisfully, and sitten in our soule restfully,
and to wonen in our soule endlesly, us al werkeng into hym; in
which werkyng he will we ben his helpers, gevyng to him al our
entendyng, lerand his loris, kep(yng) his lawes, desirand that al
be done that he doith, truely trosting in hym; for sothly I saw
that our substan(c)e is in God.</p></div>


                        <div type="chapter">                      

<head>58. God was never displesid with his chosin wif; and of iii properties
in the Trinite: faderhede, moderhede and lordhede; and how our
substance is in every person, but our sensualite is in Criste
alone - Iviii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>God, the blisful Trinite which is everlestand beyng, ryte as he
is endless from without begynnyng, ryte so it was in his purpose
endles to maken mankynd; which fair kynd first was adyte to his
owen Son, the second person. And whan he wold, be full accord of
all the Trinite, he made us all at onys; and in our makyng he
knitt us and onyd us to hymse(l)fe; be which onyng we arn kept
as clene and as noble as we were made. Be the vertue of the ilke
pretious onyng we loven our maker and liken him, praysen him and
thankyng him and endlesly enioyen in him. And this is the werke
which is wrought continuly in every soule that shal be save;
which is the godly will afornseid. And thus in our makeyng God
almigty is our kindely fader; and God al wisdam is our kindly
moder, with the love and the goodnes of the Holy Gost; which is
al one God, on lord. And in the knittyng and in the onyng he is
our very trew spouse, and we his lovid wif and his fair maiden,
with which wif he is never displesid; for he seith: "I love the
and thou lovist me, and our love shal never be departid on to.'
I beheld the werkyng of all the blissid Trinite, in which be-
holdyng I saw and vnderstode these iii properties: the properte
of the faderhede, the properte of the moderhede and the properte
of the lordhede in one God. In our Fader almyty we have our keping
and our bliss as anemts our kind(l)y substance, which is to us
be our makyng without begynnyng; and in the second person, in witt
and wisdam, we have our keping as anempts our sensualite, our re-
storyng and our savyng; for he is our moder, brother and savior.
And in our good lord the Holy Gost we have our rewarding and our
(y)eldyng for our lifyng and our travel; and endless overpassing
all that we desiren, in his mervelous curtesy, of his hey plen-
tivous grace. For al our life is in thre. In the first we have
our beyng and in the second we have our encresyng and in the thrid
we hav our fulfilling. The first is kinde; the second is mercy;
the thred is grace. For the first: I saw and vnderstod that the
hey myte of the Trinite is our fader, and the depe wisdam of the
Trinite is our moder, and the grete love of the Trinite is our
lord; and al this have we in kynd and in our substantial makyng.
And ferthermore, I saw that the second person, which is our moder
substantial, that same derworthy person is become our moder sen-
sual; for we arn duble of Gods making: that is to say, substantiall
and sensual. Our substance is the heyer parte, which we have in
our fader, Cod almyty; and the second person of the Trinite is our
moder in kynde in our substantiall makeyng, in whome we arn groundid
and rotid, and he is our moder in mercy in our sensualite takyng.
And thus our moder is to us dyvers manner werkyng, in whom our
parties are kepid ondepartid; for in our moder, Criste, we profitten
and encresin, and in mercy he reformith us and restorith, and, be
the vertue of his passion and his deth and uprisyng, onyth us to
our substance. Thus werkith our moder in mercy to all his children
which arn to him buxum and obedient. And grace werkyth with mercy,
and namely in ii propertes as it was shewid; which werkyng longyth
to the tred person, the Holy Gost. He werkith rewardyng and gefyng;
rewardyng is a large gevyng of trewth that the lord doth to hym
that hath travellid, and gevyng is a curtes workyng which he doith
frely of grace fulfill, and overpassand al that is deservid of
cretures. Thus in our fader, God almigty, we have our beyng; and
in our moder of mercy we have our reformyng and restoryng, in whome
our partes are onyd and all made perfitt man; and be yeldyng and
(gevyng) in grace of the Holy Gost we arn fulfilled. And our sub-
stance is our fader, God almyty, and our substance is ou(r) moder,
God al wisdamm, and our substance is in our lord the Holy Gost,
God al goodnes; for our substance is hole in ilke person of the
Trinite, which is on God. And our sensualite is only in the second
person, Crist Iesus, in whom is the Fader and the Holy Gost; and
in him and be him we arn mytyly taken out of helle and out of the
wretchidnes in erth, and worshipfully browte up into hevyn and
blisfully onyd to our substance, incresid in riches and noblith,
be al the vertue of Criste and be the grace and werkyng of the
Holy Gost.</p></div>


                            <div type="chapter"> 

<head>59. Wickednes is turnyd to bliss be mercy and grace in the chosyn,
for the properte of God is to do good ageyn ille, be Iesus our
moder in kynd grace; and the heyest soule in vertue is mekest,
of which ground we have other vertues - lix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And all this bliss we have be mercy and grace; which manner of
bliss we myte never had ne knowen but if that propertes of good-
ness which is God had ben contraried, wherby we have this bliss;
for wickednes hath ben suffrid to rysen contrarye to the goodnes,
and the goodnes of mercy and grace contraried ageyn the wickidnes,
and turnyd al to goodness and to worship to al these that shal
be savid; for it is the properte in God which doith good agen
evil. Thus Iesus Criste that doith good agen evill is our very
moder; we have our beyng of him wher the ground of moderhed be-
gynnyth, with al the swete kepyng of love that endlessly folowith.
As veryly as God is our fader, as verily God is our moder; and that
shewid he in all, and namely in these swete words where he seith
"I it am', that is to seyen: "I it am: the myte and the goodness
of the faderhed. I it am: the wisdam of the moderhede. I it am:
the lyte and the grace that is al blissid love. I it am: the Trinite.
I it am: the unite. I am the sovereyne goodness of all manner of
thyngs. I am that makyth the to loven. I am that makyth the to
longen. I it am: the endles fulfilling of al trew desires.' For
then the soule is heyest, noblest and worthyest when it is lowest,
mekest and myldhest; and of this substantial ground we have al
our vertues and our sensualite be gyft of kynd and be helpyng
and spedyng of mercy and grace, without the which we may not
profitten. Our hey fader, God almyty, which is beyng, he knew us
and lovid us fro aforn any tyme; of which knoweing, in his mer-
velous depe charite be the forseing endless councel of all the
blissid Trinite, he wold that the second person shuld becom our
moder, our brother and our savior. Wherof it folowith that as
verily as God is our fader, as verily God is our moder. Our fader
(wyllyth), our moder werkyth, our good lord the Holy Gost con-
firmith. And therfore it longyth to us to loven our God in whom
we have our being, him reverently thankyng and praiseyng of our
makyng, mytily prayeng to our moder of mercy and pite, and to
our lord the Holy Gost of helpe and grace; for in these iii is
all our life - kynde, mercy and grace; whereof we have mekehede,
myldhede, patiens and pite, and hatyng of synne and wickidnes; for
it longith properly to vertues to haten synne and wickidness.
And thus is Iesus our very moder in kynde, of our first makyng,
and he is our very moder in grace be takyng of our kynde made.
All the fair werkyng and all the swete kindly office of dere-
worthy moderhede is impropried to the second person; for in him
we have this godly will hole and save without ende, both in kinde
and grace, of his owne proper goodnes. I vnderstode iii manner
of beholdyng of moderhede in God: the first is groundid of our
kinde makeying; the second is taken of our kinde, and there be-
gynnyth the moderhede of grace; the thrid is moderhede of werkyng
and therin is a forthspreadyng, be the same grace, of length and
bredth and of heyth and of depenes withouten end, and al his owm
luf.</p></div>

            <div type="chapter"> 
<head>60. How we be bowte ageyn and forthspred be mercy and grace of our
swete, kynde and ever lovyng moder Iesus, and of the propertes
of moderhede; but Iesus is our very moder, not fedyng us with
mylke but with himselfe, opening his syde onto us and chalengyng
al our love - Ix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>But now behovyth to sey a litil mor of this forthspredyng, as I
vnderstond in the menyng of our lord, how that we be bowte agen
be the moderhede of mercy and grace into our kyndly stede wher
that we were made by the moderhede of kynd love; which kynd love
it never levyth us. Our kynd moder, our gracious moder, for he
wold al holy become our moder in althyng, he toke the ground of
his werke full low and ful myldely in the maydens womb. And that
he shewid in the first, where he browte that meke mayde aforn the
eye of myn vnderstondyng in the simple statur as she was whan she
conceivid; that is to sey, our hey God is sovereyn wisdom of all,
in this low place he raysid him and dyte him ful redy in our pore
flesh, himselfe to don the service and the office of moderhede in
allthyng. The moders service is nerest, redyest and sekirest, for
it is most of trueth. This office ne myte, ne couthe, ne never
non don to the full (but) he alone. We wetyn that all our moders
beryng is us to peyne and to deyeng; and what is that but our
very moder Iesus, he, al love, beryth us to ioye and to endles
lyving; blissid mot he be! Thus he susteynith us within himselfe
in love, and traveled into the full tyme that he wold suffre the
sharpist throwes and the grevousest peynes that ever were or ever
shall be, and dyed at the last. And whan he had don, and so born
us to bliss, yet myte not al this makyn aseth to his mervelous
love; and that shewid he in these hey overpassing wordes of love:
"If I myte suffre more, I wold suffre more.' He myte ne more dyen,
but he wold not stynten of werkyng. Wherfore than him behovyth to
fedyn us, for the dereworthy love of moderhede hath made him dettor
to us. The moder may geven hir child soken her mylke, but our
pretious moder Iesus, he may fedyn us with himselfe; and doith
full curtesly and full tenderly with the blissid sacrament that
is pretious fode of very lif. And with al the swete sacraments
he susteynith us ful mercifully and graciously. And so ment he
in this blissid word wher that he seid "I it am that holy church
prechith the and techith the'; that is to sey: "All the helth
and lif of sacraments, al the vertue and grace of my word, all
the godness that is ordeynid in holy church for the, I it am.'
The moder may leyn the child tenderly to her brest, but our ten-
der moder Iesus, he may homley leden us into his blissid brest
be his swete open syde, and shewyn therin party of the Godhede
and the ioyes of hevyn, with gostly sekirnes of endless bliss;
and that shewid in the (x)  gevyng the same vnderstondyng in this
swete word wher he seith "Lo how I love the', beholdand into
his syde, enioyand. This fair lovely word "moder', it is so swete
and so kynd of the self that it may ne verily be seid of none
but of him, and to hir that is very moder of hym and of all. To
the properte of moderhede longyth kinde love, wisdam and knowing,
and it is good; for thow it be so that our bodily forthbrynging
be but litil, low and semple in regard of our gostly forthbringing
yet it is he that doth it in the creatures be whom that it is done.
The kynde, loveand moder that wote and knowith the nede of hir
child, she kepith it ful tenderly as the kind and condition of
moderhede will. And as it wexith in age she chongith hir werking
but not hir love. And whan it is waxen of more age, she suffrid
that it be bristinid in brekyng downe of vices to makyn the child
to receivyn vertues and graces. This werkyng, with al that be fair
and good, our lord doith it in hem be whom it is done. Thus he is
our moder in kynde be the werkyng of grace in the lower parte,
for love of the heyer parte. And he will that we know it; for he
will have al our love festynyd to him. And in this I saw that all
our dett that we owen, be Gods biddyng, be faderhede and moderhede,
for Gods faderhede and moderhede is fulfillid in trew lovyng of
God; which blissid love Christ werkyth in us. And this was shewid
in all, and namly in the hey plentivous words wher he seith: "I
it am that thou lovest.'</p></div>


                <div type="chapter">           

<head>61. Iesus usith more tenderness in our gostly bringing forth; thow
he suffrith us to fallyn in knowing of our wretchidness, he
hastily reysith us, not brekyng his love for our trespass, for
he may not suffre his child to perish; for he will that we have
the properte of a child, fleing to him alway in our necessite -
Ixi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And in our gostly forthbringyng he usith mor tenderness of keping,
without ony likenes, be as mech as our soule is of more price in
his syte. He ky(n)delyth our vnderstondyng, he directith our weys,
he esith our consciens, he comfortith our soule, he lightith our
our herte and gevith us, in parte, knowyng and lovyng in his blis-
ful Godhede, with gracious mynd in his swete manhede and his blis-
sid passion, with curtes mervelyng in his hey, overpassyng goodnes;
and makith us to loven al that he loveth for his love, and to bend
payd with him and all his werkes. And we fallen, hastily he reysith
us be his lovely clepyng and gracious touchyng. And whan we be thus
st(r)engtid be his swete werkyng, than we wilfully chesyn him, be
his swete grace, to be his servants and his lovers lestingly with-
out end. And after this he suffrith sum of us to fallen more hard
and more grevously than ever we diden afore, as us thynkyth. And
than wene we that be be not al wyse that al wer nowte that we have
begun. But it is no so; for it nedith us to fallen, and it nedith
us to sen it; for if we felle nowte we should not knowen how febil
and how wretchid we arn of ourselfe; ne also we shuld not ful-
somely so knowen the mervelous love of our maker; for we shal sen
verily in hevyn withouten end that we have grevously synned in
this life and, notwithstondyng this, we shal sen that we were
never hurt in his love, ne were never the less of price in his
syte. And be the assay of this failyng we shall have an hey, mer-
velous knoweing of love in God without end; for herd and mervelous
is that love which may nowte, ne will not, be brokin for trespas.
And this is one understonding of profite. Another is the lownes
and mekenes that we shal gettyn be the syte of our fallyng; for
therby we shal heyly ben raysid in hevyn; to which reysing we
might never a come withoute that mekeness. And therfore it nedyth
us to sen it, and if we sen it not, thow we fellyn, it shuld not
profitt us. And commenly, first we fallen, and syth we sen it;
and both of the mercy of God. The moder may suffre the child to
fallen sumtyme and be disesid in dyvers manners for the owen pro-
fitt, but she may neve(r) suffre that ony maner of peril cum to the
child, for love. And thow our erthly moder may suffre hir child
to perishen, our hevynly moder Iesus may not suffre us that arn
his children to perishen; for he is almyty, all wisdom and al love;
and so is non but he. Blissid mot he ben! But oftentymes whan our
fallyn and our wretchidnes is shewid us, we arn so sore adred and
so gretly ashamid of ourselfe that onethys we wettyn where that
we may holden us. But than will not our curtes moder that we fle
awey, for him wer nothing lother. But he will than that we usen
the condition of a child; for whan it is disesid or dred it ren-
nith hastely to the moder for helpe with al the myte; so wil he
that we don as a meke child, sey and thus: "My kind moder, my gra-
cious moder, my dereworthy moder, have mercy on me. I have made
myselfe foule and onlike to the, and I ne may ne can amenden it
but with prive helpe and grace.' And if we fele us not than esyd
al swithe, be we sekir that he usith the condition of a wise
moder; for if he sen that it be more profitt to us to morne and
to wepen, he suffrith it with ruth and pite into the best tyme,
for love. And he will than that we usen the propertie of a child
that evermor kindly trosteth to the love of the moder in wele and
in wo. And he will that we taken us mytyly to the feith of holy
church and fyndyn there our dereworthy moder in solace of trew
vnderstondyng with al the blissid common; for on singler person
Bay oftentymes be broken as it semyth to selfe, but the hole body
of holy church was never broken, ne never shall, withouten end.
And therfore a sekir thing it is, a good and a gracious, to wil-
len mekely and mytyly ben susteynd and onyd to our moder, holy
church, that is, Crist Iesus; for the foode of mercy that is his
dereworthy blood and pretious water is plentious to make us faire
and clene. The blissid wound of our savior ben open and enioyen
to helyn us; the swete gracious hands of our moder be redy and
diligently aboute us; for he in al this werkyng usith the office
of a kinde nurse and hath not all to don but to entendyn abouten
the salvation of hir child. It is his office to saven us, it is
his worship to don us, and it is his will we knowen it; for he
will we loven him swetely and trosten in him mekely and mytyly.
And this shewid he in these gracious words: "I kepe the ful se-
kirly.'</p></div>

                    <div type="chapter">      

<head>62. The love of God suffrith never his chosen to lose tyme, for all
their troble is turnyd into endles ioye; and how we arn al bown-
den to God for kindness and for grace; for every kind is in man
and us nedyth not to seke out to know sondry kindes, but to holy
church - Ixii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>For in that tyme he shewid our frelte and our fallyngs, our bre-
kyngs and our nowtyngs, our dispits and our outcastings: all our
wo so ferforth as methowte it my(ght) fallen in this life. And
therwith he shewid his blissid myte, his blissid wisdam, his blis-
sid love, that he kepyth us in this tyme as tenderly and as swetely
to his worship and as sekirly to our salvation as he doith whan
we are in most solace and comfort; and therto he reysith us gostly
and heyly in hevyn, and turnith it al to his worship and to our
ioye, withoute end; for his love suffrith us never to lose tyme.
And all this is of the kind goodnes of God be the werkyng of grace.
God is kynde in his being: that is to sey, that goodnes that is
kind, it is God. He is the ground, he is the substance, he is the
same thing that is kindhede, and he is very fader and very moder
of kynde. And all kindes that he hath made to flowen out of him
to werkyn his will, it shall be restorid and browte ageyn into
him be the salvation of man throw the werking of grace; for of
all kyndes that he hath set in dyvers creatures be parte, in man
is all the hole in fulhede, in vertue, in fairhede and in goodhede,
in rialtie and nobley, in al manner of solemnite of pretioushede
and worshipp. Here may we sen that we arn al bound to God for
kinde, snd we arn al bound to God for grace. Here may we sen us
nedith not gretly to seken fer out to knowen sundry kindes, but
to holy church, into our moder brest; that is to sey, into our
owen soule, wher our lord wonnyth. And ther shall we fynde all;
now, in feith and in vnderstondyng; and after, verily in himselfe,
clerely, in bliss. But no man ne woman take this singler to him-
selfe; for it is not so, it is general; for it is our pretious
Criste and to him was this fair kind dyte, for the worship and
noblyth of mannys makyng, and for the ioye and the bliss of mannys
salvation; ryte as he saw, wiste and knew from without begynni(n)g. </p></div>

    <div type="chapter">        

<head>63.Synne is more peynfull than hell, and vile and hurting kinde, but
grace savith kinde and destroyith synne; the children of Iesus be
not yet all borne, which pass not the stature of childhood, livyng
in febilnes till thei come to hevyn wher ioyes arn ever new be-
gynnand without end - Ixiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Here may we sen that we have verily of kinde to haten synne, and
we have verily of grace to haten synne; for kinde is al good and
faire in the selfe, and grace was sent out to saven kind and de-
stroyen synne and b(r)yngen ageyn fair kinde to the blissid poynt
fro whens it came, that is God, with mor noble and worshipp be
the vertuous werkeyng of grace; for it shal be sen afor God of
al his holy in ioye without end that kind hath ben assayed in the
fire of tribulation and therin founden no lak, no defaut. Thus
is kind and grace of on accord; for grace is God as kind is God.
He is ii in manner werkyng and one in love, and neyther of hem wer-
kyth without other, non be departid. And whan we be mercy of God
and with his helpe accorden us to kynde and grace, we shall seen
verily that synne is very viler and peynfuller than helle, with-
out likenes; for it is contrarious to our fair kinde; for as
sothly as synne is onclene, as soth(l)y is it onkinde, and thus an
horrible thing to sen to the lovid soule that wold be al faire
and shynand in the syte of God as kinde and grace te(c)hith. 
But be we not adred of this, but in as much as drede may spede
us, but mekely make we our mone to our dereworthy moder, and he
shal al besprinkle us in his precious blode and make our soule
ful soft and ful myld, and hele us ful faire be proces of tyme,
ryte as it is most worship to him and ioy to us without end. And
of this swete fair werkyng he shall neve(r) cesyn ne stintin till
all his derworthy children be born and forth browte. And that
shewid he wher he shewid vnderstonding of gostly threst, that is
the lovelongyng that shal lestin till domysday. Thus in very moder,
Iesus, our life is groundid in the forseing wisdam of himselfe
from without begynnyng, with the hey myte of the Fader and the
hey sovereyn goodnes of the Holy Gost. And in the takyng of our
kinde he quicknid us, in his blissid deying upon the cross he
bare us to endless life; and fro that time, and now, and ever shall
onto domysday, he fedith us and (fordreth) us; and ryte as that
hey sovereign kindness of moderhede and as kindly nede of child-
hede askith. Faire and swete is our hevenly moder in the syte of
our soule; precious and lovely arn the gracious children in the
syte of our hevinly moder, with myldhede and mekeness and all the
fair vertues that long to children in kynde; for kindly the child
dispeirith not of the moder love; kindly the child presumith not
of the selfe; kindly the child lovith the moder and ilke on of the
othe(r); these arn the fair vertues, with all other that ben like,
wherwith our hevenly moder is servid and plesyd. And I vnderstode
non heyer stature in this life than childhode, in febilness and
fayleing of myte and of witte, into the time that our gracious
moder hath browte us up to our faders bliss. And than shall it
verily be made knowen to us his menyng in these swete words wher
he seith: "Al shall be wele,' and thou shalt sen thyselfe that al
maner thyng shal ben wele.' And than shall the bliss of our moder
in Criste be new to begynnen in the ioyes of our God; which new
begynning shal lesten without end, new begynnand. Thus I vnder-
stode that al his blissid children which ben comen out of him
be kinde shal be bowte ageyn into him be grace.</p></div>



        <div type="chapter">

<head>64. The xv revelation is as it shewid etc.; the absense of God in this
lif is our ful gret peyne, besyde other travels, but we shal sod-
enly be taken fro all peyne, having Iesus to our moder; and our
patient abyding is gretly plesyng to God, and God wil take our
disese lightly, for love, thinkand us alwey at the poynte to be
deliverid - Ixiiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Aforn this tyme I had gret longyng and desire of Goddis gifte to
be deliverid of this world and of this lif; for oftentimes I be-
held the wo that is here, and the wele and the bliss that is beyng
there. And if ther had ben no peyn in this lif but the absens of
our lord, methowte it was sumtime mor than I myte baren; and this
made me to morn and besyly to longen, and also of myn owen wretch-
idnes, slawth and wekehede, that me lekid not leveyn and to tra-
velyn as me fel to don. And to all this our curtes lord answerid
for comfort and patiens, and said these words: "Sodenly thou shal
be taken fro al thy peyne, fro al thi sekeness, fro al thi disese
and fro al the wo. And thou shalt commen up aboven, and thou shalt
have me to thi mede, and thou shal be fulfillid of love and of
bliss. And thou shal never have no maner of peyne, no manner of
mislekyn, no wanting of will, but ever ioye and bliss withouten
ende. What shuld it than agrevyn the to suffre awhile, sen that
it is my will and my worship?' And in this word, "Sodenly thou shal
be taken', I saw that God rewardith man of the patiens that he
hath in abyding Gods will, and of his tyme, and that man lengith
his patiens over the tyme of his living; for onknowing of his
tyme of passing, that is a gret profitt; for if a man knew his
time, he shuld not have patience over that tyme. And as God will
while the soule is in the body it semyt to the selfe that it is
ever at the poynte to be takyn; for al this life and this langor
that we have here is but a poynte, and whan we arn taken sodenly
out of peyn into bliss, than peyn shall be nowte. And in this
tyme I saw a body lyand on the erth, which body shewid hevy and
ogyley, withoute shappe and forme as it were a bolned quave of
styng and myre. And sodenly out of this body sprang a ful fair
creature, a little childe full shapen and formid, swifie and
lively, whiter than lilly, which sharpely glode up onto hevyn.
And the bolnehede of the body betokenith gret wretchidnes of our
dedly flesh, and the littlehede of the child betokenith the clenes
of purity in the soule. And (l) thowte: "With this body belevith 
no fairehede of this child, no on this child dwellith no foulehede
of this body.' It is ful blisfull, man to be taken fro peyne,
mor than peyne to be taken fro man; for if peyn be taken fro
us it may commen agen. Therfore it is a severen comfort and bliss-
full beholdyng in a lovand soule (that) we shal be taken fro peyne;
for in this behest I saw a mervelous compassion that our lord
hath in us for our wo, and a curtes behoting of clene deliver-
ance; for he will that we be comforted in the overpassing; and
that he shewid in these words: "And thou shalt come up aboven;
and thou shal have me to thi mede; and thou shall be fullfillid
of ioye and bliss.' It is God will that we setten the poynte of
our thowte in this blisfull beholdyng as often as we may, and as
long tyme kepen us therin with his grace; for this is a blissid
contemplation to the soule that is led of God, and full mekil to
his worship for the time that it lestith. And we falyn ageyn to
our hevynes and gostly blyndhede and felyng of peyens gostly and
bodily be our frelte, it is God will that we knowen that he hath
not forgetten us. And so menith he in thes words and seith for
comfort: "And thou shall never more have peyne, no manner sekenes,      .
no maner mislekyng, non wanting of will, but over ioy and bliss
withouten ende. What shuld it than agrevyn the to suffre awhile
seing it is my will and my worshippe?' It is God will we taken
his behests and his comfortings as largely and as mytyly as we
may taken hem. And also he will that we taken our abiding and
our diseses as lytely as we may taken hem, and set hem at nowte;
for the lyter we taken hem and the less price we setten at hem
for love, the less peyne shall we have in the feling of hem, and
the more thanke and mede shal we have for hem.</p></div>

                                
            <div type="chapter">        

<head>65. He that chesith God for love, with reverent mekeness, is sekir to
be savid; which reverent mekenes seith the lord mervelous grete,
and the selfe mervelous litil; and it is God will we drede no-
thing but him, for the power of our enemy is taken in our freinds
hand; and therfore al that God doith shall be gret likyng to
us - Ixv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And thus I vnderstode that what man or woman wilfully chesith God
in this life for love, he may be sekir that he is lovid without
end; which endless love werkith in him that grace; for he will
that we kepe this trosty, that we be all sekir in hope of the
bliss of hevyn whil we arn here, as we shall be in sekirnes whan
we arn there. And ever the more likyng and ioy that we taken in
this sekirness with reverens and mekenes, the better likyth him,
as it was shewid. This reverens that I mene is a holy, curtes
drede of our lord, to which mekeness is knitt: and that is, that
a creture seith the lord mervelous grete, and the selfe mervelous
litil; for these vertues arn had endlesly to the lovid of God,
and it mon now ben sen and felt in mesure be the gracious pre-
sence of our lord whan it is; which presens in althing is most
desirid, for it werkith mervelous sekirness, in trew feith and
sekir hope be gretness of charite, in drede that is swete and
delectable. It is God will that I se myselfe as mekil bounden to
him in love as if he had don for me al that he hath don. And thus
should every soule thinkyn innward of his lover: that is to seyn,
the charite of God makyth in us such a unite that whan it is
trewly seen no man can parten himse(l)fe fro other. And thus oweth
our soule to thinken that God hath don for him al that he hath
don; and this shewith he to maken us to loven him and nowte drede
but him; for it is his will that we wetyn that al the myte of our
enemy is token into our frends hand; and therfore the soule that
wott sekirly this, he shall not dredyn but him that he lovith.
All our dreds he setteth among passions and bodely sekenes and
imaginations, and therfore thow we be in so mech peyne, wo and
disese that us thinkith we can thynke ryte nowte but that we arn
in, or that we felyn, as sone as we may, pass we lytely over and
sett we it at nowte. And why? For God will we knowen, if (we) 
knowen him and loven him and reverently dredyn him, we shall have
peas and ben in grete rest; and it shall be gre(at) lykyng to
us all that he doith. And this shewid our lord in these words:
"What shuld it than agrevyn the to suffre awhile, sith it is my
will and my worshippe?' Now have I told you of xv revelations as
God vouchsafe to ministren hem to mynd, renewid by lyghtings and
tuchyngs, I hope, of the same spirite that shewid hem all; of
which xv sheweings the first beganne erly on the morne, aboute
the howre of fowre, and it lestid, shewing be proccess ful faire
and sekirly, ich folow and other, till it was none of the day
overpassid.</p></div>



                <div type="chapter">              

<head>66. The xvi revelation etc., and it is conclusion and confirmation
to all xv; and of hir frelte and morning in disese and lyte
speking after the gret comfort of Iesus, seying she had ravid,
which, being hir gret sekeness, I suppose was but venial synne;
but yet the devil after that had gret power to vexin hir ner to
deth - Ixvi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And after this the good lord shewid the xvi on the night folowing
as I shall seyn after; which xvi was conclusion and confirmation
to all xv. But first me behovith to tellen you as anempt my febil-
nes, wretchidnes and blindness. I have seid in the begynnyng "And
in this al my peine was sodenly taken from me'; of which peyne I
had no grefe, no disese, as long as the xv shewings lestid folow-
and; and at the end al was close and I saw no more. And sone I
felt that I shuld liven and langiren; and anon my sekenes cam
agen: first in my hede, with a sound and a dynne; and sodenly all
my body was fu(l)fillid with sekenes like as it was aforn, and
I was as baren and as drye as I never had comfort but litil. And
as a wretch I moned and hevyed for felyng of my bodily pey(n)es 
and for fayling of comfort, gostly and bodily. Than cam a religious
person to me and askid me how I ferid. And I seyd I had ravid
today, and he leuhe loud and inderly. And I seyd: "The cross that
stod afor my face, methowte it blode fast.' And with this word the
person that I spake to waxid al sad and mervelid. And anon I was
sor ashamid and astonyed for my recleshede, and I thowte: "This
man takith sadly the lest word that I myte seyen than saw I no
mor therof.' And whan I saw that he toke it sadly and with so
gret reverens, I wepid, ful gretly ashamid, and wold have ben
shrevyn; but at that tyme I cowde tell it no preist, for I thowte:
"How should a preist levyn me? I leve not our lord God.' This I
levid sothfastly for the tyme that I saw him, and so was than my
will and my menyng ever for done without end, but as a fole I let
it passyn from my mynd. A! lo I, wretch. This was a gret synne,
grete onkindness, that I for foly, of feling of a litill bodily
peyne, so onwisely lost for the time the comfort of all this blis-
sid shewing of our lord God. Here may you sene what I am of my-
selfe; but herein wold our curtes lord not leve me. And (l) lay
still till night trosting in his mercy, and than I gan to slepyn. 
And in the slepe, at the begynnyng, methowte the fend set him
in my throte, puttand forth a visage ful nere my face like a yong
man; and it was longe and wonder lene; I saw never none such. The
color was rede like the tilestone whan it is new brent, with blak
spots therin like blak steknes, fouler than the tilestone. His
here was rode as rust, evisid aforn, with syde lokks hongyng on
the thounys. He grynnid on me with a shrewd semelant, shewing
white teeth; and so mekil methowte it the more oggley. Body ne
hands had he none shaply, but with his pawes he held me in the
throte and would have stranglid me, but he myte not. This oggley
shewing was made slepyng, and so was non other. And in all this
time I trostid to be savid and kepid be the mercy of God. And
our curtes lord gave me grace to waken, and onethis had I my lif.
The persons that wer with me beheld me and wet my temples, and
my herte began to comforten. And anon a lyte smoke came in the
dore with a grete hete and a foule stinke. I said: "Benedicite &amp; 
domine! It is al on fire that is here!' And I wened it had ben a
bodily fire that shuld a brent us al to dede. I askid hem that
wer with me if thei felt ony stynke. Thei seyd nay, thei felt
none. I said "Blissid be God!', for that wist I wele it was the
fend that was comen to tempest me. And anon I toke to that our
lord had shewid me on the same day, with al the feith of holy
church, for I beheld it is bothen one, and fled therto as to my
comforte. And anone al vanishid away, and I was browte to gret
rest and peas withouten sekenes of body or drede of conscience.</p></div>



                    <div type="chapter">

<head>67.Of the worshipfull syte of the soule, which is so nobly create
that it myte no better a be made, in which the Trinite ioyeth
everlastingly; and the soule may have rest in nothing but in
God, which sittith therin reuling al things - Ixvii chapter. </head><lb/>


<p>And than our lord opened my gostly eye and shewid me my soule
in midds of my herte. I saw the soule so large as it were an
endles world and as it were a blisfull kyngdom; and be the con-
ditions I saw therin I understode that it is a worshipful syte.
In the midds of that syte sitts our lord Iesus, God and man, a
faire person and of large stature, heyest bishopp, solemnest
kinge, worshipfulliest lord; and I saw him clad solemnly and wor-
shiply. He sitteth in the soule even ryte in peace and rest. And
the Godhede ruleth and gemeth hevyn and erth and all that is; 
sovereyn myte, sovereyn wisedom, and sovereyn goodnes. The place
that Iesus takith in our soule, he shal never removen it without
end as to my syte; for in us is his homliest home and his endles
wonyng. And in this he shewid the lekyng that he hath of the
makyng of manys soule; for as wele as the Fader might make a crea-
ture, and as wele as the Son couth make a creature, so wele wold
the Holy Gost that manys soule were made; and so it was don. And
therfore the blissid Trinite enioyeth withouten end in the makyng
of manys soule; for he saw fro without begynnyng what shuld liken
him without end. Althing that he hath made shewith his lordship;
as vnderstonding was geven at the same tyme be example of a crea-
ture that is to sen gret noblyes and kingdomes longand to a lord,
and whan it had sen al the noblyth beneathyn, then, merveling, it
was sterid to seeke aboven to the hey place where the lord wonnyth,
knowing be reason that his dwelling is in the worthyest place; and
thus I vnderstode sothly that our soule may never have rest in
things that is beneathin itselfe. And whan it cometh aboven all
creatures into the selfe, yet may it not abyden in the beholdyng
of the selfe, but all the beholding is blisfully sett in God that
is the makar wonand therinn; for in manys soule is his very wonyng'
and the heyest lyte and the brightest shynyng of the cite is the
glorious love of our lord, as to my syte. And what may maken us
more to enioyen in God tha(n) to sen in hym that he enioyeth hegh-
est of al his werkes? For I saw in the same shewing that if the
blisfull Trinite myte have made manys soule ony better, ony fairer,
ony noblyer tha(n) it was made, he shuld not have be full plesid
with the makyng of manys soule. And he will that our herts ben
mytyly reysid above the depeness of the erth and al vayne sorows,
and enioyen in him.</p></div>

                        <div type="chapter">                     

<head>68. Of sothfast knowing that it is Iesus that shewid all this and it
was no ravyng, and how we owen to have sekir troste in all our
tribulation that we shall not be overcome - Ixviii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>This was a delectable syte and a restfull shewyng: that it is so
withouten end. And the beholding of this while we arn here, it is
ful plesant to God and full gret spede to us. And the soule that
thus beholdyth it makith it like to him that is beholdyn, and on-
yth it in rest and peas be his grace. And this was a singlar ioy
and bliss to me that I saw him sitten; for the sekirnes of sitting
shewith endles dwelling. And he gave me knowing sothfastly that it
was he that shewid me al aforn. And whan I had beholden this with
avisement, than shewid our good lord words full mekely withouten
voice and withouten openyng of lipps, ryte as he had done, and said
full swetely: "Wete it now wele that it was no raveing that thou saw
today, but take it and leve it, and kepe the therin and comfort
the therwith and troste thou therto, and thou shalt not be over-
come.' These last words wer seid for leryng of trew sekirness that
it is our lord Iesus that shewid me all. And ryte as in the first
worde that our good lord shewid, menyng his blissfull passion -
"Herwith is the devill overcome' - ryte so he seid in the last
word with full trew sekirness, menand us all: "Thou shalt not ben
overcommen.' And all this leryng in this trew comfort, it is
generall to all my even cristen as it is afornseid, and so is
Gods will. And these words: "Thou shalt not ben overcome', was
seid full sharply and full mightily for sekirness and comfort
agens all tribulations that may comen. He seid not "Thou shalt not
be tempestid, thou shalt not be travelled, thou shalt not be dis-
esid', but he seid: "Thou shalt not be overcome.' God will that
we taken heede at these words, and that we be ever myty in sekir
troste, in wele and wo; for he lovith and lekyth us, and so will
he that we love him and lekin him and mytily trosten in him; and
al shal be wele. And sone after al was close and I sow no more.</p></div>

        <div type="chapter">  

<head>69. Of the second long temptation of the devill to despeir, but she
mytyly trosted to God and to the feith of holy church, rehersing
the passion of Christe be the which she was deliverid - (lxix
chapter.) </head><lb/>

<p>After this the fend came agen with his hete and with his stinke,
and made me full besy; the stinke was so vile and so peynfull,
and also dredfull and travellous. Also I heard a bodily iangeling
as it had be of two bodies, and both, to my thynkyng, ianglyd at
one time as if they had holden a parlement with a gret bysynes;
and al was soft muttering, as I vnderstode nowte what they seid.
And al this was to stirre me to dispeir, as methowte, semand to
me as thei scornyd bidding of beds, which arn seid boistrosly
with mouth, failing devowte entending and wise diligens the which
we owen to God in our prayors. And our lord God gave me grace
mytyly for to trosten in him, and to comforten my soule with
bodily speech as I shuld have don to another person that had ben
travelled. Methowte that bysynes myte not be likenyd to no bodily
bysynes. My bodily eye I sett in the same cross wher I had ben in
comfort aforn that tyme, my tonge with speech of Crists passion
and rehersing the feith of holy church, and myn hert to festen
on God with al the trost and the myte. And I thowte to myselfe,
men and: "Thou hast now grete bysynes to kepe the in the feith,
for thou shuldst not be taken of the enemy; woldst thou now for
this time ever more be so bysy to kepe the fro synne, this were
a good and a soverain occupation'; for I thowte sothly were I saf
fro synne, I wer full saf fro all the fends of helle and enemys
of my soule. And thus he occupyed me al that nyte, and on the
morne till it was about prime day. And anon they wer all gone,
all passid, and then left nothing but stinke; and that lested
still awhile. And I scornyd him. And thus was I deliverd of hem
be the vertue of Christ passion, for therwith is the fend over-
come, as our lord Iesus Criste seid aforn.</p></div>

            <div type="chapter">         


<head>70. In all tribulation we owe to be stedfast in the feith, trosting
mytyly in God; for if our faith had no enimyte, it should deserve
no mede; and how all these shewings arn in the faith - Ixx chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>In all this blissid shewing our good lord gave vnderstondyng that
the syte shuld passyn; which blissid shewing the feith kepith,
with his owne good will and his grace; for he left with me neyther
signe nor token wherby I myte knowen it, but he left with me his
owne blissid worde in true vnderstondyng, byddand me full mytyly
that I shuld leven it. And so I do; blissied mot he ben! I beleve
that he is our savior that shewid it, and that it is the feith
that he shewid. And therfore I leve it enioy and; and therto I am
bounden be al his own menyng, with the next words that folowen:
"Kepe the therein and comfort the therewith and trost thou therto.'
Thus I am bounden to kepen it in my feith. For on the selfe day
that it was shewid, what time that the syte was passid, as a wretch
I forsoke it and openly I seid that I had ravid. Than our lord
Iesus of his mercy wold not letten it perish, but he shewid it
al agen within, in my soule, with mor fulhede, with the blissid
Lyte of his pretious love, seyand these word full mytyly and full
mekely: "Witt it now wele, it was no raving that thou saw this
day', as if he had seid: "For the syte was passid fro, the lest-
ist it and couthest not kepe it; but witt it now, that is to sey,
now that thou seest it.' This was seid not only for the same time,
but also to setten therupo(n) the ground of my feith where he seith
anon folowing: "But take it, leve it, and kepe the therin and com-
fort the therwith and trost thou therto; and thou shalt not be
overcome.' In these vi words that folowen, "Take it', his menyng
is to festyn it feyfully in our herte; for he will that it dwell
with us in feith to our lifes end, and after in fulhede of ioy,
willand that we have ever sekir trost in his blisfull behests,
knowyng his goodness; for our feith is conntried in divers man-
ners be our owne blin(d)hede and our gostly enemy, within and
without, and therfore our pretious lover helpith us with gostly
syte and trew teching on sundry manners, within and without,
wereby that we may know him. And therfore in what manner he tech-
ith us, he will we peceivyn him wisely, receivyn him swetely and
kepin us in hym feithfully; for aboven the feith is no goodnes
kept in this life, as to my sight; and beneath the feith is no
helpe of soule; but in the feith: there will the lord that we kepe
us. For we have be his goodnes and his owne werkeing to kepe us
in the feith and, be his suffrance, be gostly enmyte we are as-
sayed in the feith and made myty; for of our feith had none en-
myte it should deserve no mede, as to the vnderstondyng that I
have in all our lords menyng.</p></div>


                <div type="chapter">    

<head>71. Iesus will our soules be in g(l)ad cher to hym; for his cher is
to us mery and lovely; and how he sheweth to us iii manner cher,
of passion compassion and blissid cher - Ixxi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Glad and mery and sweete is the blisfull lovely cher of our lord
to our souleis; for he havith us ever lifand in lovelongeing,
and he will our soule be in glad cher to him to gevin him his mede.
And thus I hope with his grace he hath, and more shall, draw in,
the vtter chere to the inner cher, and maken us all at one with
him and ech of us with other, in trew lestand ioye that is Ihesus.
I have menyng of iii manner of cheres of our lord. The first is
cher of passion as he shewid while he was here in this lif, dey-
and. Thow this beholdyng be mornyng and swemful, yet it is glad
and mery, for he is God. The ii manner of chere is pite and ruth
and compassion; and this shewith he to all his lovers with sekir-
nes of keping that have to his mercy. The iii is the blisfull
cher as it shal be without end; and this was oftenest and lengest
continuid. And thus in the time of our peyne and our wo he shewith
us chere of his passion and of his cross, help and us to berer
by his owne blissid vertue. And in the time of our synnyng he shew-
ith to us chere of ruth and pite, mytily kepand us and defending
(agaynst) all our enemies. And these ii be the common cher which
he shewith to us in this life; therewith medlarid the thord, and
that is his blisfull chere, like in parte as it shall be in hevyn.
And that is a gracious touchyng and swete lyteyng of the gostly
lefe wherby that we arn kept in sekir feith, hope and charite,
with contrition and devotion and also with contemplation and
(alle manner) of true solace and swete comforts. The blisfull
chere of our lord God werkith it in us be grace.</p></div>

    <div type="chapter">

<head>72. Synne in the chosen soulis is dedly for a tyme, but thei be not
ded in the syght of God; and how we have here matter of ioy and
moneing, and that for our blindhede and weyte of flesh; and of
the most comfortable chere of God; and why these shewings were
made - Ixiii chapter. </head><lb/>

<p>But now behovith me to tellen in what manner I saw synne dedly
in the creatures which shall not dyen for synne, but liven in the
ioy of God without end. I saw that ii contrareties should never

                       
bliss and the depest peyne. The heyest bliss that is, is to have
him in cleerty of endless life, him verily seand, him swetely
feland, all perfectly haveand in fulhede of ioy. And thus was the
blisfull cheere of our lord shewid in pite; in which shewing I
saw that synne is most contrarie, so ferforth that as long as we
be medled with ony part of synne we shall never see cleerly the
blisfull cheere of our lord. And the horibler and the greivouser
that our synnes bene, the deeper are we for that time fro this
blisfull syte. And therfore it semith to us oftentimes as we wern
in peril of deth, in a party of hell, for the sorow and peyne
that the synne is to us. And thus we arn ded for the tyme fro
the very syte of our blisfull life. But in all this I saw soth-
fastly that we be not dede in the syte of God, ne he passith
never fro us; but he shall never have his full bliss in us till
we have our full bliss in him, verely seand his faire blisfull
chere; for we arn ordeynid therto in kinde, and gettyn therto
be grace. Thus I saw how synne is dedly for a short time in the
blissid creatures of endless life. And ever the more clerely that
the soule seith this blisfull chere be grace of loveyng, the more
it longyth to seen it in fullhede; for notwithstonding that our
Lord God wonnyth in us and is here with us, and al he halsith us
and beclosith us for tender love that he may never levyn us, and
is more nere to us than tongue can tellen or herte can thynken,
yet may we never stint of moning nor of weping ne of longyng til
whan we see him cleerly in his blissfull chere; for in that pre-
tious, blisfull syte there may no wo abiden ne no wele failen.
And in this I saw matter of myrth and matter of monyng: matter
of myrthe, for our lord our maker is so nere to us and in us, and
we in him, be sekirne(s) of keping of his grete goodnes; matter
of monyng, for our gostly eye is so blinde and we be so born downe
be weyte of our dedly flesh and derkhede of synne that we may not
sen our lord God clerly in his faire blisful chere. No, and be-
cause of this myrkehede unethes we can leven and trowen his grete
love, our sekirness of keping; and therefore it is that I sey we
may never stinten of moning ne of wepyng. This weping meneth not
al in poryng out of teares by our bodily eye, but also to more
gostly vnderstondyng; for the kindly desire of our soule is so
gret and so onmesurable that if it were goven us to our solace
and to our comfort al the noblyth that ever God made in hevyn and
in erth, and we saw not the fair blisfull chere of hymselfe, yet
we shuld not stynten of moning ne of gostly weping, that is to
sey, of peynfull longing, till whan we sen verily the faire blis-
full chere of our maker. And if we were in all the peyne that herte
can thy(n)ke  and tongue may tell, if we myten in that time sen
his faire, blisfull chere, all this peyn shuld us not agrevin.
Thus is that blisfull syte end of all manner of peyne to lovand
soule, and fulfilling all manner of ioy and bliss. And that shewid
he in the hey, mervelous words wher he seyd: "I it am that is
heyest; I it am that is lowist; I it am that is all.' It longith
to us to have iii manner of knowyngs: the first is that we knowen
our lord God; the ii that we knowen ourselfe, what we arn be him
in kinde and grace; the iii that we knowen mekely what ourselfe
is anempts our synne and febilness. And for these iii was all the
shewing made, as to my vnderstondyng.</p></div>


        <div type="chapter">                 

<head>73. These revelations were shewid iii wises; and of ii gostly (sekenes) 
of which God will we amend us, remembring his passion, knowing
also he is al love; for he will we have sekirnes and liking in
love, not takyng onskilfull hevyness for our synnes past - Ixxiii
chapter. </head><lb/>


<p>All the blissid teching of our lord God was shewidd be iii partes
that is to sey, by bodily syte, and by word formyd in myn vnder-
stondyng, and be gostly sight. For the bodily seyte, I have seid
as I saw as trewly as I can; and for the words, I have seid them
rith as our lord shewid hem to me; and for the gostly syght, I
have seyd sumdele, but I may neve(r) full tellen it, and therefore
of this syght I am sterrid to sey more as God will give me grace.
God shewid ii manner of sekenes that we have: that on is onpatience
or slaith, for we bere our trevell and our pey(n)es hevily; that
other is dispeir or doubtfull drede, as I shall seyen after. Gen-
erally he shewid synne wherin that all is comprehendid, but in
special he shewid not but thes two. And these ii arn thei that
most travelin and tempesten us, as be that our lord shewid me,
of which he will we be amendid; I speake of swich men and women
that for God love haten synne and disposen hem to do Gods will;
than be our gostly blindhede and bodily hevynes, we arn most enc-
linand to these; and therfore it is Gods will thei be knowen and
than shall we refusen hem as we don other synnes. And full helpe
of this ful mekely our lord shewid, the patience that he had in
his herd passion, and also the ioyeing and the likyng that he hath
of that passion for love. And this shewid in example that we shuld
gladly and wisely baren our pey(n)es; for that is gret plesing
to him and endless profitt to us. And the cause why we arn tre-
vellid with them is for onknoweing of love. Thow the iii persons
in the Trinite ben all even in the selfe, the soule toke most vnderstonding in love; ya, and he will in allthing that we have our
beholding and our enioyeyng in love. And of this knoweyng arn we
most blynde; for som of us leven that God is almyty and may don
all, and that he is al wisdam and can don all, but that he is
all love and will don all, there we astynten. And this unknowing,
it is that that lettith most Gods lovers, as to my syte; for whan
we begynnen to haten synne and amenden us be the ordinance of holy
church yet ther dwellith a drede that lettith us, for the be-
holding of ourselfe and of our synnes aforn don, and sum of us
for our everydayly synnes; for we hold nor our covenants ne kepe
not our cleness that our lord settith us in, but fallen oftentimes
in so much wretcidness that shame it is to seen it. And the beholding of this makyth us so sorry and so hevy that onethis we
can finde ony comfort. And this drede we taken sumtime for a mek-
ness, but this is a foule blyndhed and a waykenes. And we cannot
dispisen it as we don anothe(r) synne that we knowen, for it comnyth of enmite. And it is agen truth; for of all the propertes
of the blisfull Trinite it is God will that we have most sekirnes
and likeing in love; for love makith myte and wisdam full meke
to us; for ryte as be the curtesye of God he forgivith our synne
afte(r) the tyme that we repenten us, ryte so will he that we
forgiven our synne as anempts our unskilfull hevyness and our
doutfull dreds.</p></div>


            <div type="chapter">              

<head>74. There ben iiii manner of drede, but reverent drede is a lovely
true that never is without meke love; and yet thei be not both
one; and how we should pray God for the same - Ixxiiii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>For I vnderstond iiii manner dreds. One is the drede of afray
that cummith to a man sodenly be frelte. This drede doith good,
for it helpith to purge man as doeth bodily sekenes or swich
other peyne that is not synne; for all swich peynys helpe man
if thei be patiently taken. The ii is drede of peyne wherby man
is sterid and wakid fro sleepe of synne; he is not abil for the
time to perceivyn the soft comfort of the Holy Gost till he have
vnderstonding of this drede of peyne, of bodily deth and of gostly
enemyes. And this drede stirrith us to seken comfort and mercy
of God; and thus this drede helpith us to sekyn comfort and mercy
of God and abileth us to have contrition be the blisfull touching
of the Holy Gost. The iii is doubtfull drede. Doutfull drede, in
as mech as it drawith to dispeir, God will have it turnyd in us
into love be the knowing of love; that is to sey, that the bitternes
of doubt be turnyd into sweteness of kinde love be grace; for it
may never plesyn our lord that his servants douten in his goodnes.
The iiii is reverent drede for there is no drede that fully plesith God in us but reverent drede; and that is full soft, for the
more it is had, the less is it felt for swetenes of love. Love
and drede are brethren; and thei arn rotid in us be the goodnes
of our msker and thei shall never be taken fro us without end.
We have of kinde to loven and we have of grace to loven; and we
have of kinde to dreden and we have of grace to dreden. It longith
to the lordshippe and to the faderhede to be dred, as it longith
to the goodnes to be lovid; and it longith to us that arn his servants and his children to dreden him for lordshipp and faderhede,
as it longith to us to loven him for goodhede. And thow this reverent drede and love be not partid asundre, yet thei arn not both
one, but thei arn ii in properte and in werking and neither of them
may be had without other. Therfore I am sekir he that lovith, he
dredith, thow that he fele it but a littil. All dreds other than
reverent drede that arn proferid to us, thow they come under the
collor of holyness, yet arn not so trew; and hereby may they be
knowen asu(n)der. That drede that makith us hastily to fleen from
all that is not good and fallen into our lords brest as the child
into the moder barme, with all our entent and with all our mynd
knowand our febilness and our gret nede, knowing his everlesting
goodnes and his blisfull love, only sekeing to him for salvation,
clevand to with sekir troste - that drede that bringith us into
this werking, it is kinde, gracious, good and true. And all that
contraries to this, either it is wronge, or it is medlid with
wronge. Than is this the remedye, to knowen hem both and refusen
the wrong. For the kinde profitt of drede which we have in this
lif be the gracious werking of the Holy Gost, the same shall be
in hevyn aforn God, gentill, curtes and ful delectabil.And thus
we shall in love be homley and nere to God, and we shall in drede
be gentil and curtes to God; and both alike evyn. Desir we of
our lord God to dredin him reverently and to love him mekely and
to trosten in him mytyly; for whan we drede him reverently and
loven him mekely our troste is never in vaine; for the more that
we trosten and the mytylier, the more we plesyn and worshippe our
lord that we trosten in. And if us feile this reverent drede and
meke love (as God forbode we should) our trost shall sone be misrulid for the tyme. And therefore us nedith mekil for to prayen
our lord of grace that we may have this reverent drede and meke
love, of his gift, in herte and in werke; for withouten this no
man may plesyn God.</p></div>

                <div type="chapter">                 

<head>75. Us nedith love, longing and pite, and of iii manner of longing
in God which arn in us; and how in the day of dome the ioy of the
blissid shal ben incresid, seing verily the cause of allthyng that
God hath don dredfully tremeland and thankand for ioye, mervelyng
the gretnes of God (and) lulshed of all that is made - Ixxv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>I saw that God may done all that us nedith; and these iii that I
shall seyen, neden: love, longing, pite. Pite in love kepith us
in time of our nede, and longing in the same love drawith us into
hevyn; for the threist of God is to have the general man into him,
in which thrist he hath (drawyn) his holy that be now in bliss;
and gettand his lively members, ever he drawith and drinkith, and
yet he thristith and longith. I saw iii manner of longing in God,
and al to one end; of which we have the same in us, and of the
same vertue, and for the same end. The ist is for that he longyth
to learn us to knowen him and loven him evermore, as it is convenient and spedefull to us. The ii is that he longith to have
us up to his bliss as soules arn whan thei arn taken out of peyne
into hevyn. The iii is to fulfillen us in bliss; and that shall
be on the last day fulfillid ever to lesten; for I saw, as it is
knowne in our feith, that the peyne and sorow shall be endid to
all that shall be savid. And not only we shall recevyn the same
bliss the soule aforne have had in hevyn, but also we shall re-
ceive anew, which plenteously shal be flowing out of God into us
and fulfillen us; and this be the goods which he hath ordeynid
to geve us from without begynnyng; these goods are tresurid and
hidde in hymselfe; for into that time, creature is not myty ne
worthy to receivin them. In this we shall seen verily the cause
of allthyng he hat don; and evermore we shall seen the cause of
all things that he hath suffrid. And the bliss and the fulfilling
shall be so deepe and so hey that for wonder and mervell all creatures shal have to God so gret reverent drede, overpassing that
hath been seen and felt beforn, that the pillers of hevyn shall
tremelyn and quakyn. But this manner of tremelyng and drede shall
have no peyne; but it longith to the worthy myte of God thus to
be beholden of his creatures, dredfully tremeland and quakand for
mekehede of ioye, mervelyng at the greatnes of God the maker, and
of the litilhede of all that is made; for the beholdyng of this
makith the creature mervelous meke and mylde. Wherfore God will,
and also it longith to us, both in kynde and grace, to witten
and knowen of this, desirand this syte and this werking; for it
ledith us in ryte wey and kepith us in true life and onyth us
to God. And as good as God is, as gret he is; and as mekil as it
longith to his Godhede to be lovid, so mekill it longyth to his
grethede to be dredid; for this reverent drede is the faire curtesie
that is (in) hevyn aforn Gods face. And as mekil as he shall than
be knowen and lovid overpassing that he is now, in so mekill he
shall be dredid overpassing that he is now. Wherfore it behovith
needs to ben that all hevyn and erth shall tremelyn and quaken when
the pillars shall tremelyn and quaken.</p></div>

        <div type="chapter">  

<head>76. A love and soule hatith synne for vilehede more than all the peyn
of hell; and how the beholdyng of other mannys synne (but if it
be with compassion) lettith the beholdyng of God; and the devill,
be putting in remembrans our wretchidness, would letten for the
same; and of our slawth - Ixxvi chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>I speke but littil of reverent drede, for I hope it may be seen
in this matter afornseid. But wele I wot our lord shewid me no
soules but those that dred him; for wele I wott the soule that,
trewly taketh the techyng of the Holy Gost, it hatith more synme a
for vilehede and horibilite than it doth all the peyne that is
in hell; for the soule that beholdith the kindenes of our lord
Iesus, it hatith non helle but synne, as to my sygte. And therefore it is Goddis will that we knowen synne, and prayen bysyly
and travellyn willfully and sekyn, teching mekely, that we fall
not blindly therin; and if we fallen, that we risen redily, for
it is the most peyne that the soule may have, to turne fro God
ony time be synne. The soule that will be in rest, whan other
mannys synne commith (to mynde), he shall fleen it as the peyne
of helle, seking into God for remedy, for helpe (agayne) it; for
the beholdyng of other mannys synnes, it makith as it were a thick
myst aforne the eye of the soule, and we may not for the tyme se
the fairehede of God, but if we may beholden hem with contrition
with him, with compassion on him and with holy desire to God for
hem; for withouten this it noyith and tempestith and lettith the
soule that beholdith hem; for this (l) vnderstode in the shewing
of compassion. In this blisfull shewing of our lord I have vnderstondyng of ii contaries: that one is the most wisdam that ony
creture may don in this life; that other is the most foly. The
wisdam is creature to done after the wille and councell of his
heyest sovereyn freind. This blissid freind is Ihesus; and it
is his will and his councell that we holden us with him and settyn
us to him, homley, evermore, in what state so we ben; for whether
so that we ben foule or clene, we arn al one in his loveing. For
wele ne for wo he will never we fleen him; but for the chongeabilitie that we arn in in ourselfe we fallen often into synne.
Than we have this be the stering of our enemy, be our owne foly
and blyndhede; for they seien thus: "Thou wittest wele thou art
a wretch, a synner, and also ontrew; for thou kepist not the
command; thou behotist oftentymes our lord that thou shalt don
better, and anon after, thou fallist agen in the same, namely
in slauth, in lesyng of tyme'; for that is the begynning of
synne, as to my syghte, and namely to the creatures that have
goven hem to serven our lord with inward beholding of his blissid
goodness. And this makith us adred to apear afore our curtes
lord. Than is it our enemy that will putt us on bakke with his
false drede of our writchidnes, for peyne that he threatith us
by; for it is his menyng to make us so hevy and so wery in this
that we shuld lettyn out of mende the fair, blisfull beholdyng
of our everlasting freind.</p>
        </div>

            <div type="chapter">

<head>77. Off the enmite of the fend, which lesith more in our uprising
than he winnith be our fallyng, and therfore he is scornyd; and
how the scorge of God shuld be suffrid with mynde of his passion,
for that is spe(c)ially rewardid aboven penance be ourselfe chosen;
and we must nedes hove wo, but curtes God is our leder, heper
and bliss - Ixxvii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>Our good lord shewid the enmite of the fend, wherby I understode
that all that is contrarious to love and to pece, it is the fend
and of his parte. And we have of our febilnes and our foly to
fallen, and we have of mercy and grace of the Holy Gost to risen
to more ioye. And if our eneme owte wynnith of us be our fallyng,
for it is his likenes, he lesith manyfold more in our rising be
charite and mekenes. And this glorious riseing, it is to him so
gret sorow and peyne, for the hate that (he) hath to our soule,
that he brynnyt continuly in envy. And al this sorow that he wold
maken us to have, it shal turne to himselfe. And for this it was
that our lord scornyd him; and this made me mytyly to lauhen.
Than is this the remedy: that we ben aknowen (of) our writchidnes
and flen to our lord; for ever the more redier that we ben, the
more spedefull it is to us to neyghen him. And sey we thus in
our mening: "I know wele I have a shrewid peyne, but our lord
is almyty and may punish me mytyly, and he is al wisdam and can
punish me skilfully, and he is all goodnes and lovith me full
tendirly.' And in this beholdyng it is necessarye for us to
abeyden; for it is a lovely mekeness of a synful soule, wroute
be mercy and grace of the Holy Gost, whan we will willfully and
gladly taken the scorge and chastening of our lord himselfe will
geve us. And it shall be full tendir and full esy if that we will
onely holden us paid with him and with all his werkes; for the
pennance that mon taketh of himselfe was not shewid me: that is
to sey, it was not shewid specifyed; but it was shewid specialy
and heyly and with full lovely chere that we shall mekely and
patiently beryn and suffren the penance that God himselfe gevith
us, with mynde in his blissid passion; for whan we have mend in
his blissid passion, with pite and love, than we suffren with him
like as his freinds did that seen it, and (this) was shewid in
the xiii, ner at the begynnyng, wher it spekith of pite; for
he seith: "Accuse not (thy)selfe  overdon mekil, demandand that
tribulation and thy wo is al for thy defaute; for I will not that
thou be hevye ne sorowfull vndiscretly; for I tell the how so tho
do, thou shalt have wo. And therfore I will that thou wisely
know thi penance, and shalt then sothly seene that all thi living
is penance profitable. This place is prison and this lif is pen-ance, and in the remedy he will we enioyen. The remedy is that
our lord is with us, kepand and ledand into the fulhede of ioye;
for this is an endless ioy to us in our lords menyng, that he
that shall ben our bliss whan we arn there, he is our keper while
we arn here. Our wey and our hevyn is trew love and sekir troste;
and of this he gaf understonding in all, and namly in the shewing
of his passion wher he made me mytyly to chesin him for my hevyn.
Fle we to our lord and we shall be comfortid; touch we him and
we shall be made clene; cleve to him and we shall be sekir and
safe fro al maner of peril; for our curtes lord will that we ben
as homley with him as herte may thinke or soule may desiren. But
beware that we taken not so reklesly this homleyhede that we levyn
curtesy; for our lord himselfe is sovereyn homleyhede, and as
homley as he is, as curtes he is; for he is very curtes. And the
blissid creatures that shall ben in hevyn with him without end,
he will have hem like to himselfe in all things. And to be like
our lord perfectly, it is our very salvation and our full bliss.
And if we wott not how we shall don all this, desire we of our
lord and he shal lerne us; for it (is) his owne likeing and his
worship. Blissid mot he be!</p></div>

                <div type="chapter">  

<head>78. Our lord will we know iiii manner of goodnes that he doith to
us, and how we neede the lyte of grace to knowen our synne and
febilnes, for we arn nothing of ourselfe but writchidnes, and
we may not know the horribilnes of synne as it is; and how our
enemy would we should never know our synne till the last day,
wherfore we arn mekil bowndend to God that shewith it now -
Ixxviii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>Our lord of his mercy shewith us our synne and our febilnes be
the swet gracious lyte of hymselfe; for our synne is so vile
and so horrible that he of his curtesie will not shew it to us
but be the lyte of his grace and mercy. Of iiii things it is his
will that we have knowing: the first is that he is our ground
of whom we have all our life and our being; the ii, that he
kepeth us mytyly and mercifully in the tyme that we arn in our
synne and monge all our enemies that arn full fel upon us - and
so mekil we arn in the more peril for we geven him occasion therto
and kno not our owne nede; the iii is how curtesly he kepith us
and makith us to knowen that we gon amyss; the iiii is how sted-
lastly he abidith us and chongith no chere, for he will that we
be turnyd and onyd to him in love as he is to us. And thus be
this gracious knoweing we may seen our synne profitably without
despeir; for sothly us nedith to seen it; and be the syte we shall
be made ashamd of ourselfe and broken downe as anempts our pride
and presumtion; for us behovith verily to seen that of ourselfe
we arn ryte nowte but synne and wretchiddnes. And thus be the
syte of the less that our lord shewith us, the more is wastid
which we se not; for he of his curtesye mesurith the syte to us,
for it is so vile and so horrible that we shuld not enduren to
seen it as it is. And be this meke knowing thus, throw contrition
and grace we shall be broken fro all things that is not our lord,
and than shall our blissid saviour perfectly helyn us and one
us to him. This breking and this helyng our lord menith be the
general man; for he that is heyest and nerest with God, he may
seen himselfe synnefull, and nedith, with me; and I that am the
lest and lowest of those that shall be save, I may be comfortid
with him that is heyest. So hath our lord onyd us in charite
whan he shewid me that I shuld synne. And for ioy that I had in
beholdyng of him I entend not redily to that shewing; and our
curtis lord stynte than and wold not ferther tech me till that
he gave me grace and will to entenden. And hereof was I lerid,
thow that we be heyly lifted up into contemplation be the special
geft of our lord, yet us behovith nedis therwith to have knoweing
and syte of our synne and our febilnes; for withouten this knowing
we may not have trew mekenes, and without this we may not be savid.
And also I saw that we may not have this knowing of ourselfe, ne
of none of all our gostly enemies, for thei will us not so mekil
good; for if it wer be their will, we should not seen it into
our endyng day. Than be we mekil bounden to God that he will
himselfe for love shewen it us in time of mercy and grace.</p></div>


                    <div type="chapter">     

<head>79. We are lernyd to our synne, and not to our neighbors, but for their
helpe; and God will we know whatsomever stering we have contrary
to this shewing, it comith of our enemy; for the gret I(o)ve of
God knowen, we should not ben the more reckles to fallen, and if
we fallen we must hastely risen or ell we are gretly onkind to
God - lxxix chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Also I had in this more vnderstondyng: in that he shewid me that
I should synne, I toke it nakidly to myne owne singular person,
for I was none otherwise stirrid at that time; but be the hey,
gracious comfort of our lord that followid after, I saw that his
menyng was for the general man, that is to sey, all man which
is synfull and shall ben into the last day; of which man I am
a member, as I hope, be the mercy of God; for the blissid comfort
that I saw, it is large enow for us all. And here was I lerid
that I shuld se myn owne synne and not other mens synns but if
it may be for comfort and helpe of myn evin Cristen. And also
in this same shewing, where I saw that I shuld synne, there was
I leryd to be dredfull for onsekirness of myselfe; for I wott
not how I shall fallen, nor I know not the mesurre ner the gret-
ness of synne; for that wold I have wist dredfully, and therto
I had non answere. Also our curtes lord, in the same tyme, he
shewid full sekirly and mytyly the endleshede and the onchonge-
abilitie of his love; and alsa, be his gret goodnes and his grace
inwardly keping, that the love of him and our soule shal never
be departid in two, without end. And thus in this drede I have
matter of mekeness that savith me from presumption; and in the
blissid shewing of love I have matter of tru comfort and of ioy
that savith me fro dispeir. All this homley shewing of our curtes
lord, it is a lovely lesson and a swete, gracious teching of
himselfe in comforting of our soule; for he will that we knowen,
be the swetenes and homley loveing of him, that all that we seen
or felyn, within or without, which is contrarious to this is
of the enemy and not of God; as thus: if we be stered to be the
more recles of our living or of the keping of our herts be the
same cause that we have knowing of this plenteous love, than
needs us gretly to beware; for this stering, if it come, it is
ontrew, and gretly we owen to haten it, for it all hath no like-
ness of Gods will. And whan that we be fallen be frelte or blynd-
hede, than our curtes lord touchith us, stireth us and clepith
us; and than will he that we seen our wretchidness and mekely
ben it aknowen. But he will not we abiden thus, ne he will not
that we beseyn us gretly about our accusing, nor he will not that
we ben wretchfull of ourselfe; but he will that we hastily ent-
enden to him; for he stondyth al alufe and abideth us swemefully
and moningly till whan we come, and hath hast to have us to him;
for we arn his ioy and his deligte, and he is our salve and our
life. Tho I sey he stondyth al alone, I leve the speking of the
blissid company of hevyn and speke of his office and his werking
here on erth, upon the condition of the (shewyng). </p></div>

                        <div type="chapter">                   

<head>80. By iii thyngs God is worshippid and we savid; and how our knowing
now is but as an ABC; and swete Ihesus doith all, abyding and
monyng with us, but whan we arn in synne Christ monyth alone,
than it longith to us, for kindness and reverens, hastely to
turne agen to him - lxxx chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>Be iii things man stondith in this life; be which iii God is
worshipped and we be spedid, kept and savid. The ist is use of
manys reason naturall; the ii is commen teching of holy church;
the thred is inward gracious werking of the Holy Gost; and these
iii ben all of one God. God is the ground of our kindly reason;
and God, the teaching of holy church; and God is the Holy Gost.
And all ben sundry gifts to which he will we have gret regard
and attenden us therto; for these werkyn in us continualy all
to God, and these ben grete thyngs; of which gret things he will
we have knowing here as it were in one ABC: that is to seyn, that
we have a litill knoweing, whereof we shall have fullhede in hevyn;
and that is for to spede us. We knowen in our feith that God alone
toke our kinde and non but he; and ferthermore, that Criste allone
did all the werks that longin to our salvation, and none but he;
and ryte so he alone doith now the last end: that is to sey, he
wonny(t)h here with us and rulith us and governith us in this
lifing, and bringith us to his bliss. And thus shall he doe as
long as ony soule is in erth that shall come to hevyn; and so
ferforth that if ther wer no suich soule but one, he shuld be
with all alone till he had brought up to his bliss. I leve and
vnderstond the ministration of angells as clerks tellen, but it
was not shewid me; for himselfe is nerest and mekest, heyest and
lowest, and doith all; and not only all that us neds, but also
he doith all that is worshipfull, to our ioy in hevyn. And wher
I sey he abidith swemefully and monyng, it menyth all the trew
felyng that we have in ourselfe in contrition and compassion,
and all sweming and monyng that we are not onyd with our lord.
And all swich that is spedfull, it is Christ in us; and thow some
of us fele it seldam, it passith never fro Criste till what tyme
he hath browte us out of all our wo; for love suffrith never to
be without pite. And what tyme that we fallen into synne and leve
the mynd of him and the keping of our own soule, than kepith Criste
alone al the charge of us; and thus stondith he swemely and monyng.
Than longith it to us for reverence and kindeness to turne us
hastely to our lord and levyen him not alone. He is here alone
with us all: that is to sey, only for us he is here. And what
tyne I am strange to him be synne, dispeir or slawth, than I let
my lord stonden alone, in as mekill as it is in me; and thus it
farith with us all which ben synners. But thow it be so that we
do thus oftentimes, his goodnes suffrith us never to be alone;
but lestingly he is with us, and tenderly he excusith us, and
ever sheildith us fro blame in his syte.</p></div>


                   <div type="chapter">               

<head>81. This blissid woman saw God in divers manners, but she saw him
take no resting place but in manys soule; and he will we enioyen
more in his love then sorowen for often falling, remembring reward
everlasting, and liveing gladly in penance; and why God suffrith
synne - lxxxi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>Our good lord shewid him in dyvers manners, both in hevyn, in
erth, but I saw him take no place but in mannys soule. He shewid
him in erth in the swete incarnation and in his blissid passion.
And in other manner he shewid him in erth wher I sey: "I saw
God in a poynte.' And in other manner he shewid him in erth thus
as it were in pilegrimage: that is to sey, he is here with us,
ledand us, and shal ben till whan he hath browte us all to his
bliss in hevyn. He shewid him dyvers tymes reynand, as it is
afornseyd, but principally in mannys soule. He hath taken there
his resting place and his worshipfull cyte; out of which worship-
full see he shall never risen nor removen without end. Mervelous
and solemne is the place wher the lord wonnyth. And therefore
he will that we redily entenden to his gracious touching, more
enioying in his hole love than sorowand in our often fallings;
for it (is) the most worshippe to him of onything that we may
don, that we leven gladly and meryly, for his love, in our pen-
ance; for he beholdith us so tendirly that he seith all our
liveing and penance; for kind loveand is to him ay lestand pen-
ance in us, which penance he werkith in us and mercifully he
helpith us to baren it; for his love makith him to longyn, his
wisdam and his trewth with his rytfulhede makith him to suffren
us here, and in this manner he will seene it in us; for this is
our kindly penance and the heyest, as to my syte, for this pen-
ance commith never fro us till what tyme that we be fulifilled
whan we shal have him to our mede. And therefore he will that
we setten our herts in the overpassing: that is to sey, fro the
peyne that we felen into the bliss that we trosten.</p></div>

<div type="chapter">                  

<head>82. God beholdith the monyng of the soule with pite and not with blom, 
and yet we do nowte but synne, in the which we arn kept in solace
and in drede; for he will we turne us to him, redy clevand to
his love, seand that he is our medicyne; and so we must love,
in longing and in enioyeing; and whatsoever is contrarie to this
is not of God but of enmity - lxxxii chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>But here shewid our curtis lord the moneing and the morning of
the soule, menand thus: "I wote wele thou wilt liven for my love
merily and gladly suffrand all the penance that may com to the,
but in as mech as thou livest not without synne, thou woldest
suffre for my love all the wo, all the tribulation and disese
that myte come to the. And it is soth. But be not mekill agreved
with synne that fallith to the agens thy will.' And here I vnder-
stode that: that the lord beholdith the servant with pite and not
with blame, for this passing lif askith not to liven al withoute
blame and synne. He loveith us endlesly, and we synne customably,
and he shewith us full myldely; and than we sorow and mornen
discretly, turnand us into the beholding of his mercy, clevand
to his love and goodness, seand that he is our medecine, wittand
that we doe nowte but synne. And thus be the mekeness that we
getten be the syte of our synne, feythfully knowing his everlasting
love, him thanking and prayseing, we plesyn him. "I love the and
thou lovist me; and our love shall not be departid in two, and
for thi profitt I suffre.' And all this was shewid in gostly
vnderstondyng sayand these blissid words: "I kepe the full sekerly.'
And be gret desire that I have in our blissid lord that we shal
leven in this manner, that is to sey, in longing and enioyeng,
as all this lesson of love shewith, therby I vnderstode that all
that is contrarious to us is not of him, but of enmyte; and he
will that we knowen it be the swete gracious lyt of his kynde
love. If any swich lover be in erth which is continuly kept fro
falling, I know it not, for it was not shewid me. But this was
shewid: that in falling and in ryseing we arn eve(r) preciously
kept in one love; for in the beholding of God we fall not, in the
beholding of selfe we stond not, and both these ben soth, as to
my syte; but the beholdyng of our lord God is the heyest sothnes;
than arn we mekil bound to God that he will in this living shewin
us this hey sothness. And I understode that while we be in this
life, it is full spedefull to us that we sen both these at onys;
for the heyer beholding kepith us in gostly solace and trew en-
ioying in God; that other, that is the lower beholding, kepith
us in drede and makith us ashamyd of ourselfe. But our good lord
will ever that we beholden us mekil more in the beholdyng of the
heyer, and not levyn the knowing of the lower, into the time that
we (be) browte up above, wher we shall have our lord Ihesus onto
our mede, and ben fulfillid of ioy and bliss withoute end.</p></div>

     <div type="chapter">                   

<head>83. Of iii properties in God, life, love and light; and that our
reason is in God accordand; it is heyest gift; and how our feith
is a light commeing of the Fader, mesurid to us, and in this
night us ledand; and the end of our wo; sodenly our eye shall
be openid in full light and clerte of syte, which is our maker,
fader and Holy Gost in Ihesus our savior - lxxxiii chapter.</head><lb/></div>

<p>I had in parte touching, sight and feling in iii propertes of
God, in which the strength and effect of all the revelation
stondith; and thei were seene in every shewing, and most propirly
are these: lif, love and ligte. In life is mervelous homlihede, are these: lif, love and ligte. In life is mervelous homlihede,
and in love is gentil curtesye, and in lyte is endless kyndhede.
These propertes were in on goodness; into which goodnes my reason
wold ben onyd and cleve to with all the myte. I beheld with rev-
erent drede, and heyly mervelyng in the syte and in the feling
of the swete accord that our reason is in God, vnderstondyng that
it is the heyest gifte that we have receivid, and it is groundid
inkinde. Our feith is a light, kindly command of our endles day,
that is our fader, God; in which light our moder, Criste, and our
good lord the Holy Gost ledith us in this passand life. This light
is mesurid discretly, nedefully standand to us in the night. The
light is cause of our life, the night is cause of our peyne and
of al our wo, in which we deserven mede and thanks of God; for we
with mercy and grace, wilfuly knowen and leven our light, goeand
therin wisely and mytyly. And at the end of wo, sodenly our eye
shall ben openyd, and in clerte of light our sight shall be full;
which light is God our maker and Holy Gost in Christ Ihesus our
savior. Thus I saw and vnderstode that our feith is our light in
our night; which light is God our endless day.</p></div>


          <div type="chapter">                      

<head>84. Charite is this light, which is not so litil but that it is (m)ede-
full, with travel, to deserven endles worshipfull thanke of God;
for feith and hope leden us to charite, which is in iii manners -
lxxxiiii chapter.</head><lb/>

<p>The light is charite, and the mesuring of this light is don to
us profitably by the wisdam of God; for neyther the light is
so large that we may seen our blisfull day, ne it is sperid fro
us, but it is suich a light in which we may liven medefully,
w(i)th  travel deservand the endless worship of God. And this
was seen in the vi shewing where he seid: "I thank the (of) thi
service and of thi travell.' Thus charite kepith us in feith and
in hope; and hope ledith us in charite. And at the end al shall
be charite. I had iii manner of vnderstonding in this light,
charite: the first is charite onmade; the second is charite made;
the iii is charite goven. Charite onmade is God; charite made is
our soule in God; charite goven is vertue; and that is a gracious
geft of werking in which we loven God for himselfe and ourselves
in God and that God loveth, for God.</p></div>


               <div type="chapter">                  

<head>85. God lovid his chosen fro without begynnyng, and he neve(r) 
suffrith them to be hurte wherof their bliss might be lessid;
and how privities now hidde in hevyn shall be knowen, wherefore
we shall bliss our lord that everything is so wele ordeynid -
lxxxv chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>And in this sight I merveled heyley; for notwithstondyng our
simple liveing and our blindhede here, yet endlesly our curtes
lord beholdith us in this workeing, enioyand. And of allthing
we nay plesin him best wisely and truely to levin it and to en-
ioyen with him and in him; for as verily as we shall ben in the
bliss of God withouten end, him praysand and thankand, as verily
we have ben in the foresight of God lovid and knowen in his end-
less purpose fro withouten begynning; in which onbegunne love
he made us, and in the same love he kepith us and never suffrith
us to be hurte be which our bliss myte be lesid. And therfore
wham the dome is goven and we ben al browte up above, than we
cleerly se in God the privities which be now hidde to us Than
shall non of us be stirid to sey in ony wise "Lord, if it had
ben thus, than it had bene full wele'; but we shall seyn al with-
out voice: "Lord, blissid mot thou ben! For it is thus, it is
wele. And now se we verily that all thing is done as it was
then ordeynd beforn that onything was made.'</p></div>
 <div type="chapter">  

<head>86. The good lord shewid this booke shuld be otherwise performid
than at the first writing; and for his werking he will we thus
prey, him thankand, trostand, and in him enioyand; and how he
made this shewing because he will have it knowen, in which know-
eing he will give us grace to love him; for xv yeere after it
was answerid that the cause of all this shewing was love, which
Ihesus mote grant us. Amen - lxxxvi chapter.</head><lb/>


<p>This booke is begunne be Gods gift and his grace, but it is not
yet performid, as to my syte. for charite pray we all to God, :
with Godds werking, thankand, trostand, enioyand; for thus will
our good lord be prayd, as be the vnderstonding that I tooke in
al his owne mening, and in the swete words wher he seith full
merrily "I am ground of thi beseking'; for trewly I saw and under-
stode in our lords mening that he shewid it for he will have it
knowen more than it is, in which knowing he will give us grace
to loven him and clevyn to him; for he beholdith his hevenly tre-
sure with so grete love on erth that he will give us more light
and solace in hevenly ioy in drawing of our herts, for sorow and
merkness which we arn in. And fro that time that it was shewid
I desired oftentimes to witten what was our lords mening. And
xv yer after and more I was answerid in gostly vnderstonding,
seyand thus: "Woldst thou wetten thi lords mening in this thing?
Wete it wele: love was his mening. Who shewid it the? Love. What
shewid he the? Love. Wherfore shewid it he? For love. Hold the
therin and thou shalt witten and knowen more in the same; but thou
shalt never knowen ne witten therein other thing without end.'
Thus was I lerid that love was our lords mening. And I saw full
sekirly in this and in all, that ere God made us he lovid us;
which love was never slakid, no never shall. And in this love
he hath don all his werke; and in this love he hath made all
things profitable to us; and in this love our life is everlestand.
In our making we had beginning, but the love wherin he made us
was in him from withoute begynning; in which love we have our
beginning. And all this shall be seen in God without end; which
Ihesus mot grant us. Amen.</p>

<p>Thus endith the revelation of love of the blissid Trinite shewid
by our savior Christ lesu for our endles comfort and solace, and
also to enioyen in him in this passand iorney of this life.
Amen, Ihesu, Amen.</p>

                          
<p>I pray almyty God that this booke com not but to the hands of
the(m) that will be his faithfull lovers, and to those that will
submitt them to the feith of holy church and obey the holesom
vnderstondyng and teching of the men that be of vertuous life,
sadde age and profound lernyng; for this revelation is hey
divinitye and hey wisdam, wherfore it may not dwelle with him that
is thrall to synne and to the devill. And beware thou take not
on thing after thy affection and liking and leve another, for
that is the condition of an heretique. But take everything with
other and trewly vnderstonden all is according to holy scripture
and growndid in the same, and that, Ihesus our very love, light
and truth shall shew to all clen soules that with mekenes aske
perseverantly this wisdom of hym. And thou, to whome this booke
shall come, thanke heyley and hartily our savior Crist Ihesu that
he made these shewings and revelations for the, and to the, of
his endles love, mercy and goodnes, for thine and our save guide
and conduct to everlestyng bliss; the which Ihesus mot grant us.
Amen.</p>        
            </div></div></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>