<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="bradstreet-roman">
    
    <!--TEI Header BEGINS-->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <!--BEGINS File Description -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Roman Monarcy, being the fourth and last, beginning, Anno Mandi</title>
                
                <author>
                   
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Anne</forename>
                            <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                  
                </author>
                
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#" >
                            <surname></surname>
                            <forename></forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                    </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
               
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Anne</forename>
                                    <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Roman Monarcy, being the fourth and last, beginning, Anno Mandi</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="6000236">American Colonies</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1678">1678</date>
                            <note></note>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                                Our texts are taken from the Text Creation Partnership's digital edition of "Several poems compiled with great variety of wit and learning, full of delight, wherein especially is contained a compleat discourse, and description of the four elements constitutions, ages of man, seasons of the year. : Together with an exact epitome of the three first monarchyes viz. the Assyrian, Persian, Grecian. And beginning of the Romane Common-Wealth to the end of their last king:  with diverse other pleasant &amp; serious poems,  by a gentlewoman in New-England," published in Boston in 1678.                             </note>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent></extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/> <!-- I would say this is unknown -->
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7014203">New England</name> 
                    <date from="1600" to="1700">Seventeenth Century</date>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>The Roman Monarcy, being the fourth and last, beginning, Anno Mandi</head>
                <head>Anne Bradstreet</head>
                
                <lg>
                    <l n="1">Stout <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Romulus</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Romulus is the founder of Rome and son of Mars in Roman Mythology.</note>, <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Remus was the brother of Romulus. They disputed over where to settle Rome, which eventually led to the murder of Remus. Source: Wikipedia</ref>Remus Founder, and fast</l>
                <l n="2">King</l>
                <l n="3">Whom <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">vestall Rhea</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Rhea is the mother of the twins Romulus and Remus. And she is a "vestal virgin" or one of the priestesses who were in charge of the sacred fire in the Vesta Temple. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and Wikipedia</note>, into th' world did </l>
                <l n="4">bring</l>
                <l n="5">His father was not <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Mars</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Mars is the god of war and a depicted as a Military General.</note>, as some devis'd</l>
                <l n="6">But <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Aemulus</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(Draft) I can't figure out who this is</note>, in Armour all disguis'd</l>
                <l n="7">Thus, he deceiv'd his Neece, she might not know</l>
                <l n="8">The <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">double injury</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">(Draft) what is this double injury</note>, he then did doe:</l>
                <l n="9">Where she heards once had Coats, and Sheep their</l>
                <l n="10">Folds,</l>
                <l n="11">Where <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Swaines</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Countrymen, farmers, and shepherds. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and rustick Peasants and made their</l>
                <l n="12">Holds</l>
                <l n="13">A Citty Faire did Romulus erect:</l>
                <l n="14">The Mistris of the World, eachrespect</l>
                <l n="15">His Brother Remus there, <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">by him was slaine</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">This is the origin of Rome's name as Romulus had the city take his name.</note>,</l>
                <l n="16">For leaping o're the Walls with some disdaine</l>
                <l n="17">The Stones at first was cimented with blood</l>
                <l n="18">And bloody hath it prov'd, since Erst it flood</l>
                <l n="19">This City built, and Sacrifices done,</l>
                <l n="20">A formed of Government he next begun;</l>
                <l n="21">A hundred Senators he likewise chose</l>
                <l n="22">And with the stile of Patres honour'd those</l>
                <l n="23">His City to replenish, men he wants</l>
                <l n="24">Great priveleges then, to all he grants,</l>
                <l n="25">That wil within these strong built walls reside,</l>
                <l n="26">And this new gentle Government abide:</l>
                <l n="27">Of Wives there was so great scarcity,</l>
                <l n="28">They to their neighbors sue, for a supply;</l>
                <l n="29">But all disdaine alliance then to make,</l>
                <l n="30">So Romulus was forc'd this course to take</l>
                <l n="31">Great shewes he makes at <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Tilt, and Turnament</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Tilt and Tournament refers to races held on foot, chariot and horses to prove ones' worthiness. Source: The Illustrated History of Rome,477</note>,</l>
                <l n="32">To see these sports, the <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Sabins</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Sabines were an italic tribe from the mountainous region near the east of the Tiber River. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> are bent;</l>
                <l n="33">Their Daughters by the Romans then were caught,</l>
                <l n="34">Foe to recover them, a Feild was fought;</l>
                <l n="35">But in the end, to finall peace they come,</l>
                <l n="36">And Sabins, and one people, dwelt in Rome.</l>
                <l n="37">The Romulus now more potent 'gin to grow,</l>
                <l n="38">And <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Fedinates</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Fedinates are the citizens of Fidenae. Source: Wikipedia</note> they wholly over-throw:</l>
                <l n="39">But Romulus then comes unto his end,</l>
                <l n="40">Some faiining say, to heav'n he did ascend;</l>
                <l n="41">Others, the leven and thirtyeth of his reigne</l>
                <l n="42">Affirme, that by the Senate he was slaine.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                <l n="43">Numa Pompilius</l>
                <l n="44">Numa Pompilius, is next chosen King,</l>
                <l n="45">Held for his Piety, some sacred thing;</l>
                <l n="46">To <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Janus</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">God of doorways in Roman religion. Source: Encyclopedia Brittanica</note>, he that famous Temple built,</l>
                <l n="47">Kept shut in peace, but ope when blood was spilt</l>
                <l n="48">The Religious Rites and Customs instituted,</l>
                <l n="49">And Priests and <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Flamines</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Flamines are priests dedicated specifically to one deity. Source: Wikipedia</note> likewise he deputed,</l>
                <l n="50">Their <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Augurs</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">An Augur is a religious position that observed the surroundings such as animals to understand the people's standings with the Gods.</note> strange, their gestures and attire,</l>
                <l n="51">And vestal maids to keep the holy fire.</l>
                <l n="52">The Nymph <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Aegeria</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">Aegeria is the Latin goddess of knowledge and healing.</note> this to him told,</l>
                <l n="53">So to <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">delude</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">Make people believe that false things are true. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> the people he was bold:</l>
                <l n="54">Forty three years he rul'd with general praise,</l>
                <l n="55">Accounted for a God in after dayes.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                <l n="56">Tullius Hoftilius</l>
                <l n="57">Tulius Hoftilius, was third Roman King,</l>
                <l n="58">Who Martial Discipline in use did bring;</l>
                <l n="59">War with the ancient <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Albans</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">The inhabitants of Alba Longa, a city in ancient Latium. Latium was a western state on what is now Italy. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and Wikipedia</note>Albans he doth wage,</l>
                <l n="60">The strife to end, fix Brothers doe ingage;</l>
                <l n="61">Three call'd <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Horatii</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">The Horatii were triplet warriors of the Roman Empire.</note>, on Romans side;</l>
                <l n="62">And <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">Curiatii</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">The Curiatii are triplets from Alba Longa. They fought against the Horatii. The Curiatii managed to kill all but one of the Horatii, Publius. Publius however, managed to use logic and planning to defeat all three of the Curiatii by himself and win the war for Rome. Source: Wikipedia</note>, three Albans provide;</l>
                <l n="63">The Romans Conquereth, others yeeld the day,</l>
                <l n="64">Yet for their compact, after false the play</l>
                <l n="65">The Romans fore incens'd, their Generall slay,</l>
                <l n="66">And from old Alba fetch the wealth away;</l>
                <l n="67">Of Latin Kings this was long since the Seat,</l>
                <l n="68">But now demolished, to make Rome great.</l>
                <l n="69">Thirty two years did Tullius reign, then dye,</l>
                <l n="70">Left Rome in wealth, and power still growing high.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                <l n="71">Ancus Martius</l>
                <l n="72">Next Ancus Martius sits upon the Throne,</l>
                <l n="73">Nephew unto Pomphilius dead, and gone;</l>
                <l n="74">Rome he inlarg'd, new built againe the wall,</l>
                <l n="75">Much stronger, and more beautifull withall:</l>
                <l n="76">A stately Bridge he over <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">Tyber</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">The Tyber River runs through Rome.</note> made,</l>
                <l n="77">Of Boats, and Oares, no more they need the aide;</l>
                <l n="78">Faire <ref target="a021" corresp="n021">Oftia</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">(DRAFT) what or who is this? Was this a long s that just got translated as an "f"</note> he built, this Town, it flood,</l>
                <l n="79">Close by the mouth of famous Tyber flood:</l>
                <l n="80">Twenty foure yeare, th' time of his royall race,</l>
                <l n="81">Then unto death unwillingly gives place.</l>
                </lg>
                            
                <lg>
                <l n="82">Tarquinius Prifcus</l>
                <l n="83">Tarquin, a Greek, at Corinth borne, and bred,</l>
                <l n="84">Who soe <ref target="a022" corresp="n022">sedition</ref><note xml:id="n022" target="a022">Rebeliously. Source: Oxford English Dictioanry</note> from his Country fled;</l>
                <l n="85">Is entertain'd at Rome, and in short time,</l>
                <l n="86">By wealth, and favour, doth to honour climbe;</l>
                <l n="87">He after Martius death the Kingdome had,</l>
                <l n="88">A hundred Senatours he more did adde;</l>
                <l n="89">Warres with the Latins he againe renewes,</l>
                <l n="90">And Nations twelve, of Tuscany subdues:</l>
                <l n="91">To such rude triumphs, as young Rome then had,</l>
                <l n="92">Much state, and glory, did this <ref target="a023" corresp="n023">Piscus</ref><note xml:id="n023" target="a023">A great Roman diplomat. Source: Wikipedia</note> adde:</l>
                <l n="93">Thirty eight yeares (this Stranger borne) did reigne,</l>
                <l n="94">And after all, by Ancus Sons was slaine.</l>
                </lg>
                            
                <lg>
                <l n="95">Servius Tullius</l>
                <l n="96">Next, Servius Tullius fits upon the Throne,</l>
                <l n="97">Ascends not up, by merits of his owne.</l>
                <l n="98">But by the favour, and the speciall grace</l>
                <l n="99">Of Tanquil, Late Queen, obtaines the place;</l>
                <l n="100">He ranks the people, into each degree,</l>
                <l n="101">As wealth had made them of abilitie;</l>
                <l n="102">A generall Mufter takes, which by account,</l>
                <l n="103">To eighty thousand soules then did amount:</l>
                <l n="104">Forty foure yeares did Servius Tullius reigne,</l>
                <l n="105">And then by Tarquin, Prifcus Son, was slaine.</l>
                </lg>
                            
                <lg>
                <l n="106">Tarquinius Superbus, the last Roman King.</l>
                <l n="107">Tarquin the proud, from manners called so,</l>
                <l n="108">Sate on his Throne, when he had slaine his foe </l>
                <l n="109">Sixtus his Son, doth (most unworthily)</l>
                <l n="110">Lucretia force, mirrour of chastety;</l>
                <l n="111">She loathed so the fact, she loath'd her life,</l>
                <l n="112">And fled her guiltless blood, with guilty knife</l>
                <l n="113">Her Husband sore incens'd, to quit this wrong,</l>
                <l n="114">With Junius Brutus rose, and being strong,</l>
                <l n="115">The Targuins they from Rome with speed expell,</l>
                <l n="116">In banishment perpetuall, to dwell;</l>
                <l n="117">The Government they change, a new one bring,</l>
                <l n="118">And people sweat, ne're to accept of King.</l>
                </lg>
                            
                <lg>
                <l n="119">The end of the Roman Monarchy</l>
                <l n="120">being the fourth and last.</l>
                </lg>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











