<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Davids Lamentation for Saul, and Jonathan, 2 Sam. 1.19</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Anne</forename>
                    <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                    <date when="1612-03-20">Birth: 1612 March 20</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1672 September 16</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Bradstreet-Davids</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="bradstreetAnne">Anne Bradstreet`</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Davids Lamentation for Saul, and Jonathan, 2 Sam. 1.19</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>Davids Lamentation for Saul, and <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Jonathan, 2 Sam. 1.19</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001"> In this passage from the Bible, David mourns the loss of King Saul of Israel and his son, Jonathan, who died during the battle of Mount Gilboa against the Philistines. Source: King James Bible</note></head>
                <author>Anne Bradstreet</author>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>Alas, slaine is the head of Israel,</l>
                    <l>Illustrious Saul, whose beauty did excell </l>
                    <l>Upon thy places, mountan'ous and high,</l>
                    <l>How did the mighty fall and falling dye?</l>
                    <l>In <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Gath</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Gath and Ashkelon were two of the five major cities of the Philistines. Source: Encyclopedia Britannica</note>, let not this thing be spoken on, </l>
                    <l>Nor published in the streets of Askelon,</l>
                    <l>Lest Daughters of the <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Philistins</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">The Philistines were a non-Semitic people that resided in Canaan and posed a significant threat to the Israelites. Source: Encyclopedia Brittanica</note> rejoyce,</l>
                    <l><ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Lest the uncircumcis'd lift up their voyce</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004"> David does not want word of the Israelites' defeat at Mount Gilboa to reach the Philistines, who will revel in the death of Judah's king.</note>:</l>
                    <l>O! <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Gilbo Mounts</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">Mount Gilboa is a range of mountains located in the Jezreel Valley in modern-day northern Israel. Source: Encyclopedia Britannica</note>, let never pearled dew,</l>
                    <l>Nor fruitfull showres your barren tops bestrew,</l>
                    <l>Nor fields of offerings e're on you grow,</l>
                    <l>Nor any pleasant thing e're may you show;</l>
                    <l>For the mighty ones did soone decay,</l>
                    <l>The Shield of Saul was vilely cast away;</l>
                    <l>There had his dignity so sore a <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">foyle</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">A repulse, defeat in an onset or enterprise; a baffling check. Source: Oxford English Dictionary </note>,</l>
                    <l>As if his head ne're felt <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">the sacred Oyle</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">"Then Samuel took the flask of oil, poured it on his [Saul's] head, kissed him and said, 'Has not the LORED anointed you ruler over his inheritance?'" Source: 1 Sam. 10:1</note>:</l>	
                    <l>Sometimes from crimson, blood of gastly slaine,</l>
                    <l>The bow of <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Jonathon</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Jonathan was the son of Saul and a close friend of David, who made a loyalty pact with him in 1 Sam. 1:42 Source: King James Bible</note> ne're turned in vaine,</l>
                    <l>Nor from the fat, and spoyles, of mighty men,</l>
                    <l>Did <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Saul with bloodlesse Sword turne back agen</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Both Saul and Jonathan were mighty warriors; while they used different weapons, they both wielded them successfully in battle. </note>.</l>
                    <l>Pleasant and lovely were they both in life,</l>
                    <l>And in their deaths <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">was found no parting strife</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Despite Jonathan's loyalty to David and Saul's jealousy, Saul and Jonathan were united at the battle and united in death.</note>;</l>
                    <l>Swifter than swiftest Eagles, so were they,</l>
                    <l>Stronger than Lions, ramping for their prey.</l>
                    <l>O Israels Dames, o're-flow your beauteous eyes,</l>
                    <l>For valiant Saul, who on Mount Gilbo lyes;</l>
                    <l>Who cloathed you in cloath of richest dye,</l>
                    <l>And choyce delights, full of variety.</l>
                    <l>On your array put <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">ornaments of gold</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">David reflects on only the positive qualities of Saul, including the prosperity of Judah under his reign.</note>,</l>
                    <l>Which made you yet more beauteous to behold.</l>
                    <l>O! how in battell did the mighty fall,</l>
                    <l>In mid'st of strength not <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">succoured</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012"> To help, assist, or aid. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> at all:</l>	
                    <l>O! lovely Jonathan, how wert thou slaine,</l>
                    <l>In places high, full low thou dost remaine;</l>
                    <l>Distrest I am, for thee, dear Jonathan,</l>
                    <l>Thy love was wonderfull, passing a man;</l>
                    <l><ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Exceeding all the Love that's Feminine</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">David compares the closeness of his friendship with Johnathan to the intimacy and loyalty experienced within marriage. Johnathan accepted David's destiny to become king, and remained loyal to him even after the reproach of his father.</note>,</l>
                    <l>So pleasant hast thou been, dear brother mine:</l>
                    <l>How are the mighty falne into decay,</l>
                    <l>And war-like weapons perished away.</l>
                </lg>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











