<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Prologue</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Anne</forename>
                    <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                    <date when="1612-03-20">Birth: 1612 March 20</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1672 September 16</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>Tim Schott</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Bradstreet-Prologue</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="bradstreetAnne">Anne Bradstreet`</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Prologue</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>The Prologue</head>
                <author>Anne Bradstreet</author>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>To sing of Wars, of Captains, and of Kings,</l>
                    <l>Of Cities founded, Common-wealths begun,</l>
                    <l>For my <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">mean</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Moderate, middling; average. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> pen are too superior things;</l>
                    <l>Or how they all, or each their dates have run,</l>
                    <l>Let Poets and Historians set these forth,</l>
                    <l>My obscure lines shall not so dim their worth.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>But when my wond'ring eyes and envious heart</l>
                    <l>Great <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Bartas</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">French Protestant poet widely respected by the Puritans. Source: Wikipedia</note> sugar'd lines do but read o'er</l>
                    <l>Fool I do grudge the <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Muses</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Nine ancient Greek goddesses of science and art who were the daughters of Zeus. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> did not part</l>
                    <l>'Twixt him and me that over-fluent store.</l>
                    <l>A Bartas can do what a Bartas will</l>
                    <l>But simple I according to my skill.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>From School-boy's tongue no rhet'ric we expect,</l>	
                    <l>Nor yet a sweet <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Consort</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Concert. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> from broken strings,</l>
                    <l>Nor perfect beauty where's a main defect:</l>
                    <l>My foolish, broken, blemished Muse so sings</l>
                    <l>And this to mend, alas, no Art is able,</l>
                    <l>'Cause nature, made it so irreparable.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>Nor can I, like <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">that fluent sweet tongu'd Greek</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">An allusion to Demosthenes, an Athenian statesman recognized as the greatest of ancient Greek orators. He had a speech defect that he overcame on his own by speaking with pebbles in his mouth and by reciting verses when running or out of breath. Source: Wikipedia</note></l>
                    <l>Who lisp'd at first, in future times speak plain.</l>
                    <l>By Art he gladly found what he did seek</l>
                    <l>A full requital of his striving pain.</l>
                    <l>Art can do much, but this maxim's most sure</l>
                    <l>A week or wounded brain admits no cure.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>I am obnoxious to each <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">carping</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Judgemental or tending to find fault. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> tongue</l>
                    <l>Who says my hand a needle better fits.</l>
                    <l>A Poet's pen all scorn I should thus wrong,</l>
                    <l>For such despite they cast on Female wits:</l>
                    <l>If what I do prove well, it won't advance,</l>
                    <l>They'll say it's stol'n, or else it was by chance.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>But sure the Antique Greeks were far more mild</l>
                    <l>Else of our Sex, why feigned they those Nine</l>
                    <l>And poesy made, <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Calliope's</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Foremost of the nine Muses; she was later called the patron of epic poetry. Source: Wikipedia</note> own child?</l>
                    <l>So 'mongst the rest they placed the Arts Divine,</l>
                    <l>But this weak knot, they will full soon untie.</l>
                    <l>The Greeks did nought, but play the fools and lie.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>Let Greeks be Greeks, and women what they are.</l>
                    <l>Men have precedency and still excel,</l>
                    <l>It is but vain unjustly to wage war;</l>
                    <l>Men can do best, and women know it well</l>
                    <l>Preeminence in all and each is yours;</l>
                    <l>Yet grant some small acknowledgment of ours.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>And oh ye high flown quills that soar the Skies,</l>
                    <l>And ever with your prey still catch your praise,</l>
                    <l>If e're you design these lowly lines your eyes</l>
                    <l>Give <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Thyme or Parsley</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Cooking herbs</note> wreath I ask no <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Bays</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Usually in pl. Leaves or sprigs of this tree, esp. as woven into a wreath or garland to reward a conqueror or poet; hence fig. the fame and repute attained by these. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,</l>
                    <l>This mean and unrefined ore of mine</l>
                    <l>Will make your glist'ring gold, but more to shine.</l>
                </lg>          
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











