<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
    <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="bradstreet-youth">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>"Youth"</title>
                    
                    <author>
                        
                        <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                            <name>
                                <forename>Anne</forename>
                                <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                            </name>
                        </persName>
                    </author>
                    <editor>
                        <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                            <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                                <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                                <forename>John</forename>
                            </name>
                        </persName>
                    </editor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                        <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                        <name>John O'Brien</name>
                        <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <sponsor/>
                    <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                    
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    
                    <availability status="free">
                        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                            Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                            License </licence>
                    </availability>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic><title>"Youth"</title></analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                                    <name>
                                        <forename>Anne</forename>
                                        <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                                    </name>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <title type="main">Several Poems Compiled with Great Variety of Wit and Learning</title>
                            
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>
                                    <placeName key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                                </pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Foster</publisher>
                                <date when="1678">1678</date>
                                <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                                    Our texts are taken from the <ref target="http://name.umdl.umich.edu/A29149.0001.001">Text Creation Partnership's digital edition of <hi rend="italic">Several poems compiled with great variety of wit and learning</hi></ref> published in Boston in 1678. This text is sometimes referred to by its alternate title, and the sobriquet given to Anne Bradstreet, "The Tenth Muse". Title page drawn from the University of Pennsylvania's <hi rend="italic">Celebration of Women Writers</hi>.</note>
                            </imprint>    
                            <extent>pp 48-51</extent>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>    
                </sourceDesc>        
            </fileDesc>
            
            <profileDesc>
                <langUsage>
                    <language ident="en">English</language>
                </langUsage>
                <creation/>
                <textDesc n="poem">
                    <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                    <constitution type="single"/>
                    <derivation type="original"/>
                    <domain/>
                    <factuality type="fiction"/>
                    <interaction/>
                    <preparedness type="prepared"/> <!-- I would say this is unknown -->
                    <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                    <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
                </textDesc>
                <settingDesc>
                    <setting>
                        <name type="tgn" key="7014203">New England</name> 
                        <time from="1600" to="1700">Seventeenth Century</time>
                    </setting>
                </settingDesc>
            </profileDesc>
            
            <encodingDesc>
                <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
                <projectDesc>
                    <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                        project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                        sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                        the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                        and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
                </projectDesc>
                <editorialDecl>
                    <interpretation>
                        <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                            links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                            defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                            notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                            lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                    </interpretation>
                    <normalization>
                        <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                            silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                    </normalization>
                    <hyphenation>
                        <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                            word.</p>
                    </hyphenation>
                    <segmentation>
                        <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                            not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                            indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                    </segmentation>
                    <correction>
                        <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                            possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                    </correction>
                </editorialDecl>
                <tagsDecl>
                    <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                        <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                    </namespace>
                </tagsDecl>
                <classDecl>
                    <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                        <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                    </taxonomy>
                    <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                        <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                    </taxonomy>
                    <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                        <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                    </taxonomy>
                    <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                        <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                    </taxonomy>
                </classDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        
        <text><front>
            <pb n="[Title Page]" facs="pageImages/bradstreet_TP.jpeg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart>SEVERAL<lb/>
                    
                    POEMS<lb/>
                    
                    Compiled with great variety of Wit and<lb/>
                    Learning, full of Delight;<lb/>
                    Wherein especially is contained a compleat<lb/>
                    Discourse, and Description of<lb/>
                    
                    The Four {	ELEMENTS<lb/>
                    CONSTITUTIONS,<lb/>
                    AGES of Man,<lb/>
                    SEASONS of the Year.<lb/><lb/>
                    Together with an exact Epitome of<lb/>
                    the three first <hi rend="italic">Monarchyes</hi><lb/><lb/>
                    
                    Viz, The {	ASSYRIAN,<lb/>
                    PERSIAN,<lb/>
                    GRECIAN.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">And beginning of the</hi> Romane Common-wealth<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the end of their last King:</hi><lb/>
                    
                    With diverse other pleasant &amp; serious <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>,<lb/>
                    
                    By a Gentlewoman in <hi rend="italic">New-England</hi>.<lb/>
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">The second Edition, Corrected by the Author,<lb/>
                        and enlarged by an Addition of several other<lb/>
                        Poems found amongst her Papers<lb/>
                        after her Death.</hi><lb/>
                </titlePart>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace><hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, </pubPlace><publisher>Printed by <hi rend="italic">John Foster</hi>,</publisher> <docDate>1678.</docDate></docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>    
<body>
            
            
                <div type="poem">
                <head type="main">Youth</head>

                
                <lg>
              <l n="1">MY goodly cloathing, and my beauteous skin,</l>
              <l n="2">Declare some greater riches are within;</l>
              <l n="3">But what is best i'le first present to view,</l> 
              <l n="4">And then the worst, in a more ugly hue;</l> 
              <l n="5">For thus to do, we on this Stage assemble,</l> 
              <l n="6">Then let not him, which hath most craft dissemble;</l> 
              <l n="7">Mine education, and my learning's such,</l> 
              <l n="8">As might my self, and others, profit much:</l>
              <l n="9">With nurture trained up in vertues Schools,</l> 
              <l n="10">Of Science, Arts, and Tongues, I know the rules,</l> 
              <l n="11">The manners of the Court, I likewise know,</l> 
              <l n="12">Nor ignorant what they in Country do;</l> 
              <l n="13">The brave attempts of valiant Knights I prize,</l> 
                    <l n="14">That dare climbe <ref target="battlements_" corresp="battlements">Battlements</ref><note xml:id="battlements" target="battlements_">The summit of a mountain or a parapet at the top of a wall. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, rear'd to the skies;</l> 
              <l n="15">The snorting Horse, the Trumpet, Drum I like,</l> 
              <l n="16">The glistring Sword, and wel advanced Pike;</l>
              <l n="17">I cannot lye in trench, before a Town,</l> 
              <l n="18">Nor wait til good advice our hopes do crown;</l> 
              <l n="19">I scorn the heavy Corsset, Musket-proof,</l>
              <l n="20">Though thus in field, at home, to all most kind,</l> 
              <l n="21">So affable that I do suit each mind;></l>
              <l n="22">I can insinuate into the brest,</l>
              <l n="23">And by my mirth can raise the heart deprest.</l>
              <l n="24">Sweet Musick rapteth my harmonious Soul,</l>
              <l n="25">And elevates my thoughts above the Pole.</l> 
              <l n="26">My wit, my bounty, and my courtesie,</l>
              <l n="27">Makes all to place their future hopes on me.</l>
              <l n="28">This is my best, but youth (is known) alas,</l>
              <l n="29">To be as wilde as is the snuffing Asse,</l>
              <l n="30">As vain as froth, as vanity can be,</l> 
              <l n="31">That who would see vain man, may look on me:</l>
              <l n="32">My gifts abus'd, my education lost,</l> 
              <l n="33">My woful Parents longing hopes all crost,</l>
              <l n="34">My wit, evaporates in meriment:></l> 
              <l n="35">My valour, in some beastly quarrel's spent;</l>
              <l n="36">Martial deeds I love not, 'cause they're vertuous,</l> 
              <l n="37">But doing so, might seem magnanimous.</l> 
              <l n="38">My Lust doth hurry me, to all that's ill,</l>
              <l n="39">I know no Law, nor reason, but my wil;</l>
              <l n="40">Sometimes lay wait to take a wealthy purse,</l> 
              <l n="41">Or stab the man, in's own defence, that's worse,</l> 
              <l n="42">Sometimes I cheat (unkind) a female Heir, </l>
              <l n="43">Of all at once, who not so wise, as fair, </l>
              <l n="44">Trusteth my loving looks, and glozing tongue, </l>
              <l n="45">Until her freinds, treasure, and honour's gone.</l> 
              <l n="46">Sometimes I sit carousing others health,</l> 
              <l n="47">Until mine own be gone, my wit, and wealth;</l> 
              <l n="48">From pipe to pot, from pot to words, and blows,</l> 
              <l n="49">For he that loveth Wine, wanteth no woes;</l>
              <l n="50">Dayes, nights, with Ruffins, Roarers, Fidlers spend;</l> 
              <l n="51">To all obscenity, my eares I bend.</l>
              <l n="52">All counsel hate, which tends to make me wise,</l> 
              <l n="53">And dearest freinds count for mine enemies;</l> 
              <l n="54">If any care I take, 'tis to be fine,</l> 
              <l n="55">For sure my suit more then my vertues shine;</l> 
              <l n="56">If any time from company I spare,</l>
              <l n="57">'Tis spent in curling, frisling up my hair;</l>
                    <l n="58">Some young Adonis I do strive to be,</l>                                               <l n="59"><ref target="Sardanapallas_" corresp="Sardanapallas">Sardana Pallas</ref><note xml:id="Sardanapallas" target="Sardanapallas_">Sardanapallas is legendary tragic king of Assyria. Source: <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/topic/Sardanapalus-legendary-king-of-Assyria">Encyclopedia Brittanica</ref>.</note>, now survives in me:</l>
                  <l n="60">Cards, Dice, and Oaths, concomitant, I love;</l> 
                  <l n="61">To Masques, to Playes, to Taverns stil I move;</l> 
                  <l n="62">And in a word, if what I am you'd heare,</l> 
                  <l n="63">Seek out a Brittish, bruitish Cavaleer;</l> 
                  <l n="64">Such wretch, such monster am I; but yet more,</l> 
                  <l n="65">I want a heart all this for to deplore.</l>
                  <l n="66">Thus, thus alas! I have mispent my time,</l>
                  <l n="67">My youth, my best, my strength, my bud, and prime:</l>
                  <l n="68">Remembring not the dreadful day of Doom,</l> 
                  <l n="69">Nor yet that heavy reckoning for to come;</l> 
                  <l n="70">Though dangers do attend me every houre,</l> 
                  <l n="71">And gastly death oft threats me with her power,</l> 
                  <l n="72">Sometimes by wounds in idle combates taken,</l> 
                    <l n="73">Sometimes by <ref target="agues_" corresp="agues">Agues</ref><note  xml:id="agues" target="agues">Sickness with a high fever. Source: Oxford english Dictionary</note> all my body shaken;</l> 
                  <l n="74">Sometimes by Feavers, all my moisture drinking,</l> 
                  <l n="75">My heart lyes frying, and my eyes are sinking;</l> 
                    <l n="76">Sometimes the Cough, Stitch, painful <ref target="plurisie_" corresp="plurisie">Plurisie</ref><note xml:id="plurisie" target="plurisie_">Pleurisy is an illness characterized by chest pains often accompanied with coughing and inflammation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,</l> 
                  <l n="77">With sad affrights of death, doth menace me;</l>
                  <l n="78">Sometimes the loathsome Pox, my face be-mars,</l> 
                  <l n="79">With ugly marks of his eternal scars;</l>
                  <l n="80">Sometimes the Phrensie, strangely madds my Brain,</l>
                    <l n="81">That oft for it, in <ref target="bedlam_" corresp="bedlam">Bedlam</ref><note xml:id="bedlam" target="bedlam_">A truncation of Bethlehem Hospital, a facility in London for the supposed insane. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> I remain.</l> 
                  <l n="82">Too many's my Diseases to recite,</l> 
                  <l n="83">That wonder 'tis I yet behold the light,</l> 
                  <l n="84">That yet my bed in darknesse is not made,</l> 
                  <l n="85">And I in black oblivions den long laid;</l> 
                  <l n="86">Of Marrow ful my bones, of Milk my breasts,</l> 
                  <l n="87">Ceas'd by the gripes of Serjeant Death's Arrests:</l> 
                  <l n="88">Thus I have said, and what i've said you see,</l> 
                  <l n="89">Child-hood and youth is vaine, yea vanity.</l>
                </lg>
                
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











