<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="bradstreet-sidney">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>An Elegie upon that honourable and renowned Knight, Sir Philip Sidney, who was untimely slaine at the Seige of Zutphon Anno 1586</title>
                
                <author>
                   
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Anne</forename>
                            <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#" >
                            <surname></surname>
                            <forename></forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
               
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Anne</forename>
                                    <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">An Elegie upon that honourable and renowned Knight, Sir Philip Sidney, who was untimely slaine at the Seige of Zutphon Anno 1586</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="6000236">American Colonies</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1678">1678</date>
                            <note></note>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                                Our texts are taken from the Text Creation Partnership's digital edition of "Several poems compiled with great variety of wit and learning, full of delight, wherein especially is contained a compleat discourse, and description of the four elements constitutions, ages of man, seasons of the year. : Together with an exact epitome of the three first monarchyes viz. the Assyrian, Persian, Grecian. And beginning of the Romane Common-Wealth to the end of their last king:  with diverse other pleasant &amp; serious poems,  by a gentlewoman in New-England," published in Boston in 1678.                             </note>
                        </imprint>  
                        <extent></extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/> <!-- I would say this is unknown -->
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7014203">New England</name> 
                    <date from="1600" to="1700">Seventeenth Century</date>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head>An Elegie upon that honourable and renowned Knight, <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Sir Philip Sidney</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">(DRAFT)Philip Sidney (1554-1586) Sidney was a Renaissance Lyric poet of the Elizabethan Age. Some of his most famous works are his Sonnet Sequence "Astrophel and Stella" and his essay "The Defence of Poesy." Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Sidney
                
                Astrophel and stella Poem: https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/45152/astrophil-and-stella-1-loving-in-truth-and-fain-in-verse-my-love-to-show</note>, who was untimely slaine at the Seige of <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Zutphon</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Town in the Netherlands where the Battle of Zutphen was fought between the British and Dutch against the Spanish during the Eighty Years' War. Sir Philip Sidney received a mortal wound here, and the battle was won by the Spanish.</note> Anno 1586</head>
                <head>Anne Bradstreet</head>
                
                <lg>
                    <l n="1">When England did injoy her <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Halsion</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Halycon, calm, peaceful. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> dayes,</l>
                    <l n="2">Her noble Sidney wore the Crown of <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Bayes</ref><note xml:id="n004">Bay Laurel, a laurel wreath.</note>;</l>
                    <l n="3">No lesse an Honour to our British Land,</l>
                    <l n="4">Then she that sway'd the Scepter with her hand:</l>
                    <l n="5"><ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Mars and Minerva</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT put link as side bar)Roman gods, Mars is the god of War, Minerva is the goddess of Wisdom, arts, and strategy. Source: Wikipedia For more on Roman Deities: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Roman_deities</note> did in one agree,</l>
                    <l n="6">Of Armes, and Arts, thou should'st a patterne be.</l>
                    <l n="7"><ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Calliope</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">(DRAFT put link as side bar)Muse of eloquence and epic poetry. For more on the Greek Muses: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muses</note> with <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Terpsecher</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Terpsichore is the muse of dance and chorus.</note> did sing,</l>
                    <l n="8">Of <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Poesie</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Poetry</note>, and of Musick thou wert King;</l>
                    <l n="9">Thy Rhethorick it struck <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Polimnia</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Muse of sacred poetry</note> dead,</l>
                    <l n="10">Thine Eloquence made <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Mecury</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Roman god of communication and commerce</note> wax red;</l>
                    <l n="11">Thy Logick from <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Euterpe</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Muse of music</note> won the Crown,</l>
                    <l n="12">More worth was thine, then <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Clio</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">Muse of history</note> could set down.</l>
                    <l n="13"><ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Thalia</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Muse of Comedy and idyllic poetry</note>, and <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Melpomene</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">Muse of Tragedy.</note>, say th' truth,</l>
                    <l n="14">(Witness <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Arcadia</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">The Countess of Pembroke's Arcadia is a long work of prose written by Sir Philip Sidney. Source: Wikipedia</note>, penn'd in his youth)</l>
                    <l n="15">Are not his Tragick Comedies so acted.</l>
                    <l n="16">As if your nine-fold wit had been compacted;</l>
                    <l n="17">To shew the world, they never saw before,</l>
                    <l n="18">That this one volumne should exhaust your store.</l>
                    <l n="19">I prase thee not for this, it is unfit,</l>
                    <l n="20">This was thy shame, O miracle of wit;</l>
                    <l n="21">Yet doth thy shune (with all) purchase renown,</l>
                    <l n="22">What doe thy vertues then? Oh, honours crown!</l>
                    <l n="23">In all records, thy Name I ever see,</l>
                    <l n="24">Put with an Epithet of dignity;</l>
                    <l n="25">Which <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">Shewes</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">Shows. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, thy worth was great, thine honour such,</l>
                    <l n="26">The love thy country ought thee, was as much.</l>
                    <l n="27">Let then, none dis-allow of these my straines,</l>
                    <l n="28">Which have the self-same blood yet in my veines;</l>
                    <l n="29">Who honours thee for what was honourable,</l>
                    <l n="30">But leaves the rest, as most unprofitable :</l>
                    <l n="31">Thy wiser dayes, condemn'd thy witty works,</l>
                    <l n="32">Who knowes the Spels that in thy Rethorick lurks?</l>
                    <l n="33">But some infatuate fooles soone caught therein,</l>
                    <l n="34">Found Cupids <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Dam</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">(DRAFT) Someone originally defined this as "referring to Psyche" however that seems off to me, but yet I don't know how to define it otherwise</note>, had never such a <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Gin</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">Skill, ingenuity</note>;</l>
                    <l n="35">Which makes feverer eyes but scorn thy Story,</l>
                    <l n="36">And model Maids, and Wives, blush at thy glory;</l>
                    <l n="37">Yet, <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">he's a beetle head</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">Proverbial phrase for idiot</note>, that cann't <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">discry</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020" >Catch sight of. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></l>
                    <l n="38">A world of treasure, in that rubbish lye;</l>
                    <l n="39">And doth the selfe, thy worke, and honour wrong,</l>
                    <l n="40">(O brave Refiner of the British tongue;)</l>
                    <l n="41">That sees not learning, valour, and morality,</l>
                    <l n="42">Justice, friendship, and kind hospitality;</l>
                    <l n="43">Yea, and Divinity within thy Book,</l>
                    <l n="44">Such were prejudicate, and did not look:</l>
                    <l n="45">But to say truth, thy worth I <ref target="a021" corresp="n021">shale</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">(draft)Shall or does this mean to devulge or, crack open</note> but <ref target="a022" corresp="n022">staine</ref><note xml:id="n022" target="a022">(draft) What does this mean in context with shale</note>,</l>
                    <l n="46">Thy fame, and praise, is farre beyond my straine</l>
                    <l n="47">Yet great Augustus was content (we know)</l>
                    <l n="48">To be saluted by a silly Crow;</l>
                    <l n="49">Then let such Crowes as I, thy praises sing,</l>
                    <l n="50">A Crow's a Crow, and Caesar is a King.</l>
                    <l n="51">O brave <ref target="a023" corresp="n023">Achilles</ref><note xml:id="n023" target="a023">One of the great Greek mythological heroes, associated with the Iliad</note> I with some <ref target="a024" corresp="n024">Homer</ref><note xml:id="n024" target="a024">Ancient blind Greek epic poet, composed the Iliad and Odyssey</note>, would</l>
                    <l n="52">Engrave on Marble, in characters of Gold,</l>
                    <l n="53">What famous feats thou didst, on <ref target="a025" corresp="n025">Flanders</ref><note xml:id="n025" target="a025">The Northern part of Belgium that speaks Dutch. Source: Wikipedia</note> coast,</l>
                    <l n="54">Of which, this day, faire Belgia doth boast.</l>
                    <l n="55">Of Zutphon, Zutphon, that most fatall City,</l>
                    <l n="56">Made famous by thy fall, much more's the pitty,</l>
                    <l n="57">Ah, in his blooming prime, death pluckt this Rose,</l>
                    <l n="58">E're he was ripe; his thred cut <ref target="a026" corresp="n026">Atropos</ref><note xml:id="n026" target="a026">One of the three Fates; she cuts the thread of a person's life. Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moirai</note>.</l>
                    <l n="59">Thus Man is borne to dye, and dead is he,</l>
                    <l n="60">Brave <ref target="a027" corresp="n027">Hector</ref><note xml:id="n027" target="a027">A brave Trojan hero, killed by Achilles</note> by the walls of <ref target="a028" corresp="n028">Troy</ref><note xml:id="n028" target="a028">The siege of Troy was the subject of Homer's Iliad</note>, we see:</l>
                    <l n="61">Oh, who was neare thee, but did sore repine;</l>
                    <l n="62">He rescued not with life, that life of thine,</l>
                    <l n="63">But yet impartiall Death this Boone did give,</l>
                    <l n="64">Though Sidney dy'd, his valiant name should live;</l>
                    <l n="65">And live it doth, in spight of death, through fame,</l>
                    <l n="66">Thus being over-come, he over-came.</l>
                    <l n="67">Where is that envious tongue, but can afford, </l>
                    <l n="68">Of this our noble <ref target="a029" corresp="n029">Scipio</ref><note xml:id="n029" target="a029">The Roman general who defeated Hannibal's invasion of Rome</note> some good word?</l>
                    <l n="69">Noble <ref target="a030" corresp="n030">Bartas</ref><note xml:id="n030" target="a030">French Huguenot poet who served in Henry IV of France's court</note>, this to thy praise adds more,</l>
                    <l n="70">In sad, sweet verse, thou didst his death deplore;</l>
                    <l n="71">Illustrious <ref target="a031" corresp="n031">Stella</ref><note xml:id="n031" target="a031">Astrophil and Stella is a sonnet sequence written by Sir Philip Sidney. The name Astrophil is Greek for "star lover" and Stella is Latin for "star." Source: Wikipedia</note>, thou didst thine full well,</l>
                    <l n="72">If thine aspect was milde to Astrophell;</l>
                    <l n="73">I feare thou wert a Commet, did portend</l>
                    <l n="74">Such prince as he, his race should shortly end;</l>
                    <l n="75">If such Stars as these, sad presages be,</l>
                    <l n="76">I with no more such Blazers we may see;</l>
                    <l n="77">But thou art gone, such Meteors never last,</l>
                    <l n="78">And as thy beauty, so thy name would waft,</l>
                    <l n="79">But that is record by Philips hand,</l>
                    <l n="80">That such an omen once was in out land;</l>
                    <l n="81">O princely Philip, rather <ref target="a032" corresp="n032">Alexander</ref>,<note xml:id="n032" target="a032">Alexander the Great, the leader of the Macedonian empire which conqeured a large swath of Mediterranean</note></l>
                    <l n="82">Who wert of honours band, the chief Commander.</l>
                    <l n="83">How could that Stella, so confine thy will?</l>
                    <l n="84">To wait till she, her influence distill,</l>
                    <l n="85">I rather judg'd thee of his mind that wept,</l>
                    <l n="86">To be within the bounds of one world kept,</l>
                    <l n="87">But <ref target="a033" corresp="n033">Omphala</ref><note xml:id="n033" target="a033">Mistress to whom Hercules was enslaved, forced him to do traditionally women's work, among other things.</note>, set Hercules to spin,</l>
                    <l n="88">And Mars himself was ta'n by <ref target="a034" corresp="n034">Venus</ref><note xml:id="n034" target="a034">Roman goddess of love, wife of Vulcan and mistress of Mars</note> gin;</l>
                    <l n="89">Then wonder lesse, if warlike Philip yield,</l>
                    <l n="90">When such a Hero shoots him out o'th' field,</l>
                    <l n="91">Yet this <ref target="a035" corresp="n035">preheminence</ref><note xml:id="n035" target="a035">Preeminence, superiority</note> thou hast above,</l>
                    <l n="92">That thine was true, but theirs <ref target="a036" corresp="n036">adult'rate</ref><note xml:id="n036" target="a036">Make something worse by mixing in inferior substance.</note> love.</l>
                    <l n="93">Fain would I shew, how thou fame's path didst tread,</l>
                    <l n="94">But now into such Lab'rinths am I led</l>
                    <l n="95">With endlesse turnes, the way I find not out,</l>
                    <l n="96">For to persist, my muse is more in doubt:</l>
                    <l n="97">Calls me ambitious tool, that durst aspire,</l>
                    <l n="98">Enough for me to look, and so admire.</l>
                    <l n="99">And makes me now with <ref target="a037" corresp="n037">Sylvester</ref><note xml:id="n037" target="a037">(DRAFT) what/who is this</note> confesse,</l>
                    <l n="100">But Sydney's Muse, can sing his worthinesse.</l>
                    <l n="101">Too late my errour see, that durst presume</l>
                    <l n="102">To fix my faltring lines upon his tomb:</l>
                    <l n="103">Which are in wort, as far short of his due,</l>
                    <l n="104">As <ref target="a038" corresp="n038">Vulcan</ref><note xml:id="n038" target="a038">Roman god of smithing, husband of Venus.</note> is, of Venus native hue.</l>
                    <l n="105">Goodwill, did make my head-long pen to run,</l>
                    <l n="106">Like unwise <ref target="a039" corresp="n039">Phaeton</ref><note xml:id="n039" target="a039">Son of Apollo who tried to drive his father's chariot across the sky; he lost control and set the world ablaze, forcing Zeus to kill him with a thunderbolt</note> his ill guided sonne,</l>
                    <l n="107">Till taught to's cost, for his too hasty hand,</l>
                    <l n="108">He left that charge by <ref target="a040" corresp="n040">Phoebus</ref><note xml:id="n040" target="a040">or Apollo is the God of the Sun</note> to be man'd:</l>
                    <l n="109">So proudly foolish I, with Phaeton strive,</l>
                    <l n="110">Fame's flaming Chariot for to drive.</l>
                    <l n="111">Til terrour-struck for my too weighty charge.</l>
                    <l n="112">I leave't in brief, Apollo do't at large.</l>
                    <l n="113">Apollo laught to patch up what's begun,</l>
                    <l n="114">He bad drive, and he would hold the Sun,</l>
                    <l n="115">Better my hap, then was his darlings fate,</l>
                    <l n="116">For dear regard he had of Sydney's state,</l>
                    <l n="117">Who in his Deity, had so deep share,</l>
                    <l n="118">That those that name his fame, he needs must spare,</l>
                    <l n="119">He promis'd much, but th' muses had no will,</l>
                    <l n="120">To give to their detractor any quill.</l>
                    <l n="121">With high disdain, they said they gave no more,</l>
                    <l n="122">Since Sydney had exhausted all their store,</l>
                    <l n="123">That this contempt it did the more perplex,</l>
                    <l n="124">In being done by one of their own sex;</l>
                    <l n="125">They took from me, the scribling pen I had,</l>
                    <l n="126">I to be eas'd of such a task was glad.</l>
                    <l n="127">For to revenge his wrong, themselves ingage,</l>
                    <l n="128">And drave me from <ref target="a041" corresp="n041">Parnassus</ref><note xml:id="n041" target="a041">The site of the Dionysian mysteries, some of which included women who drove themselves into a frenzied state.</note> in a rage,</l>
                    <l n="129">Not because, sweet Sydney's fame was not dear,</l>
                    <l n="130">But I had blemish'd theirs, to make't appear:</l>
                    <l n="131">I pensive for my fault, sat down, and then,</l>
                    <l n="132"><ref target="a042" corresp="n042">Errata</ref><note xml:id="n042" target="a042">A writing or printing error. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, through their leave thre me my pen,</l>
                    <l n="133">For to conclude my poem two lines they daigne,</l>
                    <l n="134">Which writ, she bad return't to them again.</l>
                    <l n="135">So Sydney's fame, I leave to <ref target="a043" corresp="n043">England's Rolls</ref><note xml:id="n043" target="a043">Official records of parliamentary meetings and acts.</note>,</l>
                    <l n="136">His bones do lie interr'd in stately <ref target="a044" corresp="n044">Pauls</ref><note xml:id="n044" target="a044">Sir Philip Sidney was buried at St. Paul's cathedral in London.</note>.</l>
                </lg>    
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











