<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="bradstreet-earth">
    <teiHeader>  <!--TEI Header BEGINS-->   
        <fileDesc>  <!--BEGINS File Description -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Earth</title>
                
                <author>
                     <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                         <name>
                             <forename>Anne</forename>
                             <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                         </name>
                     </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#" >
                            <surname></surname>
                            <forename></forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>Tim Schott</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc> <!--BEGINS Source Description -->
                <bibl>Write source here
                    
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79145303">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Anne</forename>
                                    <surname>Bradstreet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Earth</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="6000236">American Colonies</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1678">1678</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                                Our texts are taken from the Text Creation Partnership's digital edition of "Several poems compiled with great variety of wit and learning, full of delight, wherein especially is contained a compleat discourse, and description of the four elements constitutions, ages of man, seasons of the year. : Together with an exact epitome of the three first monarchyes viz. the Assyrian, Persian, Grecian. And beginning of the Romane Common-Wealth to the end of their last king:  with diverse other pleasant &amp; serious poems,  by a gentlewoman in New-England," published in Boston in 1678.                             </note>
                        </imprint> 
                        <extent></extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="poem">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/> <!-- I would say this is unknown -->
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7014203">New England</name> 
                    <date from="1600" to="1700">Seventeenth Century</date>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--TEI Header Ends -->
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <head><ref target="a020" corresp="n020">Earth</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">Earth is the second poem in her collection: "The Four Elements."</note></head>
                <head>Anne Bradstreet</head>
                
                <lg>
                    <l n="1">The next in place, Earth judg'd to be her due,</l>
                    <l n="2">Sister, in worth I come not short of you;</l>
                    <l n="3">In wealth and use I doe surpasse you all,</l>
                    <l n="4">And Mother Earth, of old, men did me call,</l>
                    <l n="5">Such was my fruitfulnesse; an <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Epithite</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">(DRAFT) I don't know which definition this is or should be</note></l>
                    <l n="6">Which none ere gave, nor you could claime of right,</l>
                    <l n="7">Among my praises this I count not least,</l>
                    <l n="8">I am th'origniall of man and beast,</l>
                    <l n="9">To tell what <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">sundry</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Various. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> fruits my fat soyle yeelds,</l>
                    <l n="10">In vine-yards, orchards, gardens, and corne fields,</l>
                    <l n="11">Their kinds, their tasts, their colours, and their smels,</l>
                    <l n="12">Would so passe time, I could say nothing else;</l>
                    <l n="13">The rich and poore, wife, foole, and every sort,</l>
                    <l n="14">Of these so common things, can make report:</l>
                    <l n="15">To tell you of my Countries, and my regions</l>
                    <l n="16">Soone would they passe, not hundreds, but legions,</l>
                    <l n="17">My cities famous, rich, and populous,</l>
                    <l n="18">Whose numbers now are growne innumerous;</l>
                    <l n="19">I have not time to thinke of every part,</l>
                    <l n="20">Yet let me name my <ref target="a003" corresp="n003"><hi style="italics">Grecia</hi></ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Greece. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, 'tis my heart</l>
                    <l n="21">For Learning, Armes, and Arts, I love it well:</l>
                    <l n="22">But chiefly, cause the Muses there did dwell;</l>
                    <l n="23">I'le here skip o're my mountaines, reaching skies,</l>
                    <l n="24">Whether Pyrenian, or the Alpes; both lyes</l>
                    <l n="25">On either side the country of the <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi style="italics">Gaules</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">An area of Western Europe that now makes up what is now present France, Luxembourg, Belgium, much of Switzerland, Northern Italy, and various small parts of the netherlands and Germany. Source: Wikipedia</note>,</l>
                    <l n="26">Strong forts from the <hi style="italics">Spanish</hi> and <hi style="italics">Italian</hi> braules,</l>
                    <l n="27">And huge great <ref target="a005" corresp="n005"><hi style="italics">Taurus</hi></ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">Taurus is the second Zodiac constelaltion, the Bull. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, longer then the rest,</l>
                    <l n="28">Dividing great <hi style="italics">Armenia</hi> from the least,</l>
                    <l n="29">And <ref target="a006" corresp="n006"><hi style="italics">Hemus</hi>(DRAFT) Hemus is an area in Sweden.</ref>, whose steep sides, none foote upon,</l>
                    <l n="30">But farewell all, for deare mount <hi style="italics">Helicon</hi>,</l>
                    <l n="31">And wonderous high <hi style="italics">Olimpus</hi>, of such fame,</l>
                    <l n="32">That heaven selfe was oft call'd by that name;</l>
                    <l n="33">Sweet <ref target="a007" corresp="n007"><hi style="italics">Parnassus</hi>Mount Parnassus is regarded as a source of poetic and other literary inspiration. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</ref>, I dote too much on thee,</l>
                    <l n="34">Unless thou prove a better friend to me;</l>
                    <l n="35">But ile skip o're these Hills, not touch a <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Dale</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">A valley. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>,</l>
                    <l n="36">Nor yet <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">expatiate</ref><note xml:id="n009" corresp="n009">Walk about or roam. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, in Temple vale;</l>
                    <l n="37">Ile here let goe, my Lions of <hi style="italics">Numedia</hi>,</l>
                    <l n="38">My Panther, and my leopards of <hi style="italics">Libia</hi>,</l>
                    <l n="39">The Behemoth, and rare found Unicorne,</l>
                    <l n="40">Poysons sure antidote lyes in his horne.</l>
                    <l n="41">And my <hi style="italics">Hyena</hi> (imitates mans voyce)</l>
                    <l n="42">Out of huge numbers, I might pick my choyce,</l>
                    <l n="43">Thousands in woods, and planes, both wild, and tame,</l>
                    <l n="44">But here, or there, I list now none: name;</l>
                    <l n="45">No, though the fawning dog did urge me sore</l>
                        <l n="46">In his behalfe to speak a word the more;</l>
                        <l n="47">Whose trust, and valour I might here commend:</l>
                        <l n="48">But time's too short, and precious so to spend.</l>
                        <l n="49">But hark, ye worthy Merchants who for prize</l>
                        <l n="50">Send forth your well man'd ships, where fun doth rise</l>
                        <l n="51">After three years, when men and meat is spent</l>
                        <l n="52">My rich commodities payes double rent.</l>
                    <l n="53"><hi style="italics">Ye <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Galenists</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Followers of the medical practices of the Greek physician and philosopher Galen. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></hi>, my Drugs that come from thence</l>
                        <l n="54">Doe cure your patients, fill your purse with pence;</l>
                        <l n="55">Besides the use you have, or Hearbs and Plants,</l>
                        <l n="56">That with the lesse cost, neare home, supplyes your wants.</l>
                        <l n="57">But Marriners, where got you ships and sailes?</l>
                        <l n="58">And Oares to row, when both my sisters failes?</l>
                        <l n="59">Your tackling, Anchor, Compasse too, is mine;</l>
                        <l n="60">Which guides, when Sun, nor Moon, nor Stars do shine</l>
                        <l n="61">Ye mighty kinds, who for your lasting fames</l>
                        <l n="62">Built cities, Monuments call'd by your names;</l>
                        <l n="63">What those compiled heapes of <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">mussy</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">mossy</note>stones?</l>
                        <l n="64">That your ambition laid, ought but my bones?</l>
                        <l n="65">Ye greedy misers who do dig for gold;</l>
                        <l n="66">For gemmes, for silver, treasures which I hold:</l>
                        <l n="67">Will nor my goodly face, your rage suffice?</l>
                        <l n="68">Buy you will see what in my bowls lyes?</l>
                        <l n="69">And ye <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Artificers</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">An artisan. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, all trades and forts;</l>
                        <l n="70">My bounty calls you forth to make reports,</l>
                        <l n="71">If ought have to use, to wear, to eate?</l>
                        <l n="72">But what I freely yeeld upon your sweat?</l>
                        <l n="73">And <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">chorlerick</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">A tendency to be easily angered. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> sister, thou (for all thine ire)</l>
                        <l n="74">Well knowest, my fuell must maintain thy fire.</l>
                        <l n="75">As I ingenuously (with thanks) confesse</l>
                        <l n="76">My cold, thy (fruitful) heat, doth crave no lesse:</l>
                        <l n="77">But how my cold, dry temper, works upon</l>
                        <l n="78">The melancholy constitution.</l>
                        <l n="79">How the Autumnal season I do sway;</l>
                        <l n="80">And how I force the grey head to obey.</l>
                        <l n="81">I should here make a short, yet true narration,</l>
                        <l n="82">But that the method is my imitation.</l>
                        <l n="83">Now might I shew my adverse quality,</l>
                        <l n="84">And how I oft work mans mortality</l>
                        <l n="85">He sometimes findes, <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">maugre</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">Ill will or reproach. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> his toyling paine,</l>
                        <l n="86">Thistles and thornes, where he expected graine;</l>
                        <l n="87">My sap, to plants and trees, I must not grant,</l>
                        <l n="88">The Vine, the Olive, and the Figtree want:</l>
                        <l n="89">The Corne, and Hay, both fall before they'r mowne;</l>
                        <l n="90">And buds from fruitfull trees, before they'r blowne.</l>
                        <l n="91">Then dearth prevailes, That Nature to suffice,</l>
                        <l n="92">The tender mother on her Infant flyes:</l>
                        <l n="93">The Husband knowes no Wife, nor father sons;</l>
                        <l n="94">But to all outrages their hunger runnes.</l>
                        <l n="95">Dreadful expamples, soon I might produce,</l>
                        <l n="96">But to such auditours 'twere of no use</l>
                        <l n="97">Again, when Delvers dare in hope of gold,</l>
                        <l n="98">To ope those veines of Mine, audacious bold:</l>
                        <l n="99">While they thus in my <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">intralls</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">Entrails</note>seem to dive;</l>
                        <l n="100">Before they know, they are inter'd alive.</l>
                        <l n="101">Ye affrighted <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">wights</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">Human, man, or creature. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, appall'd how you do shake</l>
                        <l n="102">If one you feele me, your foundation, quake,</l>
                        <l n="103">Because in the abysse of my darke wombe:</l>
                        <l n="104">Your Cities and your selves I oft intombe.</l>
                        <l n="105">O dreadfull <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Sepulcher</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">A tomb or vault to house the dead. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>! that this is true,</l>
                        <l n="106"><ref target="a018" corresp="n018"><hi style="italics">Korah</hi></ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">Character from Numbers 16 in the Bible who led a rebellion against Moses and Aaron for exalting themselves above the rest of the Israelites. It did not end well for Korah and his men: God opened up the earth, and the rebels and their families were swallowed whole (gotquestions.org).</note> and all his Company well knew.</l>
                        <l n="107">And since, faire <hi style="italics">Italy</hi> full sadly knowes.</l>
                        <l n="108">What she hath lost by these my dreadfull woes.</l>
                        <l n="109">And <hi style="italics">Rome</hi>, her <hi style="italics">Curtius</hi>, can't forget I think;</l>
                        <l n="110">Who bravely rode into my yawning chinke.</l>
                        <l n="111">Again, what veines of poyson in me lye;</l>
                        <l n="112">As <hi style="italics">Stibium</hi> and unfixt <hi style="italics">Mercury</hi>:</l>
                        <l n="113">With divers moe, nay, into plants it creeps;</l>
                        <l n="114">In hot, and cold, and some <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">benums</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">Stupify or shock. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> with sleeps,</l>
                        <l n="115">Thus I occasion death to man and beast,</l>
                        <l n="116">When they seek food, and harme mistrust the least.</l>
                        <l n="117">Much might I say, of the <hi style="italics">Arabian</hi> sands;</l>
                        <l n="118">Wherein whole Armies I have overthrown;</l>
                        <l n="119">But windy sister, 'twas when you have blown.</l>
                        <l n="120">Ile say no more, yet this thing adde I must,</l>
                        <l n="121">Remember sonnes, your mould is of my dust</l>
                        <l n="122">And after death, whether inter'd, or burn'd;</l>
                        <l n="123">As earth at first, so earth into return'd.</l>	
                    
                </lg>
                
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>











