 <div type="poem">
            <head>The Extaſie.</head>
            <l>WHere, like a pillow on a bed,</l>
            <l>A Pregnant banke ſwel'd up, to reſt</l>
            <l>The violets reclining head,</l>
            <l>Sat we two, one anothers beſt;</l>
            <l>Our hands were firmely cimented</l>
            <l>With a faſt balme, which thence did ſpring,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="278" facs="tcp:22691:143"/>
Our eye-beames twiſted, and did thred</l>
            <l>Our eyes, upon one double ſtring,</l>
            <l>So to'entergraft our hands, as yet</l>
            <l>Was all the meanes to make us one,</l>
            <l>And pictures in our eyes to get</l>
            <l>Was all our propagation.</l>
            <l>As 'twixt two equall Armies, Fate</l>
            <l>Suſpends uncertaine victorie,</l>
            <l>Our ſoules, (which to advance their ſtate,</l>
            <l>Were gone out,) hung 'twixt her, and mee.</l>
            <l>And whil'ſt our ſoules negotiate there,</l>
            <l>Wee like ſepulchrall ſtatues lay,</l>
            <l>All day, the ſame our poſtures were,</l>
            <l>And wee ſaid nothing, all the day.</l>
            <l>If any, ſo by love refin'd,</l>
            <l>That he ſoules language underſtood,</l>
            <l>And by good love were growen all minde,</l>
            <l>Within convenient diſtance ſtood,</l>
            <l>He (though he knowes not which ſoule ſpake,</l>
            <l>Becauſe both meant, both ſpake the ſame)</l>
            <l>Might thence a new concoction take,</l>
            <l>And part farre purer then he came.</l>
            <l>This Extaſie doth unperplex</l>
            <l>(We ſaid) and tell us what we love,</l>
            <l>Wee ſee by this, it was not ſexe</l>
            <l>Wee ſee, we ſaw not what did move:</l>
            <l>But as all ſeverall ſoules containe</l>
            <l>Mixture of things, they know not what,</l>
            <l>Love, theſe mixt ſoules, doth mixe againe,</l>
            <l>And makes both one, each this and that.</l>
            <l>A ſingle violet tranſplant,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="279" facs="tcp:22691:143"/>
The ſtrength, the colour, and the ſize,</l>
            <l>(All which before was poore, and ſcant,)</l>
            <l>Redoubles ſtill, and multiplies.</l>
            <l>When love, with one another ſo</l>
            <l>Interanimates two ſoules,</l>
            <l>That abler ſoule, which thence doth flow,</l>
            <l>Defects of lonelineſſe controules.</l>
            <l>Wee then, who are this new ſoule, know,</l>
            <l>Of what we are compos'd, and made,</l>
            <l>For, th'Atomies of which we grow,</l>
            <l>Are ſoules, whom no change can invade.</l>
            <l>But O alas, ſo long, ſo farre</l>
            <l>Our bodies why doe wee forbeare?</l>
            <l>They are ours, though not wee, Wee are</l>
            <l>The intelligences, they the ſpheares.</l>
            <l>We owe them thankes, becauſe they thus,</l>
            <l>Did us, to us, at firſt convay,</l>
            <l>Yeelded their ſenſes force to us,</l>
            <l>Nor are droſſe to us, but allay.</l>
            <l>On man heavens influence workes not ſo,</l>
            <l>But that it firſt imprints the ayre,</l>
            <l>For ſoule into the ſoule may flow,</l>
            <l>Though it to body firſt repaire.</l>
            <l>As our blood labours to beget</l>
            <l>Spirits, as like ſoules as it can,</l>
            <l>Becauſe ſuch fingers need to knit</l>
            <l>That ſubtile knot, which makes us man:</l>
            <l>So muſt pure lovers ſoules deſcend</l>
            <l>T'affections, and to faculties,</l>
            <l>Which ſenſe may reach and apprehend,</l>
            <l>Elſe a great Prince in priſon lies.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="280" facs="tcp:22691:144"/>
To'our bodies turne wee then, that ſo</l>
            <l>Weake men on love reveal'd may looke;</l>
            <l>Loves myſteries in ſoules doe grow,</l>
            <l>But yet the body is his booke.</l>
            <l>And if ſome lover, ſuch as wee,</l>
            <l>Have heard this dialogue of one,</l>
            <l>Let him ſtill marke us, he ſhall ſee</l>
            <l>Small change, when we'are to bodies gone.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
