<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wollstonecraft-vindication-excerpted">

   <!--TEI Header BEGINS-->
   <teiHeader xml:lang="en">

      <fileDesc>
         <!--BEGINS File Description -->
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</title>
            <author>
               <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78095613">
                  <name ref="wollstonecraft.xml">
                     <forename>Mary</forename>
                     <surname>Wollstonecraft</surname>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-7400-4093">
                  <name ref="editors.xml#TH">
                     <surname>Howe</surname>
                     <forename>Tonya</forename>
                  </name>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
               <name ref="editors.xml#MUstudstaff">Students and Staff of Marymount University</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#FB">Felix Baquedano</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#NB">Nomin Bayanmunkh</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#RB">Rewan Bezabih</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#RDJ">Rosaida De Jesus</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#JMF">Josephine Fleming</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#DF">Daryl Frierson</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#TG">Tierney Goetz</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#AH">Alexandra Holmes</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#MM">Muna Mohamed</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#SM">Sarah Moustafa</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#DN">Dana Najib</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#MR">Maria Robelo</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#KS">Katelyn Smolar</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#ES">Elizabeth Swanson</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#BT">Bianca Thompson</name>
               <name ref="editors.xml#SV">Susana Valladares</name>

            </respStmt>
            <sponsor/>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>


         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Marymount University Department of Literature and Languages</addrLine>
               <addrLine>2807 N. Glebe Road</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Arlington, VA </addrLine>
               <addrLine>22207</addrLine>
               <addrLine>thowe@marymount.edu</addrLine>
               <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                  Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                  License </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>


         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman, introduction and excerpt</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78095613">
                        <forename>Mary</forename>
                        <surname>Wollstonecraft</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>J. Johnson</publisher>
                     <date when="1792">1792</date>
                     <note>Page images are sourced from <ref
                           target="https://catalog.wrlc.org/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?BBID=4173677"> the
                           first edition in Marymount University’s Gomatos collection, which is
                           imperfect and lacking the titlepage</ref>.</note>
                     <note resp="editors.xml#BT">Page images taken by Bianca Thompson.</note>
                     <note>Title page acquired from <ref
                           target="https://digital.library.lse.ac.uk/objects/lse:dur688faq">London
                           School of Economics Digital Library</ref>.</note>
                     <note>The Marymount University edition may be a later printing; see the
                        correction of the printer’s error in the catchword on page 3 of the
                        introduction.</note>
                     <note>This excerpt includes the complete introduction and section ii from
                        chapter XII.</note>
                  </imprint>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Public domain electronic facsimile copy</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>London School of Economics Digital Library</publisher>
                     <date>nd</date>
                     <note>
                        <ref target="https://digital.library.lse.ac.uk/objects/lse:dur688faq"/>
                     </note>
                  </imprint>

                  <extent>22 cm.</extent>
                  <biblScope>1-11, 414, 425-432</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>



      <profileDesc>
         <!--BEGINS Profile Description  -->
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>

         <creation/>

         <textDesc n="treatise">
            <channel mode="w">print</channel>
            <constitution type="frags"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
         </textDesc>

         <settingDesc>
            <setting>
               <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London, England</name>
               <time from="1750" to="1800">Late 18th Century</time>
            </setting>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>



      <encodingDesc>
         <!-- BEGINS Encoding Description -->
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
               project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
               sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
               the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
               and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                  links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                  defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                  notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
               </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                  silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                  word.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                  not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                  indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                  possible. See the Sources section.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
               <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
               <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
               <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>


      <revisionDesc>
         <!--BEGINS Revision Description -->
         <change when="2018-03-01" who="editors.xml#MUstudstaff">Transcription</change>
         <change when="2018-05-01" who="editors.xml#MUstudstaff">TEI encoding and
            annotation</change>
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="editors.xml#TH">Update for schema</change>
      </revisionDesc>


   </teiHeader>
   <!--TEI Header Ends -->





   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[TP]" facs="pageImages/VIN-TP.jpg"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>
                  <lb/> A <lb/> VINDICATION <lb/> OF THE <lb/> RIGHTS OF WOMAN: <lb/> WITH <lb/>
                  STRICTURES <lb/> ON <lb/> POLITICAL AND MORAL SUBJECTS <lb/></titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor>BY <ref target="wollstonecraft_" corresp="wollstonecraft">MARY WOLLSTONECRAFT</ref></docAuthor>
            <docImprint><lb/><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace><lb/><publisher><ref target="johnson_" corresp="johnson">PRINTED FOR J. JOHNSON,
               No.71, ST. PAUL’S CHURCH YARD.</ref></publisher><lb/></docImprint>
            <docDate>1792. </docDate>
         </titlePage>

      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/VIN-1.jpg"/>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>AFTER considering the historic page, and viewing the living world with anxious
               solicitude, the most melancholy emotions of sorrowful indignation have depressed my
               spirits, and I have sighed when obligated to confess, that either nature has made a
               great difference between man and man, or that the civilization which has hitherto
               taken place in the world has been very partial. I have turned over various books
               written on the subject of education, and patiently observed the conduct of parents
               and the <ref target="education_" corresp="education">management of schools</ref>; but what has
               been the result? --a profound conviction that the neglected education of my
               fellow-creatures is the grand source of the misery I deplore; and that women, in
               particular, are rendered weak and wretched by a variety of concurring causes,
               originating from a hasty conclusion. The conduct and manners of women, in fact,
               evidently prove <pb n="2" facs="pageImages/VIN-2.jpg"/> that their minds are not in a
               healthy state; for, like the flowers which are planted in too rich a soil, strength
               and usefulness are sacrificed to beauty; and the flaunting leaves, after having
               pleased a fastidious eye, fade, disregarded on the stalk, long before the season when
               they ought to have arrived at maturity.--One cause of this barren blooming I
               attribute to a false system of education, gathered from the books written on this
               subject by men, who considering females rather than human creatures, have been more
               anxious to make them alluring mistresses than rational wives; and the understanding
               of sex has been so <ref target="bubbled_" corresp="bubbled">bubbled</ref> by this specious
               homage, that the civilized women of the present century, with a few exceptions, are
               only anxious to inspire love, when they ought to cherish a nobler ambition, and by
               their abilities and virtues exact respect.</p>
            <p>In a treatise, therefore, on female rights and manners, <ref target="conduct_"
                  corresp="conduct">the works which have been particularly written for their
                  improvement</ref> must not be overlooked; especially when it is asserted, in
               direct terms, that the minds of women are enfeebled by false refinement; <pb n="3"
                  facs="pageImages/VIN-3.jpg"/> that the books of instruction, written by men of
               genius, have had the same tendency as more frivolous productions; and that, in the
               true style of <ref target="mahometanism_" corresp="mahometanism">Mahometanism</ref>, they are only
               considered as females, and not as a part of the human species, when improvable reason
               is allowed to be the dignified distinction which raises men above the brute creation,
               and puts a natural sceptre in a feeble hand. </p>
            <p> Yet, because I am a woman, I would not lead my reader to suppose that I mean
               violently to agitate the contested question respecting the equality or inferiority of
               the sex; but as the subject lies in my way, and I cannot pass it over without
               subjecting the main tendency of my reasoning to misconstruction, I shall stop a
               moment to deliver, in a few words, my opinion. --In the government of the physical
               world it is observable that the female, in general, is inferior to the male. The male
               pursues, the female yields--this is the law of nature; and it does not appear to be
               suspended or abrogated in favour of woman. This physical superiority cannot be
               denied--and it is a noble prerogative! But not content with this natural preeminence, <pb
                  n="4 [break after pre-]" facs="pageImages/VIN-4.jpg"/>men endeavour to sink us still
               lower, merely to render us alluring objects for a moment; and women, intoxicated by
               the adoration which men, under the influence of their senses, pay them, do not seek
               to obtain a durable interest in their hearts, or to become the friends of the fellow
               creatures who find amusement in their society.</p>
            <p> I am aware of an obvious inference: from every quarter have I hear exclamations
               against masculine women; but where are they to be found? If by this appellation men
               mean to inveigh against their ardour in hunting, shooting, and gaming, I shall most
               cordially join in the cry; but if it be against the imitation of <ref target="manly_"
                  corresp="manly">manly virtues</ref> or, more properly speaking, the attainment of
               those talents and virtues, the exercise of which ennobles the human character, and
               which raise females in the scale of animal being, when they are comprehensively
               termed mankind; all those who view them with a philosophical eye must, I should
               think, wish with me, that they may every day grow more and more masculine. </p>
            <p>This discussion naturally divides the subject. I shall first consider women in the
                  <pb n="5" facs="pageImages/VIN-5.jpg"/> grand light of human creatures, who, in
               common with men, are placed on this earth to unfold their faculties; and afterwards I
               shall more particularly point out their peculiar designation. </p>
            <p> I wish also to steer clear of an error which many respectable writers have fallen
               into; for the instruction which has hither been addressed to women, has rather been
               applicable to ladies, if the little indirect advice, that is scattered through <ref
                  target="sandford_merton_" corresp="sandford_merton">Sandford and Merton</ref>, be excepted; but,
               addressing my sex in a firmer tone, I pay particular attention to those in the middle
               class, because they appear to be in the most natural state. Perhaps the seeds of
               false-refinement, immorality, and vanity, have ever been shed by the great. Weak,
               artificial beings, raised above the common wants and affections of their race, in a
               premature unnatural manner, undermine the very foundation of virtue, and spread
               corruption through the whole mass of society! As a class of mankind they have the
               strongest claim to pity; the education of the rich tends to render them vain and
               helpless, and the unfolding mind is not strengthened by the practice of those duties which dignify the human <pb n="6 [break after 'hu-']"
                  facs="pageImages/VIN-6.jpg"/> 
               character.—They only live to amuse themselves, and by the same law which in nature
               invariably produces certain effects, they soon only afford barren amusement. </p>
            <p>But as I purpose taking a separate view of the <ref target="ranks_" corresp="ranks">
                  different ranks of society</ref>, and of the moral character of women, in each,
               this hint is, for the present, sufficient; and I have only alluded to the subject,
               because it appears to me to be the very essence of an introduction to give a cursory
               account of the contents of the work it introduces. </p>
            <p>My own sex, I hope, will excuse me, if I treat them like rational creatures, instead
               of flattering their <hi rend="italic">fascinating</hi> graces, and viewing them as if
               they were in a state of perpetual childhood, unable to stand alone. I earnestly wish
               to point out in what true dignity and human happiness consists—I wish to persuade
               women to endeavour to acquire strength, both of mind and body, and to convince them
               that the soft phrases, susceptibility of heart, delicacy of sentiment, and refinement
               of taste, are almost synonymous with epithets of weakness, and that those beings who
               are only the objects of pity and that kind of love, which  has been termed its sister, will soon become objects
               of contempt. </p><pb n="7"
                  facs="pageImages/VIN-7.jpg"/>
            <p> Dismissing then those pretty feminine phrases, which the men condescendingly use to
               soften our slavish dependence, and despising that weak <ref target="elegance_"
                  corresp="elegance">elegancy of mind</ref>, exquisite sensibility, and sweet docility
               of manners, supposed to be the sexual characteristics of the weaker vessel, I wish to
               shew that elegance is inferior to <ref target="virtue_" corresp="virtue">virtue</ref>,
               that the first object of laudable ambition is to obtain a character as a human being,
               regardless of the distinction of sex; and that secondary views should be brought to
               this simple touchstone. </p>
            <p> This is a rough sketch of my plan; and should I express my conviction with the
               energetic emotions that I feel whenever I think of the subject, the dictates of
               experience and reflection will be felt by some of my readers. Animated by this
               important object, I shall disdain to cull my phrases or polish my style;--I aim at
               being useful, and sincerity will render me unaffected; for, wishing rather to
               persuade by the force of my arguments, than dazzle by the elegance of my language, I
               shall not waste my time in rounding periods, or in fabricating the turgid bombast of
               artificial feelings, which, coming from the
               head, never reach the heart. – I shall be employed about <pb n="8" facs="pageImages/VIN-8.jpg"/> things, not words! – and,
               anxious to render my sex more respectable members of society, I shall try to avoid
               that flowery diction which has slided from essays into novels, and from novels into
               familiar letters and conversation. </p>
            <p>These pretty nothings – these caricatures of the real beauty of sensibility, dropping
               glibly from the tongue, vitiate the taste, and create a kind of sickly delicacy that
               turns away from simple unadorned truth; and a deluge of false sentiments and
               overstretched feelings, stifling the natural emotions of the heart, render the
               domestic pleasures insipid,--that ought to sweeten the exercise of those severe
               duties, which educate a rational and immortal being for a nobler field of action. </p>
            <p>The <ref target="schools_" corresp="schools">education of women</ref> has, of late, been
               more attended to than formerly; yet they are still reckoned a frivolous sex, and
               ridiculed or pitied by the writers who endeavor by satire or instruction to improve
               them. It is acknowledged that they spend many of the first years of their lives in
               acquiring a smattering of accomplishments:
               meanwhile strength of body and mind are sacrificed to libertine notions of beauty, to
               the desire of establishing <pb n="9 [break after 'establish-']" facs="pageImages/VIN-9.jpg"/>themselves, --the only way women can rise in the
               world,--by marriage. And this desire making mere animals of them, when they marry
               they act as such children may be expected to act: --they dress; they paint, and
               nickname God’s creatures. --Surely there weak beings are only fit for a <ref
                  target="seraglio_" corresp="seraglio">seraglio</ref>! --Can they govern a family, or take
               care of the poor bebes whom they bring into the world? </p>
            <p>If then it can be fairly deduced from the present conduct of the sex, from the
               prevalent fondness for pleasure which takes place of ambition and those nobler
               passions that open and enlarge the soul; that the instruction which women have
               received has only tended, with the constitution of civil society, to render them
               insignificant object of desire--more propagators of fools! --if it can be proved that
               in aiming to accomplish them, without cultivating their understandings, they are
               taken out of their sphere of duties, and make ridiculous and useless when the
               short-lived bloom of beauty is over<ref
                  target="auth1_" corresp="auth1">*</ref>, I presume <pb n="10" facs="pageImages/VIN-10.jpg"/>  that <hi rend="italic">rational</hi> men will excuse me for
               endeavoring to persuade them to become more masculine and respectable. </p>
            <p> Indeed the word masculine is only a bugbear: there is little reason to fear that
               women will acquire too much courage or fortitude; for their apparent inferiority with
               respect to bodily strength, must render them, in some degree, dependent on men in the
               in the various relations of life; but why should it be increased by prejudices that
               give a sex to virtue, and confound simple truths with sensual reveries? </p>
            <p> Women are, in fact, so much degraded by mistaken notions of female excellence, that
               I do not mean to add a paradox when I assert, that this artificial weakness produces
               a propensity to tyrannize, and gives birth to cunning, the natural opponent of
               strength, which leads them to play off those contemptible infantine airs that
               undermine esteem even whilst they excite desire. Do not foster these prejudices, and
               they will naturally fall into their subordinate, yet respectable station in life. It
               seems scarcely necessary to say, that I now speak of the sex in general. Many individuals <pb
                  n="11 [break after 'in-']" facs="pageImages/VIN-11.jpg"/>have more sense than their male
               relatives; and, as nothing preponderates where there is a constant struggle for an
               equilibrium, without it has naturally more gravity, some women govern their husbands
               without degrading themselves, because intellect will always govern.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="414" facs="pageImages/VIN-414.jpg"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII</head>
            <p>SOME INSTANCES OF THE FOLLY WHICH THE IGNORANCE OF WOMEN GENERATES; WITH CONCLUDING
               REFLECTIONS ON THE MORAL IMPROVEMENT THAT A REVOLUTION IN FEMALE MANNERS MIGHT
               NATURALLY BE EXPECTED TO PRODUCE.</p>
            <pb n="425" facs="pageImages/VIN-425.jpg"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>SECT. II</head>
               <p>Another instance of that feminine weakness of character, often produced by a
                  confined education, is a romantic twist of the mind, which has been very properly
                  termed <ref target="sentimental_" corresp="sentimental">
                     <hi rend="italic">sentimental</hi></ref>.</p>
               <p>Women subjected by ignorance to their sensations, and only taught to look for
                  happiness in love, refine on sensual feelings, and adopt metaphysical notions
                  respecting that passion, which lead them shamefully to neglect the duties of life,
                  and frequently in the midst of these sublime refinements they plump into actual
                  vice. </p>
               <p>Theses are women who are amused by the reveries of the <ref target="novelists_"
                     corresp="novelists">stupid novelists</ref>, who, knowing little of human nature,
                  work up stale tales, and describe meretricious scenes, all retailed in sentimental
                  jargon, which equally tend to corrupt the taste and draw the heart aside <pb
                     n="426" facs="pageImages/VIN-426.jpg"/> from its daily duties. I do not mention
                  the understanding, because never having been exercised, its slumbering energies
                  rest inactive, like the lurking particles of fire which are supposed universally
                  to pervade matter. </p>
               <p>Females, in fact, denied all political privileges, and not allowed, as married
                  women, excepting in criminal cases, a civil existence, have their attention
                  naturally drawn from the interest of the whole community to that of the minute
                  parts, though the private duty of any member of society must be very imperfectly
                  performed when not connected with the general good. The mighty business of female
                  life is to please, and restrained from entering into more important concerns by
                  political and civil oppression, sentiments become events, and reflection deepens
                  what it should, and would have effaced, if the understanding had been allowed to
                  take a wider range. </p>
               <p>But, confined to <ref target="trifling_employments_" corresp="trifling_employments">trifling employments</ref>,
                  they naturally imbibe opinions which the only kind of reading calculated to
                  interest an innocent frivolous mind, inspires. Unable to grasp anything great, is
                  it surprising that they find the reading of history a very dry talk, and <pb
                     n="427" facs="pageImages/VIN-427.jpg"/> disquisitions addressed to the
                  understanding intolerably tedious, and almost unintelligible? Thus are they
                  necessarily dependent on the novelist for amusement. Yet, when I exclaim against
                  novels, I mean when contrasted with those works which exercise the understanding
                  and regulate the imagination.--For any kind of reading I think better than leaving
                  a blank still a blank, because the mind must receive a degree of enlargement and
                  obtain a little strength by a slight exertion of its thinking powers; besides,
                  even the productions that are only addressed to the imagination, raise the reader
                  a little above the gross gratification of appetites, to which the mind has not
                  given shade of delicacy. </p>
               <p>This observation is the result of experience; for I have known several notable
                  women, and one in particular, who was a very good woman--as good as such a narrow
                  mind would allow her to be, who took care that her daughters (three in number),
                  should never see a novel. As she was a woman of fortune and fashion, they had
                  various masters to attend them, and a sort of menial <ref target="governess_"
                     corresp="governess">governess</ref> to watch their footsteps. From their masters
                  they learned how tables, chairs, &amp;c. were <pb n="428"
                     facs="pageImages/VIN-428.jpg"/> called in French and Italian; but as the few
                  books thrown in their way were far above their capacities, or devotional, they
                  neither acquired ideas nor sentiments, and passed their time when not compelled to
                  repeat words, in dressing, quarrelling with each other, or conversing with their
                  maids by stealth, till they were brought into company as marriageable. </p>
               <p>Their mother, a widow, was busy in the meantime keeping up her connections, as she
                  termed a numerous acquaintance, lest her girls should want a proper introduction
                  into the great world. And these young ladies with minds vulgar in every sense of
                  the word, and spoiled tempers, entered life puffed up with notions of their own
                  consequence, and looking down with contempt on those who could not vie with them
                  in <ref target="dress_" corresp="dress">dress and parade.</ref>
               </p>
               <p>With respect to love, nature, or their nurses had taken care to teach them the
                  physical meaning of the word; and, as they had few topics of conversation, and
                  fewer refinements on sentiment, they expressed their gross wishes not in very
                  delicate phrases, when they spoke freely, talking of matrimony.</p>
               <pb n="429" facs="pageImages/VIN-429.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <ref target="novels_" corresp="novels">Could these girls have been injured by the
                     perusal of novels?</ref> I almost forgot a shade in the character of one of
                  them; she affected a simplicity bordering on folly, and with a simper would utter
                  the most immodest remarks and questions, the full meaning of which she had learned
                  whilst secluded from the world, and afraid to speak in her mother’s presence, who
                  governed with a high hand: they were all educated, as the prided herself, in most
                  exemplary manner; and read their chapters and psalms before breakfast, never
                  touching a silly novel. </p>
               <p>This is only one influence; but I recollect many other women who, not led by
                  degrees to proper studies, and not permitted to choose for themselves, have indeed
                  been overgrown children; or have obtained, by mixing in the world, a little of
                  what is termed common sense; that is a distinct manner of feeling common
                  occurrences, as they stand detached: but what deserves the name of intellect, the
                  power of gaining general or abstract ideas, or even intermediate ones, was out of
                  the question. Their minds were quiescent, and when they were not roused by
                  sensible objects <pb n="430 [break after 'ob-']" facs="pageImages/VIN-430.jpg"/>and employments of
                  that kind, they were low-spirited, would cry, or go to sleep.</p>
               <p>When, therefore, I advise my sex not to reach such flimsy works, it is to induce
                  them to read something superior; for I coincide in opinion with sagacious man,
                  who, having a daughter and niece under his care, pursued a very different plan
                  with each.</p>
               <p>The niece, who had considerable abilities, had, before she was left to his
                  guardianship, been indulged in desultory reading. There she endeavoured to lead,
                  and did lead to history and moral essays; but his daughter, whom a fond, weak
                  mother had indulged, and who consequently was averse to everything like
                  application, he allowed to read novels: and used to justify his conduct by saying,
                  that if she ever attained a relish for reading them, he should have some
                  foundation to work upon; and that erroneous opinions were better than none at all. </p>
               <p> In fact the female mind has been so totally neglected, that knowledge was only to
                  be acquired from this muddy source, till from reading novels some women of
                  superior talents learned to despite them. </p>
               <pb n="431" facs="pageImages/VIN-431.jpg"/>
               <p> The best method, I believe, that can be adopted to correct a fondness for novels
                  is to ridicule them: not indiscriminately, for then it would have little effect;
                  but, if a judicious person, with some turn for humour, would read several to a
                  young girl, and point out both tones, and apt comparisons with pathetic incidents
                  and heroic characters in history, how foolishly and ridiculously they captured
                  human nature, just opinions might be substituted instead of romantic sentiments. </p>
               <p> In one respect, however, the majority of both sexes resemble, and equally shew a
                  want of taste and modesty. Ignorant women, forced to be chaste to preserve their
                  reputation, allow their imagination to revel in the unnatural and meretricious
                  scenes sketched by the novel writers of the day, slighting as insipid <ref
                     target="history_" corresp="history">the sober dignity and matronly graces of
                     history</ref>
                  <ref target="auth2_" corresp="auth2">*</ref>, whilst men carry the same vitiated taste
                  into life, and fly for amusement to the wanton, from the unsophisticated charms
                     <pb n="432" facs="pageImages/VIN-432.jpg"/> of virtue, and the grave
                  respectability of sense. </p>
               <p> Besides, the reading of novels makes women, and particularly ladies of fashion,
                  very fond of using strong expressions and superlatives in conversation; and,
                  though the dissipated artificial life which they lead prevents their cherishing
                  and strong legitimate passion, the language of passion in affected tones slips for
                  ever from their glib tongues, and every trifle produces those <ref target="phosphorus_"
                     corresp="phosphorus">phosphoric bursts which only mimick in the dark the flame of
                     passion</ref>. </p>
            </div>
            
         </div>

        <div type="notes"> <note type="editorial" xml:id="wollstonecraft" target="wollstonecraft_" resp="editors.xml#MUstudstaff">
            <graphic
               url="notes/mw02603.jpg"
            />Born in London on April 27, 1759, Mary Wollstonecraft is considered
            one of the principal figures in modern feminism. Her works reflected her unmarried
            middle class experience, emphasizing gender injustice, the failure of the education
            system for young women, and the position of women in unhappy marriages. Her best known
            work, <hi rend="italic">Vindication of the Rights of Women</hi> (1792), argues that to
            attain virtue, women need access to systemic education. See this <ref
               target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/empire_seapower/wollstonecraft_01.shtml"
               >biographical essay on Wollstonecraft by Janet Todd</ref>. The portrait of
            Wollstonecraft included here, painted by John Opie (1797), is housed in the <ref
               target="https://www.npg.org.uk/">National Portrait Gallery, London</ref>. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="mahometanism" target="mahometanism_" resp="editors.xml#BT">
            <graphic url="notes/Ladies_cabul1848b.jpg" alt="1848 lithograph by James Rattray showing an
               Afgan women under purdah" desc="1848 lithograph by James Rattray showing an
               Afgan women under purdah" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ladies_cabul1848b.jpg"
            />A term used by Westerners to refer to Muslims, in this context
            Mahometanism is associated with the limited opportunities and oppressed status of women
            in the eighteenth century. As discussed in <ref
               target="https://books.google.com/books?id=jumHDAAAQBAJ"><hi rend="italic">The
                  Feminization Debate in Eighteenth-Century England</hi> (2004) by E. Clery</ref>,
            women were trained to obey their father and husband. This confinement and
            domesticization was frequently described as "Mahometan" due to the misguided belief
            among the English that Islam sees women as not possessing souls. Social reformer and
            leader of the Blue Stockings Society, Elizabeth Montagu lamented in a letter about the
            effects of such "Mahometan" belief, which is used to justify women's domestic
            confinement (Clery 136). The image included here, an 1848 lithograph by James Rattray, shows
            Afgan women under purdah. <ref
               target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ladies_cabul1848b.jpg">Image via
               Wikimedia Commons</ref>.</note>
         <note type="authorial" xml:id="auth1" target="auth1_" resp="editors.xml#TH"><graphic
            url="notes/ba-obj-42138-0001-pub-large.jpg"
         />* A lively writer, I cannot
            recollect his name, asks what business women turned of forty have to do in the world?
            [Wollstonecraft's note.] The "lively writer" may be a mistaken reference to Lord Merton,
               a character in Frances Burney's epistolary novel <hi rend="italic">Evelina</hi> (1778),
               who says of the masculine Mrs. Selwyn, "I don't know what the devil a woman lives for
               after thirty: she is only in other folks way" (III.1, 7). Readers may also find <ref
                     target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015011429282;view=1up;seq=153"
                     >this satirical essay from <hi rend="italic">The London Magazine</hi> of 1777 of
                     interest, in which a gentleman proposes a tax on unmarried women over the age of
                     35</ref>. The image below, from the <ref
                        target="http://collections.britishart.yale.edu/vufind/Record/3626225">Yale Center for
                        British Art</ref>, shows "An Old Maid Treating a Favorite Cat to a Duck and Green
               Peas," a colored etching by Richard Newton (c.1792).] 
         </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="education" target="education_" resp="editors.xml#NB">
            <graphic
               url="notes/wp01dee569_0a.jpg"
            /> Mary Wollstonecraft noted the absence of proficient education for
            young women in the eighteenth century and decided to establish a school. Wollstonecraft,
            along with her sister Eliza, and friend Fanny Blood, opened the school in 1784. The
            school was established in Newington Green just outside of London. Although the school
            closed from financial distress in 1785, Wollstonecraft drew from her experience as a
            teacher and wrote <hi rend="italic">Thoughts on the Education of Daughters with
               Reflections on Female Conduct in the more important Duties of Life</hi> (1787). The
            above picture shows <ref target="http://www.plaquesoflondon.co.uk/page3312.htm">a plaque dedicated to Mary Wollstonecraft at the Newington Green
               Primary School</ref> near where the school was located in the 18th century. For more
            information on the life of Mary Wollstonecraft, read <ref
               target="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/wollstonecraft/">this biographical essay
               written by Sylvana Tomaselli</ref>. To look through a copy of Wollstonecraft's <hi
                  rend="italic">Thoughts on the Education of Daughters with Reflections on Female
                  Conduct in the more important Duties of Life</hi> click <ref
                     target="https://digital.library.lse.ac.uk/objects/lse:ruf494jak">here</ref> for an
            online version of the book from the London School of Economics’ digital library. </note>
         <note type="authorial" xml:id="auth2" target="auth2_">* I am not now alluding to that superiority
            of mind which leads to the creation of ideal beauty, when life, surveyed with a
            penetrating eye, appears a tragi-comedy, in which little can be seen to satisfy the
            heart without the help of fancy. [Wollstonecraft’s note.] </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="trifling_employments" target="trifling_employments_" resp="editors.xml#MM">
            <graphic
               url="notes/Reynolds_2000.jpg"
            />By "trifling employments," Wollstonecraft refers to the kinds of
            things elegant women did to employ their time such as needlepoint. Not allowed to
            participate in the masculine public sphere, women instead spent their time in domestic
            labor and activities. Many were mothers and homemakers. These activities were not
            masculine and serious but feminine and trifling. Read more on women’s work in the
            eighteenth century in <ref
               target="http://www.jasna.org/persuasions/on-line/vol25no1/jones.html">this article by
               Susan E. Jones</ref>, also the source of this annotation. The portrait above, <ref
                  target="https://www.frick.org/exhibitions/scottish/reynolds">via the Frick
                  Collection</ref>, is a conversation piece by Joshua Reynolds (1723–1792) showing the
            genteel young ladies Waldegrave engaged in such domestic work. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="history" target="history_"  resp="editors.xml#DN"> This is likely a reference to
            discussions about the hierarchy of genres during the eighteenth century. Dorothee Birke,
            author of <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=fujCDAAAQBAJ"><hi rend="italic"
               >Writing the Reader: Configurations of Cultural Practice in English Novel</hi>
               (2016)</ref>, explains that historical and philosophical works were seen to have
            higher value than novels and poetry. The reason behind such a hierarchical placement is
            the perception of fictional reading to be connected with ignorance as people are fed
            unrealistic words. Thus, historical and philosophical works which were often based on
            truth and it reality, were insightful readings that were ranked higher than unrealistic
            or exaggerated works (<ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=fujCDAAAQBAJ">Birke 63</ref>).</note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="sandford_merton" target="sandford_merton_" resp="editors.xml#SV"> Likely a reference to a popular
            children’s book written in the eighteenth century, <hi rend="italic">Sandford and
               Merton</hi> (1783), by Thomas Day, is about two boys who grow up differently based on
            social status. <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=eyb7nFtiPQYC">According to
               Stephen Bending and Stephen Bygrave</ref>, the book is an indictment of upper class
            "effete" masculinity (23). Tommy Merton is spoiled by middle class privileges and needs
            to be re-educated to become as fine a man as Sandford, whose lower-class status
            challenged him to develop, physically and mentally, into an admirable young man (3-4).
            Interested viewers can also <ref
               target="https://archive.org/details/historyofsandfor00daytiala">read an abridged
               version of Day’s children’s book, published in 1792, at the Internet Archive</ref>. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="novelists" target="novelists_" resp="editors.xml#KS">Wollstonecraft's question refers to an
            ongoing discussion about the work of novel-reading on young girls' intellectual growth.
            It was thought dangerous for women to read novels because society feared that they would
            not, as Anna North writes in <ref
               target="https://op-talk.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/09/14/when-novels-were-bad-for-you/"
               >"When Novels Were Bad for You,"</ref> be able to "differentiate between fiction and
            life."</note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="bubbled" target="bubbled_" resp="editors.xml#JMF">
            <graphic
               url="notes/AN00142098_001_l.jpg"
            /> According to the Oxford English Dictionary, in the eighteenth-century
            the word "bubbled" meant befooled, cheated, or deceived. Here, Wollstonecraft is saying
            women’s understandings have been fooled by the popularization and distribution of
            conduct books and their false depiction of women. "Bubbled" in this usage is also
            derived from the devastating financial bubble in the eighteenth century, including the
            South Sea Bubble of 1720. Many engravings and satirical prints of the time depict how
            the people were deceived and cheated financially, most notably, <hi rend="italic">The
               Bubbler’s Medley, or a Sketch of the Times being Europe’s Memoriam for 1720</hi>.
            The image included here is <ref target="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/search.aspx">from the British Museum's online collection</ref>. To read more, visit <ref
               target="https://www.library.hbs.edu/hc/ssb/history.html">Harvard Business School’s
               online exhibit on the South Sea Bubble</ref>, and the source of this annotation. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="conduct" target="conduct_" resp="editors.xml#BT">
            <graphic url="notes/gregory.jpg" alt="Photograph of the title page of Gregory's conduct book A Father's Legacy to His Daughters (1795)" desc="The Title page of Gregory's conduct book" source="http://www.lib.udel.edu/ud/spec/exhibits/women/courtesy.htm"/> 
             This is most likely a reference to Dr. John Gregory’s <hi
               rend="italic">A Father’s Legacy to His Daughters</hi>, a conduct book written prior
            to Dr. Gregory’s wife’s passing in 1761 and addressed to his daughters about etiquette,
            religion, conduct, and behaviors. Wollstonecraft references this book directly in many
            of her arguments. The image of the book's title page (1795) is from the <ref target="http://www.lib.udel.edu/ud/spec/exhibits/women/courtesy.htm">University of Delaware Special Collections Department</ref> is from the National Library of Scotland. <ref
               target="https://www.si.edu/object/nmah_307978">View a 1793 edition of <hi
                  rend="italic">A Father’s Legacy to His Daughters</hi> at the Internet
               Archive</ref>.</note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="johnson" target="johnson_" resp="editors.xml#TH">
            
            <graphic
               url="notes/bookshops-around-stPauls.jpeg"
            />
            Throughout the eighteenth century, St. Paul’s Church Yard was the center of the
            publishing trade. Wollstonecraft's <hi rend="italic">Vindications</hi> was published by
            Joseph Johnson, a liberal publisher with radical views, who published work by William
            Godwin, Joseph Priestly, and William Blake. Wollstonecraft lived near St. Paul’s Church
            Yard and spent many hours in this workshop as Joseph Johnson gave her writing and
            translating jobs throughout the day. For more on the relationship between Mary
            Wollstonecraft and Joseph Johnson, see this <ref
               target="http://theamericanreader.com/24-december-1787-mary-wollstonecraft-to-joseph-johnson/"
               >letter from Wollstonecraft to her publisher reprinted in <hi rend="italic">The
                  American Reader</hi></ref>. The image here, from a <ref target="http://louisville.edu/artsandsciences/news/all/shakespeare-folio">University of Louisville news
                     article on William Shakespeare's first folio</ref>, shows the locations of printers around St.
            Paul's during the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="elegance" target="elegance_"  resp="editors.xml#SM">
            <graphic
               url="notes/156253-primary-0-nativeres.jpg"
            /> Elegance in the 18th century has a specific meaning when applied to
            women. According to <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=BVKH3UIypN8C">Robert
               W. Jones, author of <hi rend="italic">Gender and the Formation of Taste in
                  Eighteenth-Century Britain</hi></ref>, feminine elegance is the combination of
            docility and enticement of men. In the eighteenth century, elegance is feminized with
            the goal that women should use it to please and seduce men through beauty and
            refinement. Elegance of the eighteenth century is the area of the pleasing and amiable
            actions from women to men, these beauty standards were important and a source of
            intrigue for the culture (Jones 109). The image here, <ref target="https://www.nga.gov/collection/art-object-page.156253.html">drawn from the National Gallery of
               Art in Washington, DC,</ref> shows <hi rend="italic">An Elegant Lady Playing a Cittern</hi> (1770), by Nathaniel
            Dance-Holland. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="virtue" target="virtue_" resp="editors.xml#RB"> Mary Wollstonecraft uses "virtue" with
            its eighteenth-century sense of power. Men were often seen as virtuous because of their
            physical strength, whereas women acquired virtue through sensibility and virginity.
            Wollstonecraft argues that true virtue can only exist with knowledge and education.
            Therefore, women must be properly educated or they would only be mimicking true virtue.
            <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=eEbY1xeU4S4C">Views of Women in
               Eighteenth Century Literature," published in the <hi rend="italic">International
                  Journal of Communication Research</hi></ref> by Adrian Brunello and Florina-Elena
            Borsan reviews the way that understandings of womanhood shifted in the period, resulting
            in the need for an exterior display of virtue, rather than true virtue (325-326). <ref
               target="https://www.nationalgallery.org.uk/paintings/godfried-schalcken-allegory-of-virtue-and-riches"
               >clicking here will direct you to the UK National Gallery of Art, showing <hi
                  rend="italic">An Allegory of Virtue and Riches</hi>, painted in 1667 by Godfried
               Schalcken. </ref>
         </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="schools" target="schools_" resp="editors.xml#FB">
            <graphic
               url="notes/N00427_10.jpg"/> The
            most common schools available for lower working class families in eighteenth-century
            were dame schools. An elderly, barely literate, woman would teach reading and sewing for
            a small fee. Read more in <ref
               target="https://content.historicengland.org.uk/images-books/publications/englands-schools/englands-schools.pdf/"
               >English Heritage’s brochure on <hi rend="italic">England’s School</hi></ref>. The
            image of children learning in a dame school, painted by Thomas Webster (1845), is housed
            in the <ref target="https://www.tate.org.uk">Tate Art Museum, London.</ref>
         </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="sentimental" target="sentimental_" resp="editors.xml#ES"> The sentimental novel is a genre which
            rose into popularity in the eighteenth century. This genre is characterized by
            excessively passionate characters, tearful scenes and dramatic, flowery dialogue. Mary
            Wollstonecraft may be using the popularity of these novels among young women to explain
            their apparent lack of rationality rather than claiming irrationality to be a naturally
            female trait. Read more about the sentimental novel in <ref
               target="https://www.britannica.com/art/sentimental-novel">
               <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>.</ref>
         </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="novels" target="novels_" resp="editors.xml#ES">As novels became more accessible they
            became more popular. Some believed that excessive exposure to fiction novels would cause
            readers to lose touch with reality and identify with characters to the point of
            mimicking dangerous or immoral behavior. Read more about a popular novel that was blamed
            for youthful suicides in this article by Frank Furedi from <ref
               target="http://www.historytoday.com/frank-furedi/media%E2%80%99s-first-moral-panic">
               <hi rend="italic">History Today</hi></ref>. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="ranks" target="ranks_" resp="editors.xml#MR"> The different ranks of society in
            England during the eighteenth century were not simply divided between the rich or poor.
            According to the eighteenth-century writer Daniel Defoe, there were seven categories:
            the great, the rich, the middle sort, the working trades, the country people, the poor,
            and the miserable. The country still relied on agriculture and, although some still died
            of hunger, there was usually enough food to go around. Trade was increasing and more men
            and women acquired jobs in industry. However, wealth was unequally distributed, with
            only 5% of the national income belonging to the general population. Read more in this
            <ref
               target="https://www.britannica.com/place/United-Kingdom/18th-century-Britain-1714-1815"
               ><hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi> entry for eighteenth-century
               Britain</ref>, and the source of this annotation. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="seraglio" target="seraglio_"  resp="editors.xml#RDJ">
            <graphic
               url="notes/John_frederick_lewis-reception1873.jpg"
            /> Wollstonecraft’s argument in <hi rend="italic"> A Vindication of the
               Rights of Woman </hi> is that women spend most of their lives acquiring knowledge to
            be perfect wives instead of strengthening their minds and bodies to place a man. Because
            the only way women can rise the world is through marriage, they are being groomed to
            become lovers much like women in a Turkish seraglio, as Susan Gubar notes in "Feminist
            Misogyny" (<ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=nxUtN1J-Z1UC">Gubar
               151</ref>). Wollstonecraft is pointing out the lack of freedom for women. The image
            included here illustrates the women’s quarter of a seraglio painted in 1873 by John
            Frederick Lewis. <ref
               target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:John_frederick_lewis-reception1873.jpg"
               >This image is from Wikimedia Commons.</ref>
         </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="dress" target="dress_" resp="editors.xml#DF">
            <graphic
               url="notes/Madame_de_Pompadour.jpg"
            />In the eighteenth century, women were encouraged to focus on their
            dress, meaning their overall attire, because <ref
               target="https://archive.org/stream/b28747021">as Dr. Gregory argues in <hi
                  rend="italic">A Father’s Legacy to His Daughters</hi>, it was supposedly natural
               to them (55)</ref>. Women were dressed in hope of catching the attention of a man;
            they would parade, or flaunt themselves to men, hoping to find a husband, which is the
            only way for a woman to "rise in the world," as Wollstonecraft notes above (9).
            Wollstonecraft didn’t want women to dress and flaunt themselves only for men’s
            attention; she wanted women to focus on their own education. This portrait of Madame
            Pompadour, located in the Alte Pinkothek Museum in Munich and via <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Madame_de_Pompadour.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</ref>, provides an example of
            women’s attire in the 1700s in which Wollstonecraft was advising them not to do. Learn
            more about eighteenth-century fashion at <ref
               target="http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/i/introduction-to-18th-century-fashion/"
               >the Victoria and Albert Museum</ref>.</note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="governess" target="governess_"  resp="editors.xml#AH"> According to <ref
            target="https://www.bl.uk/romantics-and-victorians/articles/the-figure-of-the-governess"
            >Katheryn Hughes</ref>, the governess was one of the most familiar figures in the
            Romantic period and throughout the Victorian period. Governesses were women who earned
            their living by teaching and caring for other women’s children. Most governesses lived
            with their employers and were paid a small salary on top of their board and lodging. The
            governess was seen as an outsider, not quite fitting in with the family she governed for
            but not exactly fitting in as a servant either.</note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="manly" target="manly_"  resp="editors.xml#RB">
            <graphic
               url="notes/Thomas_Gainsborough_-_Mr_and_Mrs_Andrews.jpg"/>"Manly virtues" in the eighteenth century refers to social
            behavior that encourages men to be kind, loving, and courageous both in the home and in
            the public domain. Since masculinity is, as <hi rend="italic">Intertextual War: Edmund
               Burke and the French Revolution in the Writings of Mary Wollstonecraft, Thomas Paine,
               and James Mackintosh</hi> by Steven Blakemore, states, a "restrictive misnomer for
            qualities or virtues that are human," Mary Wollstonecraft opposes men that inveigh
            against masculine women because of its imitation of manly virtues (<ref
               target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/8ecf/602a48f6e143a90d72e5cca251751bc26bae.pdf"
               >Blakemore 42</ref>). The portrait here, <hi rend="italic"> Mr. and Mrs. Andrews</hi>
            by Thomas Gainsborough (1748), is housed in the National Gallery London. This painting,
            via Wikimedia Commons, illustrates manliness in terms of gentility. </note>
         <note type="editorial" xml:id="phosphorus" target="phosphorus_"  resp="editors.xml#TG">
            <graphic
               url="notes/Joseph_Wright_of_Derby_The_Alchemist.jpg"
            />Used by alchemists throughout the seventeenth century, phosphorous was
            officially designated the thirteenth element by Antoine Lavosier in 1777. Quack
            physicians incorporated the eerily-glowing phosphorous into their "cure all" medicines.
            Here, Wollstonecraft may be referring to a long-standing association between the element
            and its use in false medicines as well as its generation of artificial light. The image
            included here, <hi rend="italic">The Alchymist, In Search of the Philosopher’s Stone,
               Discovers Phosphorus</hi> (1770) is by Joseph Wright of Derby, <ref
                  target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Alchemist_Discovering_Phosphorus#/media/File:Joseph_Wright_of_Derby_The_Alchemist.jpg"
                  >via Wikimedia Commons</ref>. Read more about the discovery of phosphorus on <ref
                     target="https://resobscura.blogspot.com/2017/06/urine-phosphorus-and-philosophers-stone.html"
                     >the personal blog <hi rend="italic">Res Obscura</hi></ref>.</note>
         
         

</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>