<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="chopin-hour">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Hills Like White Elephants"</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78078534">
                        <name ref="hemingway.xml">
                            <forename>Ernest</forename>
                            <surname>Hemingway</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>
                        <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">
                            <surname>Buford</surname>
                            <forename>Nial</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#UVAstudentsstaff">Students and Staff of The University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">Nial Buford</name>
                    
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22204-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by Literature
                        in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"Hills Like White Elephants"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName/>
                        </author>
                        <title>Transition</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7008038">Paris</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Eugene Jolas</publisher>
                            <date when="1927">1927</date>
                            <note>Text for this digital edition drawn from <ref
                                target="https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/69683">Project Gutenberg's ditigital version of 
                                <hi rend="italic">Men Without Women</hi></ref> Page images are drawn from 
                                Hathitrust's digitized copy of 
                                <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/010317195"><hi rend="italic">transition
                                </hi></ref>, sourced from the University of California and digitized by Google.</note>       
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="tale">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="1000095"> Spain</name>
                    <time from="1900" to="1950">Early Twentieth Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
                    relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th,
                    19th, and 20th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
                    developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation is retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023" who="editors.xml#HAS">Initial XML file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart>
                   HILLS LIKE WHITE ELEPHANTS</titlePart>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <docAuthor>By Ernest Hemingway</docAuthor>
                <docImprint/>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <div>
              <p>The hills across the valley of the Ebro were
long and white. On this side there was no
shade and no trees and the station was between
two lines of rails in the sun. Close against the
side of the station there was the warm shadow
of the building and a curtain, made of strings of
bamboo beads, hung across the open door into
the bar, to keep out flies. The American and
the girl with him sat at a table in the shade,
outside the building. It was very hot and the
express from Barcelona would come in forty
minutes. It stopped at this junction for two
minutes and went on to Madrid.</p>

<p>“What should we drink?” the girl asked.
She had taken off her hat and put it on the
table.</p>

<p>“It’s pretty hot,” the man said.</p>

<p>“Let’s drink beer.”</p>

<p>“Dos cervezas,” the man said into the curtain.</p>

<p>“Big ones?” a woman asked from the doorway.</p>

<p>“Yes. Two big ones.”</p>

<p>The woman brought two glasses of beer and
two felt pads. She put the felt pads and the
beer glasses on the table and looked at the man
and the girl. The girl was looking off at the
line of hills. They were white in the sun and
the country was brown and dry.</p>

<pb n="10"/>

<p>“They look like white elephants,” she said.</p>

<p>“I’ve never seen one,” the man drank his
beer.</p>

<p>“No, you wouldn’t have.”</p>

<p>“I might have,” the man said. “Just because
you say I wouldn’t have doesn’t prove
anything.”</p>

<p>The girl looked at the bead curtain.
“They’ve painted something on it,” she said.
“What does it say?”</p>

<p>“Anis del Toro. It’s a drink.”</p>

<p>“Could we try it?”</p>

<p>The man called “Listen” through the curtain.
The woman came out from the bar.</p>

<p>“Four reales.”</p>

<p>“We want two Anis del Toro.”</p>

<p>“With water?”</p>

<p>“Do you want it with water?”</p>

<p>“I don’t know,” the girl said. “Is it good
with water?”</p>

<p>“It’s all right.”</p>

<p>“You want them with water?” asked the
woman.</p>

<p>“Yes, with water.”</p>

<p>“It tastes like licorice,” the girl said and put
the glass down.</p>

<p>“That’s the way with everything.”</p>

<p>“Yes,” said the girl. “Everything tastes of
licorice. Especially all the things you’ve waited
so long for, like absinthe.”</p>

<p>“Oh, cut it out.”</p>

<p>“You started it,” the girl said. “I was being
amused. I was having a fine time.”</p>

<p>“Well, let’s try and have a fine time.”</p>

<p>“All right. I was trying. I said the mountains
looked like white elephants. Wasn’t that
bright?”</p>

<p>“That was bright.”</p>

<p>“I wanted to try this new drink. That’s all
we do, isn’t it—look at things and try new
drinks?”</p>

<p>“I guess so.”</p>

<p>The girl looked across at the hills.</p>

<p>“They’re lovely hills,” she said. “They
don’t really 

<pb n="11"/>

look like white elephants. I just
meant the coloring of their skin through the
trees.”</p>

<p>“Should we have another drink?”</p>

<p>“All right.”</p>

<p>The warm wind blew the bead curtain against
the table.</p>

<p>“The beer’s nice and cool,” the man said.</p>

<p>“It’s lovely,” the girl said.</p>

<p>“It’s really an awfully simple operation, Jig,”
the man said. “It’s not really an operation at
all.”</p>

<p>The girl looked at the ground the table legs
rested on.</p>

<p>“I know you wouldn’t mind it, Jig. It’s
really not anything. It’s just to let the air in.”</p>

<p>The girl did not say anything.</p>

<p>“I’ll go with you and I’ll stay with you all
the time. They just let the air in and then it’s
all perfectly natural.”</p>

<p>“Then what will we do afterward?”</p>

<p>“We’ll be fine afterward. Just like we were
before.”</p>

<p>“What makes you think so?”</p>

<p>“That’s the only thing that bothers us. It’s
the only thing that’s made us unhappy.”</p>

<p>The girl looked at the bead curtain, put her
hand out and took hold of two of the strings of
beads.</p>

<p>“And you think then we’ll be all right and
be happy.”</p>

<p>“I know we will. You don’t have to be
afraid. I’ve known lots of people that have
done it.”</p>

<p>“So have I,” said the girl. “And afterward
they were all so happy.”</p>

<p>“Well,” the man said, “if you don’t want
to you don’t have to. I wouldn’t have you do
it if you didn’t want to. But I know it’s perfectly
simple.”</p>

<p>“And you really want to?”</p>

<p>“I think it’s the best thing to do. But I don’t
want you to do it if you don’t really want to.”</p>

<p>“And if I do it you’ll be happy and things
will be like they were and you’ll love me?”</p>

<p>“I love you now. You know I love you.”</p>

<pb n="12"/>

<p>“I know. But if I do it, then it will be nice
again if I say things are like white elephants,
and you’ll like it?”</p>

<p>“I’ll love it. I love it now but I just can’t
think about it. You know how I get when I
worry.”</p>

<p>“If I do it you won’t ever worry?”</p>

<p>“I won’t worry about that because it’s perfectly
simple.”</p>

<p>“Then I’ll do it. Because I don’t care about
me.”</p>

<p>“What do you mean?”</p>

<p>“I don’t care about me.”</p>

<p>“Well, I care about you.”</p>

<p>“Oh, yes. But I don’t care about me. And
I’ll do it and then everything will be fine.”</p>

<p>“I don’t want you to do it if you feel that
way.”</p>

<p>The girl stood up and walked to the end of
the station. Across, on the other side, were
fields of grain and trees along the banks of the
Ebro. Far away, beyond the river, were mountains.
The shadow of a cloud moved across the
field of grain and she saw the river through the
trees.</p>

<p>“And we could have all this,” she said. “And
we could have everything and every day we
make it more impossible.”</p>

<p>“What did you say?”</p>

<p>“I said we could have everything.”</p>

<p>“We can have everything.”</p>

<p>“No, we can’t.”</p>

<p>“We can have the whole world.”</p>

<p>“No, we can’t.”</p>

<p>“We can go everywhere.”</p>

<p>“No, we can’t. It isn’t ours any more.”</p>

<p>“It’s ours.”</p>

<p>“No, it isn’t. And once they take it away,
you never get it back.”</p>

<p>“But they haven’t taken it away.”</p>

<p>“We’ll wait and see.”</p>

<p>“Come on back in the shade,” he said. “You
mustn’t feel that way.”</p>
                
                <pb n="13"/>

<p>“I don’t feel any way,” the girl said. “I
just know things.”</p>

<p>“I don’t want you to do anything that you
don’t want to do——”</p>

<p>“Nor that isn’t good for me,” she said. “I
know. Could we have another beer?”</p>

<p>“All right. But you’ve got to realize——”</p>

<p>“I realize,” the girl said. “Can’t we maybe
stop talking?”</p>

<p>They sat down at the table and the girl
looked across at the hills on the dry side of the
valley and the man looked at her and at the
table.</p>

<p>“You’ve got to realize,” he said, “that I don’t
want you to do it if you don’t want to. I’m
perfectly willing to go through with it if it
means anything to you.”</p>

<p>“Doesn’t it mean anything to you? We could
get along.”</p>

<p>“Of course it does. But I don’t want anybody
but you. I don’t want any one else. And
I know it’s perfectly simple.”</p>

<p>“Yes, you know it’s perfectly simple.”</p>

<p>“It’s all right for you to say that, but I do
know it.”</p>

<p>“Would you do something for me now?”</p>

<p>“I’d do anything for you.”</p>

<p>“Would you please please please please
please please please stop talking?”</p>

<p>He did not say anything but looked at the
bags against the wall of the station. There
were labels on them from all the hotels where
they had spent nights.</p>

<p>“But I don’t want you to,” he said, “I don’t
care anything about it.”</p>

<p>“I’ll scream,” the girl said.</p>

<p>The woman came out through the curtains
with two glasses of beer and put them down on
the damp felt pads. “The train comes in five
minutes,” she said.</p>

<p>“What did she say?” asked the girl.</p>
                
                <pb n="14"/>

<p>“That the train is coming in five minutes.”</p>

<p>The girl smiled brightly at the woman, to
thank her.</p>

<p>“I’d better take the bags over to the other
side of the station,” the man said. She smiled
at him.</p>

<p>“All right. Then come back and we’ll finish
the beer.”</p>

<p>He picked up the two heavy bags and carried
them around the station to the other tracks. He
looked up the tracks but could not see the train.
Coming back, he walked through the barroom,
where people waiting for the train were drinking.
He drank an Anis at the bar and looked
at the people. They were all waiting reasonably
for the train. He went out through the
bead curtain. She was sitting at the table and
smiled at him.</p>

<p>“Do you feel better?” he asked.</p>

<p>“I feel fine,” she said. “There’s nothing
wrong with me. I feel fine.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div> </div>
        </back>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
