<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="chopin-hour">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Sun Also Rises</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n78078534">
                        <name ref="hemingway.xml">
                            <forename>Ernest</forename>
                            <surname>Hemingway</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>
                        <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">
                            <surname>Buford</surname>
                            <forename>Nial</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#UVAstudentsstaff">Students and Staff of The University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">Nial Buford</name>
                    
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22204-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by Literature
                        in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>The Sun Also Rises</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>                            
                            <forename>Ernest</forename>
                            <surname>Hemingway</surname>
                        </author>
                        <title>The Sun Also Rises</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7007567">New York</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Scribner's</publisher>
                            <date when="1926">1926</date>
                            <note>Text for this digital edition drawn from <ref
                                target="https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/67138">Project Gutenberg's ditigital version of 
                                <hi rend="italic">The Sun Also Rises</hi></ref> </note>       
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="tale">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="1000095">Spain</name>
                    <time from="1900" to="1930">Early Twentieth Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
                    relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th,
                    19th, and 20th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
                    developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation is retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023" who="editors.xml#HAS">Initial XML file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
    <div type="epigraph">
<p>”One generation passeth away, and another generation
cometh; but the earth abideth forever. . . . The sun also
ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to the place
where he arose. . . . The wind goeth toward the south,
and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually,
and the wind returneth again according to his
circuits. . . . All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea
is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come,
thither they return again.”</p>
<p>- Ecclesiastes</p>
</div>
        </front>
<body>
<div type ="book">
<p>BOOK I</p>

<pb n="3"/>
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 1</p>
<lb/>
<p>Robert Cohn was once middleweight boxing champion of
Princeton. Do not think that I am very much impressed by that
as a boxing title, but it meant a lot to Cohn. He cared nothing for
boxing, in fact he disliked it, but he learned it painfully and
thoroughly to counteract the feeling of inferiority and shyness
he had felt on being treated as a Jew at Princeton. There was a
certain inner comfort in knowing he could knock down anybody
who was snooty to him, although, being very shy and a thoroughly
nice boy, he never fought except in the gym. He was Spider
Kelly’s star pupil. Spider Kelly taught all his young gentlemen to
box like featherweights, no matter whether they weighed one
hundred and five or two hundred and five pounds. But it seemed
to fit Cohn. He was really very fast. He was so good that Spider
promptly overmatched him and got his nose permanently flattened.
This increased Cohn’s distaste for boxing, but it gave him
a certain satisfaction of some strange sort, and it certainly improved
his nose. In his last year at Princeton he read too much
<pb n="4"/>
    and took to wearing spectacles. I never met any one of his class
who remembered him. They did not even remember that he was
middleweight boxing champion.</p>
<p>I mistrust all frank and simple people, especially when their
stories hold together, and I always had a suspicion that perhaps
Robert Cohn had never been middleweight boxing champion,
and that perhaps a horse had stepped on his face, or that maybe
his mother had been frightened or seen something, or that he had,
maybe, bumped into something as a young child, but I finally had
somebody verify the story from Spider Kelly. Spider Kelly not only
remembered Cohn. He had often wondered what had become
of him.</p>
<p>Robert Cohn was a member, through his father, of one of the
richest Jewish families in New York, and through his mother of
one of the oldest. At the military school where he prepped for
Princeton, and played a very good end on the football team, no
one had made him race-conscious. No one had ever made him
feel he was a Jew, and hence any different from anybody else,
until he went to Princeton. He was a nice boy, a friendly boy,
and very shy, and it made him bitter. He took it out in boxing, and
he came out of Princeton with painful self-consciousness and the
flattened nose, and was married by the first girl who was nice to
him. He was married five years, had three children, lost most of
the fifty thousand dollars his father left him, the balance of the
estate having gone to his mother, hardened into a rather unattractive
mould under domestic unhappiness with a rich wife; and
just when he had made up his mind to leave his wife she left him
and went off with a miniature-painter. As he had been thinking
for months about leaving his wife and had not done it because it
would be too cruel to deprive her of himself, her departure was a
very healthful shock.</p>
<p>The divorce was arranged and Robert Cohn went out to the
Coast. In California he fell among literary people and, as he still
<pb n="5"/>
had a little of the fifty thousand left, in a short time he was backing
a review of the Arts. The review commenced publication in
Carmel, California, and finished in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
By that time Cohn, who had been regarded purely as an angel,
and whose name had appeared on the editorial page merely as a
member of the advisory board, had become the sole editor. It was
his money and he discovered he liked the authority of editing. He
was sorry when the magazine became too expensive and he had to
give it up.</p>
<p>By that time, though, he had other things to worry about. He
had been taken in hand by a lady who hoped to rise with the
magazine. She was very forceful, and Cohn never had a chance of
not being taken in hand. Also he was sure that he loved her.
When this lady saw that the magazine was not going to rise, she
became a little disgusted with Cohn and decided that she might
as well get what there was to get while there was still something
available, so she urged that they go to Europe, where Cohn could
write. They came to Europe, where the lady had been educated,
and stayed three years. During these three years, the first spent in
travel, the last two in Paris, Robert Cohn had two friends, Braddocks
and myself. Braddocks was his literary friend. I was his
tennis friend.</p>
<p>The lady who had him, her name was Frances, found toward
the end of the second year that her looks were going, and her
attitude toward Robert changed from one of careless possession
and exploitation to the absolute determination that he should
marry her. During this time Robert’s mother had settled an allowance
on him, about three hundred dollars a month. During
two years and a half I do not believe that Robert Cohn looked
at another woman. He was fairly happy, except that, like many
people living in Europe, he would rather have been in America,
and he had discovered writing. He wrote a novel, and it was not
really such a bad novel as the critics later called it, although it
<pb n="6"/>
was a very poor novel. He read many books, played bridge,
played tennis, and boxed at a local gymnasium.</p>
<p>I first became aware of his lady’s attitude toward him one night
after the three of us had dined together. We had dined at
l’Avenue’s and afterward went to the Café de Versailles for coffee.
We had several fines after the coffee, and I said I must be
going. Cohn had been talking about the two of us going off somewhere
on a weekend trip. He wanted to get out of town and get
in a good walk. I suggested we fly to Strasbourg and walk up to
Saint Odile, or somewhere or other in Alsace. “I know a girl in
Strasbourg who can show us the town,” I said.</p>
<p>Somebody kicked me under the table. I thought it was accidental
and went on: “She’s been there two years and knows
everything there is to know about the town. She’s a swell girl.”</p>
<p>I was kicked again under the table and, looking, saw Frances,
Robert’s lady, her chin lifting and her face hardening.</p>
<p>“Hell,” I said, “why go to Strasbourg? We could go up to Bruges,
or to the Ardennes.”</p>
<p>Cohn looked relieved. I was not kicked again. I said good-night
and went out. Cohn said he wanted to buy a paper and would
walk to the corner with me. “For God’s sake,” he said, “why did
you say that about that girl in Strasbourg for? Didn’t you see
Frances?”</p>
<p>“No, why should I? If I know an American girl that lives in
Strasbourg what the hell is it to Frances?”</p>
<p>“It doesn’t make any difference. Any girl. I couldn’t go, that
would be all.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be silly.”</p>
<p>“You don’t know Frances. Any girl at all. Didn’t you see the way
she looked?”</p>
<p>“Oh, well,” I said, “let’s go to Senlis.”</p>
<p>“Don’t get sore.”</p>
<pb n="7"/>
<p>“I’m not sore. Senlis is a good place and we can stay at the
Grand Cerf and take a hike in the woods and come home.”</p>
<p>“Good, that will be fine.”</p>
<p>“Well, I’ll see you to-morrow at the courts,” I said.</p>
<p>“Good-night, Jake,” he said, and started back to the café.</p>
<p>“You forgot to get your paper,” I said.</p>
<p>“That’s so.” He walked with me up to the kiosque at the corner.
“You are not sore, are you, Jake?” He turned with the paper
in his hand.</p>
<p>“No, why should I be?”</p>
<p>“See you at tennis,” he said. I watched him walk back to the
café holding his paper. I rather liked him and evidently she led
him quite a life. </p></div>
<pb n="8"/>
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 2</p>
<p>That winter Robert Cohn went over to America with his novel,
and it was accepted by a fairly good publisher. His going made
an awful row I heard, and I think that was where Frances lost
him, because several women were nice to him in New York, and
when he came back he was quite changed. He was more enthusiastic
about America than ever, and he was not so simple, and he
was not so nice. The publishers had praised his novel pretty
highly and it rather went to his head. Then several women had
put themselves out to be nice to him, and his horizons had all
shifted. For four years his horizon had been absolutely limited to
his wife. For three years, or almost three years, he had never seen
beyond Frances. I am sure he had never been in love in his life.</p>
<p>He had married on the rebound from the rotten time he had in
college, and Frances took him on the rebound from his discovery
that he had not been everything to his first wife. He was not in
love yet but he realized that he was an attractive quantity to
women, and that the fact of a woman caring for him and wanting
<pb n="9"/>
to live with him was not simply a divine miracle. This changed
him so that he was not so pleasant to have around. Also, playing
for higher stakes than he could afford in some rather steep bridge
games with his New York connections, he had held cards and
won several hundred dollars. It made him rather vain of his
bridge game, and he talked several times of how a man could
always make a living at bridge if he were ever forced to.</p>
<p>Then there was another thing. He had been reading W. H.
Hudson. That sounds like an innocent occupation, but Cohn had
read and reread “The Purple Land.” “The Purple Land” is a very
sinister book if read too late in life. It recounts splendid imaginary
amorous adventures of a perfect English gentleman in an intensely
romantic land, the scenery of which is very well described.
For a man to take it at thirty-four as a guide-book to what life
holds is about as safe as it would be for a man of the same age
to enter Wall Street direct from a French convent, equipped with
a complete set of the more practical Alger books. Cohn, I believe,
took every word of “The Purple Land” as literally as though it
had been an R. G. Dun report. You understand me, he made
some reservations, but on the whole the book to him was sound.
It was all that was needed to set him off. I did not realize the
extent to which it had set him off until one day he came into
my office.</p>
<p>“Hello, Robert,” I said. “Did you come in to cheer me up?”</p>
<p>“Would you like to go to South America, Jake?” he asked.</p>
<p>“No.”</p>
<p>“Why not?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. I never wanted to go. Too expensive. You can
see all the South Americans you want in Paris anyway.”</p>
<p>“They’re not the real South Americans.”</p>
<p>“They look awfully real to me.”</p>
<p>I had a boat train to catch with a week’s mail stories, and only
half of them written.</p>
<pb n="10"/>
<p>“Do you know any dirt?” I asked.</p>
<p>“No.”</p>
<p>“None of your exalted connections getting divorces?”</p>
<p>“No; listen, Jake. If I handled both our expenses, would you
go to South America with me?”</p>
<p>“Why me?”</p>
<p>“You can talk Spanish. And it would be more fun with two of
us.”</p>
<p>“No,” I said, “I like this town and I go to Spain in the summer-time.”</p>
<p>“All my life I’ve wanted to go on a trip like that,” Cohn said.
He sat down. “I’ll be too old before I can ever do it.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be a fool,” I said. “You can go anywhere you want.
You’ve got plenty of money.”</p>
<p>“I know. But I can’t get started.”</p>
<p>“Cheer up,” I said. “All countries look just like the moving
pictures.”</p>
<p>But I felt sorry for him. He had it badly.</p>
<p>“I can’t stand it to think my life is going so fast and I’m not
really living it.”</p>
<p>“Nobody ever lives their life all the way up except bull-fighters.”</p>
<p>“I’m not interested in bull-fighters. That’s an abnormal life. I
want to go back in the country in South America. We could have
a great trip.”</p>
<p>“Did you ever think about going to British East Africa to shoot?”</p>
<p>“No, I wouldn’t like that.”</p>
<p>“I’d go there with you.”</p>
<p>“No; that doesn’t interest me.”</p>
<p>“That’s because you never read a book about it. Go on and
read a book all full of love affairs with the beautiful shiny black
princesses.”</p>
<p>“I want to go to South America.”</p>
<pb n="11"/>
<p>He had a hard, Jewish, stubborn streak.</p>
<p>“Come on down-stairs and have a drink.”</p>
<p>“Aren’t you working?”</p>
<p>“No,” I said. We went down the stairs to the café on the ground
floor. I had discovered that was the best way to get rid of friends.
Once you had a drink all you had to say was: “Well, I’ve got to
get back and get off some cables,” and it was done. It is very important
to discover graceful exits like that in the newspaper business,
where it is such an important part of the ethics that you
should never seem to be working. Anyway, we went down-stairs
to the bar and had a whiskey and soda. Cohn looked at the bottles
in bins around the wall. “This is a good place,” he said.</p>
<p>“There’s a lot of liquor,” I agreed.</p>
<p>“Listen, Jake,” he leaned forward on the bar. “Don’t you ever
get the feeling that all your life is going by and you’re not taking
advantage of it? Do you realize you’ve lived nearly half the time
you have to live already?”</p>
<p>“Yes, every once in a while.”</p>
<p>“Do you know that in about thirty-five years more we’ll be
dead?”</p>
<p>“What the hell, Robert,” I said. “What the hell.”</p>
<p>“I’m serious.”</p>
<p>“It’s one thing I don’t worry about,” I said.</p>
<p>“You ought to.”</p>
<p>“I’ve had plenty to worry about one time or other. I’m through
worrying.”</p>
<p>“Well, I want to go to South America.”</p>
<p>“Listen, Robert, going to another country doesn’t make any difference.
I’ve tried all that. You can’t get away from yourself by
moving from one place to another. There’s nothing to that.”</p>
<p>“But you’ve never been to South America.”</p>
<p>“South America hell! If you went there the way you feel now it
<pb n="12"/>
would be exactly the same. This is a good town. Why don’t you
start living your life in Paris?”</p>
<p>“I’m sick of Paris, and I’m sick of the Quarter.”</p>
<p>“Stay away from the Quarter. Cruise around by yourself and
see what happens to you.”</p>
<p>“Nothing happens to me. I walked alone all one night and
nothing happened except a bicycle cop stopped me and asked to
see my papers.”</p>
<p>“Wasn’t the town nice at night?”</p>
<p>“I don’t care for Paris.”</p>
<p>So there you were. I was sorry for him, but it was not a thing
you could do anything about, because right away you ran up
against the two stubbornnesses: South America could fix it and
he did not like Paris. He got the first idea out of a book, and I
suppose the second came out of a book too.</p>
<p>“Well,” I said, “I’ve got to go up-stairs and get off some cables.”</p>
<p>“Do you really have to go?”</p>
<p>“Yes, I’ve got to get these cables off.”</p>
<p>“Do you mind if I come up and sit around the office?”</p>
<p>“No, come on up.”</p>
<p>He sat in the outer room and read the papers, and the Editor
and Publisher and I worked hard for two hours. Then I sorted
out the carbons, stamped on a by-line, put the stuff in a couple of
big manila envelopes and rang for a boy to take them to the Gare
St. Lazare. I went out into the other room and there was Robert
Cohn asleep in the big chair. He was asleep with his head on his
arms. I did not like to wake him up, but I wanted to lock the
office and shove off. I put my hand on his shoulder. He shook his
head. “I can’t do it,” he said, and put his head deeper into his
arms. “I can’t do it. Nothing will make me do it.”</p>
<p>“Robert,” I said, and shook him by the shoulder. He looked up.
He smiled and blinked.</p>
<p>“Did I talk out loud just then?”</p>
<pb n="13"/>
<p>“Something. But it wasn’t clear.”</p>
<p>“God, what a rotten dream!”</p>
<p>“Did the typewriter put you to sleep?”</p>
<p>“Guess so. I didn’t sleep all last night.”</p>
<p>“What was the matter?”</p>
<p>“Talking,” he said.</p>
<p>I could picture it. I have a rotten habit of picturing the bedroom
scenes of my friends. We went out to the Café Napolitain to
have an <hi rend="italic">apéritif</hi> and watch the evening crowd on the Boulevard.</p>
<pb n="14"/></div>
    
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 3</p>
<p>It was a warm spring night and I sat at a table on the terrace of
the Napolitain after Robert had gone, watching it get dark and
the electric signs come on, and the red and green stop-and-go
traffic-signal, and the crowd going by, and the horse-cabs
clippety-clopping along at the edge of the solid taxi traffic, and
the <hi rend="italic">poules</hi> going by, singly and in pairs, looking for the evening
meal. I watched a good-looking girl walk past the table and
watched her go up the street and lost sight of her, and watched
another, and then saw the first one coming back again. She
went by once more and I caught her eye, and she came over and
sat down at the table. The waiter came up.</p>
<p>“Well, what will you drink?” I asked.</p>
<p>“Pernod.”</p>
<p>“That’s not good for little girls.”</p>
<p>“Little girl yourself. Dites garçon, un pernod.”</p>
<p>“A pernod for me, too.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?” she asked. “Going on a party?”
<pb n="15"/></p>
<p>“Sure. Aren’t you?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. You never know in this town.”</p>
<p>“Don’t you like Paris?”</p>
<p>“No.”</p>
<p>“Why don’t you go somewhere else?”</p>
<p>“Isn’t anywhere else.”</p>
<p>“You’re happy, all right.”</p>
<p>“Happy, hell!”</p>
<p>Pernod is greenish imitation absinthe. When you add water it
turns milky. It tastes like licorice and it has a good uplift, but it
drops you just as far. We sat and drank it, and the girl looked
sullen.</p>
<p>“Well,” I said, “are you going to buy me a dinner?”</p>
<p>She grinned and I saw why she made a point of not laughing.
With her mouth closed she was a rather pretty girl. I paid for the
saucers and we walked out to the street. I hailed a horse-cab and
the driver pulled up at the curb. Settled back in the slow,
smoothly rolling <hi rend="italic">fiacre</hi> we moved up the Avenue de l’Opéra,
passed the locked doors of the shops, their windows lighted, the
Avenue broad and shiny and almost deserted. The cab passed
the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> bureau with the window full of clocks.</p>
<p>“What are all the clocks for?” she asked.</p>
<p>“They show the hour all over America.”</p>
<p>“Don’t kid me.”</p>
<p>We turned off the Avenue up the Rue des Pyramides, through
the traffic of the Rue de Rivoli, and through a dark gate into the
Tuileries. She cuddled against me and I put my arm around her.
She looked up to be kissed. She touched me with one hand and
I put her hand away.</p>
<p>“Never mind.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter? You sick?”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“Everybody’s sick. I’m sick, too.”
<pb n="16"/></p>
    <p>We came out of the Tuileries into the light and crossed the
Seine and then turned up the Rue des Saints Pères.</p>
<p>“You oughtn’t to drink pernod if you’re sick.”</p>
<p>“You neither.”</p>
<p>“It doesn’t make any difference with me. It doesn’t make any
difference with a woman.”</p>
<p>“What are you called?”</p>
<p>“Georgette. How are you called?”</p>
<p>“Jacob.”</p>
<p>“That’s a Flemish name.”</p>
<p>“American too.”</p>
<p>“You’re not Flamand?”</p>
<p>“No, American.”</p>
<p>“Good, I detest Flamands.”</p>
<p>By this time we were at the restaurant. I called to the <hi rend="italic">cocher</hi>
to stop. We got out and Georgette did not like the looks of the
place. “This is no great thing of a restaurant.”</p>
<p>“No,” I said. “Maybe you would rather go to Foyot’s. Why don’t
you keep the cab and go on?”</p>
<p>I had picked her up because of a vague sentimental idea that
it would be nice to eat with some one. It was a long time since I
had dined with a <hi rend="italic">poule</hi>, and I had forgotten how dull it could be.
We went into the restaurant, passed Madame Lavigne at the
desk and into a little room. Georgette cheered up a little under
the food.</p>
<p>“It isn’t bad here,” she said. “It isn’t chic, but the food is all
right.”</p>
<p>“Better than you eat in Liège.”</p>
<p>“Brussels, you mean.”</p>
<p>We had another bottle of wine and Georgette made a joke.
She smiled and showed all her bad teeth, and we touched
glasses. “You’re not a bad type,” she said. “It’s a shame you’re
sick. We get on well. What’s the matter with you, anyway?”
<pb n="17"/> </p>
<p>“I got hurt in the war,” I said.</p>
<p>“Oh, that dirty war.”</p>
<p>We would probably have gone on and discussed the war and
agreed that it was in reality a calamity for civilization, and perhaps
would have been better avoided. I was bored enough. Just
then from the other room some one called: “Barnes! I say,
Barnes! Jacob Barnes!”</p>
<p>“It’s a friend calling me,” I explained, and went out.</p>
<p>There was Braddocks at a big table with a party: Cohn, Frances
Clyne, Mrs. Braddocks, several people I did not know.</p>
<p>“You’re coming to the dance, aren’t you?” Braddocks asked.</p>
<p>“What dance?”</p>
<p>“Why, the dancings. Don’t you know we’ve revived them?”
Mrs. Braddocks put in.</p>
<p>“You must come, Jake. We’re all going,” Frances said from the
end of the table. She was tall and had a smile.</p>
<p>“Of course, he’s coming,” Braddocks said. “Come in and have
coffee with us, Barnes.”</p>
<p>“Right.”</p>
<p>“And bring your friend,” said Mrs. Braddocks laughing. She
was a Canadian and had all their easy social graces.</p>
<p>“Thanks, we’ll be in,” I said. I went back to the small room.</p>
<p>“Who are your friends?” Georgette asked.</p>
<p>“Writers and artists.”</p>
<p>“There are lots of those on this side of the river.”</p>
<p>“Too many.”</p>
<p>“I think so. Still, some of them make money.”</p>
<p>“Oh, yes.”</p>
<p>We finished the meal and the wine. “Come on,” I said. “We’re
going to have coffee with the others.”</p>
<p>Georgette opened her bag, made a few passes at her face as
she looked in the little mirror, re-defined her lips with the lipstick,
and straightened her hat.
<pb n="18"/></p>
<p>“Good,” she said.</p>
<p>We went into the room full of people and Braddocks and the
men at his table stood up.</p>
<p>“I wish to present my fiancée, Mademoiselle Georgette
Leblanc,” I said. Georgette smiled that wonderful smile, and we
shook hands all round.</p>
<p>“Are you related to Georgette Leblanc, the singer?” Mrs. Braddocks
asked.</p>
<p>“Connais pas,” Georgette answered.</p>
<p>“But you have the same name,” Mrs. Braddocks insisted
cordially.</p>
<p>“No,” said Georgette. “Not at all. My name is Hobin.”</p>
<p>“But Mr. Barnes introduced you as Mademoiselle Georgette
Leblanc. Surely he did,” insisted Mrs. Braddocks, who in the excitement
of talking French was liable to have no idea what she
was saying.</p>
<p>“He’s a fool,” Georgette said.</p>
<p>“Oh, it was a joke, then,” Mrs. Braddocks said.</p>
<p>“Yes,” said Georgette. “To laugh at.”</p>
<p>“Did you hear that, Henry?” Mrs. Braddocks called down the
table to Braddocks. “Mr. Barnes introduced his fiancée as Mademoiselle
Leblanc, and her name is actually Hobin.”</p>
<p>“Of course, darling. Mademoiselle Hobin, I’ve known her for a
very long time.”</p>
<p>“Oh, Mademoiselle Hobin,” Frances Clyne called, speaking
French very rapidly and not seeming so proud and astonished as
Mrs. Braddocks at its coming out really French. “Have you been
in Paris long? Do you like it here? You love Paris, do you not?”</p>
<p>“Who’s she?” Georgette turned to me. “Do I have to talk to
her?”</p>
<p>She turned to Frances, sitting smiling, her hands folded, her
head poised on her long neck, her lips pursed ready to start talking
again.
<pb n="19"/></p>
<p>“No, I don’t like Paris. It’s expensive and dirty.”</p>
<p>“Really? I find it so extraordinarily clean. One of the cleanest
cities in all Europe.”</p>
<p>“I find it dirty.”</p>
<p>“How strange! But perhaps you have not been here very
long.”</p>
<p>“I’ve been here long enough.”</p>
<p>“But it does have nice people in it. One must grant that.”</p>
<p>Georgette turned to me. “You have nice friends.”</p>
<p>Frances was a little drunk and would have liked to have kept
it up but the coffee came, and Lavigne with the liqueurs, and
after that we all went out and started for Braddocks’s dancing-club.</p>
<p>The dancing-club was a <hi rend="italic">bal musette</hi> in the Rue de la Montagne
Sainte Geneviève. Five nights a week the working people of the
Pantheon quarter danced there. One night a week it was the
dancing-club. On Monday nights it was closed. When we arrived
it was quite empty, except for a policeman sitting near the door,
the wife of the proprietor back of the zinc bar, and the proprietor
himself. The daughter of the house came downstairs as
we went in. There were long benches, and tables ran across the
room, and at the far end a dancing-floor.</p>
<p>“I wish people would come earlier,” Braddocks said. The
daughter came up and wanted to know what we would drink.
The proprietor got up on a high stool beside the dancing-floor and
began to play the accordion. He had a string of bells around one
of his ankles and beat time with his foot as he played. Every one
danced. It was hot and we came off the floor perspiring.</p>
<p>“My God,” Georgette said. “What a box to sweat in!”</p>
<p>“It’s hot.”</p>
<p>“Hot, my God!”</p>
<p>“Take off your hat.”</p>
<p>“That’s a good idea.”
<pb n="20"/></p>
<p>Some one asked Georgette to dance, and I went over to the bar.
It was really very hot and the accordion music was pleasant in
the hot night. I drank a beer, standing in the doorway and getting
the cool breath of wind from the street. Two taxis were coming
down the steep street. They both stopped in front of the Bal. A
crowd of young men, some in jerseys and some in their shirt-sleeves,
got out. I could see their hands and newly washed, wavy
hair in the light from the door. The policeman standing by the
door looked at me and smiled. They came in. As they went in,
under the light I saw white hands, wavy hair, white faces, grimacing,
gesturing, talking. With them was Brett. She looked very
lovely and she was very much with them.</p>
<p>One of them saw Georgette and said: “I do declare. There is
an actual harlot. I’m going to dance with her, Lett. You watch
me.”</p>
<p>The tall dark one, called Lett, said: “Don’t you be rash.”</p>
<p>The wavy blond one answered: “Don’t you worry, dear.” And
with them was Brett.</p>
<p>I was very angry. Somehow they always made me angry. I
know they are supposed to be amusing, and you should be tolerant,
but I wanted to swing on one, any one, anything to shatter
that superior, simpering composure. Instead, I walked down the
street and had a beer at the bar at the next Bal. The beer was
not good and I had a worse cognac to take the taste out of my
mouth. When I came back to the Bal there was a crowd on the
floor and Georgette was dancing with the tall blond youth, who
danced big-hippily, carrying his head on one side, his eyes lifted
as he danced. As soon as the music stopped another one of them
asked her to dance. She had been taken up by them. I knew then
that they would all dance with her. They are like that.</p>
<p>I sat down at a table. Cohn was sitting there. Frances was
dancing. Mrs. Braddocks brought up somebody and introduced
him as Robert Prentiss. He was from New York by way of
<pb n="21"/>
Chicago, and was a rising new novelist. He had some sort of an
English accent. I asked him to have a drink.</p>
<p>“Thanks so much,” he said, “I’ve just had one.”</p>
<p>“Have another.”</p>
<p>“Thanks, I will then.”</p>
<p>We got the daughter of the house over and each had a <hi rend="italic">fine à
l’eau.</hi></p>
<p>“You’re from Kansas City, they tell me,” he said.</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“Do you find Paris amusing?”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“Really?”</p>
<p>I was a little drunk. Not drunk in any positive sense but just
enough to be careless.</p>
<p>“For God’s sake,” I said, “yes. Don’t you?”</p>
<p>“Oh, how charmingly you get angry,” he said. “I wish I had that
faculty.”</p>
<p>I got up and walked over toward the dancing-floor. Mrs. Braddocks
followed me. “Don’t be cross with Robert,” she said.
“He’s still only a child, you know.”</p>
<p>“I wasn’t cross,” I said. “I just thought perhaps I was going to
throw up.”</p>
<p>“Your fiancée is having a great success,” Mrs. Braddocks looked
out on the floor where Georgette was dancing in the arms of the
tall, dark one, called Lett.</p>
<p>“Isn’t she?” I said.</p>
<p>“Rather,” said Mrs. Braddocks.</p>
<p>Cohn came up. “Come on, Jake,” he said, “have a drink.” We
walked over to the bar. “What’s the matter with you? You seem all
worked up over something?”</p>
<p>“Nothing. This whole show makes me sick is all.”</p>
<p>Brett came up to the bar.</p>
<p>“Hello, you chaps.”
<pb n="22"/></p>
<p>“Hello, Brett,” I said. “Why aren’t you tight?”</p>
<p>“Never going to get tight any more. I say, give a chap a brandy
and soda.”</p>
<p>She stood holding the glass and I saw Robert Cohn looking at
her. He looked a great deal as his compatriot must have looked
when he saw the promised land. Cohn, of course, was much
younger. But he had that look of eager, deserving expectation.</p>
<p>Brett was damned good-looking. She wore a slipover jersey
sweater and a tweed skirt, and her hair was brushed back like a
boy’s. She started all that. She was built with curves like the hull
of a racing yacht, and you missed none of it with that wool
jersey.</p>
<p>“It’s a fine crowd you’re with, Brett,” I said.</p>
<p>“Aren’t they lovely? And you, my dear. Where did you get it?”</p>
<p>“At the Napolitain.”</p>
<p>“And have you had a lovely evening?”</p>
<p>“Oh, priceless,” I said.</p>
<p>Brett laughed. “It’s wrong of you, Jake. It’s an insult to all of
us. Look at Frances there, and Jo.”</p>
<p>This for Cohn’s benefit.</p>
<p>“It’s in restraint of trade,” Brett said. She laughed again.</p>
<p>“You’re wonderfully sober,” I said.</p>
<p>“Yes. Aren’t I? And when one’s with the crowd I’m with, one
can drink in such safety, too.”</p>
<p>The music started and Robert Cohn said: “Will you dance this
with me, Lady Brett?”</p>
<p>Brett smiled at him. “I’ve promised to dance this with Jacob,”
she laughed. “You’ve a hell of a biblical name, Jake.”</p>
<p>“How about the next?” asked Cohn.</p>
<p>“We’re going,” Brett said. “We’ve a date up at Montmartre.”
Dancing, I looked over Brett’s shoulder and saw Cohn, standing
at the bar, still watching her.</p>
<p>“You’ve made a new one there,” I said to her.
<pb n="23"/></p>
<p>“Don’t talk about it. Poor chap. I never knew it till just now.”</p>
<p>“Oh, well,” I said. “I suppose you like to add them up.”</p>
<p>“Don’t talk like a fool.”</p>
<p>“You do.”</p>
<p>“Oh, well. What if I do?”</p>
<p>“Nothing,” I said. We were dancing to the accordion and some
one was playing the banjo. It was hot and I felt happy. We passed
close to Georgette dancing with another one of them.</p>
<p>“What possessed you to bring her?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know, I just brought her.”</p>
<p>“You’re getting damned romantic.”</p>
<p>“No, bored.”</p>
<p>“Now?”</p>
<p>“No, not now.”</p>
<p>“Let’s get out of here. She’s well taken care of.”</p>
<p>“Do you want to?”</p>
<p>“Would I ask you if I didn’t want to?”</p>
<p>We left the floor and I took my coat off a hanger on the wall
and put it on. Brett stood by the bar. Cohn was talking to her.
I stopped at the bar and asked them for an envelope. The patronne
found one. I took a fifty-franc note from my pocket, put
it in the envelope, sealed it, and handed it to the patronne.</p>
<p>“If the girl I came with asks for me, will you give her this?” I
said. “If she goes out with one of those gentlemen, will you save
this for me?”</p>
<p>“C’est entendu, Monsieur,” the patronne said. “You go now?
So early?”</p>
<p>“Yes,” I said.</p>
<p>We started out the door. Cohn was still talking to Brett. She
said good night and took my arm. “Good night, Cohn,” I said.
Outside in the street we looked for a taxi.</p>
<p>“You’re going to lose your fifty francs,” Brett said.</p>
<p>“Oh, yes.”
<pb n="24"/></p>
<p>“No taxis.”</p>
<p>“We could walk up to the Pantheon and get one.”</p>
<p>“Come on and we’ll get a drink in the pub next door and send
for one.”</p>
<p>“You wouldn’t walk across the street.”</p>
<p>“Not if I could help it.”</p>
<p>We went into the next bar and I sent a waiter for a taxi.</p>
<p>“Well,” I said, “we’re out away from them.”</p>
<p>We stood against the tall zinc bar and did not talk and looked
at each other. The waiter came and said the taxi was outside.
Brett pressed my hand hard. I gave the waiter a franc and we
went out. “Where should I tell him?” I asked.</p>
<p>“Oh, tell him to drive around.”</p>
<p>I told the driver to go to the Parc Montsouris, and got in, and
slammed the door. Brett was leaning back in the corner, her eyes
closed. I got in and sat beside her. The cab started with a jerk.</p>
<p>“Oh, darling, I’ve been so miserable,” Brett said.
<pb n="25"/></p></div>
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 4</p>
<p>The taxi went up the hill, passed the lighted square, then on into
the dark, still climbing, then levelled out onto a dark street behind
St. Etienne du Mont, went smoothly down the asphalt,
passed the trees and the standing bus at the Place de la Contrescarpe,
then turned onto the cobbles of the Rue Mouffetard.
There were lighted bars and late open shops on each side of the
street. We were sitting apart and we jolted close together going
down the old street. Brett’s hat was off. Her head was back. I
saw her face in the lights from the open shops, then it was dark,
then I saw her face clearly as we came out on the Avenue des
Gobelins. The street was torn up and men were working on the
car-tracks by the light of acetylene flares. Brett’s face was white
and the long line of her neck showed in the bright light of the
flares. The street was dark again and I kissed her. Our lips were
tight together and then she turned away and pressed against the
corner of the seat, as far away as she could get. Her head was
down.
<pb n="26"/></p>
<p>“Don’t touch me,” she said. “Please don’t touch me.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“I can’t stand it.”</p>
<p>“Oh, Brett.”</p>
<p>“You mustn’t. You must know. I can’t stand it, that’s all. Oh,
darling, please understand!”</p>
<p>“Don’t you love me?”</p>
<p>“Love you? I simply turn all to jelly when you touch me.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t there anything we can do about it?”</p>
<p>She was sitting up now. My arm was around her and she was
leaning back against me, and we were quite calm. She was looking
into my eyes with that way she had of looking that made you
wonder whether she really saw out of her own eyes. They would
look on and on after every one else’s eyes in the world would have
stopped looking. She looked as though there were nothing on
earth she would not look at like that, and really she was afraid of
so many things.</p>
<p>“And there’s not a damn thing we could do,” I said.</p>
<p>“I don’t know,” she said. “I don’t want to go through that hell
again.”</p>
<p>“We’d better keep away from each other.”</p>
<p>“But, darling, I have to see you. It isn’t all that you know.”</p>
<p>“No, but it always gets to be.”</p>
<p>“That’s my fault. Don’t we pay for all the things we do, though?”</p>
<p>She had been looking into my eyes all the time. Her eyes had
different depths, sometimes they seemed perfectly flat. Now you
could see all the way into them.</p>
<p>“When I think of the hell I’ve put chaps through. I’m paying
for it all now.”</p>
<p>“Don’t talk like a fool,” I said. “Besides, what happened to me
is supposed to be funny. I never think about it.”</p>
<p>“Oh, no. I’ll lay you don’t.”</p>
<p>“Well, let’s shut up about it.”
<pb n="27"/></p>
<p>“I laughed about it too, myself, once.” She wasn’t looking at
me. “A friend of my brother’s came home that way from Mons.
It seemed like a hell of a joke. Chaps never know anything, do
they?”</p>
<p>“No,” I said. “Nobody ever knows anything.”</p>
<p>I was pretty well through with the subject. At one time or another
I had probably considered it from most of its various angles,
including the one that certain injuries or imperfections are a subject
of merriment while remaining quite serious for the person
possessing them.</p>
<p>“It’s funny,” I said. “It’s very funny. And it’s a lot of fun, too,
to be in love.”</p>
<p>“Do you think so?” her eyes looked flat again.</p>
<p>“I don’t mean fun that way. In a way it’s an enjoyable feeling.”</p>
<p>“No,” she said. “I think it’s hell on earth.”</p>
<p>“It’s good to see each other.”</p>
<p>“No. I don’t think it is.”</p>
<p>“Don’t you want to?”</p>
<p>“I have to.”</p>
<p>We were sitting now like two strangers. On the right was the
Parc Montsouris. The restaurant where they have the pool of live
trout and where you can sit and look out over the park was
closed and dark. The driver leaned his head around.</p>
<p>“Where do you want to go?” I asked. Brett turned her head
away.</p>
<p>“Oh, go to the Select.”</p>
<p>“Café Select,” I told the driver. “Boulevard Montparnasse.”
We drove straight down, turning around the Lion de Belfort that
guards the passing Montrouge trams. Brett looked straight ahead.
On the Boulevard Raspail, with the lights of Montparnasse in
sight, Brett said: “Would you mind very much if I asked you to
do something?”</p>
<p>“Don’t be silly.”
<pb n="28"/></p>
<p>“Kiss me just once more before we get there.”</p>
<p>When the taxi stopped I got out and paid. Brett came out putting
on her hat. She gave me her hand as she stepped down. Her
hand was shaky. “I say, do I look too much of a mess?” She
pulled her man’s felt hat down and started in for the bar. Inside,
against the bar and at tables, were most of the crowd who a
been at the dance.</p>
<p>“Hello, you chaps,” Brett said. “I’m going to have a drink.”</p>
<p>“Oh, Brett! Brett!” the little Greek portrait-painter, who called
himself a duke, and whom everybody called Zizi, pushed up to
her. “I got something fine to tell you.”</p>
<p>“Hello, Zizi,” Brett said.</p>
<p>“I want you to meet a friend,” Zizi said. A fat man came up.</p>
<p>“Count Mippipopolous, meet my friend Lady Ashley.”</p>
<p>“How do you do?” said Brett.</p>
<p>“Well, does your Ladyship have a good time here in Paris?”
asked Count Mippipopolous, who wore an elk’s tooth on his
watch-chain.</p>
<p>“Rather,” said Brett.</p>
<p>“Paris is a fine town all right,” said the count. “But I guess you
have pretty big doings yourself over in London.”</p>
<p>“Oh, yes,” said Brett. “Enormous.”</p>
<p>Braddocks called to me from a table. “Barnes,” he said, “have a
drink. That girl of yours got in a frightful row.”</p>
<p>“What about?”</p>
<p>“Something the patronne’s daughter said. A corking row. She
was rather splendid, you know. Showed her yellow card and demanded
the patronne’s daughter’s too. I say it was a row.”</p>
<p>“What finally happened?”</p>
<p>“Oh, some one took her home. Not a bad-looking girl. Wonderful
command of the idiom. Do stay and have a drink.”</p>
<p>“No,” I said. “I must shove off. Seen Cohn?”</p>
<p>“He went home with Frances,” Mrs. Braddock put in.
<pb n="29"/></p>
<p>“Poor chap, he looks awfully down,” Braddocks said.</p>
<p>“I dare say he is,” said Mrs. Braddocks.</p>
<p>“I have to shove off,” I said. “Good night.”</p>
<p>I said good night to Brett at the bar. The count was buying
champagne. “Will you take a glass of wine with us, sir?” he asked.</p>
<p>“No. Thanks awfully. I have to go.”</p>
<p>“Really going?” Brett asked.</p>
<p>“Yes,” I said. “I’ve got a rotten headache.”</p>
<p>“I’ll see you to-morrow?”</p>
<p>“Come in at the office.”</p>
<p>“Hardly.”</p>
<p>“Well, where will I see you?”</p>
<p>“Anywhere around five o’clock.”</p>
<p>“Make it the other side of town then.”</p>
<p>“Good. I’ll be at the Crillon at five.”</p>
<p>“Try and be there,” I said.</p>
<p>“Don’t worry,” Brett said. “I’ve never let you down, have I?”</p>
<p>“Heard from Mike?”</p>
<p>“Letter to-day.”</p>
<p>“Good night, sir,” said the count.</p>
<p>I went out onto the sidewalk and walked down toward the
Boulevard St. Michel, passed the tables of the Rotonde, still
crowded, looked across the street at the Dome, its tables running
out to the edge of the pavement. Some one waved at me from a
table, I did not see who it was and went on. I wanted to get
home. The Boulevard Montparnasse was deserted. Lavigne’s was
closed tight, and they were stacking the tables outside the
Closerie des Lilas. I passed Ney’s statue standing among the new-leaved
chestnut-trees in the arc-light. There was a faded purple
wreath leaning against the base. I stopped and read the inscription:
from the Bonapartist Groups, some date; I forget. He looked
very fine, Marshal Ney in his top-boots, gesturing with his sword
<pb n="30"/>
among the green new horse-chestnut leaves. My flat was just
across the street, a little way down the Boulevard St. Michel.</p>
<p>There was a light in the concierge’s room and I knocked on
the door and she gave me my mail. I wished her good night
and went up-stairs. There were two letters and some papers. I
looked at them under the gas-light in the dining-room. The letters
were from the States. One was a bank statement. It showed
a balance of $2432.60. I got out my check-book and deducted four
checks drawn since the first of the month, and discovered I had
a balance of $1832.60. I wrote this on the back of the statement.
The other letter was a wedding announcement. Mr. and Mrs.
Aloysius Kirby announce the marriage of their daughter Katherine—I
knew neither the girl nor the man she was marrying.
They must be circularizing the town. It was a funny name. I felt
sure I could remember anybody with a name like Aloysius. It
was a good Catholic name. There was a crest on the announcement.
Like Zizi the Greek duke. And that count. The count was
funny. Brett had a title, too. Lady Ashley. To hell with Brett.
To hell with you, Lady Ashley.</p>
<p>I lit the lamp beside the bed, turned off the gas, and opened
the wide windows. The bed was far back from the windows,
and I sat with the windows open and undressed by the bed. Outside
a night train, running on the street-car tracks, went by carrying
vegetables to the markets. They were noisy at night when
you could not sleep. Undressing, I looked at myself in the mirror
of the big armoire beside the bed. That was a typically French
way to furnish a room. Practical, too, I suppose. Of all the ways
to be wounded. I suppose it was funny. I put on my pajamas
and got into bed. I had the two bull-fight papers, and I took their
wrappers off. One was orange. The other yellow. They would
both have the same news, so whichever I read first would spoil
the other. <hi rend="italic">Le Toril</hi> was the better paper, so I started to read it.
I read it all the way through, including the Petite Correspondance
<pb n="31"/>
and the Cornigrams. I blew out the lamp. Perhaps I would be
able to sleep.</p>
<p>My head started to work. The old grievance. Well, it was a rotten
way to be wounded and flying on a joke front like the Italian.
In the Italian hospital we were going to form a society. It had a
funny name in Italian. I wonder what became of the others, the
Italians. That was in the Ospedale Maggiore in Milano, Padiglione
Ponte. The next building was the Padiglione Zonda. There
was a statue of Ponte, or maybe it was Zonda. That was where
the liaison colonel came to visit me. That was funny. That was
about the first funny thing. I was all bandaged up. But they had
told him about it. Then he made that wonderful speech: “You, a
foreigner, an Englishman” (any foreigner was an Englishman)
“have given more than your life.” What a speech! I would like to
have it illuminated to hang in the office. He never laughed. He
was putting himself in my place, I guess. “Che mala fortuna!
Che mala fortuna!”</p>
<p>I never used to realize it, I guess. I try and play it along and
just not make trouble for people. Probably I never would have
had any trouble if I hadn’t run into Brett when they shipped me
to England. I suppose she only wanted what she couldn’t have.
Well, people were that way. To hell with people. The Catholic
Church had an awfully good way of handling all that. Good advice,
anyway. Not to think about it. Oh, it was swell advice. Try
and take it sometime. Try and take it.</p>
<p>I lay awake thinking and my mind jumping around. Then I
couldn’t keep away from it, and I started to think about Brett
and all the rest of it went away. I was thinking about Brett and
my mind stopped jumping around and started to go in sort of
smooth waves. Then all of a sudden I started to cry. Then after
a while it was better and I lay in bed and listened to the heavy
trams go by and way down the street, and then I went to sleep.</p>
<p>I woke up. There was a row going on outside. I listened and I
<pb n="32"/>
thought I recognized a voice. I put on a dressing-gown and went
to the door. The concierge was talking down-stairs. She was very
angry. I heard my name and called down the stairs.</p>
<p>“Is that you, Monsieur Barnes?” the concierge called.</p>
<p>“Yes. It’s me.”</p>
<p>“There’s a species of woman here who’s waked the whole
street up. What kind of a dirty business at this time of night! She
says she must see you. I’ve told her you’re asleep.”</p>
<p>Then I heard Brett’s voice. Half asleep I had been sure it was
Georgette. I don’t know why. She could not have known my
address.</p>
<p>“Will you send her up, please?”</p>
<p>Brett came up the stairs. I saw she was quite drunk. “Silly
thing to do,” she said. “Make an awful row. I say, you weren’t
asleep, were you?”</p>
<p>“What did you think I was doing?”</p>
<p>“Don’t know. What time is it?”</p>
<p>I looked at the clock. It was half-past four. “Had no idea
what hour it was,” Brett said. “I say, can a chap sit down? Don’t
be cross, darling. Just left the count. He brought me here.”</p>
<p>“What’s he like?” I was getting brandy and soda and glasses.</p>
<p>“Just a little,” said Brett. “Don’t try and make me drunk. The
count? Oh, rather. He’s quite one of us.”</p>
<p>“Is he a count?”</p>
<p>“Here’s how. I rather think so, you know. Deserves to be, anyhow.
Knows hell’s own amount about people. Don’t know where
he got it all. Owns a chain of sweetshops in the States.”</p>
<p>She sipped at her glass.</p>
<p>“Think he called it a chain. Something like that. Linked them
all up. Told me a little about it. Damned interesting. He’s one of
us, though. Oh, quite. No doubt. One can always tell.”</p>
<p>She took another drink.
<pb n="33"/></p>
<p>“How do I buck on about all this? You don’t mind, do you?
He’s putting up for Zizi, you know.”</p>
<p>“Is Zizi really a duke, too?”</p>
<p>“I shouldn’t wonder. Greek, you know. Rotten painter. I rather
liked the count.”</p>
<p>“Where did you go with him?”</p>
<p>“Oh, everywhere. He just brought me here now. Offered me
ten thousand dollars to go to Biarritz with him. How much is
that in pounds?”</p>
<p>“Around two thousand.”</p>
<p>“Lot of money. I told him I couldn’t do it. He was awfully nice
about it. Told him I knew too many people in Biarritz.”</p>
<p>Brett laughed.</p>
<p>“I say, you are slow on the up-take,” she said. I had only sipped
my brandy and soda. I took a long drink.</p>
<p>“That’s better. Very funny,” Brett said. “Then he wanted me to
go to Cannes with him. Told him I knew too many people in
Cannes. Monte Carlo. Told him I knew too many people in Monte
Carlo. Told him I knew too many people everywhere. Quite true,
too. So I asked him to bring me here.”</p>
<p>She looked at me, her hand on the table, her glass raised.
“Don’t look like that,” she said. “Told him I was in love with you.
True, too. Don’t look like that. He was damn nice about it.
Wants to drive us out to dinner to-morrow night. Like to go?”</p>
<p>“Why not?”</p>
<p>“I’d better go now.”</p>
<p>“Why?”</p>
<p>“Just wanted to see you. Damned silly idea. Want to get dressed
and come down? He’s got the car just up the street.”</p>
<p>“The count?”</p>
<p>“Himself. And a chauffeur in livery. Going to drive me around
and have breakfast in the Bois. Hampers. Got it all at Zelli’s.
Dozen bottles of Mumms. Tempt you?”
<pb n="34"/></p>
<p>“I have to work in the morning,” I said. “I’m too far behind you
now to catch up and be any fun.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be an ass.”</p>
<p>“Can’t do it.”</p>
<p>“Right. Send him a tender message?”</p>
<p>“Anything. Absolutely.”</p>
<p>“Good night, darling.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be sentimental.”</p>
<p>“You make me ill.”</p>
<p>We kissed good night and Brett shivered. “I’d better go,” she
said. “Good night, darling.”</p>
<p>“You don’t have to go.”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>We kissed again on the stairs and as I called for the cordon
the concierge muttered something behind her door. I went back
up-stairs and from the open window watched Brett walking up
the street to the big limousine drawn up to the curb under the
arc-light. She got in and it started off. I turned around. On the
table was an empty glass and a glass half-full of brandy and
soda. I took them both out to the kitchen and poured the half-full
glass down the sink. I turned off the gas in the dining-room,
kicked off my slippers sitting on the bed, and got into bed. This
was Brett, that I had felt like crying about. Then I thought of
her walking up the street and stepping into the car, as I had last
seen her, and of course in a little while I felt like hell again. It is
awfully easy to be hard-boiled about everything in the daytime,
but at night it is another thing.
<pb n="35"/></p></div>
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 5</p>
<p>In the morning I walked down the Boulevard to the rue Soufflot
for coffee and brioche. It was a fine morning. The horse-chestnut
trees in the Luxembourg gardens were in bloom. There was the
pleasant early-morning feeling of a hot day. I read the papers
with the coffee and then smoked a cigarette. The flower-women
were coming up from the market and arranging their daily stock.
Students went by going up to the law school, or down to the
Sorbonne. The Boulevard was busy with trams and people going
to work. I got on an S bus and rode down to the Madeleine,
standing on the back platform. From the Madeleine I walked
along the Boulevard des Capucines to the Opéra, and up to my
office. I passed the man with the jumping frogs and the man with
the boxer toys. I stepped aside to avoid walking into the thread
with which his girl assistant manipulated the boxers. She was
standing looking away, the thread in her folded hands. The man
was urging two tourists to buy. Three more tourists had stopped
and were watching. I walked on behind a man who was pushing
<pb n="36"/>
a roller that printed the name CINZANO on the sidewalk in
damp letters. All along people were going to work. It felt pleasant
to be going to work. I walked across the avenue and turned in
to my office.</p>
<p>Up-stairs in the office I read the French morning papers,
smoked, and then sat at the typewriter and got off a good morning’s
work. At eleven o’clock I went over to the Quai d’Orsay
in a taxi and went in and sat with about a dozen correspondents,
while the foreign-office mouthpiece, a young Nouvelle Revue
Française diplomat in horn-rimmed spectacles, talked and answered
questions for half an hour. The President of the Council
was in Lyons making a speech, or, rather he was on his way
back. Several people asked questions to hear themselves talk
and there were a couple of questions asked by news service men
who wanted to know the answers. There was no news. I shared a
taxi back from the Quai d’Orsay with Woolsey and Krum.</p>
<p>“What do you do nights, Jake?” asked Krum. “I never see you
around.”</p>
<p>“Oh, I’m over in the Quarter.”</p>
<p>“I’m coming over some night. The Dingo. That’s the great
place, isn’t it?”</p>
<p>“Yes. That, or this new dive, The Select.”</p>
<p>“I’ve meant to get over,” said Krum. “You know how it is,
though, with a wife and kids.”</p>
<p>“Playing any tennis?” Woolsey asked.</p>
<p>“Well, no,” said Krum. “I can’t say I’ve played any this year.
I’ve tried to get away, but Sundays it’s always rained, and the
courts are so damned crowded.”</p>
<p>“The Englishmen all have Saturday off,” Woolsey said.</p>
<p>“Lucky beggars,” said Krum. “Well, I’ll tell you. Some day I’m
not going to be working for an agency. Then I’ll have plenty of
time to get out in the country.”
<pb n="37"/></p>
<p>“That’s the thing to do. Live out in the country and have a
little car.”</p>
<p>“I’ve been thinking some about getting a car next year.”</p>
<p>I banged on the glass. The chauffeur stopped. “Here’s my
street,” I said. “Come in and have a drink.”</p>
<p>“Thanks, old man,” Krum said. Woolsey shook his head. “I’ve
got to file that line he got off this morning.”</p>
<p>I put a two-franc piece in Krum’s hand.</p>
<p>“You’re crazy, Jake,” he said. “This is on me.”</p>
<p>“It’s all on the office, anyway.”</p>
<p>“Nope. I want to get it.”</p>
<p>I waved good-by. Krum put his head out. “See you at the lunch
on Wednesday.”</p>
<p>“You bet.”</p>
<p>I went to the office in the elevator. Robert Cohn was waiting
for me. “Hello, Jake,” he said. “Going out to lunch?”</p>
<p>“Yes. Let me see if there is anything new.”</p>
<p>“Where will we eat?”</p>
<p>“Anywhere.”</p>
<p>I was looking over my desk. “Where do you want to eat?”</p>
<p>“How about Wetzel’s? They’ve got good hors d’œuvres.”</p>
<p>In the restaurant we ordered hors d’œuvres and beer. The
sommelier brought the beer, tall, beaded on the outside of the
steins, and cold. There were a dozen different dishes of hors
d’œuvres.</p>
<p>“Have any fun last night?” I asked.</p>
<p>“No. I don’t think so.”</p>
<p>“How’s the writing going?”</p>
<p>“Rotten. I can’t get this second book going.”</p>
<p>“That happens to everybody.”</p>
<p>“Oh, I’m sure of that. It gets me worried, though.”</p>
<p>“Thought any more about going to South America?”</p>
<p>“I mean that.”
<pb n="38"/></p>
<p>“Well, why don’t you start off?”</p>
<p>“Frances.”</p>
<p>“Well,” I said, “take her with you.”</p>
<p>“She wouldn’t like it. That isn’t the sort of thing she likes. She
likes a lot of people around.”</p>
<p>“Tell her to go to hell.”</p>
<p>“I can’t. I’ve got certain obligations to her.”</p>
<p>He shoved the sliced cucumbers away and took a pickled
herring.</p>
<p>“What do you know about Lady Brett Ashley, Jake?”</p>
<p>“Her name’s Lady Ashley. Brett’s her own name. She’s a nice
girl,” I said. “She’s getting a divorce and she’s going to marry
Mike Campbell. He’s over in Scotland now. Why?”</p>
<p>“She’s a remarkably attractive woman.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t she?”</p>
<p>“There’s a certain quality about her, a certain fineness. She
seems to be absolutely fine and straight.”</p>
<p>“She’s very nice.”</p>
<p>“I don’t know how to describe the quality,” Cohn said. “I suppose
it’s breeding.”</p>
<p>“You sound as though you liked her pretty well.”</p>
<p>“I do. I shouldn’t wonder if I were in love with her.”</p>
<p>“She’s a drunk,” I said. “She’s in love with Mike Campbell, and
she’s going to marry him. He’s going to be rich as hell some
day.”</p>
<p>“I don’t believe she’ll ever marry him.”</p>
<p>“Why not?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. I just don’t believe it. Have you known her a
long time?”</p>
<p>“Yes,” I said. “She was a V. A. D. in a hospital I was in during
the war.”</p>
<p>“She must have been just a kid then.”</p>
<p>“She’s thirty-four now.”
<pb n="39"/></p>
<p>“When did she marry Ashley?”</p>
<p>“During the war. Her own true love had just kicked off with
the dysentery.”</p>
<p>“You talk sort of bitter.”</p>
<p>“Sorry. I didn’t mean to. I was just trying to give you the facts.”</p>
<p>“I don’t believe she would marry anybody she didn’t love.”</p>
<p>“Well,” I said. “She’s done it twice.”</p>
<p>“I don’t believe it.”</p>
<p>“Well,” I said, “don’t ask me a lot of fool questions if you don’t
like the answers.”</p>
<p>“I didn’t ask you that.”</p>
<p>“You asked me what I knew about Brett Ashley.”</p>
<p>“I didn’t ask you to insult her.”</p>
<p>“Oh, go to hell.”</p>
<p>He stood up from the table his face white, and stood there
white and angry behind the little plates of hors d’œuvres.</p>
<p>“Sit down,” I said. “Don’t be a fool.”</p>
<p>“You’ve got to take that back.”</p>
<p>“Oh, cut out the prep-school stuff.”</p>
<p>“Take it back.”</p>
<p>“Sure. Anything. I never heard of Brett Ashley. How’s that?</p>
<p>“No. Not that. About me going to hell.”</p>
<p>“Oh, don’t go to hell,” I said. “Stick around. We’re just starting
lunch.”</p>
<p>Cohn smiled again and sat down. He seemed glad to sit down.
What the hell would he have done if he hadn’t sat down? “You
say such damned insulting things, Jake.”</p>
<p>“I’m sorry. I’ve got a nasty tongue. I never mean it when I say
nasty things.”</p>
<p>“I know it,” Cohn said. “You’re really about the best friend I
have, Jake.”</p>
<p>God help you, I thought. “Forget what I said,” I said out loud.
“I’m sorry.”
<pb n="40"/></p>
<p>“It’s all right. It’s fine. I was just sore for a minute.”</p>
<p>“Good. Let’s get something else to eat.”</p>
<p>After we finished the lunch we walked up to the Café de la
Paix and had coffee. I could feel Cohn wanted to bring up Brett
again, but I held him off it. We talked about one thing and another,
and I left him to come to the office.
<pb n="41"/></p></div>
<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 6</p>
<p>At five o’clock I was in the Hotel Crillon waiting for Brett. She
was not there, so I sat down and wrote some letters. They were
not very good letters but I hoped their being on Crillon stationery
would help them. Brett did not turn up, so about quarter to six I
went down to the bar and had a Jack Rose with George the barman.
Brett had not been in the bar either, and so I looked for her
up-stairs on my way out, and took a taxi to the Café Select. Crossing
the Seine I saw a string of barges being towed empty down
the current, riding high, the bargemen at the sweeps as they
came toward the bridge. The river looked nice. It was always
pleasant crossing bridges in Paris.</p>
<p>The taxi rounded the statue of the inventor of the semaphore
engaged in doing same, and turned up the Boulevard Raspail,
and I sat back to let that part of the ride pass. The Boulevard
Raspail always made dull riding. It was like a certain stretch on
the P. L. M. between Fontainebleau and Montereau that always
made me feel bored and dead and dull until it was over. I suppose
<pb n="42"/>
it is some association of ideas that makes those dead places
in a journey. There are other streets in Paris as ugly as the Boulevard
Raspail. It is a street I do not mind walking down at all.
But I cannot stand to ride along it. Perhaps I had read something
about it once. That was the way Robert Cohn was about
all of Paris. I wondered where Cohn got that incapacity to enjoy
Paris. Possibly from Mencken. Mencken hates Paris, I believe.
So many young men get their likes and dislikes from Mencken.</p>
<p>The taxi stopped in front of the Rotonde. No matter what
café in Montparnasse you ask a taxi-driver to bring you to from
the right bank of the river, they always take you to the Rotonde.
Ten years from now it will probably be the Dome. It was near
enough, anyway. I walked past the sad tables of the Rotonde
to the Select. There were a few people inside at the bar, and
outside, alone, sat Harvey Stone. He had a pile of saucers in front
of him, and he needed a shave.</p>
<p>“Sit down,” said Harvey, “I’ve been looking for you.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“Nothing. Just looking for you.”</p>
<p>“Been out to the races?”</p>
<p>“No. Not since Sunday.”</p>
<p>“What do you hear from the States?”</p>
<p>“Nothing. Absolutely nothing.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. I’m through with them. I’m absolutely through
with them.”</p>
<p>He leaned forward and looked me in the eye.</p>
<p>“Do you want to know something, Jake?”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“I haven’t had anything to eat for five days.”</p>
<p>I figured rapidly back in my mind. It was three days ago that
Harvey had won two hundred francs from me shaking poker dice
in the New York Bar.
<pb n="43"/></p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“No money. Money hasn’t come,” he paused. “I tell you it’s
strange, Jake. When I’m like this I just want to be alone. I want
to stay in my own room. I’m like a cat.”</p>
<p>I felt in my pocket.</p>
<p>“Would a hundred help you any, Harvey?”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“Come on. Let’s go and eat.”</p>
<p>“There’s no hurry. Have a drink.”</p>
<p>“Better eat.”</p>
<p>“No. When I get like this I don’t care whether I eat or not.”</p>
<p>We had a drink. Harvey added my saucer to his own pile.</p>
<p>“Do you know Mencken, Harvey?”</p>
<p>“Yes. Why?”</p>
<p>“What’s he like?”</p>
<p>“He’s all right. He says some pretty funny things. Last time I
had dinner with him we talked about Hoffenheimer. ‘The trouble
is,’ he said, ‘he’s a garter snapper.’ That’s not bad.”</p>
<p>“That’s not bad.”</p>
<p>“He’s through now,” Harvey went on. “He’s written about all
the things he knows, and now he’s on all the things he doesn’t
know.”</p>
<p>“I guess he’s all right,” I said. “I just can’t read him.”</p>
<p>“Oh, nobody reads him now,” Harvey said, “except the people
that used to read the Alexander Hamilton Institute.”</p>
<p>“Well,” I said. “That was a good thing, too.”</p>
<p>“Sure,” said Harvey. So we sat and thought deeply for a while.</p>
<p>“Have another port?”</p>
<p>“All right,” said Harvey.</p>
<p>“There comes Cohn,” I said. Robert Cohn was crossing the
street.</p>
<p>“That moron,” said Harvey. Cohn came up to our table.</p>
<p>“Hello, you bums,” he said.
<pb n="44"/></p>
<p>“Hello, Robert,” Harvey said. “I was just telling Jake here that
you’re a moron.”</p>
<p>“What do you mean?”</p>
<p>“Tell us right off. Don’t think. What would you rather do if you
could do anything you wanted?”</p>
<p>Cohn started to consider.</p>
<p>“Don’t think. Bring it right out.”</p>
<p>“I don’t know,” Cohn said. “What’s it all about, anyway?”</p>
<p>“I mean what would you rather do. What comes into your
head first. No matter how silly it is.”</p>
<p>“I don’t know,” Cohn said. “I think I’d rather play football again
with what I know about handling myself, now.”</p>
<p>“I misjudged you,” Harvey said. “You’re not a moron. You’re
only a case of arrested development.”</p>
<p>“You’re awfully funny, Harvey,” Cohn said. “Some day somebody
will push your face in.”</p>
<p>Harvey Stone laughed. “You think so. They won’t, though.
Because it wouldn’t make any difference to me. I’m not a fighter.”</p>
<p>“It would make a difference to you if anybody did it.”</p>
<p>“No, it wouldn’t. That’s where you make your big mistake. Because
you’re not intelligent.”</p>
<p>“Cut it out about me.”</p>
<p>“Sure,” said Harvey. “It doesn’t make any difference to me.
You don’t mean anything to me.”</p>
<p>“Come on, Harvey,” I said. “Have another porto.”</p>
<p>“No,” he said. “I’m going up the street and eat. See you later,
Jake.”</p>
<p>He walked out and up the street. I watched him crossing the
street through the taxis, small, heavy, slowly sure of himself in
the traffic.</p>
<p>“He always gets me sore,” Cohn said. “I can’t stand him.”</p>
<p>“I like him,” I said. “I’m fond of him. You don’t want to get sore
at him.”
<pb n="45"/></p>
<p>“I know it,” Cohn said. “He just gets on my nerves.”</p>
<p>“Write this afternoon?”</p>
<p>“No. I couldn’t get it going. It’s harder to do than my first book.
I’m having a hard time handling it.”</p>
<p>The sort of healthy conceit that he had when he returned from
America early in the spring was gone. Then he had been sure of
his work, only with these personal longings for adventure. Now
the sureness was gone. Somehow I feel I have not shown Robert
Cohn clearly. The reason is that until he fell in love with Brett,
I never heard him make one remark that would, in any way, detach
him from other people. He was nice to watch on the tennis-court,
he had a good body, and he kept it in shape; he handled
his cards well at bridge, and he had a funny sort of undergraduate
quality about him. If he were in a crowd nothing he said stood
out. He wore what used to be called polo shirts at school, and
may be called that still, but he was not professionally youthful.
I do not believe he thought about his clothes much. Externally
he had been formed at Princeton. Internally he had been
moulded by the two women who had trained him. He had a
nice, boyish sort of cheerfulness that had never been trained out
of him, and I probably have not brought it out. He loved to
win at tennis. He probably loved to win as much as Lenglen, for
instance. On the other hand, he was not angry at being beaten.
When he fell in love with Brett his tennis game went all to pieces.
People beat him who had never had a chance with him. He was
very nice about it.</p>
<p>Anyhow, we were sitting on the terrace of the Café Select, and
Harvey Stone had just crossed the street.</p>
<p>“Come on up to the Lilas,” I said.</p>
<p>“I have a date.”</p>
<p>“What time?”</p>
<p>“Frances is coming here at seven-fifteen.”</p>
<p>“There she is.”
<pb n="46"/></p>
<p>Frances Clyne was coming toward us from across the street. She
was a very tall girl who walked with a great deal of movement.
She waved and smiled. We watched her cross the street.</p>
<p>“Hello,” she said, “I’m so glad you’re here, Jake. I’ve been wanting
to talk to you.”</p>
<p>“Hello, Frances,” said Cohn. He smiled.</p>
<p>“Why, hello, Robert. Are you here?” She went on, talking
rapidly. “I’ve had the darndest time. This one”—shaking her head
at Cohn—“didn’t come home for lunch.”</p>
<p>“I wasn’t supposed to.”</p>
<p>“Oh, I know. But you didn’t say anything about it to the cook.
Then I had a date myself, and Paula wasn’t at her office. I went
to the Ritz and waited for her, and she never came, and of course
I didn’t have enough money to lunch at the Ritz——”</p>
<p>“What did you do?”</p>
<p>“Oh, went out, of course.” She spoke in a sort of imitation joyful
manner. “I always keep my appointments. No one keeps
theirs, nowadays. I ought to know better. How are you, Jake,
anyway?”</p>
<p>“Fine.”</p>
<p>“That was a fine girl you had at the dance, and then went off
with that Brett one.”</p>
<p>“Don’t you like her?” Cohn asked.</p>
<p>“I think she’s perfectly charming. Don’t you?”</p>
<p>Cohn said nothing.</p>
<p>“Look, Jake. I want to talk with you. Would you come over
with me to the Dome? You’ll stay here, won’t you, Robert? Come
on, Jake.”</p>
<p>We crossed the Boulevard Montparnasse and sat down at a
table. A boy came up with the <hi rend="italic">Paris Times</hi>, and I bought one and
opened it.</p>
<p>“What’s the matter, Frances?”</p>
<p>“Oh, nothing,” she said, “except that he wants to leave me.”
<pb n="47"/></p>
<p>“How do you mean?”</p>
<p>“Oh, he told every one that we were going to be married, and
I told my mother and every one, and now he doesn’t want to
do it.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“He’s decided he hasn’t lived enough. I knew it would happen
when he went to New York.”</p>
<p>She looked up, very bright-eyed and trying to talk inconsequentially.</p>
<p>“I wouldn’t marry him if he doesn’t want to. Of course I
wouldn’t. I wouldn’t marry him now for anything. But it does
seem to me to be a little late now, after we’ve waited three years,
and I’ve just gotten my divorce.”</p>
<p>I said nothing.</p>
<p>“We were going to celebrate so, and instead we’ve just had
scenes. It’s so childish. We have dreadful scenes, and he cries and
begs me to be reasonable, but he says he just can’t do it.”</p>
<p>“It’s rotten luck.”</p>
<p>“I should say it is rotten luck. I’ve wasted two years and a half
on him now. And I don’t know now if any man will ever want to
marry me. Two years ago I could have married anybody I
wanted, down at Cannes. All the old ones that wanted to marry
somebody chic and settle down were crazy about me. Now I
don’t think I could get anybody.”</p>
<p>“Sure, you could marry anybody.”</p>
<p>“No, I don’t believe it. And I’m fond of him, too. And I’d like
to have children. I always thought we’d have children.”</p>
<p>She looked at me very brightly. “I never liked children much,
but I don’t want to think I’ll never have them. I always thought
I’d have them and then like them.”</p>
<p>“He’s got children.”</p>
<p>“Oh, yes. He’s got children, and he’s got money, and he’s got
a rich mother, and he’s written a book, and nobody will publish
<pb n="48"/>
my stuff; nobody at all. It isn’t bad, either. And I haven’t got any
money at all. I could have had alimony, but I got the divorce the
quickest way.”</p>
<p>She looked at me again very brightly.</p>
<p>“It isn’t right. It’s my own fault and it’s not, too. I ought to have
known better. And when I tell him he just cries and says he can’t
marry. Why can’t he marry? I’d be a good wife. I’m easy to get
along with. I leave him alone. It doesn’t do any good.”</p>
<p>“It’s a rotten shame.”</p>
<p>“Yes, it is a rotten shame. But there’s no use talking about it, is
there? Come on, let’s go back to the café.”</p>
<p>“And of course there isn’t anything I can do.”</p>
<p>“No. Just don’t let him know I talked to you. I know what he
wants.” Now for the first time she dropped her bright, terribly
cheerful manner. “He wants to go back to New York alone, and
be there when his book comes out so when a lot of little chickens
like it. That’s what he wants.”</p>
<p>“Maybe they won’t like it. I don’t think he’s that way. Really.”</p>
<p>“You don’t know him like I do, Jake. That’s what he wants to
do. I know it. I know it. That’s why he doesn’t want to marry. He
wants to have a big triumph this fall all by himself.”</p>
<p>“Want to go back to the café?”</p>
<p>“Yes. Come on.”</p>
<p>We got up from the table—they had never brought us a drink—and
started across the street toward the Select, where Cohn sat
smiling at us from behind the marble-topped table.</p>
<p>“Well, what are you smiling at?” Frances asked him. “Feel pretty
happy?”</p>
<p>“I was smiling at you and Jake with your secrets.”</p>
<p>“Oh, what I’ve told Jake isn’t any secret. Everybody will know
it soon enough. I only wanted to give Jake a decent version.”</p>
<p>“What was it? About your going to England?”
<pb n="49"/></p>
<p>“Yes, about my going to England. Oh, Jake! I forgot to tell you.
I’m going to England.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t that fine!”</p>
<p>“Yes, that’s the way it’s done in the very best families. Robert’s
sending me. He’s going to give me two hundred pounds and then
I’m going to visit friends. Won’t it be lovely? The friends don’t
know about it, yet.”</p>
<p>She turned to Cohn and smiled at him. He was not smiling
now.</p>
<p>“You were only going to give me a hundred pounds, weren’t
you, Robert? But I made him give me two hundred. He’s really
very generous. Aren’t you, Robert?”</p>
<p>I do not know how people could say such terrible things to
Robert Cohn. There are people to whom you could not say insulting
things. They give you a feeling that the world would be
destroyed, would actually be destroyed before your eyes, if you
said certain things. But here was Cohn taking it all. Here it was,
all going on right before me, and I did not even feel an impulse
to try and stop it. And this was friendly joking to what went on
later.</p>
<p>“How can you say such things, Frances?” Cohn interrupted.</p>
<p>“Listen to him. I’m going to England. I’m going to visit friends.
Ever visit friends that didn’t want you? Oh, they’ll have to take
me, all right. ‘How do you do, my dear? Such a long time since
we’ve seen you. And how is your dear mother?’ Yes, how is my
dear mother? She put all her money into French war bonds. Yes,
she did. Probably the only person in the world that did. ‘And what
about Robert?’ or else very careful talking around Robert. ‘You
must be most careful not to mention him, my dear. Poor Frances
has had a most unfortunate experience.’ Won’t it be fun, Robert?
Don’t you think it will be fun, Jake?”</p>
<p>She turned to me with that terribly bright smile. It was very
satisfactory to her to have an audience for this.
<pb n="50"/></p>
<p>“And where are you going to be, Robert? It’s my own fault, all
right. Perfectly my own fault. When I made you get rid of your
little secretary on the magazine I ought to have known you’d get
rid of me the same way. Jake doesn’t know about that. Should I
tell him?”</p>
<p>“Shut up, Frances, for God’s sake.”</p>
<p>“Yes, I’ll tell him. Robert had a little secretary on the magazine.
Just the sweetest little thing in the world, and he thought she
was wonderful, and then I came along and he thought I was
pretty wonderful, too. So I made him get rid of her, and he had
brought her to Provincetown from Carmel when he moved the
magazine, and he didn’t even pay her fare back to the coast. All
to please me. He thought I was pretty fine, then. Didn’t you,
Robert?</p>
<p>“You mustn’t misunderstand, Jake, it was absolutely platonic
with the secretary. Not even platonic. Nothing at all, really. It
was just that she was so nice. And he did that just to please me.
Well, I suppose that we that live by the sword shall perish by the
sword. Isn’t that literary, though? You want to remember that
for your next book, Robert.</p>
<p>“You know Robert is going to get material for a new book.
Aren’t you, Robert? That’s why he’s leaving me. He’s decided I
don’t film well. You see, he was so busy all the time that we were
living together, writing on this book, that he doesn’t remember
anything about us. So now he’s going out and get some new
material. Well, I hope he gets something frightfully interesting.</p>
<p>“Listen, Robert, dear. Let me tell you something. You won’t
mind, will you? Don’t have scenes with your young ladies. Try
not to. Because you can’t have scenes without crying, and then
you pity yourself so much you can’t remember what the other
person’s said. You’ll never be able to remember any conversations
that way. Just try and be calm. I know it’s awfully hard. But
remember, it’s for literature. We all ought to make sacrifices for
<pb n="52"/>
literature. Look at me. I’m going to England without a protest.
All for literature. We must all help young writers. Don’t you
think so, Jake? But you’re not a young writer. Are you, Robert?
You’re thirty-four. Still, I suppose that is young for a great writer.
Look at Hardy. Look at Anatole France. He just died a little while
ago. Robert doesn’t think he’s any good, though. Some of his
French friends told him. He doesn’t read French very well himself.
He wasn’t a good writer like you are, was he, Robert? Do you
think he ever had to go and look for material? What do you suppose
he said to his mistresses when he wouldn’t marry them? I
wonder if he cried, too? Oh, I’ve just thought of something.” She
put her gloved hand up to her lips. “I know the real reason why
Robert won’t marry me, Jake. It’s just come to me. They’ve sent
it to me in a vision in the Café Select. Isn’t it mystic? Some day
they’ll put a tablet up. Like at Lourdes. Do you want to hear,
Robert? I’ll tell you. It’s so simple. I wonder why I never thought
about it. Why, you see, Robert’s always wanted to have a mistress,
and if he doesn’t marry me, why, then he’s had one. She was his
mistress for over two years. See how it is? And if he marries me,
like he’s always promised he would, that would be the end of all
the romance. Don’t you think that’s bright of me to figure that
out? It’s true, too. Look at him and see if it’s not. Where are you
going, Jake?”</p>
<p>“I’ve got to go in and see Harvey Stone a minute.”</p>
<p>Cohn looked up as I went in. His face was white. Why did he
sit there? Why did he keep on taking it like that?</p>
<p>As I stood against the bar looking out I could see them through
the window. Frances was talking on to him, smiling brightly,
looking into his face each time she asked: “Isn’t it so, Robert?” Or
maybe she did not ask that now. Perhaps she said something else.
I told the barman I did not want anything to drink and went out
through the side door. As I went out the door I looked back
<pb n="53"/>
through the two thicknesses of glass and saw them sitting there.
She was still talking to him. I went down a side street to the
Boulevard Raspail. A taxi came along and I got in and gave the
driver the address of my flat.
<pb n="54"/></p></div>

<div type="chapter">
    <p>CHAPTER 7</p>
<p>As I started up the stairs the concierge knocked on the glass of
the door of her lodge, and as I stopped she came out. She had
some letters and a telegram.</p>
<p>“Here is the post. And there was a lady here to see you.”</p>
<p>“Did she leave a card?”</p>
<p>“No. She was with a gentleman. It was the one who was here
last night. In the end I find she is very nice.”</p>
<p>“Was she with a friend of mine?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. He was never here before. He was very large.
Very, very large. She was very nice. Very, very nice. Last night
she was, perhaps, a little—” She put her head on one hand and
rocked it up and down. “I’ll speak perfectly frankly, Monsieur
Barnes. Last night I found her not so gentille. Last night I formed
another idea of her. But listen to what I tell you. She is très, très
gentille. She is of very good family. It is a thing you can see.”</p>
<p>“They did not leave any word?”</p>
<p>“Yes. They said they would be back in an hour.”
<pb n="55"/></p>
<p>“Send them up when they come.”</p>
<p>“Yes, Monsieur Barnes. And that lady, that lady there is some
one. An eccentric, perhaps, but quelqu’une, quelqu’une!”</p>
<p>The concierge, before she became a concierge, had owned a
drink-selling concession at the Paris race-courses. Her life-work
lay in the pelouse, but she kept an eye on the people of the
pesage, and she took great pride in telling me which of my guests
were well brought up, which were of good family, who were
sportsmen, a French word pronounced with the accent on the
men. The only trouble was that people who did not fall into any
of those three categories were very liable to be told there was no
one home, chez Barnes. One of my friends, an extremely underfed-looking
painter, who was obviously to Madame Duzinell
neither well brought up, of good family, nor a sportsman,
wrote me a letter asking if I could get him a pass to get by the
concierge so he could come up and see me occasionally in the
evenings.</p>
<p>I went up to the flat wondering what Brett had done to the
concierge. The wire was a cable from Bill Gorton, saying he was
arriving on the <hi rend="italic">France.</hi> I put the mail on the table, went back to
the bedroom, undressed and had a shower. I was rubbing down
when I heard the door-bell pull. I put on a bathrobe and slippers
and went to the door. It was Brett. Back of her was the count. He
was holding a great bunch of roses.</p>
<p>“Hello, darling,” said Brett. “Aren’t you going to let us in?”</p>
<p>“Come on. I was just bathing.”</p>
<p>“Aren’t you the fortunate man. Bathing.”</p>
<p>“Only a shower. Sit down, Count Mippipopolous. What will you
drink?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know whether you like flowers, sir,” the count said,
“but I took the liberty of just bringing these roses.”</p>
<p>“Here, give them to me.” Brett took them. “Get me some water
in this, Jake.” I filled the big earthenware jug with water in the
<pb n="56"/>
kitchen, and Brett put the roses in it, and placed them in the
centre of the dining-room table.</p>
<p>“I say. We have had a day.”</p>
<p>“You don’t remember anything about a date with me at the
Crillon?”</p>
<p>“No. Did we have one? I must have been blind.”</p>
<p>“You were quite drunk, my dear,” said the count.</p>
<p>“Wasn’t I, though? And the count’s been a brick, absolutely.”</p>
<p>“You’ve got hell’s own drag with the concierge now.”</p>
<p>“I ought to have. Gave her two hundred francs.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be a damned fool.”</p>
<p>“His,” she said, and nodded at the count.</p>
<p>“I thought we ought to give her a little something for last
night. It was very late.”</p>
<p>“He’s wonderful,” Brett said. “He remembers everything that’s
happened.”</p>
<p>“So do you, my dear.”</p>
<p>“Fancy,” said Brett. “Who’d want to? I say, Jake, <hi rend="italic">do we get a
drink?”</hi></p>
<p>“You get it while I go in and dress. You know where it is.”</p>
<p>“Rather.”</p>
<p>While I dressed I heard Brett put down glasses and then a
siphon, and then heard them talking. I dressed slowly, sitting on
the bed. I felt tired and pretty rotten. Brett came in the room, a
glass in her hand, and sat on the bed.</p>
<p>“What’s the matter, darling? Do you feel rocky?”</p>
<p>She kissed me coolly on the forehead.</p>
<p>“Oh, Brett, I love you so much.”</p>
<p>“Darling,” she said. Then: “Do you want me to send him
away?”</p>
<p>“No. He’s nice.”</p>
<p>“I’ll send him away.”</p>
<p>“No, don’t.”
<pb n="57"/></p>
<p>“Yes, I’ll send him away.”</p>
<p>“You can’t just like that.”</p>
<p>“Can’t I, though? You stay here. He’s mad about me, I tell you.”</p>
<p>She was gone out of the room. I lay face down on the bed. I
was having a bad time. I heard them talking but I did not listen.
Brett came in and sat on the bed.</p>
<p>“Poor old darling.” She stroked my head.</p>
<p>“What did you say to him?” I was lying with my face away
from her. I did not want to see her.</p>
<p>“Sent him for champagne. He loves to go for champagne.”</p>
<p>Then later: “Do you feel better, darling? Is the head any
better?”</p>
<p>“It’s better.”</p>
<p>“Lie quiet. He’s gone to the other side of town.”</p>
<p>“Couldn’t we live together, Brett? Couldn’t we just live together?”</p>
<p>“I don’t think so. I’d just <hi rend="italic">tromper</hi> you with everybody. You
couldn’t stand it.”</p>
<p>“I stand it now.”</p>
<p>“That would be different. It’s my fault, Jake. It’s the way I’m
made.”</p>
<p>“Couldn’t we go off in the country for a while?”</p>
<p>“It wouldn’t be any good. I’ll go if you like. But I couldn’t live
quietly in the country. Not with my own true love.”</p>
<p>“I know.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t it rotten? There isn’t any use my telling you I love you.”</p>
<p>“You know I love you.”</p>
<p>“Let’s not talk. Talking’s all bilge. I’m going away from you,
and then Michael’s coming back.”</p>
<p>“Why are you going away?”</p>
<p>“Better for you. Better for me.”</p>
<p>“When are you going?”</p>
<p>“Soon as I can.”
<pb n="58"/></p>
<p>“Where?”</p>
<p>“San Sebastian.”</p>
<p>“Can’t we go together?”</p>
<p>“No. That would be a hell of an idea after we’d just talked it
out.”</p>
<p>“We never agreed.”</p>
<p>“Oh, you know as well as I do. Don’t be obstinate, darling.”</p>
<p>“Oh, sure,” I said. “I know you’re right. I’m just low, and when
I’m low I talk like a fool.”</p>
<p>I sat up, leaned over, found my shoes beside the bed and put
them on. I stood up.</p>
<p>“Don’t look like that, darling.”</p>
<p>“How do you want me to look?”</p>
<p>“Oh, don’t be a fool. I’m going away to-morrow.”</p>
<p>“To-morrow?”</p>
<p>“Yes. Didn’t I say so? I am.”</p>
<p>“Let’s have a drink, then. The count will be back.”</p>
<p>“Yes. He should be back. You know he’s extraordinary about
buying champagne. It means any amount to him.”</p>
<p>We went into the dining-room. I took up the brandy bottle and
poured Brett a drink and one for myself. There was a ring at the
bell-pull. I went to the door and there was the count. Behind him
was the chauffeur carrying a basket of champagne.</p>
<p>“Where should I have him put it, sir?” asked the count.</p>
<p>“In the kitchen,” Brett said.</p>
<p>“Put it in there, Henry,” the count motioned. “Now go down
and get the ice.” He stood looking after the basket inside the
kitchen door. “I think you’ll find that’s very good wine,” he said.
“I know we don’t get much of a chance to judge good wine in the
States now, but I got this from a friend of mine that’s in the
business.”</p>
<p>“Oh, you always have some one in the trade,” Brett said.
<pb n="59"/></p>
<p>“This fellow raises the grapes. He’s got thousands of acres of
them.”</p>
<p>“What’s his name?” asked Brett. “Veuve Cliquot?”</p>
<p>“No,” said the count. “Mumms. He’s a baron.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t it wonderful,” said Brett. “We all have titles. Why
haven’t you a title, Jake?”</p>
<p>“I assure you, sir,” the count put his hand on my arm. “It never
does a man any good. Most of the time it costs you money.”</p>
<p>“Oh, I don’t know. It’s damned useful sometimes,” Brett said.</p>
<p>“I’ve never known it to do me any good.”</p>
<p>“You haven’t used it properly. I’ve had hell’s own amount of
credit on mine.”</p>
<p>“Do sit down, count,” I said. “Let me take that stick.”</p>
<p>The count was looking at Brett across the table under the gas-light.
She was smoking a cigarette and flicking the ashes on the
rug. She saw me notice it. “I say, Jake, I don’t want to ruin your
rugs. Can’t you give a chap an ash-tray?”</p>
<p>I found some ash-trays and spread them around. The chauffeur
came up with a bucket full of salted ice. “Put two bottles in it,
Henry,” the count called.</p>
<p>“Anything else, sir?”</p>
<p>“No. Wait down in the car.” He turned to Brett and to me.
“We’ll want to ride out to the Bois for dinner?”</p>
<p>“If you like,” Brett said. “I couldn’t eat a thing.”</p>
<p>“I always like a good meal,” said the count.</p>
<p>“Should I bring the wine in, sir?” asked the chauffeur.</p>
<p>“Yes. Bring it in, Henry,” said the count. He took out a heavy
pigskin cigar-case and offered it to me. “Like to try a real American
cigar?”</p>
<p>“Thanks,” I said. “I’ll finish the cigarette.”</p>
<p>He cut off the end of his cigar with a gold cutter he wore on
one end of his watch-chain.
<pb n="60"/></p>
<p>“I like a cigar to really draw,” said the count “Half the cigars
you smoke don’t draw.”</p>
<p>He lit the cigar, puffed at it, looking across the table at Brett.
“And when you’re divorced, Lady Ashley, then you won’t have
a title.”</p>
<p>“No. What a pity.”</p>
<p>“No,” said the count. “You don’t need a title. You got class all
over you.”</p>
<p>“Thanks. Awfully decent of you.”</p>
<p>“I’m not joking you,” the count blew a cloud of smoke. “You got
the most class of anybody I ever seen. You got it. That’s all.”</p>
<p>“Nice of you,” said Brett. “Mummy would be pleased. Couldn’t
you write it out, and I’ll send it in a letter to her.”</p>
<p>“I’d tell her, too,” said the count. “I’m not joking you. I never
joke people. Joke people and you make enemies. That’s what I
always say.”</p>
<p>“You’re right,” Brett said. “You’re terribly right. I always joke
people and I haven’t a friend in the world. Except Jake here.”</p>
<p>“You don’t joke him.”</p>
<p>“That’s it.”</p>
<p>“Do you, now?” asked the count. “Do you joke him?”</p>
<p>Brett looked at me and wrinkled up the corners of her eyes.</p>
<p>“No,” she said. “I wouldn’t joke him.”</p>
<p>“See,” said the count. “You don’t joke him.”</p>
<p>“This is a hell of a dull talk,” Brett said. “How about some of
that champagne?”</p>
<p>The count reached down and twirled the bottles in the shiny
bucket. “It isn’t cold, yet. You’re always drinking, my dear. Why
don’t you just talk?”</p>
<p>“I’ve talked too ruddy much. I’ve talked myself all out to Jake.”</p>
<p>“I should like to hear you really talk, my dear. When you talk
to me you never finish your sentences at all.”
<pb n="61"/></p>
<p>“Leave ’em for you to finish. Let any one finish them as they
like.”</p>
<p>“It is a very interesting system,” the count reached down and
gave the bottles a twirl. “Still I would like to hear you talk some
time.”</p>
<p>“Isn’t he a fool?” Brett asked.</p>
<p>“Now,” the count brought up a bottle. “I think this is cool.”</p>
<p>I brought a towel and he wiped the bottle dry and held it up.
“I like to drink champagne from magnums. The wine is better
but it would have been too hard to cool.” He held the bottle,
looking at it. I put out the glasses.</p>
<p>“I say. You might open it,” Brett suggested.</p>
<p>“Yes, my dear. Now I’ll open it.”</p>
<p>It was amazing champagne.</p>
<p>“I say that is wine,” Brett held up her glass. “We ought to toast
something. ‘Here’s to royalty.’ ”</p>
<p>“This wine is too good for toast-drinking, my dear. You don’t
want to mix emotions up with a wine like that. You lose the
taste.”</p>
<p>Brett’s glass was empty.</p>
<p>“You ought to write a book on wines, count,” I said.</p>
<p>“Mr. Barnes,” answered the count, “all I want out of wines is to
enjoy them.”</p>
<p>“Let’s enjoy a little more of this,” Brett pushed her glass forward.
The count poured very carefully. “There, my dear. Now
you enjoy that slowly, and then you can get drunk.”</p>
<p>“Drunk? Drunk?”</p>
<p>“My dear, you are charming when you are drunk.”</p>
<p>“Listen to the man.”</p>
<p>“Mr. Barnes,” the count poured my glass full. “She is the only
lady I have ever known who was as charming when she was drunk
as when she was sober.”</p>
<p>“You haven’t been around much, have you?”
<pb n="62"/></p>
<p>“Yes, my dear. I have been around very much. I have been
around a very great deal.”</p>
<p>“Drink your wine,” said Brett. “We’ve all been around. I dare
say Jake here has seen as much as you have.”</p>
<p>“My dear, I am sure Mr. Barnes has seen a lot. Don’t think I
don’t think so, sir. I have seen a lot, too.”</p>
<p>“Of course you have, my dear,” Brett said. “I was only ragging.”</p>
<p>“I have been in seven wars and four revolutions,” the count
said.</p>
<p>“Soldiering?” Brett asked.</p>
<p>“Sometimes, my dear. And I have got arrow wounds. Have you
ever seen arrow wounds?”</p>
<p>“Let’s have a look at them.”</p>
<p>The count stood up, unbuttoned his vest, and opened his shirt.
He pulled up the undershirt onto his chest and stood, his chest
black, and big stomach muscles bulging under the light.</p>
<p>“You see them?”</p>
<p>Below the line where his ribs stopped were two raised white
welts. “See on the back where they come out.” Above the small
of the back were the same two scars, raised as thick as a finger.</p>
<p>“I say. Those are something.”</p>
<p>“Clean through.”</p>
<p>The count was tucking in his shirt.</p>
<p>“Where did you get those?” I asked.</p>
<p>“In Abyssinia. When I was twenty-one years old.”</p>
<p>“What were you doing?” asked Brett. “Were you in the army?”</p>
<p>“I was on a business trip, my dear.”</p>
<p>“I told you he was one of us. Didn’t I?” Brett turned to me.
“I love you, count. You’re a darling.”</p>
<p>“You make me very happy, my dear. But it isn’t true.”</p>
<p>“Don’t be an ass.”</p>
<p>“You see, Mr. Barnes, it is because I have lived very much that
now I can enjoy everything so well. Don’t you find it like that?”
<pb n="63"/></p>
<p>“Yes. Absolutely.”</p>
<p>“I know,” said the count. “That is the secret. You must get to
know the values.”</p>
<p>“Doesn’t anything ever happen to your values?” Brett asked.</p>
<p>“No. Not any more.”</p>
<p>“Never fall in love?”</p>
<p>“Always,” said the count. “I am always in love.”</p>
<p>“What does that do to your values?”</p>
<p>“That, too, has got a place in my values.”</p>
<p>“You haven’t any values. You’re dead, that’s all.”</p>
<p>“No, my dear. You’re not right. I’m not dead at all.”</p>
<p>We drank three bottles of the champagne and the count left
the basket in my kitchen. We dined at a restaurant in the Bois.
It was a good dinner. Food had an excellent place in the count’s
values. So did wine. The count was in fine form during the meal.
So was Brett. It was a good party.</p>
<p>“Where would you like to go?” asked the count after dinner.
We were the only people left in the restaurant. The two waiters
were standing over against the door. They wanted to go home.</p>
<p>“We might go up on the hill,” Brett said. “Haven’t we had a
splendid party?”</p>
<p>The count was beaming. He was very happy.</p>
<p>“You are very nice people,” he said. He was smoking a cigar
again. “Why don’t you get married, you two?”</p>
<p>“We want to lead our own lives,” I said.</p>
<p>“We have our careers,” Brett said. “Come on. Let’s get out of
this.”</p>
<p>“Have another brandy,” the count said.</p>
<p>“Get it on the hill.”</p>
<p>“No. Have it here where it is quiet.”</p>
<p>“You and your quiet,” said Brett. “What is it men feel about
quiet?”</p>
<p>“We like it,” said the count. “Like you like noise, my dear.”
<pb n="64"/></p>
<p>“All right,” said Brett. “Let’s have one.”</p>
<p>“Sommelier!” the count called.</p>
<p>“Yes, sir.”</p>
<p>“What is the oldest brandy you have?”</p>
<p>“Eighteen eleven, sir.”</p>
<p>“Bring us a bottle.”</p>
<p>“I say. Don’t be ostentatious. Call him off, Jake.”</p>
<p>“Listen, my dear. I get more value for my money in old brandy
than in any other antiquities.”</p>
<p>“Got many antiquities?”</p>
<p>“I got a houseful.”</p>
<p>Finally we went up to Montmartre. Inside Zelli’s it was
crowded, smoky, and noisy. The music hit you as you went in.
Brett and I danced. It was so crowded we could barely move.
The nigger drummer waved at Brett. We were caught in the jam,
dancing in one place in front of him.</p>
<p>“Hahre you?”</p>
<p>“Great.”</p>
<p>“Thaats good.”</p>
<p>He was all teeth and lips.</p>
<p>“He’s a great friend of mine,” Brett said. “Damn good
drummer.”</p>
<p>The music stopped and we started toward the table where the
count sat. Then the music started again and we danced. I looked
at the count. He was sitting at the table smoking a cigar. The
music stopped again.</p>
<p>“Let’s go over.”</p>
<p>Brett started toward the table. The music started and again we
danced, tight in the crowd.</p>
<p>“You are a rotten dancer, Jake. Michael’s the best dancer I
know.”</p>
<p>“He’s splendid.”</p>
<p>“He’s got his points.”
<pb n="65"/></p>
<p>“I like him,” I said. “I’m damned fond of him.”</p>
<p>“I’m going to marry him,” Brett said. “Funny. I haven’t thought
about him for a week.”</p>
<p>“Don’t you write him?”</p>
<p>“Not I. Never write letters.”</p>
<p>“I’ll bet he writes to you.”</p>
<p>“Rather. Damned good letters, too.”</p>
<p>“When are you going to get married?”</p>
<p>“How do I know? As soon as we can get the divorce. Michael’s
trying to get his mother to put up for it.”</p>
<p>“Could I help you?”</p>
<p>“Don’t be an ass. Michael’s people have loads of money.”</p>
<p>The music stopped. We walked over to the table. The count
stood up.</p>
<p>“Very nice,” he said. “You looked very, very nice.”</p>
<p>“Don’t you dance, count?” I asked.</p>
<p>“No. I’m too old.”</p>
<p>“Oh, come off it,” Brett said.</p>
<p>“My dear, I would do it if I would enjoy it. I enjoy to watch
you dance.”</p>
<p>“Splendid,” Brett said. “I’ll dance again for you some time. I
say. What about your little friend, Zizi?”</p>
<p>“Let me tell you. I support that boy, but I don’t want to have
him around.”</p>
<p>“He is rather hard.”</p>
<p>“You know I think that boy’s got a future. But personally I
don’t want him around.”</p>
<p>“Jake’s rather the same way.”</p>
<p>“He gives me the willys.”</p>
<p>“Well,” the count shrugged his shoulders. “About his future you
can’t ever tell. Anyhow, his father was a great friend of my father.”</p>
<p>“Come on. Let’s dance,” Brett said.</p>
<p>We danced. It was crowded and close.
<pb n="66"/></p>
<p>“Oh, darling,” Brett said, “I’m so miserable.”</p>
<p>I had that feeling of going through something that has all happened
before. “You were happy a minute ago.”</p>
<p>The drummer shouted: “You can’t two time—”</p>
<p>“It’s all gone.”</p>
<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know. I just feel terribly.”</p>
<p>“. . . . . .” the drummer chanted. Then turned to his sticks.</p>
<p>“Want to go?”</p>
<p>I had the feeling as in a nightmare of it all being something
repeated, something I had been through and that now I must go
through again.</p>
<p>“. . . . . .” the drummer sang softly.</p>
<p>“Let’s go,” said Brett. “You don’t mind.”</p>
<p>“. . . . . .” the drummer shouted and grinned at Brett.</p>
<p>“All right,” I said. We got out from the crowd. Brett went to the
dressing-room.</p>
<p>“Brett wants to go,” I said to the count. He nodded. “Does she?
That’s fine. You take the car. I’m going to stay here for a while,
Mr. Barnes.”</p>
<p>We shook hands.</p>
<p>“It was a wonderful time,” I said. “I wish you would let me get
this.” I took a note out of my pocket.</p>
<p>“Mr. Barnes, don’t be ridiculous,” the count said.</p>
<p>Brett came over with her wrap on. She kissed the count and
put her hand on his shoulder to keep him from standing up. As
we went out the door I looked back and there were three girls at
his table. We got into the big car. Brett gave the chauffeur the
address of her hotel.</p>
<p>“No, don’t come up,” she said at the hotel. She had rung and
the door was unlatched.</p>
<p>“Really?”</p>
<p>“No. Please.”
<pb n="67"/></p>
<p>“Good night, Brett,” I said. “I’m sorry you feel rotten.”</p>
<p>“Good night, Jake. Good night, darling. I won’t see you again.”
We kissed standing at the door. She pushed me away. We kissed
again. “Oh, don’t!” Brett said.</p>
<p>She turned quickly and went into the hotel. The chauffeur
drove me around to my flat. I gave him twenty francs and he
touched his cap and said: “Good night, sir,” and drove off. I rang
the bell. The door opened and I went up-stairs and went to bed.</p>
</div></div>
    <pb n="68"/>
    <div type="book">
        <p>BOOK II</p>
        <pb n="69"/>
        <div type="chapter">
            <p>CHAPTER 8</p>
        </div>
    </div>
</body>
    </text>
</TEI>
