<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-addison-steele">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Joseph Addison and Richard Steele</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                    </name></author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Headnote by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date>2019-5-26</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#addison-spectator-1"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#addison-spectator-10"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#addison-spectator-37"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#steele-spectator-2"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#steele-spectator-11"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-addison-steele" active="#steele-spectator-65"/>
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are
                made here!</change>
            <change when="2019-01-18" who="editors.xml#TH">ADDED: Tonya Howe, John O'Brien,
                Christine Ruotolo, Winona Salesky, Ally Freeland, Amy Ridderhof, James West, Sabrina
                Koumoin, Sara Brunstetter</change>
            <change when="2019-05-11" who="editors.xml#TH">Added occupation, affiliation, and notes
                to contributor details.</change>
            <change when="2019-05-19" who="editors.xml#TH">Added new contributors</change>
            <change when="2023-02-12" who="editors.xml#JOB">revised text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p> Joseph Addison (1672-1719) and Richard Steele (1672-1729) lived rich lives on their
                own, but here we will briefly talk about them together as a way of introducing the
                collaborative journalism for which they are now best remembered, the essay
                series <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> (1709-1711) and <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> (1711-1712). 
                <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/addison-steele-spectator/addison.jpg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>Born just a few weeks
                apart, Addison and Steele knew each other from the age of thirteen, and they also
                overlapped at Oxford (though they attended different colleges, Addison going to
                Queen's and Magdelen and Steele to Christ Church and Merton). They crossed paths
                again in London in the early part of the eighteenth century; both of them had
                political and literary ambitions. By all accounts, Addison and Steele had very
                different personalities. Addison had many friends and seems to have been brilliant
                at getting influential people to support and help him. But his personal demeanor was
                serious and he wrote ambitious poems and the century's most significant verse
                tragedy, <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> (1713), a play that is rarely staged now but was a staple of the
                repertory for decades. Steele was more a journalist at heart, and his plays are all
                comedies (to be sure, Addison wrote a comedy, too, but it was not very successful,
                whereas Steele had several hits). And a lot of people seemed to be unable to take
                Steele very seriously; he was notorious for running up big debts, and was often
                mocked in the public press of the period. </p>
            <p> Surely part of the difference between the two men and the way that they were
                received by others  had to do with issues of class and ethnicity. Steele was Irish,
                and although he was from a respectable family in Dublin (his father was an attorney)
                he did not have much of a family network in England to help him make his way in the
                world. He almost certainly faced his share of the prejudice against Irish people
                that many English people harbored for centuries. <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/addison-steele-spectator/steele.jpg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>After his time at Oxford (which he
                left without completing a degree), Steele went into the army, and did well, rising
                to become a captain. He started writing poetry and drama as a side project while he
                was still in the military. At some point, though, his military career stalled, and
                he came to London to work in the government; he got a position at court, and took on
                the job of editing the official newspaper, the <hi rend="italic">London Gazette</hi>. Addison was not from
                a particularly wealthy or noble family, either, but the Addisons were well-placed in
                the power structure of the Church of England, the official state church. Addison's
                father Lancelot was the chaplain of the English garrison at Tangier, in Morocco, and
                would later become the Dean of the cathedral at Lichfield. One of Addison's brothers
                became the English governor of Madras, in India. Joseph Addison seems to have been
                identified early on as someone who would have a significant public career. After
                finishing his degree at Oxford, he was sent on a grand tour of the continent at
                government expense, and would go on to be a member of Parliament (he was essentially
                given a seat there; he did not have to campaign) and a cabinet minister. </p>
            <p> Steele left <hi rend="italic">London Gazette</hi> and started <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> in 1709. This journal, which was
                published three times a week, was something new and innovative. Rather than focusing
                on the news, it offered essays on a variety of topics: theater reviews, essays on
                clothing and manners, and so on. It was fast-paced, entertaining, and in an age when
                much print publication was bitterly political, was non-partisan. <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> was
                immediately popular. Steele asked Addison and other friends to join him (it was
                surely hard to come up with enough material on his own), and Addison contributed
                several dozen essays. <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi> folded at the start of 1711, but was almost
                    immediately followed by <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>. Here Addison took the lead, contributing a
                larger number of essays than Steele and, most scholars agree, setting the tone for
                the new journal. <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, which was published every day except Sunday, ran 555
                issues, until finally running out of steam. </p>
            <p> Both journals were widely read in their first publication, and perhaps even more so
                over the course of the next two centuries when they were collected together and
                bound up as book-length volumes. A set of <hi rend="italic">The Tatlers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Spectators</hi> was
                something that every middle-class household with aspirations to looking like its
                members took literature seriously would want to have. These essays were published in
                that kind of format scores of times in the English-speaking world, their essays
                often being offered to students as examples of clear, vigorous English prose; they
                were also translated into most of the European languages. In our time, these essays
                have become newly relevant as having inaugurated what the sociologist Jürgen
                Habermas dubbed "the bourgeois public sphere," a domain of society separate from the
                state or the royal courts where middle class people came together to debate social
                issues. Even more recently, these short, comparatively informal essays, published
                frequently, have been compared to blogging. Well, maybe. Whatever the case, the
                early eighteenth-century journalism of Joseph Addison and Richard Steele remains an
                entertaining look into the attitudes, tastes, and styles of their period. </p>
            
            <lb/>
            <p>At top: Joseph Addison; below, Richard Steele. Both of these portraits were painted by Godfrey Kneller, as part of a series he did around 1710 of portraits of members of the "Kit-Kat Club," a group of Whig politicians who met for drinking and sociability. Both portraits are now in the National Portrait Gallery, London. </p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
