<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-eliot">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Headnote for T. S. Eliot</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Tonya</forename>
                        <surname>Howe</surname>
                    </name></author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Headnote by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date>2023-01-05</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><author>
                        <name>
                            <forename>Tonya</forename>
                            <surname>Howe</surname>
                        </name>
                    </author></bibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-eliot" active="#eliot-waste-land"/>
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are
                made here!</change>
            <change when="2023-01-05" who="editors.xml#TH">headnote XML</change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <graphic
                    url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/eliot-waste-land/notes/eliot-evans.jpeg"
                    style="float:right" width="200px"/>Thomas Sterns Eliot (1888-1965) was born in
                St. Louis, Missouri, to a wealthy family historically from New England; his father
                was a business man, and his mother a social worker and a poet. He lived in St. Louis
                for much of his youth, studying at a college preparatory school affiliated with
                Washington University, before leaving for Massachusetts. He earned a BA from Harvard
                in 1909, and continued on to earn a MA, both degrees in literature. Youthful
                attempts at poetry failed, but during his college years he became much more
                successful and he met many influential people, including the future publisher of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>. Eliot also studied philosophy at the Sorbonne
                and Sanskrit, again at Harvard. It is likely that his natural tendency toward books
                was enhanced by physical limitations caused by a hernia; he that he focused so much
                of his energy on literature. As the first World War broke out, Eliot was heading to
                Oxford on a scholarship, but he spent a lot of time in London, which was accessible
                by train. There, he met the poet Ezra Pound, to whom Eliot dedicated <hi
                    rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>. Having left his first love, Emily Hale, in
                the US, he married Vivienne Haigh-Wood in 1915—though they did not have a happy
                relationship and eventually separated (Vivienne died in a mental asylum, and Eliot
                remarried very late in life to the 30-year old Esme Fletcher. Eliot officially
                renounced US citizenship for British citizenship in 1927. </p>
            <p> Eliot’s first major poetic success was "The Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock,
                published in 1915 in Poetry, an important magazine then edited by Pound. Seven years
                later, he published The Waste Land, and after that, several other poems and plays.
                His playful collection of poems, <hi rend="italic">Old Possum’s Book of Practical
                    Cats</hi>, became the basis for the hit Broadway musical <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cats</hi>. His last major work was <hi rend="italic">The Four Quartets</hi>,
                published in four separate named parts from 1936 to 1942. It was this work that led
                to the Nobel Prize in Literature, which he was awarded in 1948, "for his
                outstanding, pioneer contribution to present-day poetry." Eliot also wrote plays and
                literary criticism. To learn more about Eliot, you might find <ref
                    target="https://www.thoughtco.com/biography-of-t-s-eliot-poet-playwright-and-essayist-4780373"
                    >Angelica Frey’s biography</ref> of interest. This headnote draws on material
                from this article and other commonly available web sources. Eliot was also <ref
                    target="https://forward.com/culture/142722/ts-eliots-on-again-off-again-anti-semitism/"
                    >something of an anti-semite</ref>, often expressing stereotypical beliefs about
                Jewish people. His friend and mentor Ezra Pound, however, was not only anti-Semitic
                but <ref
                    target="https://www.thenation.com/article/archive/coming-to-terms-with-ezra-pounds-politics/"
                    >fascist as well, and under indictment for treason against the US</ref>, he
                ended up in St. Elizabeths Hospital, a federal mental institution near Washington,
                DC. </p>

            <p> Perhaps one of the most challenging and influential of texts in all of Modernist
                literature, The Waste Land features multiple characters, multiple voices, and
                multiple vignettes flitting in and out of visibility. Published in 1922 (first in a
                London journal, then in an American one, and finally as a standalone book with
                footnotes by the author), the long poem is most often examined as a response to the
                shattering experience of the First World War, using the Grail legend as a loosely
                connective thread. The grail has a long and varied literary history, possibly
                beginning with early fertility rituals. In the 12th century, it was given Christian
                meaning through Cretien de Troyes’ early medieval romance Perceval. It is also the
                holy object sought by the Arthurian knights, popularized in Thomas Malory’s Le Morte
                Darthur (1485). The grail in Western Christian contexts is associated with the
                resurrection of Jesus, specifically the cup that was used to hold the blood of
                Christ. Throughout medieval Arthurian romance, the grail was guarded by the Fisher
                King, a Christ-like character, depicted as infertile or wounded—which also becomes a
                metaphor for the state of his kingdom. His wounds (and those of the land) will be
                healed when the quest is completed by the hero asking the Fisher King the right
                question: whom does the grail serve? There are many variations of the story, from
                many different cultural contexts. Eliot uses the grail quest to heal the Fisher King
                as a broad metaphor for the wounded modern world, torn apart by modernity and the
                cataclysmic violence of the Great War. You can see something of the style of modernism in the photographic portrait of Eliot here, by Cecil Beaton (1956), housed in the <ref target="https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/person/mp01450/thomas-stearns-ts-eliot">National Portrait Gallery UK</ref>.</p>
            <p> <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/eliot-waste-land/notes/eliot-beaton.jpeg"
                style="float:right" width="200px"/><hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> is a modernist text. Modernism is a philosophical and aesthetic
                movement of the early 20th century, broadly 1890-1940, which developed after and as
                a result of the innovations of the industrial revolution. The industrial revolution,
                which began in the 18th century and culminated in the middle of the 19th century,
                radically altered the basic nature of life in Western society and ushered in the
                technological era we experience today. In literary history, modernism reached its
                most clear articulation during the period of World War I, which seemed to epitomize
                the mechanized destruction of older forms of human experience. Factory production
                turned people into cogs in a much larger machine; new work in science saw the
                development of mustard gas and other forms of chemical warfare used for the first
                time in World War I; so too with the machine gun, the tank, the bomb, all among the
                new technologies of death that killed millions and demolished the landscape of much
                of Western Europe. The Waste Land was the work that cemented Eliot’s reputation as
                an important writer in the modernist movement. The title of the poem is virtually a
                direct allusion to the effect of shelling. Though Eliot himself dismissed this
                reading, <ref
                    target="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2023/01/ts-eliot-the-waste-land-poem-anniversary/672231/"
                    >it is difficult not to see his work through this lens</ref>. The panoramic
                photograph below, from the <ref target="https://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/205072732">Imperial War Museum</ref>, shows the ruins of a farm after the
                Battle of the Somme in 1916, captured by Lieutenant Ernest Brooks. Modernist poets
                and artists rejected the aesthetic forms of the previous generations and the mode of
                storytelling that often accompanied them—for instance, the realism of the 19th
                century was rejected in favor of fragmented, daring modes of expression that tried
                to capture a new, broken reality. Modernist writers like James Joyce, Virginia
                Woolf, T. S. Eliot, and Gertrude Stein channeled the questions raised by the modern
                world—in particular the question of whether and to what extent it is possible to
                tell stories or make art in this brave new world—into the very fabric of their work.
                Artists in many media were responding as well—in music, Claude Debussey and Igor
                Stravinsky were creating radically new modes of expression; in painting, Georges
                Braque and Pablo Picasso built on the experimentations of the Impressionists, who
                fractured light in pursuit of new ways of seeing. The first portrait of Eliot, above (1920), was painted by Powys Evans, also a modernist most well-known for his caricatures (<ref target="https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/person/mp01450/thomas-stearns-ts-eliot">National Portrait Gallery UK</ref>). To read more about the impact of
                the first World War on the development of modernism in literature, you might find
                this accessible article from <hi rend="italic">The Irish Times</hi> interesting; the
                article touches on <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> and several other key
                pieces of literature from the era. </p>
            <p><graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/eliot-waste-land/notes/somme-1916.jpeg"
                style="float:center" width="60%"/></p>
            <p> Eliot’s poem is as challenging--and rewarding for the curious reader--as it is
                influential; however, it can be read fruitfully without a deep understanding of the
                literary tradition that informs it. For a detailed discussion of the many allusions
                and other references in The Waste Land, see Allyson Booth’s <ref
                    target="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1057/9781137482846#toc">Reading The
                    Waste Land from the Bottom Up</ref> (2015). The first pages of each chapter are
                available as free preview, but your institution may have electronic access to the
                book as a whole. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
