<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-equiano">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Headnote for Olaudah Equiano</title>
                <author>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                    </name></author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date>2019-5-26</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>
                        <name>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </author>
                    <title>Headnote for Olaudah Equiano</title>
                </bibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-equiano"
                        active="#equiano-interesting-narrative"/>
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are
                made here!</change>
            <change when="2019-01-18" who="editors.xml#TH">ADDED: Tonya Howe, John O'Brien,
                Christine Ruotolo, Winona Salesky, Ally Freeland, Amy Ridderhof, James West, Sabrina
                Koumoin, Sara Brunstetter</change>
            <change when="2019-05-11" who="editors.xml#TH">Added occupation, affiliation, and notes
                to contributor details.</change>
            <change when="2019-05-19" who="editors.xml#TH">Added new contributors</change>
            <change when="2024-01-04" who="editors.xml#TH">Added attribute material to images</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><graphic
                url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/equiano-interesting-narrative/equiano-frontispiece.jpeg" style="flaot:right" width="300px" alt="frontispiece portrait of Equiano" source="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/equiano-interesting-narrative/equiano-frontispiece.jpeg" desc="Frontispiece portrait of Equiano, from 'The Interesting Narrative'"/>
                <hi rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano</hi> is
                the first example in English of the slave narrative, the autobiography written by
                one of the millions of persons from Africa or of African descent who were enslaved
                in the Atlantic world between the sixteenth and the nineteenth centuries. Equiano’s
                is an extraordinary memoir, telling the author’s life story from his birth in west
                Africa, in what was then known as Essaka (in what is now the nation of Nigeria), his
                kidnapping, the middle passage across the Atlantic ocean in a slave ship, the
                brutality of the slave system in the American colonies in the Caribbean, the
                mainland of North America, and at sea. Equiano also tells the story of his life as a
                free man of color; after he was finally able to purchase his freedom in 1766, he was
                a merchant, a seaman, a musician, a barber, a civil servant, and, finally, a writer
                who took to the pages of London newspapers to argue on behalf of his fellow
                Afro-Britons before publishing this account of his life. </p>

            <p>Equiano’s book offered the first full description of the middle passage, a
                description harrowing in its sensory vividness:</p>

            <p><hi rend="italic">The stench of the hold while we were on the coast was so
                    intolerably loathsome, that it was dangerous to remain there for any time, and
                    some of us had been permitted to stay on the deck for the fresh air; but now
                    that the whole ship’s cargo were confined together, it became absolutely
                    pestilential. The closeness of the place, and the heat of the climate, added to
                    the number in the ship, which was so crowded that each had scarcely room to turn
                    himself, almost suffocated us. This produced copious perspirations, so that the
                    air soon became unfit for respiration, from a variety of loathsome smells, and
                    brought on a sickness among the slaves, of which many died, thus falling victims
                    to the improvident avarice, as I may call it, of their purchasers. This wretched
                    situation was again aggravated by the galling of the chains, now become
                    insupportable; and the filth of the necessary tubs, into which the children
                    often fell, and were almost suffocated. The shrieks of the women, and the groans
                    of the dying, rendered the whole a scene of horror almost inconceivable. Happily
                    perhaps for myself I was soon reduced so low here that it was thought necessary
                    to keep me almost always on deck; and from my extreme youth I was not put in
                    fetters. In this situation I expected every hour to share the fate of my
                    companions, some of whom were almost daily brought upon deck at the point of
                    death, which I began to hope would soon put an end to my miseries. Often did I
                    think many of the inhabitants of the deep much more happy than myself. I envied
                    them the freedom they enjoyed, and as often wished I could change my condition
                    for theirs. Every circumstance I met with served only to render my state more
                    painful, and heighten my apprehensions, and my opinion of the cruelty of the
                    whites.</hi></p>

            <p>Equiano’s book is both a personal story and a powerful item of testimony about the
                larger system of slave-trading that supported the economic system through which
                Britain developed a global empire. Spanning the transatlantic world, Equiano’s story
                powerfully captures the lived experience of slavery in the eighteenth century
                through the eyes of an observer with almost unbelievable resourcefulness and
                resilience. The book is also interesting as a literary document. Equiano is clearly
                familiar with the genre of the spiritual autobiography, the Puritan form of
                self-examination and life writing that shaped works such as Defoe’s <ref
                    target="https://anthologydev.lib.virginia.edu/work/Defoe/defoe-crusoe"><hi
                        rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi></ref>, and he also cites English poets
                such as John Milton and Alexander Pope, demonstrating his mastery of the canon of
                great English literature. Equiano’s <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> is
                one of the most absorbing, indeed <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi> first-person
                stories of the entire century, a work that both narrates a remarkable set of
                experiences and shrewdly shapes it through the forms available to its author to make
                the case for the abolition of the slave trade.</p>

            <p>It is important to note, however, that in the last two decades, scholars have raised
                doubts about the truth of some parts of Equiano’s <hi rend="italic">Interesting
                    Narrative</hi>. Vincent Carretta, probably the leading scholar in the United
                States on Equiano’s work and life, has discovered documents such as Royal Navy
                muster rolls where Equiano (who was identified for much of his adult life as
                “Gustavus Vassa,” the name given to him by Michael Pascal, his first owner) is
                recorded as having been born in colonial South Carolina. So too does the record of
                his baptism into Christianity in 1759 at St. Margaret’s Church in London. It is
                possible, then, that Equiano is misrepresenting his place of birth, perhaps because
                he believed that his story would be more compelling if he were able to describe
                himself as a native-born African. Other scholars have suggested that there may be
                other reasons to account for the discrepancy; Equiano was not responsible for
                creating these records, and there may be all sorts of reasons why the people who
                were in charge of these documents, or he, might have decided not to have identified
                him as having born in Africa, some of which we probably cannot reconstruct from this
                distance. The question of where Equiano was born will probably remain unresolved
                until better documentary evidence or new ways of understanding the evidence that we
                already have become available. What no one has ever questioned is that Equiano’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> is extremely accurate in its depiction
                of the way that the eighteenth-century slave system worked, the horrors of the
                middle passage, and the constant threats to their freedom and well-being experienced
                by free people of color, particularly in the American colonies.</p>

            <p>The publication of the <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> was an important
                event in its own right. First issued in the spring of 1789, the book was timed to
                coincide with a Parliamentary initiative to end Britain’s participation in the
                international slave trade. This was the goal of the first abolitionist movement, a
                movement originating largely with Quakers that was adopted and secularized by a
                combination of evangelical and more secular writers in the 1780s and that found its
                institutional centers of gravity in the largely white Society for Effecting the
                Abolition of the Slave Trade, founded in 1787, and in the Sons of Africa, a society
                of free persons of African descent in Great Britain in which Equiano had a
                leadership role. This generation of abolitionists focused on ending the slave trade
                rather than for the ending of slavery as an institution and the emancipation of all
                enslaved people in large part because they believed it to be unviable politically.
                Rather, they focused on ending the slave trade, arguing that if slave owners were
                unable to purchase new slaves kidnapped and transported from Africa, they would be
                forced to be more benevolent to their own slaves, and the institution would be
                forced to reform itself. Equiano was active in these abolitionist circles, and his
                book in part serves the function of a petition to Parliament to end the slave trade,
                with the names of the book’s subscribers identifying themselves as allies and
                co-petitioners in the cause. The first edition begins by including the names of 311
                people who subscribed to it and thereby subsidized its printing, and later editions
                (nine in all in Equiano’s lifetime, a testimony to the great demand for his book)
                added more, eventually totalling over a thousand, as more people wanted both to own
                the book and to ally themselves with the abolitionist cause. Subscribers were thus
                taking an interest in this book in the financial sense, publicly advancing resources
                to support Equiano and the movement that the book was published to support. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> was first printed in the United States
                in New York in 1791 (without Equiano’s permission, as was typical for books
                reprinted from Britain in the early decades of the new republic), and was widely
                reprinted throughout the first half of the nineteenth century.</p>

            <p>Equiano toured throughout the British Isles in the early 1790s, making speaking
                engagements to promote the abolitionist cause, and also to support sales of his
                book, for which he had retained copyright. This turned out to be a smart business
                decision; he made a fair amount of money from sales of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Interesting Narrative</hi>. Equiano married a woman named Susannah Cullen in
                1792; they had two daughters, only one of whom survived to adulthood. But neither
                Olaudah or Susannah was able to enjoy their married life for very long. Susanna died
                in 1796 and Olaudah died in 1797. The abolitionist cause to which the <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> was a major contributor succeeded only
                after his death, as Britain ended its participation in the slave trade in 1807, and
                finally abolished slavery in its colonial holdings in 1833. Slavery in the United
                States continued until the Emancipation Proclamation of 1863.</p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
