<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-finch">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Headnote for Anne Finch</title>
                <author>
                     <name><forename>James</forename><surname>West</surname></name>
                     <name><forename>Tonya</forename><surname>Howe</surname></name>
                </author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
               <respStmt>
                    <resp>Headnote by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JW">James West</name>
                </respStmt>               
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <publisher></publisher>
                <date>2018-07-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-finch" active="#finch-nightingale"/>
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are made here!</change>
            <change when="2019-01-18" who="editors.xml#TH">ADDED: Tonya Howe, John O'Brien, Christine Ruotolo, Winona Salesky, Ally Freeland, Amy Ridderhof, James West, Sabrina Koumoin, Sara Brunstetter</change>
            <change when="2019-05-11" who="editors.xml#TH">Added occupation, affiliation, and notes to contributor details.</change>
            <change when="2019-05-19" who="editors.xml#TH">Added new contributors</change>
            <change when="2024-01-04" who="editors.xml#TH">Added attribute material to images</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><graphic
                url="https://collectionimages.npg.org.uk/large/mw06861/Anne-Finch-Countess-of-Winchilsea.jpg"
                style="float:right" width="300px" source="https://collectionimages.npg.org.uk/large/mw06861" alt="portrait of Anne Finch, Countess of Winchilsea, miniature watercolor by Peter Cross (c.1690)" source="https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/portrait/mw06861" desc="Miniature watercolor portrait of Finch (National Portrait Gallery, UK)"/> Anne Finch, Countess of Winchilsea,
                was born in April 1661 to Anne Haselwood and Sir William Kingsmill. At age
                twenty-one she was appointed maid of honor to <ref
                    target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-of-Modena">Mary Modena</ref>,
                the wife of the Duke of York, in the Court of Charles II. During her time in the
                Court, <ref target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/anne-finch">Anne
                    Kingsmill</ref> was courted by and eventually married to Colonel Heneage Finch.
                In 1689, after a shift in political power, the Finches faced monetary problems and
                moved several times, eventually settling in <placeName type="tgn" key="7027563"
                    >Eastwell</placeName> with their nephew.</p>
            <p>As a woman writer in the <ref
                target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/learn/glossary-terms/augustan-age"
                >Augustan era</ref>, Finch was also out of place. <ref
                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=-JldIaiQvkEC">Barbara McGovern's 2002
                    critical biography of Finch</ref> explores these displacements both in her life
                and her poetry. Finch struggled, as McGovern notes, to define her poetic identity
                in an era when women were excluded from the conditions that would allow them to
                cultivate their minds or their voices. The poet was seen as male, and publishing
                poetry, a masculine, public activity; for a woman to do so was, in the Augustan
                period, risque and licentious (See Katherine Rogers' essay, "Anne Finch, Countess
                of Winchelsea: An Augustan Woman Writer," in <ref
                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pE-gBAAAQBAJ">Pacheco 227</ref>);
                Finch had to negotiate these competing cultural rules in her poetry. </p>
            <p>Finch's
                poetry from 1701-1714 was wide ranging. She wrote on subjects typically allowed to
                be feminine, like her love for her husband, but she also wrote about public and
                political issues, like the succession of power in London. In 1701, Finch
                anonymously published <hi rend="italic">"Upon the Death of King James the
                    Second"</hi>. Poems such as <ref
                        target="http://www.eighteenthcenturypoetry.org/works/o4784-w0160.shtml">"The
                        Spleen"</ref>and <ref
                            target="http://www.eighteenthcenturypoetry.org/works/o4784-w0020.shtml">"All is
                            Vanity"</ref> exemplify the idea of faith despite tribulation, a subject she
                explored often. Prior to the 1713 publication of <hi rend="italic">Miscellany
                    Poems on Several Occasions</hi>, Finch circulated private manuscripts of her
                poems and gained a favorable literary reputation. For more information on women
                writers and manuscript circulation, see George Justice's introduction to <ref
                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=2v_RciKgeuAC"><hi rend="italic"
                        >Women's Writing and the Circulation of Ideas: Manuscript Publication in
                        England, 1550-1800</hi></ref> (2002) or Margaret Ezell's <ref
                            target="https://books.google.com/books?id=45lAXaDsjz0C"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Social Authorship and the Advent of Print</hi></ref>
                (1999).</p>
            <p><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=pE-gBAAAQBAJ">Rogers
                emphasizes Finch's Augustan roots, highlighting her use of form</ref> as well
                as her love poetry, satirical prose, and ideas on the relationship between man and
                nature (225). According to Rogers, Finch became one of the few female authors in
                the Augustan era to successfully master the masculine rules of the literary
                tradition. During the early modern period, women "frequently found themselves
                denied opportunities for publication and serious public reception, or had their
                writings denigrated and trivialized by a patriarchal literary world" (<ref
                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=-JldIaiQvkEC">McGovern 2</ref>)--as
                detailed in Finch's poem "The Introduction," which remained unpublished during her
                lifetime. Finch was able to make her voice heard by working within the masculine
                restraints of Augustan form.</p>
            <p>Finch died on August 5, 1720. According to the <hi
                rend="italic"><ref target="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/anne-finch"
                    >National Poetry Foundation</ref></hi> the first recognized modern edition
                of her work was released in 1903. Since the advent of feminist recovery criticism
                in the 1970s and 1980s, Anne Finch has gained critical acclaim; she is now
                regarded as one of the most important English women writers of the 18th century.
                The image to the right shows a <ref
                    target="https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/portrait/mw06861">miniature
                    watercolor portrait of Anne Finch by Peter Cross</ref>, housed in the National
                Portrait Gallery, London.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>