<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-philips">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Headnote for Katherine Philips</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>John</forename>
                    <surname>O'Brien</surname></author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Headnote by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date>2019-5-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><author>
                        <name>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </author></bibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-philips"
                        active="#philips-rosania #philips-double-murder #philips-god-reconciling-world #philips-3-september #philips-dearest-lucasia #philips-to-the-duchess-of-york #philips-death #philips-death-walter-lloid-knight #philips-religion #philips-against-pleasure"
                    />
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are
                made here!</change>
            <change when="2024-01-04" who="editors.xml#TH">Added attribute material to
                images</change>
            <change when="2025-09-02" who="editors.xml#JOB">minor corrections</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><graphic
                url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c7/Portrait_of_Catherine_Philips_%284674221%29.jpg" source="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Portrait_of_Catherine_Philips_(4674221).jpg" alt="Engraved portrait of Katherine Philips" desc="Portrait of Katherine Philips by William Faithorne (Wikimedia Commons)"
                    style="float:center" width="500px"/> Katherine Philips (1632-1664) had one of the
                most interesting and richest–if short–writing careers of any poet in English in the
                seventeenth century. Philips is remembered now as a <hi rend="italic">coterie</hi> poet, that is, a poet
                whose first audience was family and friends, intimate acquaintances who knew her
                well. Philips made friendship and family into the major themes and topics of her
                poetry. She gave her friends code names: her husband James, for example, was known
                in her poems as “Antenor”; her best female friend Ann Owen was called “Lucasia”;
                Philips identified herself in her poetry as “Orinda.” Toward the end of her short
                life (she died of smallpox in 1664; she was only 32), Philips was becoming more
                widely known to readers in England when her works, which had previously circulated
                only in manuscript copies, began to be given a wider circulation through being
                printed for the first time. Critics and readers hailed her as the “matchless Orinda”
                for the elegance of her writing and the calm intelligence and grace of the persona
                she constructed for herself in her verse. She also did some translations of French
                plays into English. She translated Pierre Corneille’s tragedy <hi rend="italic">La Mort de Pompee</hi> from
                French into English and the play was performed in Dublin and then in London. At the time
                of Philips's death, she was working on a translation of Corneille’s play <hi rend="italic">Horace</hi>. For
                decades to come, the figure of “Orinda” lived on in the memory of readers, becoming
                the idealized emblem of the female writer, the literary lady whose talent and moral
                virtue shone through her work.</p>

            <p>Because so much of Katherine Philips's writing is about her friends, and because her career
                possibilities were so fully shaped by the political transformations that she
                witnessed in her lifetime, it is worth giving attention to her life story. Philips
                was born as Katherine Fowler in London in 1632. Her father was a cloth merchant, and
                her family seems to have shared the Puritan affinities that were common in
                middle-class trading circles in that era. But after her marriage to James Philips--a
                24-year-old widower who was related to her stepfather--in 1648, Katherine spent most
                of her adult life in the countryside, in Wales, and seems to have been sympathetic
                to the royalist cause and to more conventional Anglicanism--even though her husband
                affiliated with the anti-Royalist Parliamentary cause and the Commonwealth
                government that ruled Britain from 1649 to 1660. (For many years, it was believed
                that James Philips was 54 years old at the time of the marriage, but that has been
                corrected recently; in spite of his comparative youth, however, he was already
                widowed, and would be again when Katherine died in 1664). In spite of the split in
                their political sympathies, Katherine and James seem to have had a happy marriage.
                James’s poetic name “Antenor,” given to him by Katherine, refers to the ancient
                Trojan who tried to make peace between Greece and Troy during the Trojan War,
                suggesting that Katherine admired her husband’s moderation and desire to find common
                ground between opposing camps.</p>

            <p>Living in Wales, far from her London family, Philips may have used poetry as a means
                of keeping in contact with her circle of friends and relatives. And, too, writing
                about friendship, giving pet names to acquaintances, became popular among people
                associated with the British court during the years of the Commonwealth in the 1650s,
                when part of the Stuart court was in exile, and when its sympathizers in Britain
                itself had to lie low. Idealizing friendship and Platonic love was a good way of
                keeping family bonds and the court culture alive, and coteries such as Philips’s
                emerged as ways in which the identity of a group was kept alive in spite of distance
                and political hazards.</p>

            <p>Philips’s friends read her poems in manuscript, perhaps in a copy that Philips
                herself wrote out. Such a copy is called an “autograph” copy, and one of these that
                contains many of Philips’s poems has survived. Other copies would be made by friends
                or by professional scribes. With so much hand-copying going on, changes, revisions,
                and mistakes are very common. Poems circulated in this way often exist in multiple
                versions, as authors revised their works over time, or, perhaps, as others in the
                coterie amended the original text. Often, the manuscript versions are so different
                from one another that we will never know which one is the real, authoritative
                version. Or, maybe even better, the conditions of coterie writing and “publication”
                remind us that in many cases the idea of a single authoritative text is more an
                illusion than a reality; texts are always changeable, subject to forces well beyond
                their originator’s control.</p>

            <p>In such a context, having one’s poems printed for general readers seems like a
                violation of privacy, as it exposes texts that were intended for an audience of
                people you know intimately to a public that you do not know. When Philips’s poems were first printed, it was because
                an unscrupulous publisher managed to get hold of a manuscript copy and printed them
                against her will. Philips was angry, and managed to get what she called “this false
                Edition of my Verses” suppressed. It was only in 1667, three years after her death,
                that a family friend, Sir Charles Cotterell, probably working in collaboration with
                James Philips, published a handsome printed edition of her poetry that helped set
                the terms under which her writing was read and interpreted for generations. For a
                long time after her death, Katherine Philips lived on in the memory of readers as
                “Orinda,” the ideal of a woman writer, living a life of elegant retirement and
                writing beautiful verse on domestic topics. This was an idealization that does not
                capture the range of Philips’s engagements and interests, which included religion,
                philosophy, and politics. Philips was a poet of great gifts and complex political
                affiliations whose career was about to enter a new and more public phase when it was
                interrupted by her death.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
