<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="headnote-whitman">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Headnote for Walt Whitman</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                    </name></author>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</principal>
                <principal ref="editors.xml#CR">Christine Ruotolo</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Headnote by</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date>2024-04-19</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-whitman" active="#whitman-america"/>
                    <relation type="headnote" passive="#headnote-whitman" active="#whitman-songs"/>
                </listRelation>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change type="reminder">Please be sure to update the publication date when changes are
                made here!</change>
            <change when="2019-01-18" who="editors.xml#TH">ADDED: Tonya Howe, John O'Brien,
                Christine Ruotolo, Winona Salesky, Ally Freeland, Amy Ridderhof, James West, Sabrina
                Koumoin, Sara Brunstetter</change>
            <change when="2019-05-11" who="editors.xml#TH">Added occupation, affiliation, and notes
                to contributor details.</change>
            <change when="2024-04-19" who="editors.xml#JOB">Added Whitman headnote</change>
            
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p> Imagine that it is the summer of 1855, and that you have wandered into a book shop in Brooklyn, New York. On a front table, along with other just-published books, you see a slender volume with a distinctive, embossed and gilded green cover. The title is <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass.</hi> 
                
                <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/headnote-whitman/leaves-cover.jpg" width="300px" style="float:right" alt="cover of Walt Whitman's Leaves of Grass" source="Walt Whitman Archive" desc="Cover of 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass."/>
                
                You are intrigued; is this a book about gardening, maybe? Opening the book, you are surprised to discover that this is a book of poetry, and you turn to a poem, also entitled “Leaves of Grass.” It is unlike any poem that you have ever seen before. The lines vary from very short to extremely long. There are very few rhymes, but the rhythms of the poem are beautiful, like incantations or Biblical verses:</p> 
            <lg>
                <l>I celebrate myself, and sing myself,</l>
                <l>And what I assume you shall assume.</l>
                <l>For every atom belonging to me as good belongs to you.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And so on: pages and pages of beautiful, hypnotic verse, spoken by voice that invites the reader in to celebrate a shared world of sensual pleasures, among them the sheer pleasure of language itself. No author is identified on the title page. But there is a portrait of a man in the place where author’s portraits tend to be. This too is stange: the man is not dressed in the kind of respectable suit that you would expect, but in workingman’s clothes, with his undershirt visible. You are intrigued; you purchase the book.</p>
            
            <p>The author, of course, was Walt Whitman, and <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> would become one of the most important works in all of American literature. The book seemed to come out of nowhere. Whitman was at this point 36 years old, unmarried and working odd construction jobs and living with his parents in Brooklyn, while contributing freelance poetry, stories, and essays to a number of publications. To this point, his most substantial published work had been a serialized novel, <hi rend="italic">The Life and Adventures of Jack Engel: An Auto-Biography</hi>, published in the <hi rend="italic">New York Sunday Dispatch</hi> in March and April 1852. (It's a strange book, a novel advancing the cause of temperance--that is, avoiding alcohol--that, because it was published anonymously, was not realized to be by Whitman until only the last few years.<hi rend="italic"> Leaves of Grass </hi> was something quite different: a full-sized book, of poetry that did not always look like poetry, in a voice that was very different from any poetic voice that had been heard before.. The book got some attention early on, when Whitman solicited, and received, the endorsement of Ralph Waldo Emerson, endorsement that Whitman published in a New York newspaper and put in the next printing of the book, a move that surprised and disconcerted Emerson. Among Whitman’s many skills was that of self-promotion.
                <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.amazonaws.com/headnote-whitman/whitman-frontispiece.png" width="300px" style="float:right" alt="frontispiece" source="Walt Whitman Archive" desc="Frontispiece portrait of Walt Whitman, from 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass"/></p>
            
            <p>In the years since, <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> has been an influence on many poets, establishing a line of loose-limbed, colloquial verse that runs from Whitman through Edna St. Vincent Millay, Allen Ginsberg and many others. Whitman's works have been set to music by something like 500 different composers. Whitman set out to become what he called an “American Bard,” the poet of a nation that still felt new in his lifetime; as an adult, Whitman fondly recalled being hoisted as a child on the shoulders of Lafayette during the Revolutionary War hero’s visit to Brooklyn in 1826. The integrity of that nation would be tested a few years after the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> by the outbreak of the American Civil War. Whitman moved to Washington, where he held clerical jobs and volunteered in hospitals to help care for wounded soldiers. Whitman maintained his faith in the project of American democracy through the war and after.</p>
            
            
            <p>Multiple editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> followed that first publication in Brooklyn in 1855. In each one, Whitman revised and expanded, adding new poems, rearranging them, giving them new names. The central poem in each version, and the most important poem of Whitman’s career, is the poem that became known as “Song of Myself,” which celebrates Whitman, America, the human body, and life itself. Our edition of Whitman’s poems is taken from the last edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, published in 1892. </p>
            
           
            
            <lb/>
            

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
