<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="franklin-dogood-4">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Silence Dogood 4</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <date when="1722">April 2, 1722</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <title type="sub">4</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    May 14, 1722 [No. 4] <lb/><lb/>
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi>An sum etiam nunc vel Graecè loqui vel Latinè docendus?</hi> Cicero.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"Should I be taught to speak either Greek or Latin?" Franklin is quoting here from the Roman orator Cicero. The essay that follows, taking the form of a dream vision, is a satire on Harvard College and its requirement that students study Greek and Latin.</note> <lb/><lb/>
                    To the Author of the <hi>New-England Courant</hi>. <lb/><lb/><lb/>
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Discoursing the other Day at Dinner with my Reverend Boarder, formerly mention'd, (whom for Distinction sake we will call by the Name of Clericus,) concerning the Education of Children, I ask'd his Advice about my young Son William, whether or no I had best bestow upon him Academical Learning, or (as our Phrase is) <hi>bring him up at our College</hi>: He perswaded me to do it by all Means, using many weighty Arguments with me, and answering all the Objections that I could form against it; telling me withal, that he did not doubt but that the Lad would take his Learning very well, and not idle away his Time as too many there now-a-days do. These Words of Clericus gave me a Curiosity to inquire a little more strictly into the present Circumstances of that famous <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Seminary</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A place of education such as a school or a college. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of Learning; but the Information which he gave me, was neither pleasant, nor such as I expected.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>As soon as Dinner was over, I took a solitary Walk into my Orchard, still ruminating on Clericus's Discourse with much Consideration, until I came to my usual Place of Retirement under the <hi>Great Apple-Tree</hi>; where having seated my self, and carelessly laid my Head on a <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">verdant</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Green; of vegetation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Bank, I fell by Degrees into a soft and undisturbed Slumber. My waking Thoughts remained with me in my Sleep, and before I awak'd again, I dreamt the following Dream.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I fancy'd I was travelling over pleasant and delightful Fields and Meadows, and thro' many small Country Towns and Villages; and as I pass'd along, all Places resounded with the Fame of the Temple of Learning: Every Peasant, who had wherewithal, was preparing to send one of his Children at least to this famous Place; and in this Case most of them consulted their own Purses instead of their Childrens Capacities: So that I observed, a great many, <!-- YEA? -->yea, the most part of those who were travelling thither, were little better than Dunces and Blockheads. Alas! alas!</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>At length I entred upon a spacious Plain, in the Midst of which was erected a large and stately Edifice: It was to this that a great Company of Youths from all Parts of the Country were going; so stepping in among the Crowd, I passed on with them, and presently arrived at the Gate.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>The Passage was kept by two sturdy <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Porters</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Gatekeepers. Source: Oxford English Dictionoary</note> named <hi>Riches and Poverty</hi>, and the latter obstinately refused to give Entrance to any who had not first gain'd the Favour of the former; so that I observed, many who came even to the very Gate, were obliged to travel back again as ignorant as they came, for want of this necessary Qualification. However, as a <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Spectator</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT-DC add more?)A nod to the series of letters, The Spectator, which Franklin used as a heavy influence for his Silence Dogood letters.</note> I gain'd Admittance, and with the rest entred directly into the Temple.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>In the Middle of the great Hall stood a stately and magnificent Throne, which was ascended to by two high and difficult Steps. On the Top of it sat Learning in awful State; she was apparelled wholly in Black, and surrounded almost on every Side with innumerable Volumes in all Languages. She seem'd very busily employ'd in writing something on half a Sheet of Paper, and upon Enquiry, I understood she was preparing a Paper, call'd, <hi>The New-England Courant</hi>. On her Right Hand sat <hi>English</hi>, with a pleasant smiling Countenance, and handsomely attir'd; and on her left were seated several <hi>Antique Figures</hi> with their Faces vail'd. I was considerably puzzl'd to guess who they were, until one informed me, (who stood beside me,) that those Figures on her left Hand were <hi>Latin</hi>, <hi>Greek</hi>, <hi>Hebrew</hi>, &amp;c. and that they were very much reserv'd, and seldom or never unvail'd their Faces here, and then to few or none, tho' most of those who have in this Place acquir'd so much Learning as to distinguish them from <hi>English</hi>, pretended to an intimate Acquaintance with them. I then enquir'd of him, what could be the Reason why they continued vail'd, in this Place especially: He pointed to the Foot of the Throne, where I saw <hi>Idleness</hi>, attended with <hi>Ignorance</hi>, and these (he informed me) were they, who first vail'd them, and still kept them so.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Now I observed, that the whole Tribe who entred into the Temple with me, began to climb the Throne; but the Work proving troublesome and difficult to most of them, they withdrew their Hands from the Plow, and contented themselves to sit at the Foot, with Madam <hi>Idleness</hi> and her Maid <hi>Ignorance</hi>, until those who were assisted by Diligence and a <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">docible</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Ready to be taught; submissive to instruction. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Temper, had well <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">nigh</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Near or almost. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> got up the first Step: But the Time drawing nigh in which they could no way avoid ascending, they were <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">fain</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Happy, please. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to crave the Assistance of those who had got up before them, and who, for the Reward perhaps of a <hi>Pint of Milk</hi>, or a <hi>Piece of <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Plumb-Cake</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">A fruit-cake packed full of different types of candied and dried fruits such as plums, raisins, and orange peel. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></hi>, lent the <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Lubbers</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">A large clumsy idiot who is often lazy and idle. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> a helping Hand, and sat them in the Eye of the World, upon a Level with themselves.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>The other Step being in the same Manner ascended, and the usual Ceremonies at an End, every <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Beetle-Scull</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">(DRAFT)I assume this is some kind of insult but I can't find any reference to it except here.</note> seem'd well satisfy'd with his own Portion of Learning, tho' perhaps he was <hi>e'en just</hi> as ignorant as ever. And now the Time of their Departure being come, they march'd out of Doors to make Room for another Company, who waited for Entrance: And I, having seen all that was to be seen, quitted the hall likewise, and went to make my Observations on those who were just gone out before me.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Some I perceiv'd took to <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Merchandizing</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">Engaged in the selling and trade of goods. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, others to Travelling, some to one Thing, some to another, and some to Nothing; and many of them from henceforth, for want of <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Patrimony</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Property that, by ancient right, belongs to an institution. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, liv'd as poor as <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Church Mice</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">The expression "church mice" is used to attribute people as poor and quiet. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, being unable to dig, and asham'd to beg, and to live by their Wits it was impossible. But the most Part of the Crowd went along a large beaten Path, which led to a Temple at the further End of the Plain, call'd, <hi>The Temple of <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Theology</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">The Study of God, and God's relations with man and the universe. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></hi>/hi>. The Business of those who were employ'd in this Temple being laborious and painful, I wonder'd exceedingly to see so many go towards it; but while I was pondering this Matter in my Mind, I spy'd <ref target="a016" corresp="n016"><hi>Pecunia</hi></ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">(DRAFT) I don't know what this is supposed to be</note> behind a Curtain, beckoning to them with her Hand, which Sight immediately satisfy'd me for whose Sake it was, that a great Part of them (I will not say all) travel'd that Road. In this Temple I saw nothing worth mentioning, except the ambitious and fraudulent Contrivances of <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Plagius</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">(DRAFT)Is this from the root of plagiarism.</note>, who (notwithstanding he had been severely reprehended for such Practices before) was diligently transcribing some eloquent Paragraphs out of <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Tillotson's <hi>Works</hi></ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">(DRAFT) John Tillotson? the Archbishop of Canterbury in late 17th century.</note>, &amp;c., to embellish his own.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Now I <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">bethought</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">(DRAFT) What is the meaning of this as opposed to just "thought"</note> my self in my Sleep, that it was Time to be at Home, and as I fancy'd I was travelling back thither, I reflected in my Mind on the extream Folly of those Parents, who, blind to their Childrens Dulness, and insensible of the Solidity of their Skulls, because they think their Purses can afford it, will needs send them to the Temple of Learning, where, for want of a suitable Genius, they learn little more than how to carry themselves handsomely, and enter a Room <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">genteely</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">In the manner of the gentry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, (which might as well be acquir'd at a Dancing-School,) and from whence they return, after Abundance of Trouble and Charge, as great Blockheads as ever, only more proud and self-conceited.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>While I was in the midst of these unpleasant Reflections, Clericus (who with a Book in his Hand was walking under the Trees) accidentally awak'd me; to him I related my Dream with all its Particulars, and he, without much Study, presently interpreted it, assuring me, <hi>That it was </hi><ref target="a021" corresp="n021"><hi>a lively Representation of</hi> Harvard College</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">(DRAFT) I'd be curious to see if there are any academic rebutals to this of note.</note>, <hi>Etcetera</hi>. I remain, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p><lb/><lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>  
