<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="franklin-dogood-8">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Silence Dogood 8</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <date when="1722">April 2, 1722</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <title type="sub">8</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    July 9, 1722 [No. 8] <lb/><lb/>
                    To the Author of the <hi>New-England Courant</hi>. <lb/><lb/><lb/>
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I prefer the following Abstract from the London Journal to any Thing of my own, and therefore shall present it to your Readers this week without any further Preface.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"Without Freedom of Thought, there can be no such Thing as Wisdom; and no such Thing as publick Liberty, without Freedom of Speech; which is the Right of every Man, as far as by it, he does not hurt or controul the Right of another: And this is the only Check it ought to suffer, and the only Bounds it ought to know.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"This sacred Privilege is so essential to free Goverments, that the Security of Property, and the Freedom of Speech always go together; and in those wretched Countries where a Man cannot call his Tongue his own, he can scarce call any Thing else his own. Whoever would overthrow the Liberty of a Nation, must begin by subduing the Freeness of Speech; a <hi>Thing</hi> terrible to Publick Traytors.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"This Secret was so well known to the Court of <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">King Charles the First</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">(DRAFT)Charles I of England reigned from 1625-1649 until his execution. Charles I was defeated in the English Civil War and was eventually beheaded by Oliver Cromwell's army after being found guilty of high treason. Source: Wikipedia</note>, that his wicked Ministry procured a Proclamation, to forbid the People to talk of Parliaments, which those Traytors had laid aside. To assert the undoubted Right of the Subject, and defend his Majesty's legal Prerogative, was called <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Disaffection</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Hostility or animosity. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and punished as <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Sedition</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Mutiny or rebellion. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. Nay, People were forbid to talk of Religion in their Families: For the Priests had combined with the Ministers to cook up Tyranny, and suppress Truth and the Law, while <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">the late King James</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">(DRAFT)James VI and I, was the King of Scotland as Jame VI from 1567 and King of England and Ireland as James I from 1603 until his death in 1625. During his reign he experienced the Gunpowder Plot, an attempt on his life by English Catholics.</note>, when Duke of York, went avowedly to Mass, Men were fined, imprisoned and undone, for saying he was a <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Papist</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">A Roman Catholic. Source: Oxford English Dictionoary</note>: And that <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">King Charles the Second</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">After Oliver Cromwell's death in 1658 the monarchy was restored with Charles II in 1660. During his reign he re-established the Church of England and saw the rise of the Whig and Tory parties. His reign ended in 1685 with his death. Source: Wikipedia</note> might live more securely a Papist, there was an Act of Parliament made, declaring it Treason to say that he was one.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"That Men ought to speak well of <hi>their Governours</hi> is true, while <hi>their Governours</hi> deserve to be well spoken of; but to do publick Mischief, without hearing of it, is only the Prerogative and <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Felicity</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">(DRAFT-DC is Happiness the right connotation)Happiness. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of Tyranny: A free People will be shewing that they are <hi>so</hi>, by their Freedom of Speech.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"The Administration of Government, is nothing else but the Attendance of the <hi>Trustees of the People</hi> upon the Interest and Affairs of the People: And as it is the Part and Business of the People, for whose Sake alone all publick Matters are, or ought to be transacted, to see whether they be well or ill transacted; so it is the Interest, and ought to be the Ambition, of all honest Magistrates, to have their Deeds openly examined, and publickly scann'd: Only the <hi>wicked Governours</hi> of Men dread what is said of them; <ref target="a008" corresp="n008"><hi>Audivit Tiberius probra queis lacerabitur, atque</hi> perculsus est</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">(DRAFT-Translate)It appears to be from Cato's Letters</note>. The publick Censure was true, else he had not felt it bitter.</p><lb/><lb/> <!-- Why is the end of the Latin phrase not in italics -->
                <p>"Freedom of Speech is ever the Symptom, as well as the Effect of a good Government. In old Rome, all was left to the Judgment and Pleasure of the People, who examined the publick Proceedings with such Discretion, and censured those who administred them with such Equity and Mildness, that in the space of Three Hundred Years, not five publick Ministers suffered unjustly. Indeed whenever the <hi>Commons</hi> proceeded to Violence, the great Ones had been the Agressors.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"<hi>Guilt</hi> only dreads Liberty of Speech, which drags it out of its lurking Holes, and exposes its Deformity and Horrour to Daylight. <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Horatius</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009"></note>, <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Valerius</ref><note xml:Id="n009" target="a009"></note>, <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Cincinnatus</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011"></note>, and other vertuous and undesigning Magistrates of the Roman Commonwealth, had nothing to fear from Liberty of Speech. <hi>Their virtuous</hi> Administration, the more it was examin'd, the more it brightned and gain'd by Enquiry. When Valerius in particular, was accused upon some slight grounds of affecting the <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Diadem</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">A crown. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; he, who was the first Minister of Rome, does not accuse the People for examining his Conduct, but approved his Innocence in a Speech to them; and gave such Satisfaction to them, and gained such Popularity to himself, that they gave him a new Name; <ref target="a013" corresp="n013"><hi>inde cognomen factum Publicolae est</hi></ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">(DRAFT)</note>; to denote that he was their Favourite and their Friend. <ref target="a014" corresp="n014"><hi>Latae deinde leges — Ante omnes de provocatione</hi> Adversus Magistratus Ad Populum, Livii, lib. 2. Cap. 8.</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">(DRAFT)</note></p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"But Things afterwards took another Turn. Rome, with the Loss of its Liberty, lost also its Freedom of Speech; then Mens Words began to be feared and watched; and then first began the <hi>poysonous Race of Informers</hi>, banished indeed under the righteous Administration of <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Titus, Narva, Trajan, Aurelius</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015"></note>, &amp;c. but encouraged and enriched under the <hi>vile Ministry</hi> of <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">Sejanus, Tigillinus, Pallas, and Cleander</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016"></note>: <ref target="a017" corresp="n017"><hi>Queri libet, quod in secreta nostra non inquirant principes, nisi quos Odimus</hi>, says Pliny to Trajan</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017"></note>.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"The best Princes have ever encouraged and promoted Freedom of Speech; they know that upright Measures would defend themselves, and that all upright Men would defend them. <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Tacitus</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">(DRAFT)</note>, speaking of the Reign of some of the Princes abovemention'd, says with Extasy, <ref target="a019" corresp="n019"><hi>Rara Temporum felicitate, ubi sentire quae velis, &amp; quae sentias dicere licet</hi></ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">(DRAFT)</note>: A blessed Time when you might think what you would, and speak what you thought.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>"I doubt not but old Spencer and his Son, who were the <hi>Chief Ministers</hi> and <hi>Betrayers</hi> of <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">Edward the Second</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">(DRAFT)</note>, would have been very glad to have stopped the Mouths of all the honest Men in England. They dreaded to be called <hi>Traytors</hi>, because they were <hi>Traytors</hi>. And I dare say, <ref target="a021" corresp="n021">Queen Elizabeth's Walsingham</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">(draft)</note>, who deserved no Reproaches, feared none. Misrepresentation of publick Measures is easily overthrown, by representing publick Measures truly; when they are honest, they ought to be publickly known, that they may be publickly commended; but if they are <ref target="a022" corresp="n022">knavish</ref><note xml:id="n022" target="a022">(DRAFT-DC)Vulgar or villainous; mischievous. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> or <ref target="a023" corresp="n023">pernicious</ref><note xml:id="n023" target="a023">(DRAFT-DC)Wicked, intending harm. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, they ought to be publickly exposed, in order to be publickly detested." Yours, &amp;c.,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p><lb/><lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>  
