<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="franklin-autobiography">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Autobiography of Benjamin Franklin</title>
            <author>
                <persName type="lccn" key="n50016726">
                    <name>
                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                     </name>
                </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
                <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">

                        <forename>John</forename>John 
                        <surname>O'Brien</surname></name> </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>

                    <name>Faculty, librarians, and students of the University of Virginia </name>

                    <name ref="editors.xml#EF">Ellen French</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#AM">Andrew Michael</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#NT">Natalie Thompson</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#MD">Monica David</name>      
                </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName>Literature in Context</orgName>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                </address>
                <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
            </distributor>
            <availability status="free">
                <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                    Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                    License </licence>
            </availability>
            <authority>
                <idno>franklin-autobiography</idno>
            </authority>
        </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n50027909">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Autobiography of Benjamin Franklin</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="usa">United States of America</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>P. F. Collier and Son, 1909</publisher>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                               Franklin's manuscript was left incomplete at his death, and was printed in stages in the course of the early nineteenth century. Our text is based on the University of Virginia Library’s Electronic Text Center’s digital edition, created in the 1990s and early 2000s. This digital text was produced from the print edition edited by Charles Eliot and published by P. F. Collier and Son in New York in 1909. The page images are from the original manuscript that is held at the Huntington Library in San Marino, California.</note>
                          
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="autobiography">
                <channel mode="w">manuscript</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston, Massachusetts</name>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7014406">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</name>
                    <time from="1706" to="1790">18th Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc> <p>This text is prepared as part of the Literature in Context project,
            which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
            relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th
            century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
            developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p></projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible
                resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If
                you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p></interpretation>
            <normalization><p>Original spelling is retained, but capitalization has been normalized in this case.</p></normalization>
            <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                the word.</p></hyphenation>
            <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running
                headers have not.</p></segmentation>
            <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCCN">
                <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCC">
                <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
                <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="ORCID">
                <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
    <front>
        <pb n="Title Page" facs="pageImages/franklin-title-page.jpg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart><ref target="a0001" corresp="n0001">The life of</ref><lb/></titlePart>
                <titlePart>Benjamin Franklin<lb/></titlePart>
                <titlePart>an autographical manuscript<lb/></titlePart>
            </titlePage>   
    </front>
   <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p1.jpg"/>
        <p>TWYFORD, at the <ref target="a0002" corresp="n0002">Bishop of St. Asaph's,</ref><lb/>
            1771.<lb/>	
        </p>
        <p>DEAR <ref target="a0003" corresp="n0003">SON</ref>: I have ever had pleasure in obtaining any little anecdotes of my ancestors. You may remember the inquiries I made among the remains of my relations when you were with me in England, and the journey I undertook for that purpose. Imagining it may be equally agreeable to you to know the circumstances of my life, many of which you are yet unacquainted with, and expecting the enjoyment of a week's uninterrupted leisure in my present country retirement, I sit down to write them for you. To which I have besides some other inducements. Having emerged from the poverty and obscurity in which I was born and bred, to a state of affluence and some degree of reputation in the world, and having gone so far through life with a considerable share of felicity, the conducing means I made use of, which with the blessing of God so well succeeded, my posterity may like to know, as they may find some of them suitable to their own situations, and therefore fit to be imitated.
        </p>
        <p>That felicity, when I reflected on it, has induced me sometimes to say, that were it offered to my choice, I should have no objection to a repetition of the same life from its beginning, <ref target="a0004" corresp="n0004">only asking the advantages authors have in a second edition to correct some faults of the first.</ref> So I might, besides correcting the faults, change some <ref target="a0005" corresp="n0005">sinister</ref> accidents and events of it for others more favorable. But though this were denied, I should still accept the offer. Since such a repetition is not to be expected, the next thing most like living one's life over again seems to be a recollection of that life, and to make that recollection as durable as possible by putting it down in writing.
            
        </p><p>Hereby, too, I shall indulge the inclination so natural in old men, to be talking of themselves and their own past actions; and I shall indulge it without being tiresome to others, who, through respect to age, might conceive themselves obliged to give me a hearing, since this may be read or not as any one pleases. And, lastly (I may as well confess it, since my denial of it will be believed by nobody), perhaps I shall a good deal gratify my own vanity. Indeed, I scarce ever heard or saw the introductory words,<hi rend="italic">"Without vanity I may say,"</hi> &#x0026;amp;c., but some vain thing immediately followed. Most people dislike vanity in others, whatever share theyhave of it themselves; but I give it fair quarter wherever I meet with it, being persuaded that it is often productive of good to the possessor, and to others that are within his sphere of action; and therefore, in many cases, it would not be altogether absurd if a man were to thank God for his vanity among the other comforts of life.
        </p>
        <p>And now I speak of thanking God, I desire with all humility to acknowledge that I owe the mentioned happiness of my past life to His kind providence, which lead me to the means I used and gave them success. My belief of this induces me to <hi rend="italic">hope,</hi> though I must not <hi rend="italic">presume,</hi> that the same goodness will still be exercised toward me, in continuing that happiness, or enabling me to bear a fatal reverse, which I may experience as others have done: the complexion of my future fortune being known to Him only in whose power it is to bless to us even our afflictions.
        </p>
        <p>The notes one of my uncles (who had the same kind of curiosity in collecting family anecdotes) once put into my hands, furnished me with several particulars relating to our ancestors. From these notes I learned that the family had lived in the same village, Ecton, in Northamptonshire, for three hundred years, and how much longer he knew not (perhaps from the time when the name of <ref target="a0006" corresp="n0006">Franklin</ref>, that before was the name of an order of people, was assumed by them as a surname when others took surnames all over the kingdom), on a <ref target="a0007" corresp="n0007">freehold</ref> of about thirty acres, aided by the smith's business, which had continued in the family till his time, the eldest son being always bred to that business; a custom which he and my father followed as to their eldest sons. When I searched the registers at Ecton, I found an account of their births, marriages and burials from the year 1555 only, there being no registers kept in that parish at any time preceding. By that register I perceived that I was the youngest son of the youngest son for five generations back. My grandfather Thomas, who was born in 1598, lived at Ecton till he grew too old to follow business longer, when he went to live with his son John, a dyer at Banbury, in Oxfordshire, with whom my father served an apprenticeship. There my grandfather 
            <pb n="2" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p2.jpg"/>
            died and lies buried. We saw his gravestone in 1758. His eldest son Thomas lived in the house at Ecton, and left it with the land to his only child, a daughter, who, with her husband, one Fisher, of Wellingborough, sold it to Mr. Isted, now lord of the manor there. My grandfather had four sons that grew up, viz.: Thomas, John, Benjamin and Josiah.  I will give you what account I can of them, at this distance from my papers, and if these are not lost in my absence, you will among them find many more particulars.
        </p>
    <p>Thomas was bred a smith under his father; but, being ingenious, and encouraged in learning (as all my brothers were) by an Esquire Palmer, then the principal gentleman in that parish, he qualified himself for the business of <ref target="a0008" corresp="n0008">scrivener</ref>; became a considerable man in the county; was a chief mover of all public-spirited undertakings for the county or town of Northampton, and his own village, of which many instances were related of him; and much taken notice of and patronized by the then Lord Halifax. <ref target="a0009" corresp="n0009">He died in 17O2, January 6, old style, just four years to a day before I was born.</ref>  The account we received of his life and character from some old people at Ecton, I remember, struck you as something extraordinary, from its similarity to what you knew of mine.
        </p>
        <p>"Had he died on the same day," you said, "one might have supposed a transmigration."
        </p>
        <p>John was bred a dyer, I believe of woolens. Benjamin was bred a silk dyer, serving an apprenticeship at London. 
            <pb n="3" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p3.jpg"/>
            
            He was an ingenious man.  I remember him well, for when I was a boy he came over to my father in Boston, and lived in the house with us some years. He lived to a great age. His grandson, Samuel Franklin, now lives in Boston. He left behind him two quarto volumes, <ref target="a0100" corresp="n0100">MS.</ref>, of his own poetry, consisting of little occasional pieces addressed to his friends and relations, of which the following, sent to me, is a specimen.
        </p>
        <p>Sent to My Name upon a Report
        of his Inclination to Martial affairs
        7 July 1710
        </p>
       <lg>
        <l>Beleeve me Ben. It is a Dangerous Trade</l>
        <l>The Sword has Many Marr'd as well as Made</l>
        <l>By it doe many fall Not Many Rise</l>
        <l>Makes Many poor few Rich and fewer Wise</l>
        <l>Fills Towns with Ruin, fields with blood beside</l>
        <l>Tis Sloths Maintainer, And the Shield of pride</l>
        <l>Fair Citties Rich to Day, in plenty flow</l>
        <l>War fills with want, Tomorrow, &#x0026; with woe</l>
        <l>Ruin'd Estates, The Nurse of Vice, broke limbs &#x0026; scarss</l>
        <l>Are the Effects of Desolating Warrs.</l>
        </lg>
        <l>Sent to B. F. in N. E. 15 July 1710</l>
        <lg>
        <l>B  e to they parents an Obedient Son</l>
        <l>E  ach Day let Duty constantly be Done</l>
        <l>N  ever give Way to sloth or lust or pride</l>
        <l>I  f free you'd be from Thousand Ills beside</l>
        <l>A  bove all ILls be sure Avoid the shelfe</l>
        <l>M  an's Danger lyes in Satan sin and selfe</l>
        <l>I  n vertue Learning Wisdome progress Make</l>
        <l>N  ere shrink at Suffering for thy saviours sake</l>
        <l>F  raud and all Falshood in thy Dealings Flee</l>
        <l>R  eligious Always in thy station be</l>
        <l>A  dore the Maker of thy Inward part</l>
        <l>N  ow's the Accepted time, Give him thy Heart</l>
        <l>K  eep a Good Consceince 'tis a constant Frind</l>
        <l>L  ike Judge and Witness This Thy Acts Attend</l>
        <l>I  n Heart with bended knee Alone Adore</l>
        <l>N  one but the Three in One Forevermore.</l>
        </lg>
       <p>
           He had formed a short-hand of his own, which he taught me, but, never practising it, I have now forgot it. I was named after this uncle, there being a particular affection between him and my father. He was very pious, a great attender of sermons of the best preachers, which he took down in his short-hand, and had with him many volumes of them. He was also much of a politician; too much, perhaps, for his station. There fell lately into my hands, in London, a collection he had made of all the principal pamphlets, relating to public affairs, from 1641 to 1717; many of the volumes are wanting as appears by the numbering, but there still remain <ref target="a0011" corresp="n0011">eight volumes in folio, and twenty-four in quarto and in octavo.</ref> A dealer in old books met with them, and knowing me by my sometimes buying of him, he brought them to me. It seems my uncle must have left them here, when he went to America, which was about fifty years since. There are many of his notes in the margins.
        </p>
       <p>This obscure family of ours was early in the Reformation, and continued Protestants through the reign 
           <pb n="4" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p4.jpg"/>
           
           of Queen Mary, when they were sometimes in danger of trouble on account of their zeal <ref target="a0012" corresp="n0012">against popery</ref>. They had got an <ref target="a0013" corresp="n0013">English Bible</ref>, and to conceal and secure it, it was fastened open with tapes under and within the cover of a joint-stool. When my great-great-grandfather read it to his family, he turned up the joint-stool upon his knees, turning over the leaves then under the tapes. One of the children stood at the door to give notice if he saw the apparitor coming, who was an officer of the spiritual court. In that case the stool was turned down again upon its feet, when the Bible remained concealed under it as before. This anecdote I had from my uncle Benjamin. The family continued all of the Church of England till about the end of Charles the Second's reign, when some of the ministers that had been <ref target="a0014" corresp="n0014">outed for non-conformity holding conventicles</ref> in Northamptonshire, Benjamin and Josiah adhered to them, and so continued all their lives: the rest of the family remained with the Episcopal Church.
        </p>
        <p>Josiah, my father, married young, and carried his wife with three children into New England, about 1682. The conventicles having been forbidden by law, and frequently disturbed, induced some considerable men of his acquaintance to remove to that country, and he was prevailed with to accompany them thither, where they expected to enjoy their mode of religion with freedom. By the same wife he had four children more born there, and by a second 
            <pb n="5" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p5.jpg"/>
            wife ten more, in all seventeen; of which I remember thirteen sitting at one time at his table, who all grew up to be men and women, and married; I was the youngest son, and the youngest child but two, and was born in Boston, New England. My mother, the second wife, was Abiah Folger, daughter of <ref target="a0015" corresp="n0015">Peter Folger</ref>, one of the first settlers of New England, of whom honorable mention is made by <ref target="a0016" corresp="n0016">Cotton Mather</ref> in his church history of that country, entitled Magnalia Christi Americana, as <hi rend="italic">"a godly, learned Englishman,"</hi> if I remember the words rightly.  I have heard that he wrote sundry small occasional pieces, but only one of them was printed, which I saw now many years since. It was written in 1675, in the home-spun verse of that time and people, and addressed to those then concerned in the government there. It was in favor of liberty of conscience, and in behalf of the Baptists, Quakers, and other sectaries that had been under persecution, ascribing the Indian wars, and other distresses that had befallen the country, to that persecution, as so many judgments of God to punish so heinous an offense, and exhorting a repeal of those uncharitable laws.
            
            The whole appeared to me as written with a good deal of decent plainness and manly freedom.  The six concluding lines I remember, though I have forgotten the two first of the stanza; but the purport of them was, that his censures proceeded from good-will, and, therefore, he would be known to be the author.
            <q><lg type="stanza"><l>because to be a Libeller (says he)</l>
                <l>        I hate it with my heart;</l>
                <l>     From Sherburne town, where now I dwell</l>
                <l>        My name I do put here;</l>
                <l>     Without offense your real friend,</l>
                <l>        It is Peter Folgier.</l></lg></q>
        </p><p><ref target="a0017" corresp="n0017">My elder brothers were all put apprentices to different trades.  I was put to the grammar-school at eight years of age, my father intending to devote me, as the tithe of his sons, to the service of the Church.</ref> My early readiness in learning to read (which must have been very early, as I do not remember when I could not read), and the opinion of all his friends, that I should certainly make a good scholar, encouraged him in this purpose of his.  My uncle Benjamin, too, approved of it, and proposed to give me all his short-hand volumes of sermons, I suppose as a stock to set up with, if I would learn his character.  I continued, however, at the grammar-school not quite one year, though in that time I had risen gradually from the middle of the class of that year to be the head of it, and farther was removed into the next class above it, in order to go with that into the third at the end of the year. But my father, in the meantime, from a view of the expense of a college education, which having so large a family he could not well afford, and the mean living many so educated were afterwards able to obtain reasons that be gave to his friends in my hearing altered his first intention, took me from the grammar-school, and sent me to a school for writing and arithmetic, kept by a then famous man, <ref target="a0018" corresp="n0018">Mr. George Brownell</ref>, very successful in his 
       <pb n="6" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p6.jpg"/>
       profession generally, and that by mild, encouraging methods. Under him I acquired fair writing pretty soon, but I failed in the arithmetic, and made no progress in it. At ten years old I was taken home to assist my father in his business, which was that of a tallow-chandler and sope-boiler; a business he was not bred to, but had assumed on his arrival in New England, and on finding his dying trade would not maintain his family, being in little request. Accordingly, I was employed in cutting wick for the candles, filling the dipping mold and the molds for cast candles, attending the shop, going of errands, etc.
        </p>
        <p><ref target="a0019" corresp="n0019">I disliked the trade, and had a strong inclination for the sea, but my father declared against it;</ref> however, living near the water, I was much in and about it, learnt early to swim well, and to manage boats; and when in a boat or canoe with other boys, I was commonly allowed to govern, especially in any case of difficulty; and upon other occasions I was generally a leader among the boys, and sometimes led them into scrapes, of which I will mention one instance, as it shows an early projecting public spirit, tho' not then justly conducted.
        </p>
        <p>There was a salt-marsh that bounded part of the mill-pond, on the edge of which, at high water, we used to stand to fish for minnows.  By much trampling, we had made it a mere quagmire.  My proposal was to build a wharff there fit for us to stand upon, and I showed my comrades a large heap of stones, which were intended for a new house near the marsh, and which would very well suit 
            <pb n="7" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p7.jpg"/>
            our purpose. Accordingly, in the evening, when the workmen were gone, I assembled a number of my play-fellows, and working with them diligently like so many <ref target="a0020" corresp="n0020">emmets</ref>, sometimes two or three to a stone, we brought them all away and built our little wharff.  The next morning the workmen were surprised at missing the stones, which were found in our wharff.  Inquiry was made after the removers; we were discovered and complained of; several of us were corrected by our fathers; and though I pleaded the usefulness of the work, mine convinced me that nothing was useful which was not honest.
        </p><p>I think you may like to know something of his person and character.  He had an excellent constitution of body, was of middle stature, but well set, and very strong; he was ingenious, could draw prettily, was skilled a little in music, and had a clear pleasing voice, so that when he played psalm tunes on his violin and sung withal, as he sometimes did in an evening after the business of the day was over, it was extremely agreeable to hear.  He had a mechanical genius too, and, on occasion, was very handy in the use of other tradesmen's tools; but his great excellence lay in a sound understanding and solid judgment in prudential matters, both in private and publick affairs.  In the latter, indeed, he was never employed, the numerous family he had to educate and the straitness of his circumstances keeping him close to his trade; but I remember well his being frequently visited by leading people, who consulted him for his opinion in affairs of the town or of the church he belonged to, and showed a good deal of respect for his judgment 
       <pb n="8" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p8.jpg"/>
       and advice: he was also much consulted by private persons about their affairs when any difficulty occurred, and frequently chosen an arbitrator between contending parties.
        </p><p>At his table he liked to have, as often as he could, some sensible friend or neighbor to converse with, and always took care to start some ingenious or useful topic for discourse, which might tend to improve the minds of his children.  By this means he turned our attention to what was good, just, and prudent in the conduct of life; and little or no notice was ever taken of what related to the victuals on the table, whether it was well or ill dressed, in or out of season, of good or bad flavor, preferable or inferior to this or that other thing of the kind, so that I was bro't up in such a perfect inattention to those matters as to be quite indifferent what kind of food was set before me, and so unobservant of it, that to this day if I am asked I can scarce tell a few hours after dinner what I dined upon.  This has been a convenience to me in travelling, where my companions have been sometimes very unhappy for want of a suitable gratification of their more delicate, because better instructed, tastes and appetites.
            
        </p><p>My mother had likewise an excellent constitution: she suckled all her ten children.  I never knew either my father or mother to have any sickness but that of which they dy'd, he at 89, and she at 85 years of age. They lie buried together at Boston, where I some years since placed a marble over their grave, with this inscription:
            
            JOSIAH FRANKLIN,<lb/>
            and<lb/>
            ABIAH his Wife,<lb/>
            lie here interred.<lb/>
            They lived lovingly together in wedlock<lb/>
            fifty-five years.<lb/>
            Without an estate, or any gainful employment,<lb/>
            By constant labor and industry,<lb/>
            with God's blessing,<lb/>
            They maintained a large family<lb/>
            comfortably,<lb/>
            and brought up thirteen children<lb/>
            and seven grandchildren<lb/>
            reputably.<lb/>
            From this instance, reader,<lb/>
            Be encouraged to diligence in thy calling,<lb/>
            And distrust not Providence.<lb/>
            He was a pious and prudent man;<lb/>
            She, a discreet and virtuous woman.<lb/>
            Their youngest son,<lb/>
            In filial regard to their memory,<lb/>
            Places this stone.<lb/>
            J.F. born 1655, died 1744, AEtat 89.<lb/>
            A.F. born 1667, died 1752, 85.<lb/>
            
           
            <pb n="9" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p9.jpg"/>

            
        </p><p>By my rambling digressions I perceive myself to be grown old.  I us'd to write more methodically.  But one does not dress for private company as for a publick ball.  'Tis perhaps only negligence.
            

        </p><p>To return: I continued thus employed in my father's business for two years, that is, till I was twelve years old; and my brother John, who was bred to that business, having left my father, married, and set up for himself at Rhode Island, there was all appearance that I was destined to supply his place, and become a tallow-chandler.  But my dislike to the trade continuing, my father was under apprehensions that if he did not find one for me more agreeable, I should break away and get to sea, as his son Josiah had done, to his great vexation.  He therefore sometimes took me to walk with him, and see joiners, bricklayers, turners, braziers, etc., at their work, that he might observe my inclination, and endeavor to fix it on some trade or other on land.  It has ever since been a pleasure to me to see good workmen handle their tools; and it has been useful to me, having learnt so much by it as to be able to do little jobs myself in my house when a workman could not readily be got, and to construct little machines <pb n="10" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p10.jpg"/>for my experiments, while the intention of making the experiment was fresh and warm in my mind.  My father at last fixed upon the cutler's trade, and my uncle Benjamin's son Samuel, who was bred to that business in London, being about that time established in Boston, I was sent to be with him some time on liking.  But his expectations of a fee with me displeasing my father, I was taken home again.

        </p><p>To return: I continued thus employed in my father's business for two years, that is, till I was twelve years old; and my brother John, who was bred to that business, having left my father, married, and set up for himself at Rhode Island, there was all appearance that I was destined to supply his place, and become a tallow-chandler.  But my dislike to the trade continuing, my father was under apprehensions that if he did not find one for me more agreeable, I should break away and get to sea, as his son Josiah had done, to his great vexation.  He therefore sometimes took me to walk with him, and see joiners, bricklayers, turners, braziers, etc., at their work, that he might observe my inclination, and endeavor to fix it on some trade or other on land.  It has ever since been a pleasure to me to see good workmen handle their tools; and it has been useful to me, having learnt so much by it as to be able to do little jobs myself in my house when a workman could not readily be got, and to construct little machines <pb n="10" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p10.jpg"/>for my experiments, while the intention of making the experiment was fresh and warm in my mind.  My father at last fixed upon the cutler's trade, and my uncle Benjamin's son Samuel, who was bred to that business in London, being about that time established in Boston, I was sent to be with him some time on liking.  But his expectations of a fee with me displeasing my father, I was taken home again.

            
        </p><p>From a child I was fond of reading, and all the little money that came into my hands was ever laid out in books. Pleased with the Pilgrim's Progress, my first collection was of John Bunyan's works in separate little volumes.  I afterward sold them to enable me to buy <ref target="a0021" corresp="n0021">R. Burton's Historical Collections</ref>; they were small chapmen's books, and cheap, 40 or 50 in all.  My father's little library consisted chiefly of books in polemic divinity, most of which I read, and have since often regretted that, at a time when I had such a thirst for knowledge, more proper books had not fallen in my way since it was now resolved I should not be a clergyman.  Plutarch's Lives there was in which I read abundantly, and I still think that time spent to great advantage. There was also a book of De Foe's, called an <ref target="a0022" corresp="n0022">Essay on Projects</ref>, and another of Dr. Mather's, called <ref target="a0023" corresp="n0023">Essays to do Good</ref>, which perhaps gave me a turn of thinking that had an influence on some of the principal future events of my life.
            
        </p><p>This bookish inclination at length determined my father to make me a printer, though he had already one son (James) of that profession.  In 1717 my brother James returned from England with a press and letters to set up his business in Boston.  I liked it much better than that of my father, but still 

    
            <pb n="11" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p11.jpg"/>

            
            had a hankering for the sea.  To prevent the apprehended effect of such an inclination, my father was impatient to have me bound to my brother.  I stood out some time, but at last was persuaded, and signed the indentures when I was yet but twelve years old.  I was to serve as an apprentice till I was <ref target="a0024" corresp="n0024">twenty-one years of age</ref>, only I was to be allowed journeyman's wages during the last year.  In a little time I made great proficiency in the business, and became a useful hand to my brother.  I now had access to better books.  An acquaintance with the apprentices of booksellers enabled me sometimes to borrow a small one, which I was careful to return soon and clean. Often I sat up in my room reading the greatest part of the night, when the book was borrowed in the evening and to be returned early in the morning, lest it should be missed or wanted.
        </p>
       <p>And after some time an ingenious tradesman, Mr. Matthew Adams, who had a pretty collection of books, and who frequented our printing-house, took notice of me, invited me to his library, and very kindly lent me such books as I chose to read.  I now took a fancy to poetry, and made some little pieces; my brother, thinking it might turn to account, encouraged me, and put me on composing occasional ballads. One was called <hi rend="italic">The Lighthouse Tragedy,</hi> and contained an account of the drowning of Captain Worthilake, with his two daughters: the other was a sailor's song, on the taking of <hi rend="italic">Teach</hi> (or Blackbeard) the pirate.<ref target="a0025" corresp="n0025">They were wretched stuff</ref>, in the Grub-street-ballad style; and when they were printed he sent me about the town to sell them. The first sold wonderfully, the event being recent, having made a great noise.  This flattered my vanity; but my father discouraged me by ridiculing my performances, and telling me verse-makers were generally beggars.  So I escaped being a poet, most probably a very bad one; but as prose writing bad been of great use to me in the course of my life, and was a principal means of my advancement, 

           <pb n="12" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p12.jpg"/>
           I shall tell you how, in such a situation, I acquired what little ability I have in that way.
       </p>
       <p>There was another bookish lad in the town, John Collins by name, with whom I was intimately acquainted.  We sometimes disputed, and very fond we were of argument, and very desirous of confuting one another, which disputatious turn, by the way, is apt to become a very bad habit, making people often extremely disagreeable in company by the contradiction that is necessary to bring it into practice; and thence, besides souring and spoiling the conversation, is productive of disgusts and, perhaps enmities where you may have occasion for friendship.  I had caught it by reading my father's books of dispute about religion.  Persons of good sense, I have since observed, seldom fall into it, except lawyers, university men, and men of all sorts that have been bred at Edinborough.
           
       </p><p>A question was once, somehow or other, started between Collins and me, of the propriety of educating the female sex, and their abilities for study.  He was of opinion that it was improper, and that they were naturally unequal to it.  I took the contrary side, perhaps a little for dispute's sake.  He was naturally more eloquent, had a ready plenty of words; and sometimes, as I thought, bore me down more by his fluency than by the strength of his reasons. As we parted without settling the point, and were not to see 
           <pb n="13" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p13.jpg"/>
           one another again for some time, I sat down to put my arguments in writing, which I copied fair and sent to him. He answered, and I replied.  Three or four letters of a side had passed, when my father happened to find my papers and read them.  Without entering into the discussion, he took occasion to talk to me about the manner of my writing; observed that, though I had the advantage of my antagonist in correct spelling and  <ref target="a0026" corresp="n0026">pointing</ref> (which I ow'd to the printing-house), I fell far short in elegance of expression, in method and in perspicuity, of which he convinced me by several instances.  I saw the justice of his remark, and thence grew more attentive to the manner in writing, and determined to endeavor at improvement.
           
       </p><p>About this time I met with an odd volume of the <ref target="a0027" corresp="n0027"><hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi></ref>. It was <ref target="a0028" corresp="n0028">the third</ref>. I had never before seen any of them.  I bought it, read it over and over, and was much delighted with it.  I thought the writing excellent, and wished, if possible, to imitate it.  With this view I took some of the papers, and, making short hints of the sentiment in each sentence, laid them by a few days, and then, without looking at the book, try'd to compleat the papers again, by expressing each hinted sentiment at length, and as fully as it had been expressed before, in any suitable words that should come to hand.  Then I compared my <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> with the original, discovered some of my faults, and corrected them. But I found I wanted a stock of words, or a readiness in recollecting and using them, which I thought I should have acquired before that time if I had gone on making verses; since the continual occasion for words of the same import, but of different length, to suit the measure, or of different sound for the rhyme, would have laid me under a constant necessity of searching for variety, and also 
           <pb n="14" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p14.jpg"/>
           have tended to fix that variety in my mind, and make me master of it. Therefore I took some of the tales and turned them into verse; and, after a time, when I had pretty well forgotten the prose, turned them back again.  I also sometimes jumbled my collections of hints into confusion, and after some weeks endeavored to reduce them into the best order, before I began to form the full sentences and compleat the paper.  This was to teach me method in the arrangement of thoughts.  By comparing my work afterwards with the original, I discovered many faults and amended them; but I sometimes had the pleasure of fancying that, in certain particulars of small import, I had been lucky enough to improve the method or the language, and this encouraged me to think I might possibly in time come to be a tolerable English writer, of which I was extremely ambitious.  My time for these exercises and for reading was at night, after work or before it began in the morning, or on Sundays, when I contrived to be in the printing-house alone, evading as much as I could the common attendance on public worship which my father used to exact on me when I was under his care, and which indeed I still thought a duty, though I could not, as it seemed to me, afford time to practise it.
           
       </p><p>When about 16 years of age I happened to meet with a book, written by one Tryon, recommending <ref target="a0029" corresp="n0029">a vegetable diet</ref>. I determined to go into it.  My brother, being 
           <pb n="15" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p15.jpg"/>
           yet unmarried, did not keep house, but boarded himself and his apprentices in another family.  My refusing to eat flesh occasioned an inconveniency, and I was frequently chid for my singularity. I made myself acquainted with Tryon's manner of preparing some of his dishes, such as boiling potatoes or rice, making  <ref target="a0030" corresp="n0030">hasty pudding</ref>, and a few others, and then proposed to my brother, that if he would give me, weekly, half the money he paid for my board, I would board myself.  He instantly agreed to it, and I presently found that I could save half what he paid me.  This was an additional fund for buying books.  But I had another advantage in it.  My brother and the rest going from the printing-house to their meals, I remained there alone, and, despatching presently my light repast, which often was no more than a bisket or a slice of bread, a handful of raisins or a tart from the pastry-cook's, and a glass of water, had the rest of the time till their return for study, in which I made the greater progress, from that greater clearness of head and quicker apprehension which usually attend temperance in eating and drinking.
           
       </p><p>And now it was that, being on some occasion made asham'd of my ignorance in figures, which I had twice failed in learning when at school, I took <ref target="a0031" corresp="n0031">Cocker's book of Arithmetick</ref>, and went through the whole by myself with great ease.  I also read <ref target="a0032" corresp="n0032">Seller's and Shermy's books of Navigation</ref>, and became acquainted with the little geometry they contain; but never proceeded far in that science.  And I read about this time <ref target="s0033" corresp="n0033">Locke <hi rend="italic">On Human Understanding,</hi></ref> and <ref target="a0034" corresp="n0034">the <hi rend="italic">Art of Thinking,</hi> by Messrs. du Port Royal</ref>.
           
       </p><p>While I was intent on improving 
           <pb n="16" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p16.jpg"/>
           my language, I met with an English grammar (I think it was <ref target="a0035" corresp="n0035">Greenwood's)</ref>, at the end of which there were two little sketches of the arts of rhetoric and logic, the latter finishing with a specimen of a dispute in the Socratic method; and soon after I procur'd <ref target="a036" corresp="n0036">Xenophon's Memorable Things of Socrates</ref>, wherein there are many instances of the same method.  I was charm'd with it, adopted it, dropt my abrupt contradiction and positive argumentation, and put on the humble inquirer and doubter. And being then, from reading <ref target="a0037" corresp="n0037">Shaftesbury and Collins</ref>, become a real doubter in many points of our religious doctrine, I found this method safest for myself and very embarrassing to those against whom I used it; therefore I took a delight in it, practis'd it continually, and grew very artful and expert in drawing people, even of superior knowledge, into concessions, the consequences of which they did not foresee, entangling them in difficulties out of which they could not extricate themselves, and so obtaining victories that neither myself nor my cause always deserved.  I continu'd this method some few years, but gradually left it, retaining only the habit of expressing myself in terms of modest diffidence; never using, when I advanced any thing that may possibly be disputed, the words <hi rend="italic">certainly, undoubtedly,</hi> or any others that give the air of positiveness to an opinion; but rather say, I conceive or apprehend a thing to be so and so; it appears to me, or 
           
           <pb n="17" facs="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Franklin-p17.jpg"/>
           <hi rend="italic">I should think it so or so,</hi> for such and such reasons; or ,<hi rend="italic">I imagine it to be so;</hi> or <hi rend="italic">it is so, if I am not mistaken</hi>.  This habit, I believe, has been of great advantage to me when I have had occasion to inculcate my opinions, and persuade men into measures that I have been from time to time engag'd in promoting; and, as the chief ends of conversation are to <hi rend="italic">inform</hi> or to be <hi rend="italic">informed,</hi> to <hi rend="italic">please</hi> or to <hi rend="italic">persuade,</hi> I wish well-meaning, sensible men would not lessen their power of doing good by a positive, assuming manner, that seldom fails to disgust, tends to create opposition, and to defeat every one of those purposes for which speech was given to us, to wit, giving or receiving information or pleasure.  For, if you would inform, a positive and dogmatical manner in advancing your sentiments may provoke contradiction and prevent a candid attention.  If you wish information and improvement from the knowledge of others, and yet at the same time express yourself as firmly fix'd in your present opinions, modest, sensible men, who do not love disputation, will probably leave you undisturbed in the possession of your error.  And by such a manner, you can seldom hope to recommend yourself in pleasing your hearers, or to persuade those whose concurrence you desire.<ref target="a0038" corresp="n0038">Pope says, judiciously</ref>:
   </p>
   <p>Men should be taught as if you taught them not,
   And things unknown propos'd as things forgot,</p>
      

           <pb n="12" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p12.jpg"/>
       <p>I shall tell you how, in such a situation, I acquired what little ability I have in that way.</p>  
    
       <p>There was another bookish lad in the town, John Collins by name, with whom I was intimately acquainted.  We sometimes disputed, and very fond we were of argument, and very desirous of confuting one another, which disputatious turn, by the way, is apt to become a very bad habit, making people often extremely disagreeable in company by the contradiction that is necessary to bring it into practice; and thence, besides souring and spoiling the conversation, is productive of disgusts and, perhaps enmities where you may have occasion for friendship.  I had caught it by reading my father's books of dispute about religion.  Persons of good sense, I have since observed, seldom fall into it, except lawyers, university men, and men of all sorts that have been bred at Edinborough.
           
       </p><p>A question was once, somehow or other, started between Collins and me, of the propriety of educating the female sex, and their abilities for study.  He was of opinion that it was improper, and that they were naturally unequal to it.  I took the contrary side, perhaps a little for dispute's sake.  He was naturally more eloquent, had a ready plenty of words; and sometimes, as I thought, bore me down more by his fluency than by the strength of his reasons. As we parted without settling the point, and were not to see 
           <pb n="13" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p13.jpg"/>
           one another again for some time, I sat down to put my arguments in writing, which I copied fair and sent to him. He answered, and I replied.  Three or four letters of a side had passed, when my father happened to find my papers and read them.  Without entering into the discussion, he took occasion to talk to me about the manner of my writing; observed that, though I had the advantage of my antagonist in correct spelling and  <ref target="a0026" corresp="n0026">pointing</ref> (which I ow'd to the printing-house), I fell far short in elegance of expression, in method and in perspicuity, of which he convinced me by several instances.  I saw the justice of his remark, and thence grew more attentive to the manner in writing, and determined to endeavor at improvement.
           
       </p><p>About this time I met with an odd volume of the <ref target="a0027" corresp="n0027"><hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi></ref>. It was <ref target="a0028" corresp="n0028">the third</ref>. I had never before seen any of them.  I bought it, read it over and over, and was much delighted with it.  I thought the writing excellent, and wished, if possible, to imitate it.  With this view I took some of the papers, and, making short hints of the sentiment in each sentence, laid them by a few days, and then, without looking at the book, try'd to compleat the papers again, by expressing each hinted sentiment at length, and as fully as it had been expressed before, in any suitable words that should come to hand.  Then I compared my <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> with the original, discovered some of my faults, and corrected them. But I found I wanted a stock of words, or a readiness in recollecting and using them, which I thought I should have acquired before that time if I had gone on making verses; since the continual occasion for words of the same import, but of different length, to suit the measure, or of different sound for the rhyme, would have laid me under a constant necessity of searching for variety, and also 
           <pb n="14" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p14.jpg"/>
           have tended to fix that variety in my mind, and make me master of it. Therefore I took some of the tales and turned them into verse; and, after a time, when I had pretty well forgotten the prose, turned them back again.  I also sometimes jumbled my collections of hints into confusion, and after some weeks endeavored to reduce them into the best order, before I began to form the full sentences and compleat the paper.  This was to teach me method in the arrangement of thoughts.  By comparing my work afterwards with the original, I discovered many faults and amended them; but I sometimes had the pleasure of fancying that, in certain particulars of small import, I had been lucky enough to improve the method or the language, and this encouraged me to think I might possibly in time come to be a tolerable English writer, of which I was extremely ambitious.  My time for these exercises and for reading was at night, after work or before it began in the morning, or on Sundays, when I contrived to be in the printing-house alone, evading as much as I could the common attendance on public worship which my father used to exact on me when I was under his care, and which indeed I still thought a duty, though I could not, as it seemed to me, afford time to practise it.
           
       </p><p>When about 16 years of age I happened to meet with a book, written by one Tryon, recommending <ref target="a0029" corresp="n0029">a vegetable diet</ref>. I determined to go into it.  My brother, being 
           <pb n="15" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p15.jpg"/>
           yet unmarried, did not keep house, but boarded himself and his apprentices in another family.  My refusing to eat flesh occasioned an inconveniency, and I was frequently chid for my singularity. I made myself acquainted with Tryon's manner of preparing some of his dishes, such as boiling potatoes or rice, making  <ref target="a0030" corresp="n0030">hasty pudding</ref>, and a few others, and then proposed to my brother, that if he would give me, weekly, half the money he paid for my board, I would board myself.  He instantly agreed to it, and I presently found that I could save half what he paid me.  This was an additional fund for buying books.  But I had another advantage in it.  My brother and the rest going from the printing-house to their meals, I remained there alone, and, despatching presently my light repast, which often was no more than a bisket or a slice of bread, a handful of raisins or a tart from the pastry-cook's, and a glass of water, had the rest of the time till their return for study, in which I made the greater progress, from that greater clearness of head and quicker apprehension which usually attend temperance in eating and drinking.
           
       </p><p>And now it was that, being on some occasion made asham'd of my ignorance in figures, which I had twice failed in learning when at school, I took <ref target="a0031" corresp="n0031">Cocker's book of Arithmetick</ref>, and went through the whole by myself with great ease.  I also read <ref target="a0032" corresp="n0032">Seller's and Shermy's books of Navigation</ref>, and became acquainted with the little geometry they contain; but never proceeded far in that science.  And I read about this time <ref target="s0033" corresp="n0033">Locke <hi rend="italic">On Human Understanding,</hi></ref> and <ref target="a0034" corresp="n0034">the <hi rend="italic">Art of Thinking,</hi> by Messrs. du Port Royal</ref>.
           
       </p><p>While I was intent on improving 
           <pb n="16" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p16.jpg"/>
           my language, I met with an English grammar (I think it was <ref target="a0035" corresp="n0035">Greenwood's)</ref>, at the end of which there were two little sketches of the arts of rhetoric and logic, the latter finishing with a specimen of a dispute in the Socratic method; and soon after I procur'd <ref target="a036" corresp="n0036">Xenophon's Memorable Things of Socrates</ref>, wherein there are many instances of the same method.  I was charm'd with it, adopted it, dropt my abrupt contradiction and positive argumentation, and put on the humble inquirer and doubter. And being then, from reading <ref target="a0037" corresp="n0037">Shaftesbury and Collins</ref>, become a real doubter in many points of our religious doctrine, I found this method safest for myself and very embarrassing to those against whom I used it; therefore I took a delight in it, practis'd it continually, and grew very artful and expert in drawing people, even of superior knowledge, into concessions, the consequences of which they did not foresee, entangling them in difficulties out of which they could not extricate themselves, and so obtaining victories that neither myself nor my cause always deserved.  I continu'd this method some few years, but gradually left it, retaining only the habit of expressing myself in terms of modest diffidence; never using, when I advanced any thing that may possibly be disputed, the words <hi rend="italic">certainly, undoubtedly,</hi> or any others that give the air of positiveness to an opinion; but rather say, I conceive or apprehend a thing to be so and so; it appears to me, or 
           
           <pb n="17" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p17.jpg"/>
           <hi rend="italic">I should think it so or so,</hi> for such and such reasons; or ,<hi rend="italic">I imagine it to be so;</hi> or <hi rend="italic">it is so, if I am not mistaken</hi>.  This habit, I believe, has been of great advantage to me when I have had occasion to inculcate my opinions, and persuade men into measures that I have been from time to time engag'd in promoting; and, as the chief ends of conversation are to <hi rend="italic">inform</hi> or to be <hi rend="italic">informed,</hi> to <hi rend="italic">please</hi> or to <hi rend="italic">persuade,</hi> I wish well-meaning, sensible men would not lessen their power of doing good by a positive, assuming manner, that seldom fails to disgust, tends to create opposition, and to defeat every one of those purposes for which speech was given to us, to wit, giving or receiving information or pleasure.  For, if you would inform, a positive and dogmatical manner in advancing your sentiments may provoke contradiction and prevent a candid attention.  If you wish information and improvement from the knowledge of others, and yet at the same time express yourself as firmly fix'd in your present opinions, modest, sensible men, who do not love disputation, will probably leave you undisturbed in the possession of your error.  And by such a manner, you can seldom hope to recommend yourself in pleasing your hearers, or to persuade those whose concurrence you desire.<ref target="a0038" corresp="n0038">Pope says, judiciously</ref>:
   </p>
   <p>Men should be taught as if you taught them not,
   And things unknown propos'd as things forgot,</p>
       
       <pb n="18" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p18.jpg"/>

   <p> farther recommending it to us,</p>
       <p>To speak tho' sure, with seeming Diffidence.       
   </p></body>
            <back>
            <note xml:id="n0001" target="a0001" type="headnote" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><p>
                
            <graphic url="notes/Benjamin_Franklin_by_Joseph_Siffrein_Duplessis.jpg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>
                The book that we know as Benjamin Franklin's "Autobiography" was composed in several stages over more than two decades, and was never printed or published in Franklin's lifetime. And Franklin's conception of what this book was and what its purposes should be changed over time. The first section was composed in the summer of 1771, when Franklin, then living in London and serving as the colonial representative for several of the American colonies, was on an extended visit to the country home of his friend Jonathan Shipley. The text, which Franklin thought of as his "memoir" or his "life" took the ostensible form of a letter to his son William, though it is clear that this is a fiction, and that this was never a "letter" in the conventional sense, one intended to go through the post to its recipient. The later sections, composed in stages in the 1780s, seem addressed to a more general audience, in part perhaps because of Franklin's estrangement from his son, but also perhaps because Franklin saw this book as an opportunity to address a larger audience.</p>
                <p>The manuscript, here titled "The Life of Benjamin Franklin" by an unknown hand, is unfinished. Franklin picked up the manuscript in late 1789 and early 1790, but died before completing his memoir, which only goes up to the 1760s. The publication of the manuscript is complicated, and it was not for several decades the the "Autobiography" assumed the form and the title that it now generally bears. Our edition includes page images of the original manuscript, which is housed at the Huntington Library in California. We have edited it to make it legible to modern reader, expanding abbreviations and regularizing the spelling. Our annotations are designed to provide important contextual information that Franklin's first readers would have known.</p></note>
  
            <note xml:id="n0002" target="a0002" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Jonathan Shipley (1714-1788) <p><graphic url="notes/Jonathan-Shipley.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/>was the bishop of St. Asaph in Wales, but he spent much of his time at Twyford House, a large Tudor-era mansion in Hampshire in the south of England that had been in his family for generations. Shipley became a good friend and correspondent of Franklin's. He was sympathetic to the cause of the American colonists in their conflict with the government in London. Franklin wrote the first section of this memoir while he was visiting Shipley and his family at Twyford House for several weeks in July and August 1771. </p></note>
                
            <note xml:id="n0003" target="a0003" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">William Franklin (c. 1730-1813) was Benjamin's illegitimate son. His mother has never been identified with confidence; it might have been Franklin's common-law wife Deborah Read, but it also might have been another woman whose identity is lost to history. William had worked with his father in London. In 1771, when this was written, he held the position of the royal governor of New Jersey. Father and son would later be estranged over the American Revolutionary War; William remained loyal to the British crown and became a leading Loyalist opposing the American rebels, who by this time included his father. William and Benjamin met a few times after the war, but never really reconciled. <graphic url="notes/William_Franklin.-by-Mather_brownjpg.jpg" style="float:left" width="300px"/></note>
                
            <note xml:id="n0004" target="a0004" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Franklin's figurative language wryly draws on his experience as a printer here and many times in the book, most obviously in his reflections on the "errata" or mistakes of his life, "errata" being a print-house term for a typographical error.</note>
                
           <note xml:id="n0005" target="a0005" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Prejudicial, adverse, unfavourable, darkly suspicious." (OED)</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0006" target="a0006" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">The word "franklin" was a class signifier in England from the twelfth through the fifteenth centuries. A franklin was a free man ranking between the classes of serf and landed gentry. Franklins often owned land, but not enough to raise them anything close to the ranks of the gentry. The thirty acres that Benjamin Franklin describes as being owned by his ancestor was typical; enough of one's own land to survive, but not enough to become wealthy. For a classic literary example of a Franklin, see Chaucer's Franklin in <hi rend="italic">The Canterbury Tales.</hi></note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0007" target="a0007" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">"Permanent and absolute tenure of land or property with freedom to dispose of it at will." Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0008" target="a0008" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">A person employed to copy or transcribe documents, or to write documenets on behalf of someone else; a scribe, a copyiest; a clerk, a secretary." Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0009" target="a0009" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">For much of its history England used the Julian calendar (originally introduced by Julius Caesar in 46 B.C.) which was rather inaccurate over long periods of time. By the eighteenth century England was several days behind the rest of Europe, which used the Gregorian calendar. Britain switched over to the Gregorian calendar in 1752 A.D. by an act of Parliament, resulting in the "loss" of several days. For this reason, Franklin had to celebrate his birthday on the 17th of January instead of the 6th, and resulting in his need for a clarification of the date as in the "old style."</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0010" target="a0010" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">that is, in manuscript</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0011" target="a0011" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">"Folio," "quarto," and "octavo" denote sizes of books, determined by the standard size of paper used in a print shop. A folio is a large volume where the paper is folded once; a quarto (sized at one-fourth the sheet) is half that size, and an octavo (where each page one-eighth of the sheet) is half the size of that. This would have been a very substantial collection of pamphlets.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0012" target="a0012" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The Franklin family's story, as told here, was fairly typical of that of many English families, as their religious faith intersected with and was shaped by political events. By "early in the Reformation," Franklin marks that his family left the Roman Catholic Church (mocked by many as "popery") not long after Henry VIII separated from Rome in 1534, founding the Church of England. When his daughter Mary became Queen in 1553, she returned England to the religious jurisdiction of the Roman Catholic Church, and persecuted prominent Protestants.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0013" target="a0013" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">A Bible translated into English. The Roman church had preferred to use the Bible in Latin, but after the Reformation, there was a new emphasis on individuals being able to read the Bible for themselves, and a spate of translations into English emerged, such as the one done by William Tyndale and Miles Coverdale, available by the late 1530s; the Franklin family Bible might have been this edition.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0014" target="a0014" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Nonconformity: Refusal to conform to the doctrine, discipline, or usages of the Church of England, or of any established church, etc.; the principles or practice of nonconformists. Now usually: Protestant dissent; the body of nonconformists or nonconformist opinion. Conventicle: A meeting of (Protestant) Nonconformists or Dissenters from the Church of England for religious worship, during the period when such meetings were prohibited by the law. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0015" target="a0015" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Peter Folger (1617-1690): Folger, born in Norwich, migrated to Massachusetts in 1635. He learned the Algonquian language and became an interpreter and “intermediary with the American Indian population” on the islands of Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket. He also worked other jobs such as teacher, surveyor, farmer, and clerk of courts. His was a prominent family that produced “American scientists, merchants, and politicians, the most famous of whom was Benjamin Franklin, Folger’s grandson.” Source: Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0016" target="a0016" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF"><p>Cotton Mather, born in Boston, Massachusetts in 1663 to one of the city's most influential families, became arguably the most prominent minister in the American colonies. <graphic url="notes/Cotton_Mather.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/> Indeed, his influence was so widely felt he could be described as one of the major transatlantic figures of the time. Ordained at Boston's North Church, he served there as minister for the entirety of his career. However, Mather's influence was not only limited to religion. He was politically active, and he studied science as well, eventually gaining admittance to London's Royal Society.</p>  
                <p> A prolific author, he published approximately 380 texts, including <hi rend="italic">Magnalia Christi Americana</hi> (on the movement of Christianity from Europe to America) and Bonifacius, <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi>. By the end of his life, Mather’s influence on Christianity in the colonies laid the groundwork for religious figures such as Jonathan Edwards. Mather died in February 1728 at the age of 65.</p>
                <p>Mather’s works were wide-reaching, so it is unsurprising that Franklin felt his influence—most notably through Mather’s <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi>. While working as an apprentice in his brother’s print shop in 1722, sixteen-year-old Franklin wrote essays under the pseudonym of Silence Dogood—the surname "Dogood" was surely taken directly from Mather’s title. The persona Franklin assumed as Silence Dogood was a middle-aged minister’s widow who wrote on a variety of social topics such as politics, fashion, and education. Franklin silently slid these essays under the door of his brother’s business, hoping for publication. His ploy worked, and Franklin's pseudonymous works were published until October of 1722. Some critics have suggested that the the pseudonym and some of the essays were actually a mockery of Mather since the initial run of essays from Silence Dogood appeared at approximately the same time as widespread debates surrounding inoculation, a practice opposed by James Franklin, Benjamin’s brother and owner of <hi rend="italic">The New England Courant.</hi></p>
                <p>For his part, Mather was a strong proponent of inoculation to the extent that in 1721, Mather and Dr. Zabdiel Boylston inoculated over 200 people during a smallpox epidemic, in the process eliciting a certain amount of public outcry. At the same time, James Franklin published numerous articles against inoculation in the Courant. Years later, and after his own child contracted smallpox, Franklin changed his position on inoculation, regretting his failure to inoculate his son.</p>
                <p>Though Mather and Benjamin Franklin held opposing views upon various matters, there is no doubt that Mather exerted major influence upon Franklin. For instance, <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi> provides practical tips for how to “do good” for the “Saviour, and for His People in the world.” The book is short and easily read, and its practicality and warmth made it popular throughout the colonies and in England. Franklin appears to have extrapolated not only the form, but the ethical substance from the book, publishing his own Poor Richard's Almanac, an annual journal consisting of practical tips, witty sayings, and household advice. In the Autobiography, he notes that his father’s library held a copy of Mather's book, and that reading it “perhaps gave me a Turn of Thinking that had an Influence on some of the principal future Events of my Life.” In a letter written to Mather’s son Samuel in 1773, Franklin acknowledged Mather’s influence: "When I was a boy, I met with a book, entitled “Essays to do good,” which, I think, was written by your father. It had been so little regarded by a former possessor, that several leaves of it were torn out: but the remainder gave me such a turn, for thinking, as to have an influence on my conduct through life; for I have always set a greater value on the character of a doer of good, than any other kind of reputation; and if I have been, as you seem to think, a useful citizen, the public owes the advantage of it to that book." --Ellen French</p></note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0017" target="a0017" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF">Under the system of primogeniture that governed the inheritance of property in the landowning classes of Anglo-America, only the oldest son could inherit his father's land. Because of this, the younger sons were often sent off to practice law, join the military, or become ministers in the church. This trend extended into the middle class as well, as often the younger sons were sent, as here, as a "tithe" to the church for both religious and practical reasons.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0018" target="a0018" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Brownell was born in London and arrived in the Noth American colonies around 1703. By 1712 he was running a boarding school in Boston with his wife. Franklin attended Brownell's school from 1715 to 1716, at which point the cost apparently became too great for his family to sustain.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0019" target="a0019" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF">Sons leaving home for adventure and quick profit was a common trope in the literature of this period due to the increase in England's colonial presence throughout the century. Robinson Crusoe presents one such example, but the ocean as a metaphor for both empire and capitalist gains was present in many eighteenth century stories.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0020" target="a0020" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">ants. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0021" target="a0021" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">"Richard Burton" or "RB" were pseudonyms for Nathaniel Crouch (c. 1632-1725), who published dozens of popular histories in the second half of the 1600s, books that went through many editions. Most of these were pretty much plagiarized from the works of other writers, but many readers, like the young Franklin, learned a good deal of history through his inexpensive digests of longer works.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0022" target="a0022" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Daniel Defoe's <hi rend="italic">An Essay upon Projects</hi>, published in 1697, outlines a number of plans for organizing associations to improve English society, including special courts for merchants and an early form of life insurance.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0023" target="a0023" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">As noted above, Mather was an important influence on Franklin whose persona of "Silence Dogood" in his first published essays allude to the title of Mather's book.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0024" target="a0024" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#NT"><p>It is worth noting that this is an unusually long apprenticeship; most were for seven rather than nine years. We do not know why Benjamin's apprenticeship was stipulated to be that long. The provision that he get "journeyman's wages," that is, the salary of a flully-fledged printer, might have been offered as a comprimise.
                The fact of Franklin's apprenticeship, and his early departure from his brother's ship, which is coming up in in a few pages, informs much of this early part of the Autobiography. During his trip from Boston to Philadelphia Franklin recounts being wary about attracting attention, noting, “it seemed to be suspected from my youth and appearance, that I might be some runaway.” This statement seems odd, considering Franklin technically was a runaway—he had left his apprenticeship with his brother against the will of the family. Why did Franklin not consider himself classed with other young runaways, when he did fear being mistaken for one and returned to Boston?  He certainly had run away from Boston, knowing that if he left openly, “means would be used to prevent [him].” Yet Franklin was in a somewhat unique position: he had technically run away without his brother’s permission, yet he knew that he would not be treated as a common runaway apprentice.</p>
                <p>Apprenticeship  in the American colonies had its roots in the practices of the English system, which dates back to the middle ages. One of the major pieces of legislation governing apprenticeship was the English Statute of Artificers (1563),  which required parents who did not otherwise provide for the education of their sons to bind them to a trade or the agricultural system. The seven year term, longer than the normal length of apprenticeship in France and Germany, “was designed to ensure English supremacy in handmade manufactures and to discourage the wandering and strolling that had characterized earlier periods of English life.”  Another aspect of English law and custom that influenced apprenticeship in the colonies was the English Poor Law (1601)  which required local authorities to bind poor or orphaned children into apprenticeship if their parents did not do so. Benjamin Franklin belonged to the class of apprentices who bound themselves “by their own free will and consent” to a master to learn his trade, not the apprentices involuntarily bound under the auspices of the Poor Law. </p>
                <p>These English statutes applied to the American colonies in theory. However, these laws and customs depended on the medieval guild system for enforcement—a system which never developed in the colonies. Eighteenth-century colonial America did not have the deep pool of skilled laborers that characterized the guild system and had no enforcement mechanism to monitor quality of work, admit members to the status of journeyman or master, or standardize apprentice training.  In the colonies, “anyone could call himself a master artisan, and any such artisan could take an apprentice”—or many apprentices at once.  During Franklin’s boyhood in Boston, the real wages of artisans were falling and apprenticeship contracts often did not demand fees from parents, except for those in high-status crafts. It was guild enforcement that kept wages high and ensured quality craft in the English system, because it created a closed labor market—no artisan could work without permission from his guild.</p>
                <p>In England, if an apprentice ran away from his master, there was an ironclad system in place to keep him from practicing his craft anywhere in the country. The guild system ensured that jurisdiction rules were enforced, and any new practitioner would have to be an approved guild member. In America, runaway penalties did not extend beyond the borders of each colony,  and, as Franklin’s narrative attests, the demand for skilled labor meant even a partially-trained apprentice would likely be hired, perhaps even with the status of a journeyman (though this label did not hold the weight it would in England).  If an American apprentice ran away, his master would circulate a description of the runaway with an offer of reward, and if returned, the apprentice would have to serve for a longer period.  The reward was the enforcement mechanism, meaning citizens might be on the lookout for apparent runaways.</p> 
                <p>Technically, to be legal, an apprenticeship contract (called an “indenture”) needed to be registered with municipal authorities so it could be used as evidence in case of disputes. This was true even in the colonies.  However, the nature of indenture papers meant that possession of one’s half of the contract should have constituted evidence without consulting town records: “indenture”  papers were indented on both halves of the document so they could later be identified as one contract.  Benjamin Franklin’s original contract with his brother would probably have been properly registered—but the second set of indentures, which were secret, would only have been held by the master and the apprentice.  James probably could have proved Benjamin was his apprentice by comparing the two halves of the indenture, but once his brother was out of Boston, this means of redress was impractical at best. And of course, in attempting to regain his apprentice, James would have had to admit his real ownership of the Courant. --Natalie Thompson</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0025" target="a0025" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Neither of these poems has survived. But what Franklin was doing was a fairly typical thing in this period; newspapers were often filled with poems about recent events, particularly events as notable and spectacular as the two mentioned here.  The death by drowning of George Worthilake, his wife and daughter (Franklin misremembers this as having been two daughters) as they were returning from church by boat to the lighthouse that Worthilake was in charge of in Novenber 1716 became known as the "Lighthouse Tragedy." Edward Teach, the pirate known as Blackbeard, was killed in a firefight with ships from the Royal Navy off the coast of North Carolina on November 22, 1718. The "Grub Street-ballad-style" that Franklin laments using here was nothing to be ashamed of; many authors in this period wrote popular ballads published in the kind of popular journals that became associated with "Grub Street," the physical home of mass market printing in London.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0026" target="a0026" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">punctuation</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0027" target="a0027" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM"><hi rend="italics">The Spectator</hi> was a newspaper created by Joseph Addison and Richard Steele that ran from March 3, 1711 to December 6, 1712. It consisted of a series of essays that were for the most part written by either Steele or Addison, but they assumed the viewpoint of the persona of “Mr. Spectator.” “Mr. Spectator” was a quiet observer of English society who commented on politics, fashion, and social issues through these essays, which were widely popular in both England and the colonies. They were read as models of good English style, and also as guides for civilized, middle-class behavior. Benjamin Franklin was influenced by <hi rend="italic">Spectator's</hi> prose style. And the  persona of "Silence Dogood" that he would use in his own periodical essays was clearly influenced by the silent "Mr. Spectator" of Addison and Steele's influential journal.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0028" target="a0028" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                    <p>Given Franklin's later interest in public finance, it is striking to see that the particular essay of the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>that he remembers as his introduction to the series is a famous piece by Addison on the topic of "public credit." Here it is in its entirety.</p>
                    <p>No. 3. Saturday, March 3, 1711.</p>               
                    <p>
                    
                    
                    'Quoi quisque ferè studio devinctus adhæret:
                    Aut quibus in rebus multùm sumus antè morati:
                    Atque in quâ ratione fuit contenta magis mens;
                    In somnis eadem plerumque videmur obire.'</p>
                    
                    <p>Lucr. L. 4.</p>
                    
                    
                    <p>In one of my late Rambles, or rather Speculations, I looked into the
                    great Hall where the Bank is kept, and was not a little pleased to
                    see the Directors, Secretaries, and Clerks, with all the other Members
                    of that wealthy Corporation, ranged in their several Stations, according
                    to the Parts they act in that just and regular Oeconomy. This revived in
                    my Memory the many Discourses which I had both read and heard,
                    concerning the Decay of Publick Credit, with the Methods of restoring
                    it, and which, in my Opinion, have always been defective, because they
                    have always been made with an Eye to separate Interests and Party
                    Principles.</p>
                    
                    <p>The Thoughts of the Day gave my Mind Employment for the whole Night, so
                    that I fell insensibly into a kind of Methodical Dream, which disposed
                    all my Contemplations into a Vision or Allegory, or what else the Reader
                    shall please to call it.</p>
                    
                    <p>Methoughts I returned to the Great Hall, where I had been the Morning
                    before, but to my Surprize, instead of the Company that I left there, I
                    saw, towards the Upper-end of the Hall, a beautiful Virgin seated on a
                    Throne of Gold. Her Name (as they told me) was _Publick Credit_. The
                    Walls, instead of being adorned with Pictures and Maps, were hung with
                    many Acts of Parliament written in Golden Letters. At the Upper end of
                    the Hall was the _Magna Charta_, with the Act of Uniformity on
                    the right Hand, and the Act of Toleration on the left. At the Lower
                    end of the Hall was the Act of Settlement, which was placed full in
                    the Eye of the Virgin that sat upon the Throne. Both the Sides of the
                    Hall were covered with such Acts of Parliament as had been made for the
                    Establishment of Publick Funds. The Lady seemed to set an unspeakable
                    Value upon these several Pieces of Furniture, insomuch that she often
                    refreshed her Eye with them, and often smiled with a Secret Pleasure, as
                    she looked upon them; but at the same time showed a very particular
                    Uneasiness, if she saw any thing approaching that might hurt them. She
                    appeared indeed infinitely timorous in all her Behaviour: And, whether
                    it was from the Delicacy of her Constitution, or that she was troubled
                    with the Vapours, as I was afterwards told by one who I found was none
                    of her Well-wishers, she changed Colour, and startled at everything she
                    heard. She was likewise (as I afterwards found) a greater Valetudinarian
                    than any I had ever met with, even in her own Sex, and subject to such
                    Momentary Consumptions, that in the twinkling of an Eye, she would fall
                    away from the most florid Complexion, and the most healthful State of
                    Body, and wither into a Skeleton. Her Recoveries were often as sudden as
                    her Decays, insomuch that she would revive in a Moment out of a wasting
                    Distemper, into a Habit of the highest Health and Vigour.</p>
                    
                    <p>I had very soon an Opportunity of observing these quick Turns and
                    Changes in her Constitution. There sat at her Feet a Couple of
                    Secretaries, who received every Hour Letters from all Parts of the
                    World; which the one or the other of them was perpetually reading to
                    her; and according to the News she heard, to which she was exceedingly
                    attentive, she changed Colour, and discovered many Symptoms of Health or
                    Sickness.</p>
                    
                    <p>Behind the Throne was a prodigious Heap of Bags of Mony, which were
                    piled upon one another so high that they touched the Ceiling. The Floor
                    on her right Hand, and on her left, was covered with vast Sums of Gold
                    that rose up in Pyramids on either side of her: But this I did not so
                    much wonder at, when I heard, upon Enquiry, that she had the same Virtue
                    in her Touch, which the Poets tell us a 'Lydian' King was formerly
                    possessed of; and that she could convert whatever she pleased into that
                    precious Metal.</p>
                    
                        <p>After a little Dizziness, and confused Hurry of Thought, which a Man
                    often meets with in a Dream, methoughts the Hall was alarm'd, the Doors
                    flew open, and there entered half a dozen of the most hideous Phantoms
                    that I had ever seen (even in a Dream) before that Time. They came in
                    two by two, though match'd in the most dissociable Manner, and mingled
                    together in a kind of Dance. It would be tedious to describe their
                    Habits and Persons; for which Reason I shall only inform my Reader that
                    the first Couple were Tyranny and Anarchy, the second were Bigotry and
                    Atheism, the third the Genius of a Common-Wealth, and a young Man of
                    about twenty-two Years of Age, hose Name I could not learn. He had
                    a Sword in his right Hand, which in the Dance he often brandished at the
                    Act of Settlement; and a Citizen, who stood by me, whispered in my Ear,
                    that he saw a Spunge in his left Hand. The Dance of so many jarring
                    Natures put me in mind of the Sun, Moon, and Earth, in the 'Rehearsal',
                    that danced together for no other end but to eclipse one another.</p>
                    
                            <p>The Reader will easily suppose, by what has been before said, that the
                    Lady on the Throne would have been almost frightened to Distraction, had
                    she seen but any one of these Spectres; what then must have been her
                    Condition when she saw them all in a Body? She fainted and dyed away at
                    the sight.</p>
                    
                    <p>'Et neq; jam color est misto candore rubori;
                    Nec Vigor, et Vires, et quæ modò visa placebant;
                    Nec Corpus remanet ...'</p>
                    
                        <p>Ov. 'Met.' Lib. 3.</p>
                    
                    
                    <p>There was as great a Change in the Hill of Mony Bags, and the Heaps of
                    Mony, the former shrinking, and falling into so many empty Bags, that I
                    now found not above a tenth part of them had been filled with Mony. The
                    rest that took up the same Space, and made the same Figure as the Bags
                    that were really filled with Mony, had been blown up with Air, and
                    called into my Memory the Bags full of Wind, which Homer tells us his
                    Hero received as a present from Æolus. The great Heaps of Gold, on
                    either side of the Throne, now appeared to be only Heaps of Paper, or
                    little Piles of notched Sticks, bound up together in Bundles, like
                    Bath-Faggots.</p>
                    
                    <p>Whilst I was lamenting this sudden Desolation that had been made before
                    me, the whole Scene vanished: In the Room of the frightful Spectres,
                    there now entered a second Dance of Apparitions very agreeably matched
                    together, and made up of very amiable Phantoms. The first Pair was
                    Liberty, with Monarchy at her right Hand: The Second was Moderation
                    leading in Religion; and the third a Person whom I had never seen,
                    with the genius of _Great Britain_. At their first Entrance the
                    Lady reviv'd, the Bags swell'd to their former Bulk, the Piles of
                    Faggots and Heaps of Paper changed into Pyramids of Guineas: And for
                    my own part I was so transported with Joy, that I awaked, tho' I must
                    confess I would fain have fallen asleep again to have closed my Vision,
                    if I could have done it.</p>
                </note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0029" corresp="a0029" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Thomas Tryon's <hi rend="italic">The Way to Health, Long Life, and Happiness</hi>, <graphic url="https://s3.amazonaws.com/lic-assets-staging/Franklin/Thomas_Tryon.jpg" style="float:left" width="300px"/>(Source: Wikimedia Commons) published in 1691, advocated a vegetarian diet. Which was unusual in this period; vegetarianism was rare, and it cannot have been easy to get enough nutrition through a vegetarian diet in colonial New England in this period, given the difficulty of finding fresh vegetables in the winter season.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0030" corresp="a0030" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Hasty pudding was a grain porridge; in the American colonies, it was usually made of corn, but could also be made of wheat, oats, or some other grain.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0031" corresp="a0031" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Edward Cocker's textbook, first published in 1677 under the title <hi rend="italic">Cocker's Arithmetick: being a plain and familiar method suitable to the meanest capacity for the full understanding of that incomparable art, as it is now taught by the ablest school-masters in city and country</hi>, and then republished under various titles for decades to come became the standard book for learning basic arithmetic in the eighteenth-century Anglophone world. It would have been comparatively easy for Franklin to have come across a copy of this book, which went through scores of editions.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0032" corresp="a0032" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><hi rend="italic">Practical Navigation: or an Introduction to the Whole Art</hi>first published in London in 1669, was a widely-reprinted text in the period; its author, John Seller (1632-1697) was a mapmaker and cartographer who was awarded with the title of "hydrophapher to the king." Samuel Sturmy (1633-1669) was the author of <hi rend="italic">The Mariner's Magazine</hi>, first published in 1669 and, like Seller's book, reprinted several times in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. This was a large and ambitious text, with sections on navigation and math, but also on things like nautical weaponry.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0033" corresp="a0033" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">The English philosopher John Locke (1632-1704) published <hi rend="italic">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> in 1690. Locke's philosophical skepticism and strong endorsement of religious toleration seem to have found a strong positive response in Franklin. Locke's book is still considered a foundational text in the philosophical tradition of English empiricism.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0034" corresp="a0034" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM"><hi rend="italic">Logic, or, The Art of Thinking</hi> written by Antoine Arnauld and Pierre Nicole, was published in French in 1662, and soon thereafter translated into English and other languages. Known familiarly as the "Port Royal Logic," this, like Locke's book, was a highly influential text for centuries, and is still read by historians of philosophy. Source: https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/port-royal-logic/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0035" corresp="a0035" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The book that Franklin thinks that he is remembering is James Greenwood's <hi rend="italics">An Essay towards a Practical English Grammar</hi>, first published in 1711. But he is probably misremembering here, since that book does not have the Socratic dialogue to which he refers. He is more likely think of <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of the English Tongue</hi>, published anonymously but written by Charles Gildon in 1712. That book conclues with an essay called "Of the Socratic Method in Disputing," that describes and then models a method of debating controversial topics by means of open-ended, non-confrontational questions. Franklin says that he took this kind of method to heart, training himself to handle disputes by avoiding dogmatic statements of his own position and instead asking careful questions to learn more the positions of others.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0036" corresp="a0036" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Xenophon (430-354 B.C.E.) was an ancient Greek historian whose writings included the "Memorabilia," a text containing many Socratic-style dialogues. Source: http://www.iep.utm.edu/xenophon/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0037" corresp="a0037" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Franklin is referring to works by Anthony Ashley Cooper, the earl of Shaftesbury and Anthony Collins. Both authors were well known in this period for their philosophical skepticism and their classification as "deists," that is, their belief that although a deity of some sort existed and had created the known universe, he, or perhaps better, it did not trouble himself much in the everyday doings of that creation.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0038" corresp="a0038" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">These lines are from the 1711 poem "An Essay on Criticism" by Alexander Pope, though Franklin slightly misquotes, probably relying on his memory.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0039" target="a0039" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Thomas Tryon's <hi rend="italic">The Way to Health, Long Life, and Happiness</hi>, <graphic url="notes/Thomas_Tryon.jpg" style="float:left" width="300px"/>(Source: Wikimedia Commons) published in 1691, advocated a vegetarian diet. Which was unusual in this period; vegetarianism was rare, and it cannot have been easy to get enough nutrition through a vegetarian diet in colonial New England in this period, given the difficulty of finding fresh vegetables in the winter season.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0040" target="a0040" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Hasty pudding was a grain porridge; in the American colonies, it was usually made of corn, but could also be made of wheat, oats, or some other grain.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0041" target="a0041" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Edward Cocker's textbook, first published in 1677 under the title <hi rend="italic">Cocker's Arithmetick: being a plain and familiar method suitable to the meanest capacity for the full understanding of that incomparable art, as it is now taught by the ablest school-masters in city and country</hi>, and then republished under various titles for decades to come became the standard book for learning basic arithmetic in the eighteenth-century Anglophone world. It would have been comparatively easy for Franklin to have come across a copy of this book, which went through scores of editions.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0042" target="a0042" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><hi rend="italic">Practical Navigation: or an Introduction to the Whole Art</hi>first published in London in 1669, was a widely-reprinted text in the period; its author, John Seller (1632-1697) was a mapmaker and cartographer who was awarded with the title of "hydrophapher to the king." Samuel Sturmy (1633-1669) was the author of <hi rend="italic">The Mariner's Magazine</hi>, first published in 1669 and, like Seller's book, reprinted several times in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. This was a large and ambitious text, with sections on navigation and math, but also on things like nautical weaponry.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0043" target="a0043" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">The English philosopher John Locke (1632-1704) published <hi rend="italic">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> in 1690. Locke's philosophical skepticism and strong endorsement of religious toleration seem to have found a strong positive response in Franklin. Locke's book is still considered a foundational text in the philosophical tradition of English empiricism.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0044" target="a0044" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM"><hi rend="italic">Logic, or, The Art of Thinking</hi> written by Antoine Arnauld and Pierre Nicole, was published in French in 1662, and soon thereafter translated into English and other languages. Known familiarly as the "Port Royal Logic," this, like Locke's book, was a highly influential text for centuries, and is still read by historians of philosophy. Source: https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/port-royal-logic/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0045" target="a0045" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The book that Franklin thinks that he is remembering is James Greenwood's <hi rend="italics">An Essay towards a Practical English Grammar</hi>, first published in 1711. But he is probably misremembering here, since that book does not have the Socratic dialogue to which he refers. He is more likely think of <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of the English Tongue</hi>, published anonymously but written by Charles Gildon in 1712. That book conclues with an essay called "Of the Socratic Method in Disputing," that describes and then models a method of debating controversial topics by means of open-ended, non-confrontational questions. Franklin says that he took this kind of method to heart, training himself to handle disputes by avoiding dogmatic statements of his own position and instead asking careful questions to learn more the positions of others.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0046" target="a0046" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Xenophon (430-354 B.C.E.) was an ancient Greek historian whose writings included the "Memorabilia," a text containing many Socratic-style dialogues. Source: http://www.iep.utm.edu/xenophon/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0047" target="a0047" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Franklin is referring to works by Anthony Ashley Cooper, the earl of Shaftesbury and Anthony Collins. Both authors were well known in this period for their philosophical skepticism and their classification as "deists," that is, their belief that although a deity of some sort existed and had created the known universe, he, or perhaps better, it did not trouble himself much in the everyday doings of that creation.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0048" target="a0048" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">These lines are from the 1711 poem "An Essay on Criticism" by Alexander Pope, though Franklin slightly misquotes, probably relying on his memory.</note>

            </back>
    
</text>
</TEI>


