<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="franklin-autobiography">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Autobiography of Benjamin Franklin</title>
            <author>
                <persName>
                    <name>
                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                     </name>
                </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
                <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">

                        <forename>John</forename>John 
                        <surname>O'Brien</surname></name></persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>

                    <name>Faculty, librarians, and students of the University of Virginia </name>

                    <name ref="editors.xml#EF">Ellen French</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#AM">Andrew Michael</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#NT">Natalie Thompson</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#MD">Monica David</name>      
                </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
            <distributor>
                <orgName>Literature in Context</orgName>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                </address>
                <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
            </distributor>
            <availability status="free">
                <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                    Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                    License </licence>
            </availability>
            <authority>
                <idno>franklin-autobiography</idno>
            </authority>
        </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">The Autobiography of Benjamin Franklin</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="usa">United States of America</placeName>
                                <placeName type="city" key="nyc">New York</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>P. F. Collier and Son, 1909</publisher>
                            <date when="1909"></date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                               Franklin's manuscript was left incomplete at his death, and was printed in stages in the course of the first half of the nineteenth century. (It is an interesting, but a complicated story.) Our text is based on the University of Virginia Library’s Electronic Text Center’s digital edition, created in the 1990s and early 2000s. This digital text was produced from the print edition edited by Charles Eliot and published by P. F. Collier and Son in New York in 1909. The page images are from the original manuscript that is held at the Huntington Library in San Marino, California. The notes were added by faculty and students in the graduate program in English at the University of Virginia.</note>
                          
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="autobiography">
                <channel mode="w">manuscript</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston, Massachusetts</name>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7014406">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</name>
                    <time from="1706" to="1790">18th Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc> <p>This text is prepared as part of the Literature in Context project,
            which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
            relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th
            century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
            developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p></projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible
                resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If
                you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p></interpretation>
            <normalization><p>Original spelling is retained, but capitalization has been normalized in this case.</p></normalization>
            <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                the word.</p></hyphenation>
            <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running
                headers have not.</p></segmentation>
            <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCCN">
                <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCC">
                <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
                <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="ORCID">
                <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
    <front>
        <pb n="Title Page" facs="pageImages/franklin-title-page.jpg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart><ref target="a0001" corresp="n0001">The life of</ref><lb/></titlePart>
                <titlePart>Benjamin Franklin<lb/></titlePart>
                <titlePart>an autographical manuscript<lb/></titlePart>
            </titlePage>   
    </front>
   <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p1.jpg"/>
        <p>TWYFORD, at the <ref target="a0002" corresp="n0002">Bishop of St. Asaph's,</ref><lb/>
            1771.<lb/>	
        </p>
        <p>DEAR <ref target="a0003" corresp="n0003">SON</ref>: I have ever had pleasure in obtaining any little anecdotes of my ancestors. You may remember the inquiries I made among the remains of my relations when you were with me in England, and the journey I undertook for that purpose. Imagining it may be equally agreeable to you to know the circumstances of my life, many of which you are yet unacquainted with, and expecting the enjoyment of a week's uninterrupted leisure in my present country retirement, I sit down to write them for you. To which I have besides some other inducements. Having emerged from the poverty and obscurity in which I was born and bred, to a state of affluence and some degree of reputation in the world, and having gone so far through life with a considerable share of felicity, the conducing means I made use of, which with the blessing of God so well succeeded, my posterity may like to know, as they may find some of them suitable to their own situations, and therefore fit to be imitated.
        </p>
        <p>That felicity, when I reflected on it, has induced me sometimes to say, that were it offered to my choice, I should have no objection to a repetition of the same life from its beginning, <ref target="a0004" corresp="n0004">only asking the advantages authors have in a second edition to correct some faults of the first.</ref> So I might, besides correcting the faults, change some <ref target="a0005" corresp="n0005">sinister</ref> accidents and events of it for others more favorable. But though this were denied, I should still accept the offer. Since such a repetition is not to be expected, the next thing most like living one's life over again seems to be a recollection of that life, and to make that recollection as durable as possible by putting it down in writing.
            
        </p><p>Hereby, too, I shall indulge the inclination so natural in old men, to be talking of themselves and their own past actions; and I shall indulge it without being tiresome to others, who, through respect to age, might conceive themselves obliged to give me a hearing, since this may be read or not as any one pleases. And, lastly (I may as well confess it, since my denial of it will be believed by nobody), perhaps I shall a good deal gratify my own vanity. Indeed, I scarce ever heard or saw the introductory words,<hi rend="italic">"Without vanity I may say,"</hi> &amp;c., but some vain thing immediately followed. Most people dislike vanity in others, whatever share theyhave of it themselves; but I give it fair quarter wherever I meet with it, being persuaded that it is often productive of good to the possessor, and to others that are within his sphere of action; and therefore, in many cases, it would not be altogether absurd if a man were to thank God for his vanity among the other comforts of life.
        </p>
        <p>And now I speak of thanking God, I desire with all humility to acknowledge that I owe the mentioned happiness of my past life to His kind providence, which lead me to the means I used and gave them success. My belief of this induces me to <hi rend="italic">hope,</hi> though I must not <hi rend="italic">presume,</hi> that the same goodness will still be exercised toward me, in continuing that happiness, or enabling me to bear a fatal reverse, which I may experience as others have done: the complexion of my future fortune being known to Him only in whose power it is to bless to us even our afflictions.
        </p>
        <p>The notes one of my uncles (who had the same kind of curiosity in collecting family anecdotes) once put into my hands, furnished me with several particulars relating to our ancestors. From these notes I learned that the family had lived in the same village, Ecton, in Northamptonshire, for three hundred years, and how much longer he knew not (perhaps from the time when the name of <ref target="a0006" corresp="n0006">Franklin</ref>, that before was the name of an order of people, was assumed by them as a surname when others took surnames all over the kingdom), on a <ref target="a0007" corresp="n0007">freehold</ref> of about thirty acres, aided by the smith's business, which had continued in the family till his time, the eldest son being always bred to that business; a custom which he and my father followed as to their eldest sons. When I searched the registers at Ecton, I found an account of their births, marriages and burials from the year 1555 only, there being no registers kept in that parish at any time preceding. By that register I perceived that I was the youngest son of the youngest son for five generations back. My grandfather Thomas, who was born in 1598, lived at Ecton till he grew too old to follow business longer, when he went to live with his son John, a dyer at Banbury, in Oxfordshire, with whom my father served an apprenticeship. There my grandfather 
            <pb n="2" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p2.jpg"/>
            died and lies buried. We saw his gravestone in 1758. His eldest son Thomas lived in the house at Ecton, and left it with the land to his only child, a daughter, who, with her husband, one Fisher, of Wellingborough, sold it to Mr. Isted, now lord of the manor there. My grandfather had four sons that grew up, viz.: Thomas, John, Benjamin and Josiah.  I will give you what account I can of them, at this distance from my papers, and if these are not lost in my absence, you will among them find many more particulars.
        </p>
    <p>Thomas was bred a smith under his father; but, being ingenious, and encouraged in learning (as all my brothers were) by an Esquire Palmer, then the principal gentleman in that parish, he qualified himself for the business of <ref target="a0008" corresp="n0008">scrivener</ref>; became a considerable man in the county; was a chief mover of all public-spirited undertakings for the county or town of Northampton, and his own village, of which many instances were related of him; and much taken notice of and patronized by the then Lord Halifax. <ref target="a0009" corresp="n0009">He died in 1702, January 6, old style, just four years to a day before I was born.</ref>  The account we received of his life and character from some old people at Ecton, I remember, struck you as something extraordinary, from its similarity to what you knew of mine.
        </p>
        <p>"Had he died on the same day," you said, "one might have supposed a transmigration."
        </p>
        <p>John was bred a dyer, I believe of woolens. Benjamin was bred a silk dyer, serving an apprenticeship at London. 
            <pb n="3" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p3.jpg"/>
            
            He was an ingenious man.  I remember him well, for when I was a boy he came over to my father in Boston, and lived in the house with us some years. He lived to a great age. His grandson, Samuel Franklin, now lives in Boston. He left behind him two quarto volumes, <ref target="a0100" corresp="n0100">MS.</ref>, of his own poetry, consisting of little occasional pieces addressed to his friends and relations, of which the following, sent to me, is a specimen.
        </p>
        <p>Sent to My Name upon a Report
        of his Inclination to Martial affairs
        7 July 1710
        </p>
       <lg>
        <l>Beleeve me Ben. It is a Dangerous Trade</l>
        <l>The Sword has Many Marr'd as well as Made</l>
        <l>By it doe many fall Not Many Rise</l>
        <l>Makes Many poor few Rich and fewer Wise</l>
        <l>Fills Towns with Ruin, fields with blood beside</l>
        <l>Tis Sloths Maintainer, And the Shield of pride</l>
        <l>Fair Citties Rich to Day, in plenty flow</l>
        <l>War fills with want, Tomorrow, &#x0026; with woe</l>
        <l>Ruin'd Estates, The Nurse of Vice, broke limbs &#x0026; scarss</l>
        <l>Are the Effects of Desolating Warrs.</l>
        </lg>
        <l>Sent to B. F. in N. E. 15 July 1710</l>
        <lg>
        <l>B  e to they parents an Obedient Son</l>
        <l>E  ach Day let Duty constantly be Done</l>
        <l>N  ever give Way to sloth or lust or pride</l>
        <l>I  f free you'd be from Thousand Ills beside</l>
        <l>A  bove all ILls be sure Avoid the shelfe</l>
        <l>M  an's Danger lyes in Satan sin and selfe</l>
        <l>I  n vertue Learning Wisdome progress Make</l>
        <l>N  ere shrink at Suffering for thy saviours sake</l>
        <l>F  raud and all Falshood in thy Dealings Flee</l>
        <l>R  eligious Always in thy station be</l>
        <l>A  dore the Maker of thy Inward part</l>
        <l>N  ow's the Accepted time, Give him thy Heart</l>
        <l>K  eep a Good Consceince 'tis a constant Frind</l>
        <l>L  ike Judge and Witness This Thy Acts Attend</l>
        <l>I  n Heart with bended knee Alone Adore</l>
        <l>N  one but the Three in One Forevermore.</l>
        </lg>
       <p>
           He had formed a short-hand of his own, which he taught me, but, never practising it, I have now forgot it. I was named after this uncle, there being a particular affection between him and my father. He was very pious, a great attender of sermons of the best preachers, which he took down in his short-hand, and had with him many volumes of them. He was also much of a politician; too much, perhaps, for his station. There fell lately into my hands, in London, a collection he had made of all the principal pamphlets, relating to public affairs, from 1641 to 1717; many of the volumes are wanting as appears by the numbering, but there still remain <ref target="a0011" corresp="n0011">eight volumes in folio, and twenty-four in quarto and in octavo.</ref> A dealer in old books met with them, and knowing me by my sometimes buying of him, he brought them to me. It seems my uncle must have left them here, when he went to America, which was about fifty years since. There are many of his notes in the margins.
        </p>
       <p>This obscure family of ours was early in the Reformation, and continued Protestants through the reign 
           <pb n="4" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p4.jpg"/>
           
           of Queen Mary, when they were sometimes in danger of trouble on account of their zeal <ref target="a0012" corresp="n0012">against popery</ref>. They had got an <ref target="a0013" corresp="n0013">English Bible</ref>, and to conceal and secure it, it was fastened open with tapes under and within the cover of a joint-stool. When my great-great-grandfather read it to his family, he turned up the joint-stool upon his knees, turning over the leaves then under the tapes. One of the children stood at the door to give notice if he saw the apparitor coming, who was an officer of the spiritual court. In that case the stool was turned down again upon its feet, when the Bible remained concealed under it as before. This anecdote I had from my uncle Benjamin. The family continued all of the Church of England till about the end of Charles the Second's reign, when some of the ministers that had been <ref target="a0014" corresp="n0014">outed for non-conformity holding conventicles</ref> in Northamptonshire, Benjamin and Josiah adhered to them, and so continued all their lives: the rest of the family remained with the Episcopal Church.
        </p>
        <p>Josiah, my father, married young, and carried his wife with three children into New England, about 1682. The conventicles having been forbidden by law, and frequently disturbed, induced some considerable men of his acquaintance to remove to that country, and he was prevailed with to accompany them thither, where they expected to enjoy their mode of religion with freedom. By the same wife he had four children more born there, and by a second 
            <pb n="5" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p5.jpg"/>
            wife ten more, in all seventeen; of which I remember thirteen sitting at one time at his table, who all grew up to be men and women, and married; I was the youngest son, and the youngest child but two, and was born in Boston, New England. My mother, the second wife, was Abiah Folger, daughter of <ref target="a0015" corresp="n0015">Peter Folger</ref>, one of the first settlers of New England, of whom honorable mention is made by <ref target="a0016" corresp="n0016">Cotton Mather</ref> in his church history of that country, entitled Magnalia Christi Americana, as <hi rend="italic">"a godly, learned Englishman,"</hi> if I remember the words rightly.  I have heard that he wrote sundry small occasional pieces, but only one of them was printed, which I saw now many years since. It was written in 1675, in the home-spun verse of that time and people, and addressed to those then concerned in the government there. It was in favor of liberty of conscience, and in behalf of the Baptists, Quakers, and other sectaries that had been under persecution, ascribing the Indian wars, and other distresses that had befallen the country, to that persecution, as so many judgments of God to punish so heinous an offense, and exhorting a repeal of those uncharitable laws.
            
            The whole appeared to me as written with a good deal of decent plainness and manly freedom.  The six concluding lines I remember, though I have forgotten the two first of the stanza; but the purport of them was, that his censures proceeded from good-will, and, therefore, he would be known to be the author.
            <q><lg type="stanza"><l>because to be a Libeller (says he)</l>
                <l>        I hate it with my heart;</l>
                <l>     From Sherburne town, where now I dwell</l>
                <l>        My name I do put here;</l>
                <l>     Without offense your real friend,</l>
                <l>        It is Peter Folgier.</l></lg></q>
        </p><p><ref target="a0017" corresp="n0017">My elder brothers were all put apprentices to different trades.  I was put to the grammar-school at eight years of age, my father intending to devote me, as the tithe of his sons, to the service of the Church.</ref> My early readiness in learning to read (which must have been very early, as I do not remember when I could not read), and the opinion of all his friends, that I should certainly make a good scholar, encouraged him in this purpose of his.  My uncle Benjamin, too, approved of it, and proposed to give me all his short-hand volumes of sermons, I suppose as a stock to set up with, if I would learn his character.  I continued, however, at the grammar-school not quite one year, though in that time I had risen gradually from the middle of the class of that year to be the head of it, and farther was removed into the next class above it, in order to go with that into the third at the end of the year. But my father, in the meantime, from a view of the expense of a college education, which having so large a family he could not well afford, and the mean living many so educated were afterwards able to obtain reasons that be gave to his friends in my hearing altered his first intention, took me from the grammar-school, and sent me to a school for writing and arithmetic, kept by a then famous man, <ref target="a0018" corresp="n0018">Mr. George Brownell</ref>, very successful in his 
       <pb n="6" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p6.jpg"/>
       profession generally, and that by mild, encouraging methods. Under him I acquired fair writing pretty soon, but I failed in the arithmetic, and made no progress in it. At ten years old I was taken home to assist my father in his business, which was that of a tallow-chandler and sope-boiler; a business he was not bred to, but had assumed on his arrival in New England, and on finding his dying trade would not maintain his family, being in little request. Accordingly, I was employed in cutting wick for the candles, filling the dipping mold and the molds for cast candles, attending the shop, going of errands, etc.
        </p>
        <p><ref target="a0019" corresp="n0019">I disliked the trade, and had a strong inclination for the sea, but my father declared against it;</ref> however, living near the water, I was much in and about it, learnt early to swim well, and to manage boats; and when in a boat or canoe with other boys, I was commonly allowed to govern, especially in any case of difficulty; and upon other occasions I was generally a leader among the boys, and sometimes led them into scrapes, of which I will mention one instance, as it shows an early projecting public spirit, tho' not then justly conducted.
        </p>
        <p>There was a salt-marsh that bounded part of the mill-pond, on the edge of which, at high water, we used to stand to fish for minnows.  By much trampling, we had made it a mere quagmire.  My proposal was to build a wharff there fit for us to stand upon, and I showed my comrades a large heap of stones, which were intended for a new house near the marsh, and which would very well suit 
            <pb n="7" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p7.jpg"/>
            our purpose. Accordingly, in the evening, when the workmen were gone, I assembled a number of my play-fellows, and working with them diligently like so many <ref target="a0020" corresp="n0020">emmets</ref>, sometimes two or three to a stone, we brought them all away and built our little wharff.  The next morning the workmen were surprised at missing the stones, which were found in our wharff.  Inquiry was made after the removers; we were discovered and complained of; several of us were corrected by our fathers; and though I pleaded the usefulness of the work, mine convinced me that nothing was useful which was not honest.
        </p><p>I think you may like to know something of his person and character.  He had an excellent constitution of body, was of middle stature, but well set, and very strong; he was ingenious, could draw prettily, was skilled a little in music, and had a clear pleasing voice, so that when he played psalm tunes on his violin and sung withal, as he sometimes did in an evening after the business of the day was over, it was extremely agreeable to hear.  He had a mechanical genius too, and, on occasion, was very handy in the use of other tradesmen's tools; but his great excellence lay in a sound understanding and solid judgment in prudential matters, both in private and publick affairs.  In the latter, indeed, he was never employed, the numerous family he had to educate and the straitness of his circumstances keeping him close to his trade; but I remember well his being frequently visited by leading people, who consulted him for his opinion in affairs of the town or of the church he belonged to, and showed a good deal of respect for his judgment 
       <pb n="8" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p8.jpg"/>
       and advice: he was also much consulted by private persons about their affairs when any difficulty occurred, and frequently chosen an arbitrator between contending parties.
        </p><p>At his table he liked to have, as often as he could, some sensible friend or neighbor to converse with, and always took care to start some ingenious or useful topic for discourse, which might tend to improve the minds of his children.  By this means he turned our attention to what was good, just, and prudent in the conduct of life; and little or no notice was ever taken of what related to the victuals on the table, whether it was well or ill dressed, in or out of season, of good or bad flavor, preferable or inferior to this or that other thing of the kind, so that I was bro't up in such a perfect inattention to those matters as to be quite indifferent what kind of food was set before me, and so unobservant of it, that to this day if I am asked I can scarce tell a few hours after dinner what I dined upon.  This has been a convenience to me in travelling, where my companions have been sometimes very unhappy for want of a suitable gratification of their more delicate, because better instructed, tastes and appetites.
            
        </p><p>My mother had likewise an excellent constitution: she suckled all her ten children.  I never knew either my father or mother to have any sickness but that of which they dy'd, he at 89, and she at 85 years of age. They lie buried together at Boston, where I some years since placed a marble over their grave, with this inscription:
            
            JOSIAH FRANKLIN,<lb/>
            and<lb/>
            ABIAH his Wife,<lb/>
            lie here interred.<lb/>
            They lived lovingly together in wedlock<lb/>
            fifty-five years.<lb/>
            Without an estate, or any gainful employment,<lb/>
            By constant labor and industry,<lb/>
            with God's blessing,<lb/>
            They maintained a large family<lb/>
            comfortably,<lb/>
            and brought up thirteen children<lb/>
            and seven grandchildren<lb/>
            reputably.<lb/>
            From this instance, reader,<lb/>
            Be encouraged to diligence in thy calling,<lb/>
            And distrust not Providence.<lb/>
            He was a pious and prudent man;<lb/>
            She, a discreet and virtuous woman.<lb/>
            Their youngest son,<lb/>
            In filial regard to their memory,<lb/>
            Places this stone.<lb/>
            J.F. born 1655, died 1744, AEtat 89.<lb/>
            A.F. born 1667, died 1752, 85.<lb/>
            
           
            <pb n="9" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p9.jpg"/>

            
        </p><p>By my rambling digressions I perceive myself to be grown old.  I us'd to write more methodically.  But one does not dress for private company as for a publick ball.  'Tis perhaps only negligence.
            

        </p><p>To return: I continued thus employed in my father's business for two years, that is, till I was twelve years old; and my brother John, who was bred to that business, having left my father, married, and set up for himself at Rhode Island, there was all appearance that I was destined to supply his place, and become a tallow-chandler.  But my dislike to the trade continuing, my father was under apprehensions that if he did not find one for me more agreeable, I should break away and get to sea, as his son Josiah had done, to his great vexation.  He therefore sometimes took me to walk with him, and see joiners, bricklayers, turners, braziers, etc., at their work, that he might observe my inclination, and endeavor to fix it on some trade or other on land.  It has ever since been a pleasure to me to see good workmen handle their tools; and it has been useful to me, having learnt so much by it as to be able to do little jobs myself in my house when a workman could not readily be got, and to construct little machines <pb n="10" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p10.jpg"/>for my experiments, while the intention of making the experiment was fresh and warm in my mind.  My father at last fixed upon the cutler's trade, and my uncle Benjamin's son Samuel, who was bred to that business in London, being about that time established in Boston, I was sent to be with him some time on liking.  But his expectations of a fee with me displeasing my father, I was taken home again.

            
        </p><p>From a child I was fond of reading, and all the little money that came into my hands was ever laid out in books. Pleased with the Pilgrim's Progress, my first collection was of John Bunyan's works in separate little volumes.  I afterward sold them to enable me to buy <ref target="a0021" corresp="n0021">R. Burton's Historical Collections</ref>; they were small chapmen's books, and cheap, 40 or 50 in all.  My father's little library consisted chiefly of books in polemic divinity, most of which I read, and have since often regretted that, at a time when I had such a thirst for knowledge, more proper books had not fallen in my way since it was now resolved I should not be a clergyman.  Plutarch's Lives there was in which I read abundantly, and I still think that time spent to great advantage. There was also a book of De Foe's, called an <ref target="a0022" corresp="n0022">Essay on Projects</ref>, and another of Dr. Mather's, called <ref target="a0023" corresp="n0023">Essays to do Good</ref>, which perhaps gave me a turn of thinking that had an influence on some of the principal future events of my life.
            
        </p><p>This bookish inclination at length determined my father to make me a printer, though he had already one son (James) of that profession.  In 1717 my brother James returned from England with a press and letters to set up his business in Boston.  I liked it much better than that of my father, but still 

    
            <pb n="11" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p11.jpg"/>

            
            had a hankering for the sea.  To prevent the apprehended effect of such an inclination, my father was impatient to have me bound to my brother.  I stood out some time, but at last was persuaded, and signed the indentures when I was yet but twelve years old.  I was to serve as an apprentice till I was <ref target="a0024" corresp="n0024">twenty-one years of age</ref>, only I was to be allowed journeyman's wages during the last year.  In a little time I made great proficiency in the business, and became a useful hand to my brother.  I now had access to better books.  An acquaintance with the apprentices of booksellers enabled me sometimes to borrow a small one, which I was careful to return soon and clean. Often I sat up in my room reading the greatest part of the night, when the book was borrowed in the evening and to be returned early in the morning, lest it should be missed or wanted.
        </p>
       <p>And after some time an ingenious tradesman, Mr. Matthew Adams, who had a pretty collection of books, and who frequented our printing-house, took notice of me, invited me to his library, and very kindly lent me such books as I chose to read.  I now took a fancy to poetry, and made some little pieces; my brother, thinking it might turn to account, encouraged me, and put me on composing occasional ballads. One was called <hi rend="italic">The Lighthouse Tragedy,</hi> and contained an account of the drowning of Captain Worthilake, with his two daughters: the other was a sailor's song, on the taking of <hi rend="italic">Teach</hi> (or Blackbeard) the pirate.<ref target="a0025" corresp="n0025">They were wretched stuff</ref>, in the Grub-street-ballad style; and when they were printed he sent me about the town to sell them. The first sold wonderfully, the event being recent, having made a great noise.  This flattered my vanity; but my father discouraged me by ridiculing my performances, and telling me verse-makers were generally beggars.  So I escaped being a poet, most probably a very bad one; but as prose writing bad been of great use to me in the course of my life, and was a principal means of my advancement, 

           <pb n="12" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p12.jpg"/>
           I shall tell you how, in such a situation, I acquired what little ability I have in that way.
       </p>
       <p>There was another bookish lad in the town, John Collins by name, with whom I was intimately acquainted.  We sometimes disputed, and very fond we were of argument, and very desirous of confuting one another, which disputatious turn, by the way, is apt to become a very bad habit, making people often extremely disagreeable in company by the contradiction that is necessary to bring it into practice; and thence, besides souring and spoiling the conversation, is productive of disgusts and, perhaps enmities where you may have occasion for friendship.  I had caught it by reading my father's books of dispute about religion.  Persons of good sense, I have since observed, seldom fall into it, except lawyers, university men, and men of all sorts that have been bred at Edinborough.
           
       </p><p>A question was once, somehow or other, started between Collins and me, of the propriety of educating the female sex, and their abilities for study.  He was of opinion that it was improper, and that they were naturally unequal to it.  I took the contrary side, perhaps a little for dispute's sake.  He was naturally more eloquent, had a ready plenty of words; and sometimes, as I thought, bore me down more by his fluency than by the strength of his reasons. As we parted without settling the point, and were not to see 
           <pb n="13" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p13.jpg"/>
           one another again for some time, I sat down to put my arguments in writing, which I copied fair and sent to him. He answered, and I replied.  Three or four letters of a side had passed, when my father happened to find my papers and read them.  Without entering into the discussion, he took occasion to talk to me about the manner of my writing; observed that, though I had the advantage of my antagonist in correct spelling and  <ref target="a0026" corresp="n0026">pointing</ref> (which I ow'd to the printing-house), I fell far short in elegance of expression, in method and in perspicuity, of which he convinced me by several instances.  I saw the justice of his remark, and thence grew more attentive to the manner in writing, and determined to endeavor at improvement.
           
       </p><p>About this time I met with an odd volume of the <ref target="a0027" corresp="n0027"><hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi></ref>. It was <ref target="a0028" corresp="n0028">the third</ref>. I had never before seen any of them.  I bought it, read it over and over, and was much delighted with it.  I thought the writing excellent, and wished, if possible, to imitate it.  With this view I took some of the papers, and, making short hints of the sentiment in each sentence, laid them by a few days, and then, without looking at the book, try'd to compleat the papers again, by expressing each hinted sentiment at length, and as fully as it had been expressed before, in any suitable words that should come to hand.  Then I compared my <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> with the original, discovered some of my faults, and corrected them. But I found I wanted a stock of words, or a readiness in recollecting and using them, which I thought I should have acquired before that time if I had gone on making verses; since the continual occasion for words of the same import, but of different length, to suit the measure, or of different sound for the rhyme, would have laid me under a constant necessity of searching for variety, and also 
           <pb n="14" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p14.jpg"/>
           have tended to fix that variety in my mind, and make me master of it. Therefore I took some of the tales and turned them into verse; and, after a time, when I had pretty well forgotten the prose, turned them back again.  I also sometimes jumbled my collections of hints into confusion, and after some weeks endeavored to reduce them into the best order, before I began to form the full sentences and compleat the paper.  This was to teach me method in the arrangement of thoughts.  By comparing my work afterwards with the original, I discovered many faults and amended them; but I sometimes had the pleasure of fancying that, in certain particulars of small import, I had been lucky enough to improve the method or the language, and this encouraged me to think I might possibly in time come to be a tolerable English writer, of which I was extremely ambitious.  My time for these exercises and for reading was at night, after work or before it began in the morning, or on Sundays, when I contrived to be in the printing-house alone, evading as much as I could the common attendance on public worship which my father used to exact on me when I was under his care, and which indeed I still thought a duty, though I could not, as it seemed to me, afford time to practise it.
           
       </p><p>When about 16 years of age I happened to meet with a book, written by one Tryon, recommending <ref target="a0029" corresp="n0029">a vegetable diet</ref>. I determined to go into it.  My brother, being 
           <pb n="15" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p15.jpg"/>
           yet unmarried, did not keep house, but boarded himself and his apprentices in another family.  My refusing to eat flesh occasioned an inconveniency, and I was frequently chid for my singularity. I made myself acquainted with Tryon's manner of preparing some of his dishes, such as boiling potatoes or rice, making  <ref target="a0030" corresp="n0030">hasty pudding</ref>, and a few others, and then proposed to my brother, that if he would give me, weekly, half the money he paid for my board, I would board myself.  He instantly agreed to it, and I presently found that I could save half what he paid me.  This was an additional fund for buying books.  But I had another advantage in it.  My brother and the rest going from the printing-house to their meals, I remained there alone, and, despatching presently my light repast, which often was no more than a bisket or a slice of bread, a handful of raisins or a tart from the pastry-cook's, and a glass of water, had the rest of the time till their return for study, in which I made the greater progress, from that greater clearness of head and quicker apprehension which usually attend temperance in eating and drinking.
           
       </p><p>And now it was that, being on some occasion made asham'd of my ignorance in figures, which I had twice failed in learning when at school, I took <ref target="a0031" corresp="n0031">Cocker's book of Arithmetick</ref>, and went through the whole by myself with great ease.  I also read <ref target="a0032" corresp="n0032">Seller's and Shermy's books of Navigation</ref>, and became acquainted with the little geometry they contain; but never proceeded far in that science.  And I read about this time <ref target="s0033" corresp="n0033">Locke <hi rend="italic">On Human Understanding,</hi></ref> and <ref target="a0034" corresp="n0034">the <hi rend="italic">Art of Thinking,</hi> by Messrs. du Port Royal</ref>.
           
       </p><p>While I was intent on improving 
           <pb n="16" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p16.jpg"/>
           my language, I met with an English grammar (I think it was <ref target="a0035" corresp="n0035">Greenwood's)</ref>, at the end of which there were two little sketches of the arts of rhetoric and logic, the latter finishing with a specimen of a dispute in the Socratic method; and soon after I procur'd <ref target="a036" corresp="n0036">Xenophon's Memorable Things of Socrates</ref>, wherein there are many instances of the same method.  I was charm'd with it, adopted it, dropt my abrupt contradiction and positive argumentation, and put on the humble inquirer and doubter. And being then, from reading <ref target="a0037" corresp="n0037">Shaftesbury and Collins</ref>, become a real doubter in many points of our religious doctrine, I found this method safest for myself and very embarrassing to those against whom I used it; therefore I took a delight in it, practis'd it continually, and grew very artful and expert in drawing people, even of superior knowledge, into concessions, the consequences of which they did not foresee, entangling them in difficulties out of which they could not extricate themselves, and so obtaining victories that neither myself nor my cause always deserved.  I continu'd this method some few years, but gradually left it, retaining only the habit of expressing myself in terms of modest diffidence; never using, when I advanced any thing that may possibly be disputed, the words <hi rend="italic">certainly, undoubtedly,</hi> or any others that give the air of positiveness to an opinion; but rather say, I conceive or apprehend a thing to be so and so; it appears to me, or 
           
           <pb n="17" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p17.jpg"/>
           <hi rend="italic">I should think it so or so,</hi> for such and such reasons; or,<hi rend="italics">I imagine it to be so;</hi> or <hi rend="italic">it is so, if I am not mistaken</hi>.  This habit, I believe, has been of great advantage to me when I have had occasion to inculcate my opinions, and persuade men into measures that I have been from time to time engag'd in promoting; and, as the chief ends of conversation are to <hi rend="italics">inform</hi> or to be <hi rend="italics">informed,</hi> to <hi rend="italic">please</hi> or to <hi rend="italic">persuade,</hi> I wish well-meaning, sensible men would not lessen their power of doing good by a positive, assuming manner, that seldom fails to disgust, tends to create opposition, and to defeat every one of those purposes for which speech was given to us, to wit, giving or receiving information or pleasure.  For, if you would inform, a positive and dogmatical manner in advancing your sentiments may provoke contradiction and prevent a candid attention.  If you wish information and improvement from the knowledge of others, and yet at the same time express yourself as firmly fix'd in your present opinions, modest, sensible men, who do not love disputation, will probably leave you undisturbed in the possession of your error.  And by such a manner, you can seldom hope to recommend yourself in pleasing your hearers, or to persuade those whose concurrence you desire.<ref target="a0038" corresp="n0038">Pope says, judiciously</ref>:
   </p>
   <p>Men should be taught as if you taught them not,
   And things unknown propos'd as things forgot,</p>
      
       <pb n="18" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p18.jpg"/>

   <p> farther recommending it to us,</p>
       <p>To speak tho' sure, with seeming Diffidence.       
   </p>
      <p> And he might have coupled with this line that which he has coupled with another, I think, less properly,
       <lg type="line"><l> <hi rend="italics">"For want of modesty is want of sense."</hi></l></lg>
       If you ask, Why less properly? I must repeat the lines,
       <q><lg type="couplet"><l> <hi rend="italics"> "Immodest words admit of no defense,</hi></l>
           <l><hi rend="italics">For want of modesty is want of sense."</hi></l></lg></q>
Now, is not <hi rend="italics">want of sense</hi> (where a man is so unfortunate as to want it) some apology for his <hi rend="italic">want of modesty?</hi> and would not the lines stand more justly thus?
       
     
       <q><lg type="stanza"><l>"Immodest words admit <hi rend="italic">but</hi> this defense,</l>
           <l>That want of modesty is want of sense."</l></lg></q>
       This, however, I should submit to better judgments.</p>
       <p>My brother had, in 1720 or 1721, begun to print a newspaper.
           It was the second that appeared in America, and was called <ref target="a0039" corresp="n0039"><hi rend="italics">The New England Courant</hi>. The only one before it was <hi rend="italics">The Boston News-Letter</hi></ref>.  I remember his being dissuaded by some of his friends from the undertaking, as not likely to succeed, one newspaper being, in their judgment, enough for America. At this time (1771) there are not less than five-and-twenty.  He went on, however, with the undertaking, and after having worked in composing the types and printing off the sheets, I was employed to carry the papers thro' the streets to the customers.</p>
       
<p>He had some ingenious men among his friends, who amus'd themselves by writing little pieces for this paper, which gain'd it credit and made it more in demand, and these gentlemen often visited us.  Hearing their conversations, and their accounts of the approbation their papers were received with, 
    
    <pb n="19" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p19.jpg"/>
    
I was excited to try my hand among them; but, being still a boy, and suspecting that my brother would object to printing anything of mine in his paper if he knew it to be mine, I contrived to disguise my hand, and, <ref target="a0040" corresp="n0040">writing an anonymous paper</ref>, I put it in at night under the door of the printing-house.  It was found in the morning, and communicated to his writing friends when they call'd in as usual.  They read it, commented on it in my hearing, and I had the exquisite pleasure of finding it met with their approbation, and that, in their different guesses at the author, none were named but men of some character among us for learning and ingenuity.  I suppose now that I was rather lucky in my judges, and that perhaps they were not really so very good ones as I then esteem'd them.</p>
          
       <p>Encourag'd, however, by this, I wrote and convey'd in the same way to the press several more papers which were equally approv'd; and I kept my secret till my small fund of sense for such performances was pretty well exhausted and then I discovered it, when I began to be considered a little more by my brother's acquaintance, and in a manner that did not quite please him, as he thought, probably with reason, that it tended to make me too vain.  And, perhaps, this might be one occasion of the differences that we began to have about this time.  Though a brother, he considered himself as my master, and me as his apprentice, and accordingly, expected 
           <pb n="20" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p20.jpg"/>
           
the same services from me as he would from another, while I thought he demean'd me too much in some he requir'd of me, who from a brother expected more indulgence.  Our disputes were often brought before our father, and I fancy I was either generally in the right, or else a better pleader, because the judgment was generally in my favor.  But my brother was passionate, and had often beaten me, which I took extreamly amiss; and, thinking my apprenticeship very tedious, I was continually wishing for some opportunity of shortening it, which at length offered in a manner unexpected.</p>
       
       <p>One of the Pieces in our Newspaper on some political point, which I have now forgotten, gave offense to the Assembly. He was taken up, censur'd, and imprison'd for a month, by the speaker's warrant, I suppose, because he would not discover his author. I too was taken up and examin'd before the council; but, tho' I did not give them any satisfaction, they content'd themselves with admonishing me, and dismissed me, considering me, perhaps, as an apprentice, who was bound to keep his master's secrets.</p>
       
      <p>During my brother's confinement, which I resented a good deal, notwithstanding our private differences, I had the management of the paper; and I made bold to give our rulers some rubs in it, which my brother took very kindly,while others began to consider me in an unfavorable 
          
          <pb n="21" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p21.jpg"/>
          
light, as a young genius that had a turn for libelling and satyr. My brother's discharge was accompany'd with an order of the House (a very odd one), that <hi rend="italic">"James Franklin should no longer print the paper called the New England Courant."</hi>
       </p>
       <p>There was a consultation held in our printing-house among his friends, what he should do in this case.  Some proposed to evade the order by changing the name of the paper; but my brother, seeing inconveniences in that, it was finally concluded on as a better way, to let it be printed for the future under the name of <hi rend="italics">Benjamin Franklin</hi>; and to avoid the censure of the Assembly, that might fall on him as still printing it by his apprentice, the contrivance was that my old indenture should be return'd to me, with a full discharge on the back of it, to be shown on occasion, but to secure to him the benefit of my service, I was to sign new indentures for the remainder of the term, which were to be kept private.  A very flimsy scheme it was; however, it was immediately executed, and the paper went on accordingly, under my name for several months.
       </p>
       <p>At length, a fresh difference arising between my brother  and me, I took upon me to assert my freedom, presuming that he would not venture to produce the new indentures. It was not fair in me to take this 
           
           <pb n="22" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p22.jpg"/>
           
advantage, and this I therefore reckon one of the first errata of my life; but the unfairness of it weighed little with me, when under the impressions of resentment for the blows his passion too often urged him to bestow upon me, though he was otherwise not an ill-natur'd man: perhaps I was too saucy and provoking.
       </p>  
 <p>When he found I would leave him, he took care to preveny my getting employment in any other printing-house ofthe town, by going round and speaking to every master, who accordingly refus'd to give me work. I then thought of going to New York, as the nearest place where there was a printer; and I was rather inclin'd to leave Boston when I reflected that I had already made myself a little obnoxious to the governing party, and, from the arbitrary proceedings of the Assembly in my brother's case, it was likely I might, if I stay'd, soon bring myself into scrapes; and farther, that my indiscrete disputations about religion began to make me pointed at with horror by good people as an infidel or atheist.  I determin'd on the point, but my father now siding with my brother, I was sensible that, if I attempted to go openly, means would be used to prevent me. My friend Collins, therefore, undertook to manage a little for me.  He agreed with the captain of a New York sloop for my passage, under the notion of my being a young acquaintance of his, that had got a naughty girl with child, whose friends would compel me to marry her, and therefore I could not appear or come away publicly.</p>

<p>So I sold some of my books to raise a little money, was taken on board, and as we had a fair wind, in three days I found myself in New York, near 300 miles from home, a boy of but 17, but without the least recommendation, or knowledge of any person in the place, and with very little money in my pocket.
 </p>
       <pb n="23" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p23.jpg"/>
       
       <p>My inclinations for the sea were by this time worne out, or I might now have gratify'd them. But, having a trade, and supposing myself a pretty good workman, I offer'd my service to the printer in the place, old <ref target="a0041" corresp="n0041">Mr. William Bradford</ref>, who had been the first printer in Pennsylvania, but removed from thence upon the quarrel of George Keith.  He could give me no employment, having little to do, and help enough already; but says he, "My son at Philadelphia has lately lost his principal hand, Aquila Rose, by death; if you go thither, I believe he may employ you." Philadelphia was a hundred miles further; I set out, however, in a boat for <ref target="a0042" corresp="n0042">Amboy</ref>, leaving my chest and other things to follow me round by sea.
       </p>
       <p>In crossing the bay, we met with a squall that tore our rotten sails to pieces, prevented our getting into the <ref target="a0043" corresp="n0043">Kill</ref> and drove us upon Long Island. In our way, a drunken Dutchman, who was a passenger too, fell overboard; when he was sinking, I reached through the water to his <ref target="a0044" corresp="n0044">shock pate</ref>, and drew him up, so that we got him in again.  His ducking sobered him a little, and he went to sleep, taking first out of his pocket a book, which he desir'd I would dry for him. It proved to be my old favorite author, Bunyan's <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim's Progress</hi>, in Dutch, finely printed on good paper, with <ref target="a0045" corresp="n0045">copper cuts</ref>, a dress better than I had ever 
           <pb n="24" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p24.jpg"/>
           
           seen it wear in its own language. I have since found that it has been translated into most of the languages of Europe, and suppose it has been more generally read than any other book, except perhaps the Bible.  Honest John was the first that I know of who mix'd narration and dialogue; a method of writing very engaging to the reader, who in the most interesting parts finds himself, as it were, brought into the company and present at the discourse. <ref target="a0046" corresp="n0046">De Foe in his Cruso, his Moll Flanders, Religious Courtship, Family Instructor, and other pieces, has imitated it with success</ref>;and <ref target="a0047" corresp="n0047">Richardson has done the same, in his Pamela, etc.</ref>
       </p>
       <p>When we drew near the island, we found it was at a place where there could be no landing, there being a great surff on the stony beach.  So we dropt anchor, and swung round towards the shore. Some people came down to the water edge and hallow'd to us, as we did to them; but the wind was so high, and the surff so loud, that we could nothear so as to understand each other. There were canoes on the shore, and we made signs, and hallow'd that they should fetch us; but they either did not understand us, or thought it impracticable, so they went away, 
           <pb n="25" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p25.jpg"/>
           and night coming on, we had no remedy but to wait till the wind should abate; and, in the meantime, the boatman and I concluded to sleep, if we could; and so crowded into the scuttle, with the Dutchman, who was still wet, and the spray beating over the head of our boat, leak'd thro' to us, so that we were soon almost as wet as he. In this manner we lay all night, with very little rest; but, the wind abating the next day, we made a shift to reach Amboy before night, having been thirty hours on the water, without victuals, or any drink but a bottle of filthy rum, and the water we sail'd on being salt.
       </p>
       <p>In the evening I found myself very feverish, and went in to bed; but, having read somewhere that cold water drank plentifully was good for a fever, I follow'd the prescription, sweat plentiful most of the night, my fever left me, and in the morning, crossing the ferry, I proceeded on my journey on foot, having fifty miles to Burlington, where I was told I should find boats that would carry me the rest of the way to Philadelphia.
          </p>
       <p>It rained very hard all the day; I was thoroughly soak'd, and by noon a good deal tired; so I stopt at a poor 
           <pb n="26" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p26.jpg"/>
           inn, where I staid all night, beginning now to wish that I had never left home.  I cut so miserable a figure, too, that I found, by the questions ask'd me, I was suspected to be some runaway servant, and in danger of being taken up on that suspicion.  However, I proceeded the next day, and got in the evening  to an inn, within eight or ten milesn of Burlington, kept by one Dr. Brown.  He entered into conversation with me while I took some refreshment, and, finding I had read a little, became very sociable and friendly. Our acquaintance continu'd as long as he liv'd. He had been, I imagine, an <ref target="a0048" corresp="n0048">itinerant</ref> doctor, for there was no town in England, or country in Europe, of which he could not give a very particular account. He had some letters, and was ingenious, but much of an unbeliever, and <ref target="a0049" corresp="n0049">wickedly undertook, some years after, to travestie the Bible in doggrel verse as Cotton had done Virgil</ref>.  By this means he set many of the facts in a very ridiculous light, and might have hurt weak minds if his work had been published; but it never was.
       </p>
       <p>At his house I lay that night, and the next morning reach'd Burlington, but had the mortification to find that the regular boats<pb n="27" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p27.jpg"/> were gone a little before my coming, and no other expected to go before Tuesday, this being Saturday; wherefore I returned to an old woman in the town, of whom I had bought gingerbread to eat on the water, and ask'd her advice.  She invited me to lodge at her house till a passage by water should offer; and being tired with my foot travelling, I accepted the invitation.  She understanding I was a printer, would have had me stay at that town and follow my business, being ignorant of the stock necessary to begin with.  She was very hospitable, gave me a dinner of ox-cheek with great good will, accepting only a pot of ale in return; and I thought myself fixed till Tuesday should come.  However, walking in the evening by the side of the river, a boat came by, which I found was going towards Philadelphia, with several people in her. They took me in, and, as there was no wind, we row'd all the way; and about midnight, not having yet seen the city, some of the company were confident we must have passed it, and would row no farther; the others knew not where we were; so we put toward the shore, got into a creek, landed near an old fence, with the rails of which we made a fire, the night being cold, in October, and there we remained till daylight. Then one of the company knew the place to be Cooper's Creek, a little above Philadelphia, which we saw as soon as we got out of the creek, and arriv'd there about eight or nine o'clock on the Sunday morning, and landed at the Market-street wharf.
</p>
       <p>I have been the more particular in this description of my journey, and shall be so of my first entry into that city, that you may in your mind compare such unlikely beginnings with the figure I have since made there. I was in my working dress, my best cloaths being to come round by sea. I was dirty from my journey; my pockets were stuff'd out with shirts and stockings, and I knew no soul nor where  to look for lodging. I was fatigued with travelling, rowing, and want of rest, I was very hungry; and my whole stock of cash consisted of a Dutch dollar, and about a shilling in copper. The latter I gave the people of the boat for my passage, who at first refus'd it, on account 
           <pb n="28" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p28.jpg"/>
           of my rowing; but I insisted on their taking it.  A man being sometimes more generous when he has but a little money than when he has plenty, perhaps thro' fear of being thought to have but little.
       </p>
       <p>Then I walked up the street, gazing about till near the market-house I met a boy with bread.  I had made many a meal on bread, and, inquiring where he got it, I went immediately to the baker's he directed me to, in Second-street, and ask'd for bisket, intending such as we had in Boston; but they, it seems, were not made in Philadelphia. Then I asked for a three-penny loaf, and was told they had none such.  So not considering or knowing the difference of money, and the greater cheapness nor the names of his bread, I made him give me three-penny worth of any sort. He gave me, accordingly, three great puffy rolls.  I was surpriz'd at the quantity, but took it, and, having no room in my pockets, walk'd off with a roll under each arm, and eating the other.  Thus I went up Market-street as far as Fourth-street, passing by the door of Mr. Read, my future wife's father; when she, standing at the door, saw me, and thought I made, as I certainly did, a most awkward, ridiculous appearance.  Then I turned and went down Chestnut-street and part of Walnut-street, eating my roll all the way, and, coming round, found myself again at Market-street wharf, near the boat I came in, to which I went for a draught of the river water; and, being filled with one of my rolls, gave the other two to a woman and her child that came down the river in the boat with us, and were waiting to go farther.</p>
       
       <pb n="29" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p29.jpg"/>
       <p>Thus refreshed, I walked again up the street, which by this time had many clean-dressed people in it, who were all walking the same way.  I joined them, and thereby was led into the great meeting-house of the Quakers near the market.  I sat down among them, and, after looking round awhile and hearing nothing said, being very drowsy thro' labor and want of rest the preceding night, I fell fast asleep, and continued so till the meeting broke up, when one was kindenough to rouse me.  This was, therefore, the first house I was in, or slept in, in Philadelphia.
       </p>
       <p>Walking down again toward the river, and, looking in the faces of people, I met a young Quaker man, whose countenance I lik'd, and, accosting him, requested he would tell me where a stranger could get lodging.  We were then near the sign of the Three Mariners.  "Here," says he, "is one place that entertains strangers, but it is not a reputable house; if thee wilt walk with me, I'll show thee a better." He brought me to the Crooked Billet in Water-street.  Here I got a dinner; and, while I was eating it, several sly questions were asked me, as it seemed to be suspected from my youth and appearance, that I might be some runaway.
           
           <pb n="30" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p30.jpg"/>
       </p>
       <p>After dinner, my sleepiness return'd, and being shown to a bed, I lay down without undressing, and slept till six in the evening, was call'd to supper, went to bed again very early, and slept soundly till next morning.  Then I made myself as tidy as I could, and went to Andrew Bradford the printer's.  I found in the shop the old man his father, whom I had seen at New York, and who, travelling on horseback, had got to Philadelphia before me.  He introduc'd me to his son, who receiv'd me civilly, gave me a breakfast, but told me he did not at present want a hand, being lately suppli'd with one; but there was another printer in town, lately set up, one <ref target="a0050" corresp="n0050">Keimer</ref>, who, perhaps, might employ me; if not, I should be welcome to lodge at his house, and he would give me a little work to do now and then till fuller business should offer.
       </p>
       <p>The old gentleman said he would go with me to the new printer; and when we found him, "Neighbor," says Bradford, "I have brought to see you a young man of your business; perhaps you may want such a one." He ask'd me a few questions, put a composing stick in my hand to see how I work'd, and then said he would employ me soon, though he had just then nothing for me to do; and, taking old Bradford, whom he had never seen before, to be one of the town's people that had a good will for him, enter'd into a conversation on his present undertaking and projects; while Bradford, not
           <pb n="31" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p31.jpg"/>
           discovering that he was the other printer's father, on Keimer's saying he expected soon to get the greatest part of the business into his own hands, drew him on by artful questions, and starting little doubts, to explain all his views, what interests he reli'd on, and in what manner he intended to proceed.  I, who stood by and heard all, saw immediately that one of them was a crafty old sophister, and the other a mere novice.  Bradford left me with Keimer, who was greatly surpris'd when I told him who the old man was.
       </p>
       <p>Keimer's printing-house, I found, consisted of an old shatter'd press, and one small, worn-out font of English  which he was then using himself, composing an <ref target="a0051" corresp="n0051">Elegy on Aquila Rose</ref>, before mentioned, an ingenious young man, of excellent character, much respected in the town, clerk of the Assembly, and a pretty poet.  Keimer made verses too, but very indifferently.  He could not be said to write them, for his manner was to compose them in the types directly out of his head.  So there being no copy, but one pair of cases, and the Elegy likely to require all the letter, no one could help him.  I endeavor'd to put his press (which he had not yet us'd, and of which he understood nothing) into order fit to be work'd with; and, promising to come and print off his Elegy as soon as he should have got it ready, I return'd to Bradford's, who gave me a little job to do for the present, and there I lodged and dieted, A few days after, Keimer sent for me to print off the Elegy.  And  <pb n="32" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p32.jpg"/>now he had got another pair of cases, and a pamphlet to reprint, on which he set me to work.
       </p>
       <p>These two printers I found poorly qualified for their business. Bradford had not been bred to it, and was very illiterate; and Keimer, tho' something of a scholar, was a <ref target="a0052" corresp="n0052">mere compositor, knowing nothing of presswork</ref>. He had been one of the <ref target="a0053" corresp="n0053">French prophets</ref>, and could act their enthusiastic agitations.  At this time he did not profess any particular religion, but something of all on occasion; was very ignorant of the world, and had, as I afterward found, a good deal of the knave in his composition.  He did not like my lodging at Bradford's while I work'd with him.  He had a house, indeed, but without furniture, so he could not lodge me; but he got me a lodging at Mr. Read's, before mentioned, who was the owner of his house; and, my chest and  clothes being come by this time, I made rather a more respectable appearance in the eyes of Miss Read than I had done when she first happen'd to see me eating my roll in the street.
       </p>
       <p>I began now to have some acquaintance among the young people of the town, that were lovers of reading, with whom I spent my evenings very pleasantly; and gaining money by my industry and frugality, I lived very agreeably, forgetting Boston as much as I could, and not desiring that any there should know where I resided, except my friend Collins, who was in my secret, and kept it when I wrote to him.  At length, an incident happened that sent me back again much sooner than I had intended.  <pb n="33" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p33.jpg"/> I had a brother-in-law, Robert Holmes, master of a sloop that traded between Boston and Delaware.  He being at Newcastle, forty miles below Philadelphia, heard there of me, and wrote me a letter mentioning the concern of my friends in Boston at my abrupt departure, assuring me of their good will to me, and that every thing would be accommodated to my mind if I would return, to which he exhorted me very earnestly I wrote an answer to his letter, thank'd him for his advice, but stated my reasons for quitting Boston fully and in such a light as to convince him I was not so wrong as he had apprehended.
       </p>
       <p><ref target="a0054" corresp="n0054">Sir William Keith, governor of the province</ref>, was then at  Newcastle, and Captain Holmes, happening to be in company with him when my letter came to hand, spoke to him of me, and show'd him the letter.  The governor read it, and seem'd surpris'd when he was told my age.  He said I appear'd a young man of promising parts, and therefore should be encouraged; the printers at Philadelphia were wretched ones; and, if I would set up there, he made no doubt I should succeed; for his part, he would procure me the public business, and do me every other service in his power.  This my brother-in-law afterwards told me in Boston, but I knew as yet nothing of it; when, one day, Keimer and I being at  <pb n="34" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p34.jpg"/>work together near the window, we saw the governor and another gentleman (which proved to be Colonel French, of Newcastle), finely dress'd, come directly across the street to our house, and heard them at the door.
       </p>
       <p>Keimer ran down immediately, thinking it a visit to him; but the governor inquir'd for me, came up, and with a condescension of politeness I had been quite unus'd to, made me many compliments, desired to be acquainted with me, blam'd me kindly for not having made myself known to him when I first came to the place, and would have me away with him to the tavern, where he was going with <ref target="a0055" corresp="n0055">Colonel French to taste, as he said, some excellent Madeira</ref>. I was not a little surprised, and Keimer star'd like a pig poison'd.  I went, however, with the governor and Colonel French to a tavern, at the corner of Third-street, and over the Madeira he propos'd my setting up my business, laid before me the probabilities of success, and both he and Colonel French assur'd me I should have their interest and influence in procuring the public business of both governments. On my doubting whether my father would assist me in it, Sir William said he would give me a letter to him, in which he would state the advantages, and he did not doubt of prevailing with him.  So it was concluded I should return to Boston in the first vessel, with the governor's letter recommending me to my father.  In the mean time the intention was to be kept a secret, and I went on working with Keimer as usual, the governor sending for me now and then to dine with him, a very great honor I thought it, and conversing with me in the most affable, familiar, and  friendly manner imaginable. <pb n="35" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p35.jpg"/>
       </p>
       <p>About the end of April, 1724, a little vessel offer'd for Boston.  I took leave of Keimer as going to see my friends. The governor gave me an ample letter, saying many flattering things of me to my father, and strongly recommending the project of my setting up at Philadelphia as a thing that must make my fortune.  We struck on a <ref target="a0056" corresp="n0056">shoal</ref> in going down the bay, and sprung a leak; we had a blustering time at sea, and were oblig'd to pump almost continually, at which I took my turn.  We arriv'd safe, however, at Boston in about a <ref target="a0057" corresp="n0057">fortnight</ref>.  I had been absent seven months, and my friends had heard nothing of me; for my br.  Holmes was not yet return'd, and had not written about me.  My unexpected appearance surpriz'd the family; all were, however, very glad to see me, and made me welcome, except my brother.  I went to see him at his printing-house.  I was better dress'd than ever while in his service, having a genteel new suit from head to foot, a watch, and my pockets lin'd with near five pounds sterling in silver.  He receiv'd me not very frankly, look'd me all over, and turn'd to his work again.
       </p>
       <p>The journeymen were inquisitive where I had been, what sort of a country it was, and how I lik'd it.  I prais'd it much, the happy life I led in it, expressing strongly my intention of returning to it; and, one of them asking what kind of money we had there, I produc'd a handful of silver, and spread it before them, which was a kind of <ref target="a0058" corresp="n0058">raree-show</ref> they had not been us'd to, paper being the money of Boston. Then I took an opportunity of letting them see my watch; and, lastly (my brother still grum and sullen), I gave them a piece of eight to drink, and took my leave.  <pb n="36" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p36.jpg"/> This visit of  mine offended him extreamly; for, when my mother some time after spoke to him of a reconciliation, and of her wishes to see us on good terms together, and that we might live for the future as brothers, he said I had insulted him in such a manner before his people that he could never forget or forgive it.  In this, however, he was mistaken.
       </p>
       <p>My father received the governor's letter with some apparent surprise, but said little of it to me for some days, when Capt. Holmes returning he showed it to him, ask'd him if he knew Keith, and what kind of man he was; adding his opinion that he must be of small discretion to think of setting a boy up in business who wanted yet three years of being at man's estate.  Holmes said what he could in favor of the project, but my father was clear in the impropriety of it, and at last gave a flat denial to it.  Then he wrote a civil letter to Sir William, thanking him for the patronage he had so kindly offered me, but declining toassist me as yet in setting up, I being, in his opinion, too young to be trusted with the management of a business so important, and for which the preparation must be so expensive.</p>
       
       <p>My friend and companion <ref target="a0059" corresp="n0059">Collins</ref>, who was a clerk in the post-office, pleas'd with the account I gave him of my new country, determined to go thither also; and, while I waited  for my father's determination, he set out before me by land to Rhode Island, leaving his books, which were a pretty <pb n="37" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p37.jpg"/>collection of mathematicks and natural philosophy, to come with mine and me to New York, where he propos'd to wait for me.
</p>
       <p>My father, tho' he did not approve Sir William's proposition, was yet pleas'd that I had been able to obtain so advantageous a character from a person of such note where I had resided, and that I had been so industrious and careful as to equip myself so handsomely in so short a time; therefore,  seeing no prospect of an accommodation between my brother and me, he gave his consent to my returning again to Philadelphia, advis'd me to behave respectfully to the people there, endeavor to obtain the general esteem, and avoid <ref target="a0060" corresp="n0060">lampooning</ref> and libeling, to which he thought I had too much inclination; telling me, that by steady industry and a prudent parsimony I might save enough by the time I was one-and-twenty to set me up; and that, if I came near the matter, he would help me out with the rest.  This was all I could obtain, except some small gifts as tokens of his and my mother's love, when I embark'd again for New York, now with their approbation and their blessing.
</p>
       <p>The sloop putting in at Newport, Rhode Island, I visited my brother John, who had been married and settled there some years.  He received me very affectionately, for he always lov'd me.  A friend of his, one Vernon, having some money due to him in Pensilvania, about thirty-five pounds currency, desired I would receive it for him, and keep it till I had his directions what to remit it in.  Accordingly, he gave me an order.  This afterwards occasion'd me a good deal of uneasiness.
</p>
       <p>At Newport we took in a number of passengers for New York, among which were two <pb n="38" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p38.jpg"/>young women, companions, and a grave, sensible, matron-like Quaker woman, with her attendants.  I had shown an obliging readiness to do her some little services, which impress'd her I suppose with a degree of good will toward me; therefore, when she saw a daily growing familiarity between me and the two young women, which they appear'd to encourage, she took me aside, and said: "Young man, I am concern'd for thee, as thou has no friend with thee, and seems not to know much of the world, or of the snares youth is expos'd to; depend upon it, those are very bad women; I can see it in all their actions; and if thee art not upon thy guard, they will draw thee into some danger; they are strangers to thee, and I advise thee, in a friendly concern for thy welfare, to have no acquaintance with them." As I seem'd at first not to think so ill of them as she did, she mentioned some things she had observ'd and heard that had escap'd my notice, but now convinc'd me she was right.  I thank'd her for her kind advice, and promis'd to follow it.  When we arriv'd at New York, they told me where they liv'd, and invited me to come and see them; but I avoided it, and it was well I did; for the next day the captain miss'd a silver spoon and some other things, that had been taken out of his cabbin, and, knowing that these were a couple of <ref target="a0061" corresp="n0060">strumpets</ref>, he got a warrant to search their lodgings, found the stolen goods, and had the thieves punish'd. So, tho' we had escap'd a sunken rock, which we scrap'd upon in the passage, I thought this escape of rather more importance to me.
</p>
       <pb n="39" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p39.jpg"/>
       <p>At New York I found my friend Collins, who had arriv'd there some time before me.  We had been intimate from children, and had read the same books together; but he had the advantage of more time for reading and studying, and a wonderful genius for mathematical learning, in which he far outstript me.  While I liv'd in Boston most of my hours of leisure for conversation were spent with him, and he continu'd a sober as well as an industrious lad; was much respected for his learning by several of the clergy and other gentlemen, and seemed to promise making a good figure in life.  But, during my absence, he had acquir'd a habit of sotting with brandy; and I found by his own account, and what I heard from others, that he had been drunk every day since his arrival at New York, and behav'd very oddly. He had gam'd, too, and lost his money, so that I was oblig'd to discharge his lodgings, and defray his expenses to and at Philadelphia, which prov'd extremely inconvenient to me.
</p>
       <p>The then governor of New York, <ref target="a0062" corresp="n0062">Burnet (son of Bishop Burnet)</ref>, hearing from the captain that a young man, one of his passengers, had a great many books, desir'd he would bring me to see him.  I waited upon him accordingly, and should have taken Collins with me but that he was not sober. The gov'r. treated me with great civility, show'd me his library, which was a very large one, and we had a good deal of conversation about books and authors.  This was the second governor who had done me the honor to take <pb n="40" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p40.jpg"/> notice of me; which, to a poor boy like me, was very pleasing.
</p>
       <p>We proceeded to Philadelphia. I received on the way Vernon's money, without which we could hardly have finish'd our journey.  Collins wished to be employ'd in some counting-house, but, whether they discover'd his <ref target="a0063" corresp="n0063">dramming</ref> by his breath, or by his behaviour, tho' he had some recommendations, he met with no success in any application, and continu'd lodging and boarding at the same house with me, and at my expense.  Knowing I had that money of Vernon's, he was continually borrowing of me, still promising repayment as soon as he should be in business.  At length he had got so much of it that I was distress'd to think what I should do in case of being call'd on to remit it.
</p>
       <p>His drinking continu'd, about which we sometimes quarrell'd; for, when a little intoxicated, he was very fractious. Once, in a boat on the Delaware with some other young men, he refused to row in his turn.  "I will be row'd home," says he.  "We will not row you," says I. "You must, or stay all night on the water," says he, "just as you please.The others said, "Let us row; what signifies it?" But, my mind being soured with his other conduct, I continu'd to refuse.  So he swore he would make me row, or throw me overboard; and coming along, stepping on the thwarts, toward me, when he came up and struck at me, I clapped my hand under his crotch, and, rising, pitched him head-foremost into the river.  I knew he was a good swimmer, and so was under little concern about him; but before he could get round to lay hold of the boat, we had with a few strokes pull'd her out of his reach; and ever when he drew near the boat, we ask'd if he would row, striking a few strokes to slide her away from him.  He was ready to die with vexation, and obstinately would not promise to row. However, seeing him at last beginning to tire, we lifted him in and brought him home dripping wet in the evening. We hardly exchang'd a civil word afterwards, and a West India captain, who had a commission to procure a tutor for the sons of a gentleman at Barbadoes, happening to meet with him, agreed to carry him thither.  He left me then, promising to remit me the first money he should receive in order to discharge the debt; but I never heard of him after.
</p>
       <p>The breaking into this money of Vernon's was one of the first great <ref target="a0064" corresp="n0064">errata</ref> of my life; and this affair show'd that my father was not much out in his judgment when he suppos'd me too young to manage business of importance.  But Sir William, on reading his letter, said he was too prudent. <pb n="41" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p41.jpg"/>There was great difference in persons; and discretion did not always accompany years, nor was youth always without it. "And since he will not set you up," says he, "I will do it myself.  Give me an inventory of the things necessary to be had from England, and I will send for them. You shall repay me when you are able; I am resolv'd to have a good printer here, and I am sure you must succeed." This was spoken with such an appearance of cordiality, that I had not the least doubt of his meaning what he said.  I had hitherto kept the proposition of my setting up, a secret in Philadelphia, and I still kept it.  Had lt been known that I depended on the governor, probably some friend, that knew him better, would have advis'd me not to rely on him, as I afterwards heard it as his known character to be liberal of promises which he never meant to keep.  Yet, unsolicited as he was by me, how could I think his generous offers insincere? I believ'd him one of the best men in the world.
</p>
       <p>I presented him an inventory of a little print'g-house, amounting by my computation to about <ref target="a0064a" corresp="n0064a">one hundred pounds sterling</ref> . He lik'd it, but ask'd me if my being on the spot in England to chuse the types, and see that every thing was  good of the kind, might not be of some advantage.  "Then," says he, <pb n="42" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p42.jpg"/> "when there, you may make acquaintances, and establish correspondences in the bookselling and stationery way." I agreed that this might be advantageous.  "Then," says he, "get yourself ready to go with <ref target="a0065" corresp="n0065">Annis</ref>;" which was the annual ship, and the only one at that time usually passing between London and Philadelphia.  But it would be some months before Annis sail'd, so I continu'd working with Keimer, fretting about the money Collins had got from me, and in daily apprehensions of being call'd upon by Vernon, which, however, did not happen for some years after.
</p>
       <p>I believe I have omitted mentioning that, in my first voyage from Boston, being <ref target="a0066" corresp="n0066">becalm'd</ref> off Block Island, our people set about catching cod, and hauled up a great many. Hitherto I had stuck to my resolution of not eating animal food, and on this occasion consider'd, with my master Tryon, the taking every fish as a kind of unprovoked murder, since none of them had, or ever could do us any injury that might justify the slaughter.  All this seemed very reasonable. But I had formerly been a great lover of fish, and, when this came hot out of the frying-pan, it smelt admirably well.  I balanc'd some time between principle and inclination, till I recollected that, when the fish were opened, I saw smaller fish taken out of their stomachs; then thought I, "If you eat one another, I don't see why we mayn't eat you." So I din'd upon cod very heartily, and continued to eat with other people, returning only now and then occasionally to a vegetable diet.  So convenient a thing it is to be a <hi rend="italic">reasonable creature,</hi> since it enables one to find or make a reason for everything one has a mind to do.
</p>
       <p>Keimer and I liv'd on a pretty good familiar footing, and agreed tolerably well, for he suspected nothing of my setting up. <pb n="43" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p43.jpg"/>He retained a great deal of his old enthusiasms and lov'd argumentation. We therefore had many disputations. I used to work him so with my Socratic method, and had <ref target="a0067" corresp="n0067">trepann'd</ref> him so often by questions apparently so distant from any point we had in hand, and yet by degrees lead to the point, and brought him into difficulties and contradictions, that at last he grew ridiculously cautious, and would hardly answer me the most common question, without asking first, <hi rend="italic">"What do you intend to infer from that?"</hi> However, it gave him so high an opinion of my abilities in the confuting way, that he seriously proposed my being his colleague in a project he had of setting up a new sect. He was to preach the doctrines, and I was to confound all opponents.  When he came to explain with me upon the doctrines, I found several conundrums which I objected to, unless I might have my way a little too, and introduce some of mine.
</p>
       <p>Keimer wore his beard at full length, because somewhere in the <ref target="a0068" corresp="n0068">Mosaic law</ref> it is said, <hi rend="italic">"Thou shalt not mar the corners of thy beard."</hi> He likewise kept the <ref target="a0069" corresp="n0069">Seventh day, Sabbath</ref>; and these two points were essentials with him.  I dislik'd  both; but agreed to admit them upon condition of his adopting the doctrine of using no animal food. "I doubt," said he, "my constitution will not bear that." I assur'd him it would, and that he would be the better for it.  He was usually a great glutton, and I promised myself some diversionin half starving him.  He agreed to try the practice, if I would keep him company.  I did so, and we held it for three months.  We had our victuals dress'd, and brought to us regularly by a woman in the neighborhood, who had from me a list of forty dishes to be prepar'd for us at different times, in all which there was neither fish, flesh, nor fowl, and the whim suited me the better at this time from the cheapness of it, not costing us above eighteenpence sterling each per week.  I have since kept several Lents most strictly, leaving the common diet for that, and that for the common, abruptly, without the least inconvenience, so that I think there is little in the advice of making those changes by easy gradations.  I went on pleasantly, but poor Keimer suffered grievously, tired of the project, long'd for the <ref target="a0070" corresp="n0070">flesh-pots</ref> of Egypt, and order'd a roast pig.  He invited me and two women friends to dine with him; but, it being brought too soon upon table, he could not resist the temptation, and ate the whole before we came.
</p>
       
       <p>I had made some courtship during this time to Miss Read. I had a great respect and affection for her, and had some reason to believe she had the same for me; but, as I was about to take a long voyage, and we were both very young, only a little above eighteen, it was thought most prudent by her mother to prevent our going too far at present, as a marriage, if it was to take place, would be more convenient after my return, when I should be, as I expected,set up in my business.  Perhaps, too, she thought my expectations not so well founded as I imagined them to be.
</p>
       <p>My chief acquaintances at this time were <ref target="a0071" corresp="n0071">Charles Osborne, Joseph Watson, and James Ralph</ref>, all lovers of reading. The two first were clerks to an eminent scrivener or conveyancer in the town, Charles Brogden; the other was clerk to a merchant. <pb n="44" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p44.jpg"/> Watson was a pious, sensible young man, of great integrity; the others rather more lax in their principles of religion, particularly Ralph, who, as well as Collins, had been unsettled by me, for which they both made me suffer.  Osborne was sensible, candid, frank; sincere and affectionate to his friends; but, in literary matters, too fond of criticising.  Ralph was ingenious, genteel in his manners, and extremely eloquent; I think I never knew a prettier talker.  Both of them great admirers of poetry, and began to try their hands in little pieces.  Many pleasant walks we four had together on Sundays into the woods, near <ref target="a0072" corresp="n0072">Schuylkill</ref>, where we read to one another, and conferr'd on what we read.
</p>
       <p>Ralph was inclin'd to pursue the study of poetry, not doubting but he might become eminent in it, and make his fortune by it, alleging that the best poets must, when they first began to write, make as many faults as he did.  Osborne dissuaded him, assur'd him he had no genius for poetry, and advis'd him to think of nothing beyond the business he was bred to; that, in the mercantile way, tho' he had no stock, he might, by his diligence and punctuality, recommend himself to employment as a factor, and in time acquire wherewith to trade on his own account.  I approv'd the amusing one's self with poetry now and then, so far as to improve one's language, but no farther.
</p>
       <p>On this it was propos'd that we should each of us, at our next meeting, produce a piece of our own composing, in order to improve by our mutual observations, criticisms, and corrections.  As language and expression were what we had in view, we excluded all considerations of invention by agreeing that the <pb n="45" facs="pageImages/Franklin-p45.jpg"/>task should be a version of the eighteenth Psalm, which describes the descent of a Deity. When the time of our meeting drew nigh, Ralph called on me first, and let me know his piece was ready.  I told him I had been busy, and, having little inclination, had done nothing.  He then show'd me his piece for my opinion, and I much approv'd it, as it appear'd to me to have great merit.  "Now," says he, "Osborne never will allow the least merit in any thing of mine, but makes 1000 criticisms out of mere envy.  He is not so jealous of you; I wish, therefore, you would take this piece, and produce it as yours; I will pretend not to have had time, and so produce nothing. We shall then see what he will say to it." It was agreed, and I immediately transcrib'd it, that it might appear in my own hand.
</p>
       <p>We met; Watson's performance was read; there were some beauties in it, but many defects.  Osborne's was read; it was much better; Ralph did it justice; remarked some faults, but applauded the beauties.  He himself had nothing to produce.  I was backward; seemed desirous of being excused; had not had sufficient time to correct, etc.; but no excuse could be admitted; produce I must.  It was read and repeated; Watson and Osborne gave up the contest, and join'd in applauding it.  Ralph only made some criticisms, and propos'd some amendments; but I defended my text.  Osborne was against Ralph, and told him he was no better a critic than poet, so he dropt the argument.  As they two went home together, Osborne expressed himself still more strongly in favor of what he thought my production;having restrain'd himself before, as he said, lest I should think it flattery.  "But who would have imagin'd," said he, "that Franklin had been capable of such a performance; such painting, such force, such fire! He has even improv'd the original.  In his common conversation he seems to have no choice of words; he hesitates and blunders; and yet, good God! how he writes!" When we next met, Ralph discovered the trick we had plaid him, and Osborne was a little laught at.
</p>
      
   </body>
            <back>
            <note xml:id="n0001" target="a0001" type="headnote" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><p>
                
            <graphic url="notes/Benjamin_Franklin_by_Joseph_Siffrein_Duplessis.jpg" style="float:right" width="400px"/>
                The book that we know as Benjamin Franklin's "Autobiography" was composed in several stages over more than two decades, and was never printed or published in Franklin's lifetime. And Franklin's conception of what this book was and what its purposes should be changed over time. The first section was composed in the summer of 1771, when Franklin, then living in London and serving as the colonial representative for several of the American colonies, was on an extended visit to the country home of his friend Jonathan Shipley. The text, which Franklin thought of as his "memoir" or his "life" took the ostensible form of a letter to his son William, though it is clear that this is a fiction, and that this was never a "letter" in the conventional sense, one intended to go through the post to its recipient. The later sections, composed in stages in the 1780s, seem addressed to a more general audience, in part perhaps because of Franklin's estrangement from his son, but also perhaps because Franklin saw this book as an opportunity to address a larger audience.</p>
                <p>The manuscript, here titled "The Life of Benjamin Franklin" by an unknown hand, is unfinished. Franklin picked up the manuscript in late 1789 and early 1790, but died before completing his memoir, which only goes up to the 1760s. The publication of the manuscript is complicated, and it was not for several decades the the "Autobiography" assumed the form and the title that it now generally bears. Our edition includes page images of the original manuscript, which is housed at the Huntington Library in California. We have edited it to make it legible to modern reader, expanding abbreviations and regularizing the spelling. Our annotations are designed to provide important contextual information that Franklin's first readers would have known.</p></note>
  
            <note xml:id="n0002" target="a0002" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Jonathan Shipley (1714-1788) <p><graphic url="notes/Jonathan-Shipley.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/>was the bishop of St. Asaph in Wales, but he spent much of his time at Twyford House, a large Tudor-era mansion in Hampshire in the south of England that had been in his family for generations. Shipley became a good friend and correspondent of Franklin's. He was sympathetic to the cause of the American colonists in their conflict with the government in London. Franklin wrote the first section of this memoir while he was visiting Shipley and his family at Twyford House for several weeks in July and August 1771. </p></note>
                
            <note xml:id="n0003" target="a0003" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">William Franklin (c. 1730-1813) was Benjamin's illegitimate son. His mother has never been identified with complete confidence; it might have been Franklin's common-law wife Deborah Read, but it also might have been another woman whose identity is lost to history. William worked with his father in London, when Benjamin Franklin was serving as the representative of several of the American colonies to the government in Westminster. In 1771, when this part of the narrative was written, he held the position of the royal governor of New Jersey. Father and son would later be estranged over the American Revolutionary War; William remained loyal to the British crown and became a leading Loyalist opposing the American rebels. This of course included his father, who could not understand how his son could oppose him. William and Benjamin met a few times after the war, but never really reconciled. <graphic url="notes/William_Franklin.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/></note>
                
            <note xml:id="n0004" target="a0004" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Franklin's figurative language wryly draws on his experience as a printer here and many times in the book, most obviously in his reflections on the "errata" or mistakes of his life, "errata" being a print-house term for a typographical error.</note>
                
           <note xml:id="n0005" target="a0005" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Prejudicial, adverse, unfavourable, darkly suspicious." (OED)</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0006" target="a0006" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">The word "franklin" was a class signifier in England from the twelfth through the fifteenth centuries. A franklin was a free man ranking between the classes of serf and landed gentry. Franklins often owned land, but not enough to raise them anything close to the ranks of the gentry. The thirty acres that Benjamin Franklin describes as being owned by his ancestor was typical; enough of one's own land to survive, but not enough to become wealthy. For a classic literary example of a Franklin, see Chaucer's Franklin in <hi rend="italic">The Canterbury Tales.</hi></note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0007" target="a0007" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">"Permanent and absolute tenure of land or property with freedom to dispose of it at will." Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0008" target="a0008" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">A person employed to copy or transcribe documents, or to write documenets on behalf of someone else; a scribe, a copyiest; a clerk, a secretary." Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0009" target="a0009" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">For much of its history England used the Julian calendar (originally introduced by Julius Caesar in 46 B.C.) which was rather inaccurate over long periods of time. By the eighteenth century England was several days behind the rest of Europe, which used the Gregorian calendar. Britain switched over to the Gregorian calendar in 1752 A.D. by an act of Parliament, resulting in the "loss" of several days. For this reason, Franklin had to celebrate his birthday on the 17th of January instead of the 6th, and resulting in his need for a clarification of the date as in the "old style."</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0010" target="a0010" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">that is, in manuscript</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0011" target="a0011" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">"Folio," "quarto," and "octavo" denote sizes of books, determined by the standard size of paper used in a print shop. A folio is a large volume where the paper is folded once; a quarto (sized at one-fourth the sheet) is half that size, and an octavo (where each page one-eighth of the sheet) is half the size of that. This would have been a very substantial collection of pamphlets.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0012" target="a0012" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The Franklin family's story, as told here, was fairly typical of that of many English families, as their religious faith intersected with and was shaped by political events. By "early in the Reformation," Franklin marks that his family left the Roman Catholic Church (mocked by many as "popery") not long after Henry VIII separated from Rome in 1534, founding the Church of England. When his daughter Mary became Queen in 1553, she returned England to the religious jurisdiction of the Roman Catholic Church, and persecuted prominent Protestants.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0013" target="a0013" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">A Bible translated into English. The Roman church had preferred to use the Bible in Latin, but after the Reformation, there was a new emphasis on individuals being able to read the Bible for themselves, and a spate of translations into English emerged, such as the one done by William Tyndale and Miles Coverdale, available by the late 1530s; the Franklin family Bible might have been this edition.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0014" target="a0014" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Nonconformity: Refusal to conform to the doctrine, discipline, or usages of the Church of England, or of any established church, etc.; the principles or practice of nonconformists. Now usually: Protestant dissent; the body of nonconformists or nonconformist opinion. Conventicle: A meeting of (Protestant) Nonconformists or Dissenters from the Church of England for religious worship, during the period when such meetings were prohibited by the law. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0015" target="a0015" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Peter Folger (1617-1690): Folger, born in Norwich, migrated to Massachusetts in 1635. He learned the Algonquian language and became an interpreter and “intermediary with the American Indian population” on the islands of Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket. He also worked other jobs such as teacher, surveyor, farmer, and clerk of courts. His was a prominent family that produced “American scientists, merchants, and politicians, the most famous of whom was Benjamin Franklin, Folger’s grandson.” Source: Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0016" target="a0016" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF"><p>Cotton Mather, born in Boston, Massachusetts in 1663 to one of the city's most influential families, became arguably the most prominent minister in the American colonies. <graphic url="notes/Cotton_Mather.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/> Indeed, his influence was so widely felt he could be described as one of the major transatlantic figures of the time. Ordained at Boston's North Church, he served there as minister for the entirety of his career. However, Mather's influence was not only limited to religion. He was politically active, and he studied science as well, eventually gaining admittance to London's Royal Society.</p>  
                <p> A prolific author, he published approximately 380 texts, including <hi rend="italic">Magnalia Christi Americana</hi> (on the movement of Christianity from Europe to America) and Bonifacius, <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi>. By the end of his life, Mather’s influence on Christianity in the colonies laid the groundwork for religious figures such as Jonathan Edwards. Mather died in February 1728 at the age of 65.</p>
                <p>Mather’s works were wide-reaching, so it is unsurprising that Franklin felt his influence—most notably through Mather’s <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi>. While working as an apprentice in his brother’s print shop in 1722, sixteen-year-old Franklin wrote essays under the pseudonym of Silence Dogood—the surname "Dogood" was surely taken directly from Mather’s title. The persona Franklin assumed as Silence Dogood was a middle-aged minister’s widow who wrote on a variety of social topics such as politics, fashion, and education. Franklin silently slid these essays under the door of his brother’s business, hoping for publication. His ploy worked, and Franklin's pseudonymous works were published until October of 1722. Some critics have suggested that the the pseudonym and some of the essays were actually a mockery of Mather since the initial run of essays from Silence Dogood appeared at approximately the same time as widespread debates surrounding inoculation, a practice opposed by James Franklin, Benjamin’s brother and owner of <hi rend="italic">The New England Courant.</hi></p>
                <p>For his part, Mather was a strong proponent of inoculation to the extent that in 1721, Mather and Dr. Zabdiel Boylston inoculated over 200 people during a smallpox epidemic, in the process eliciting a certain amount of public outcry. At the same time, James Franklin published numerous articles against inoculation in the Courant. Years later, and after his own child contracted smallpox, Franklin changed his position on inoculation, regretting his failure to inoculate his son.</p>
                <p>Though Mather and Benjamin Franklin held opposing views upon various matters, there is no doubt that Mather exerted major influence upon Franklin. For instance, <hi rend="italic">Essays to do Good</hi> provides practical tips for how to “do good” for the “Saviour, and for His People in the world.” The book is short and easily read, and its practicality and warmth made it popular throughout the colonies and in England. Franklin appears to have extrapolated not only the form, but the ethical substance from the book, publishing his own Poor Richard's Almanac, an annual journal consisting of practical tips, witty sayings, and household advice. In the Autobiography, he notes that his father’s library held a copy of Mather's book, and that reading it “perhaps gave me a Turn of Thinking that had an Influence on some of the principal future Events of my Life.” In a letter written to Mather’s son Samuel in 1773, Franklin acknowledged Mather’s influence: "When I was a boy, I met with a book, entitled “Essays to do good,” which, I think, was written by your father. It had been so little regarded by a former possessor, that several leaves of it were torn out: but the remainder gave me such a turn, for thinking, as to have an influence on my conduct through life; for I have always set a greater value on the character of a doer of good, than any other kind of reputation; and if I have been, as you seem to think, a useful citizen, the public owes the advantage of it to that book." --Ellen French</p></note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0017" target="a0017" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF">Under the system of primogeniture that governed the inheritance of property in the landowning classes of Anglo-America, only the oldest son could inherit his father's land. Because of this, the younger sons were often sent off to practice law, join the military, or become ministers in the church. This trend extended into the middle class as well, as often the younger sons were sent, as here, as a "tithe" to the church for both religious and practical reasons.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0018" target="a0018" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Brownell was born in London and arrived in the Noth American colonies around 1703. By 1712 he was running a boarding school in Boston with his wife. Franklin attended Brownell's school from 1715 to 1716, at which point the cost apparently became too great for his family to sustain.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0019" target="a0019" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#EF">Sons leaving home for adventure and quick profit was a common trope in the literature of this period due to the increase in England's colonial presence throughout the century. Robinson Crusoe presents one such example, but the ocean as a metaphor for both empire and capitalist gains was present in many eighteenth century stories.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0020" target="a0020" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">ants. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0021" target="a0021" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">"Richard Burton" or "RB" were pseudonyms for Nathaniel Crouch (c. 1632-1725), who published dozens of popular histories in the second half of the 1600s, books that went through many editions. Most of these were pretty much plagiarized from the works of other writers, but many readers, like the young Franklin, learned a good deal of history through his inexpensive digests of longer works.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0022" target="a0022" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Daniel Defoe's <hi rend="italic">An Essay upon Projects</hi>, published in 1697, outlines a number of plans for organizing associations to improve English society, including special courts for merchants and an early form of life insurance.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0023" target="a0023" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">As noted above, Mather was an important influence on Franklin whose persona of "Silence Dogood" in his first published essays allude to the title of Mather's book.</note>
            
            <note xml:id="n0024" target="a0024" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#NT"><p>It is worth noting that this is an unusually long apprenticeship; most apprenticeships were for seven rather than nine years. We do not know why Benjamin's apprenticeship was stipulated to be that long. The provision that he get "journeyman's wages," that is, the salary of a flully-fledged printer, might have been offered as a compromise.</p>
                <p>The fact of Franklin's apprenticeship, and his early departure from his brother's ship, which is coming up in in a few pages, informs much of this early part of the narrative. During his trip from Boston to Philadelphia Franklin recounts being wary about attracting attention, noting, “it seemed to be suspected from my youth and appearance, that I might be some runaway.” This statement seems odd, considering Franklin technically was a runaway—he had left his apprenticeship with his brother against the will of the family. Why did Franklin not consider himself classed with other young runaways, when he did fear being mistaken for one and returned to Boston?  He certainly had run away from Boston, knowing that if he left openly, “means would be used to prevent [him].” Yet Franklin was in a somewhat unique position: he had technically run away without his brother’s permission, yet he knew that he would not be treated as a common runaway apprentice.</p>
                <p>Apprenticeship  in the American colonies had its roots in the practices of the English system, which dates back to the middle ages. One of the major pieces of legislation governing apprenticeship was the English Statute of Artificers (1563),  which required parents who did not otherwise provide for the education of their sons to bind them to a trade or the agricultural system. The seven year term, longer than the normal length of apprenticeship in France and Germany, “was designed to ensure English supremacy in handmade manufactures and to discourage the wandering and strolling that had characterized earlier periods of English life.”  Another aspect of English law and custom that influenced apprenticeship in the colonies was the English Poor Law (1601)  which required local authorities to bind poor or orphaned children into apprenticeship if their parents did not do so. Benjamin Franklin belonged to the class of apprentices who bound themselves “by their own free will and consent” to a master to learn his trade, not the apprentices involuntarily bound under the auspices of the Poor Law. </p>
                <p>These English statutes applied to the American colonies in theory. However, these laws and customs depended on the medieval guild system for enforcement—a system which never developed in the colonies. Eighteenth-century colonial America did not have the deep pool of skilled laborers that characterized the guild system and had no enforcement mechanism to monitor quality of work, admit members to the status of journeyman or master, or standardize apprentice training.  In the colonies, “anyone could call himself a master artisan, and any such artisan could take an apprentice”—or many apprentices at once.  During Franklin’s boyhood in Boston, the real wages of artisans were falling and apprenticeship contracts often did not demand fees from parents, except for those in high-status crafts. It was guild enforcement that kept wages high and ensured quality craft in the English system, because it created a closed labor market—no artisan could work without permission from his guild.</p>
                <p>In England, if an apprentice ran away from his master, there was an ironclad system in place to keep him from practicing his craft anywhere in the country. The guild system ensured that jurisdiction rules were enforced, and any new practitioner would have to be an approved guild member. In America, runaway penalties did not extend beyond the borders of each colony,  and, as Franklin’s narrative attests, the demand for skilled labor meant even a partially-trained apprentice would likely be hired, perhaps even with the status of a journeyman (though this label did not hold the weight it would in England).  If an American apprentice ran away, his master would circulate a description of the runaway with an offer of reward, and if returned, the apprentice would have to serve for a longer period.  The reward was the enforcement mechanism, meaning citizens might be on the lookout for apparent runaways.</p> 
                <p>Technically, to be legal, an apprenticeship contract (called an “indenture”) had to be registered with municipal authorities so it could be used as evidence in case of disputes. This was true even in the colonies.  However, the nature of indenture papers meant that possession of one’s half of the contract should have constituted evidence without consulting town records: “indenture”  papers were indented on both halves of the document so they could later be identified as one contract.  Benjamin Franklin’s original contract with his brother would probably have been properly registered—but the second set of indentures, which were secret, would only have been held by the master and the apprentice.  James probably could have proved Benjamin was his apprentice by comparing the two halves of the indenture, but once his brother was out of Boston, this means of redress was impractical at best. And of course, in attempting to regain his apprentice, James would have had to admit his real ownership of the Courant.</p></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0025" target="a0025" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Neither of these poems has survived. But what Franklin was doing was a fairly typical thing in this period; newspapers were often filled with poems about recent events, particularly events as notable and spectacular as the two mentioned here.  The death by drowning of George Worthilake, his wife and daughter (Franklin misremembers this as having been two daughters) as they were returning from church by boat to the lighthouse that Worthilake was in charge of in Novenber 1716 became known as the "Lighthouse Tragedy." Edward Teach, the pirate known as Blackbeard, was killed in a firefight with ships from the Royal Navy off the coast of North Carolina on November 22, 1718. The "Grub Street-ballad-style" that Franklin laments using here was nothing to be ashamed of; many authors in this period wrote popular ballads published in the kind of popular journals that became associated with "Grub Street," the physical home of mass market printing in London.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0026" target="a0026" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">punctuation</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0027" target="a0027" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM"><hi rend="italics">The Spectator</hi> was a newspaper created by Joseph Addison and Richard Steele that ran from March 3, 1711 to December 6, 1712. It consisted of a series of essays that were for the most part written by either Steele or Addison, but they assumed the viewpoint of the persona of “Mr. Spectator.” “Mr. Spectator” was a quiet observer of English society who commented on politics, fashion, and social issues through these essays, which were widely popular in both England and the colonies. They were read as models of good English style, and also as guides for civilized, middle-class behavior. Benjamin Franklin was influenced by <hi rend="italic">Spectator's</hi> prose style. And the  persona of "Silence Dogood" that he would use in his own periodical essays was clearly influenced by the silent "Mr. Spectator" of Addison and Steele's influential journal.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0028" target="a0028" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                    Given Franklin's later interest in public finance, it is striking to see that the particular essay of the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>that he remembers as his introduction to the series is a famous piece by Addison on the topic of "public credit."</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0029" target="a0029" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Thomas Tryon's <hi rend="italic">The Way to Health, Long Life, and Happiness</hi>, <graphic url="notes/Thomas_Tryon.jpg" style="float:left" width="300px"/>(Source: Wikimedia Commons) published in 1691, advocated a vegetarian diet. Which was unusual in this period; vegetarianism was rare, and it cannot have been easy to get enough nutrition through a vegetarian diet in colonial New England in this period, especially given the difficulty of finding fresh vegetables in the winter season.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0030" target="a0030" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Hasty pudding was a grain porridge; in the American colonies, it was usually made of corn, but could also be made of wheat, oats, or some other grain.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0031" target="a0031" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Edward Cocker's textbook, first published in 1677 under the title <hi rend="italic">Cocker's Arithmetick: being a plain and familiar method suitable to the meanest capacity for the full understanding of that incomparable art, as it is now taught by the ablest school-masters in city and country</hi>, and then republished under various titles for decades to come, became the standard book for learning basic arithmetic in the eighteenth-century Anglophone world. It would have been comparatively easy for Franklin to have come across a copy of this book, which went through scores of editions.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0032" target="a0032" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB"><hi rend="italic">Practical Navigation: or an Introduction to the Whole Art</hi>first published in London in 1669, was a widely-reprinted text in the period; its author, John Seller (1632-1697) was a mapmaker and cartographer who was awarded with the title of "hydrophager to the king." Samuel Sturmy (1633-1669) was the author of <hi rend="italic">The Mariner's Magazine</hi>, first published in 1669 and, like Seller's book, reprinted several times in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. This was a large and ambitious text, with sections on navigation and math, but also on things like nautical weaponry.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0033" target="a0033" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">The English philosopher John Locke (1632-1704) published <hi rend="italic">An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> in 1690. Locke's philosophical skepticism and strong endorsement of religious toleration seem to have found a strong positive response in Franklin. Locke's book is still considered a foundational text in the philosophical tradition of English empiricism.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0034" target="a0034" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM"><hi rend="italic">Logic, or, The Art of Thinking</hi> written by Antoine Arnauld and Pierre Nicole, was published in French in 1662, and soon thereafter translated into English and other languages. Known familiarly as the "Port Royal Logic," this, like Locke's book, was a highly influential text for centuries, and is still read by historians of philosophy. Source: https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/port-royal-logic/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0035" target="a0035" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The book that Franklin thinks that he is remembering is James Greenwood's <hi rend="italics">An Essay towards a Practical English Grammar</hi>, first published in 1711. But he is probably misremembering here, since that book does not have the Socratic dialogue to which he refers. He is more likely thinking of <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of the English Tongue</hi>, published anonymously but written by Charles Gildon in 1712. That book concludes with an essay called "Of the Socratic Method in Disputing," that describes and then models a method of debating controversial topics by means of open-ended, non-confrontational questions. Franklin says that he took this kind of method to heart, training himself to handle disputes by avoiding dogmatic statements of his own position and instead asking careful questions to learn more the positions of others.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0036" target="a0036" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AM">Xenophon (430-354 B.C.E.) was an ancient Greek historian whose writings included the "Memorabilia," a text containing many Socratic-style dialogues. Source: http://www.iep.utm.edu/xenophon/</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0037" target="a0037" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Franklin is referring to works by Anthony Ashley Cooper, the earl of Shaftesbury, and Anthony Collins. Both authors were well known in this period for their philosophical skepticism and their classification as "deists." They believed that although a deity of some sort existed and had created the known universe, he, or perhaps better, it was not much concerned with the everyday doings of that creation.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0038" target="a0038" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">These lines are from the 1711 poem "An Essay on Criticism" by Alexander Pope, though Franklin slightly misquotes, probably relying on his memory.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0039" target="a0039" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Franklin is misremembering here, as there were other newspapers before these. But <hi rend="italic">The New England Courant</hi> was indeed a landmark in newspaper publication in the American colonies, as it included poetry, opinion pieces, and other kinds of content beyond the official news. <graphic url="notes/NewEnglandCourant.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/>And it was the place where Benjamin Franklin's first surviving publications, his essays published in the <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi> under the pseudonym "Silence Dogood" reached print. James Franklin ran afoul of the government several times in the course of publishing the newspaper (at one point, Benjamin took over as the official editor while his brother was in jail), and it was eventually suppressed, ceasing publication in June 1726.</note>  
                
                <note xml:id="n0040" target="a0040" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Franklin is referring to the first of his essays published under the name "Silence Dogood." Writing in imitation of <hi rend="italics">The Spectator</hi>, Franklin did something quite original in taking on the voice and persona of a woman, here an old widow who, in the course of the series, made observations on contemporary life.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0041" target="a0041" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">William Bradford (1663-1752), was one of the earliest printers in the American colonies. Born in England, he came to Pennsylvania in the 1680s and established the first printing office there. When he ran afoul of the political authorities in Pennsylvania in the 1690s, he moved to New York, and set up a print shop in the city, which he ran until the 1740s. He had government contracts for printing forms, paper money, and the proceedings of the New Jersey Assembly, and also issued the usual fare of printers in this period: religious tracts, almanacs, and eventually a newspaper, the <hi rend="italic">New-York Gazette</hi>, the first newspaper published in the city.</note>
                <note xml:id="n0042" target="a0042" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Perth Amboy, New Jersey, at the southern end of the outer harbor of New York City.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0043" target="a0043" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The Arthur Kill, a body of water that runs between Staten Island and New Jersey, terminating at about Perth Amboy. By "Long Island," Franklin is probably referring to the coastline of what is now Brooklyn, or perhaps the peninsula now called the Rockaways.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0044" target="a0044" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The pate is the crown of your head, and a "shock" is a crop of hair, so the sense is that the Dutchman had a thick mass of hair to grab.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0045" target="a0045" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Copper cut illustrations or engravings, which were expensive to produce. They would have been much more detailed and finer than the woodcuts used for cheap books.</note>
                <note xml:id="n0046" target="a0046" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Daniel Defoe (c.1660-1731), famous now as the author of <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi> and other novels such as <hi rend="italic">Moll Flanders</hi>, was at least as well known to readers in the period for his "conduct manuals"--guides to the proper way to live--such as <hi rend="italic">The Family Instructor (1715)</hi>and <hi rend="italic">Religious Courtship (1722)</hi>, both of which went through multiple editions in the eighteenth century.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0047" target="a0047" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Samuel Richardson's 1740 epistolary novel <hi rend="italic">Pamela, or, Virtue Rewarded</hi> was one of the most popular novels of the period in the English-speaking world, and was also widely translated into other European languages. Franklin published an edition of the novel in 1742 in Philadelphia, which he labelled the "fifth edition" of the work without any authorization at all. [Image courtesy the American Antiquarian Society] <graphic url="notes/franklin-pamela.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/>He was simply reprinting a copy of the book that had been obtained for him in London. The evidence suggests that it was not a great success commercially; novels remained suspect to many readers until well into the nineteenth century, and Franklin did not follow this up with other such piracies.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0048" target="a0048" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">That is, a traveling doctor. Nothing is known of Dr. John Browne's career as a physician except for what is recorded here. When Browne met Franklin, he was fifty-six years old and running an inn in Bordentown, New Jersey.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0049" target="a0049" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">A travesty is a parody, and doggerel verse would be deliberately bad, comically irregular verse designed to mock its subject. The English poet Charles Cotton (1630-1687) published "Scarronides, or, Virgil Travestie" in 1664 and 1665, a parody of Virgil's classical epic the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>. Franklin is right; Browne's parodic version of the Bible does not appear ever to have been published.</note> 
            
                <note xml:id="n0050" target="a0050" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Born in England in 1689, Samuel Keimer ran a printing business  in London in the 1710s, publishing a variety of things, including plays by Susanna Centlivre, essays by Daniel Defoe, a newspaper, and religious works, including some that testify to his affiliation with the "French Prophets," a millenarian group that preached in London in the early part of the eighteenth century (about which more below). Keimer was jailed in 1715 for seditious libel; the best guess is that he printed something in support of a failed Jacobite uprising in that year, but we cannot be sure. He moved to the American colonies sometime around 1720, and by 1723 he was once again printing, this time in Philadelphia. Much of what we know of Keimer's career in Philadelphia comes from Franklin, who, as we will see, was often dismissive of his abilities as a printer and his character. After going bankrupt in Philadelphia, Keimer ended up in Barbados, and founded the first newspaper there, the  <hi rend="italic">Barbados Gazette</hi>. He died there in 1742.  Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi>.</note>
            
                <note xml:id="n0051" target="a0051" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">This broadside elegy for Aquila Rose, the young poet and printer whose death at the age of 28 was the reason why William Bradford had recommended Franklin to come to Philadelphia in the first place, is the first thing that Franklin printed in Philadelphia.  The broadside was lost for decades, but a single copy was rediscovered just in the last few years, and is owned by the University of Pennsylvania Library: <graphic url="http://hdl.library.upenn.edu/1017/d/print/9967680253503681"
                    style="float:right" width="300px"/> </note> 
            
                <note xml:id="n0052" target="a0052" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">That is, Keimer knew how to "compose"--to set type on a compositing stick and arrange lines on a form--but didn't know how to ink a page or otherwise use a printing press. Given that Keimer had been through London printing apprenticeship and had run print shops of his own, Keimer's apparent ignorance of these crucial tasks is surprising, and we only have Franklin's word to go on. It is possible that Keimer was a better printer than Franklin was willing to acknowledge, even if he did not have the kind of financial success that would come to Franklin later.</note>
            
                <note xml:id="n0053" target="a0053" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The French Prophets, also known as the Camisards, were a millenarian sect who preached in London, and, then, other parts of England in the early part of the eighteenth century. They were begun by a small group of Huguenots, French Protestants who had fled persecution there by emigrating to England in 1706. They preached the imminent coming of the Messiah, and attracted a number of followers including, apparently for a while, Keimer. Like many people in this period, Franklin was suspicious of the kind of religious intensity displayed by Keimer and other millenarians, what Franklin calls "enthusiasm"; it shows up soon in his response, later, to the similarly intense preaching of George Whitfield, the evangelist and Methodist.</note> 
                
                <note xml:id="n0054" target="a0054" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#NT">Sir William Keith (c. 1669–1749) <graphic
                    url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/8/8d/Williamkeith.jpg"
                    style="float:right" width="300px"/>was granted the position of surveyor-general of the customs in the southern colonies of North America in 1713 by Robert Harley, then the leading minister in the government in Westminster. After his dismissal in July 1715 in a political purge, he persuaded William Penn, the proprietor of Pennsylvania, to appoint him to the position of deputy governor (this was in effect the leading executive power in the colony, since the monarch had the official title of governor). When Penn died in 1718, Keith tried to gain more power by creating a power base in the assembly. A political falling out took place when Keith sided with tradesmen and merchants on the issue of paper currency in 1723. Because of this, Keith's political opponents worked to oust him, and he was dismissed from the governorship in 1726. After this, Keith returned to England to appeal to the king for the governorship of the three lower colonies, but he was unsuccessful. He also attempted a few other political maneuvers, including an attempt at the governorship of New Jersey and the creation of a new colony called Georgia. He was unsuccessful at these as well. Penn found himself in financial trouble which led to a case against him, and he spent 1734 and 1735 in debtor's prison. After this, he became a journalist, and he died on November 18, 1749 in London. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0055" target="a0055" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Colonel John French was the speaker of the Delaware Assembly. "Madeira" is a fortified wine (that is, a wine with additional alcohol added to stabilize it) produced in the Madeira Islands, Portuguese-held islands off the west coast of Africa. Because it was the closest place that made wine to the American colonies, it was very popular there in the eighteenth century. But, expensive and taxed, Madeira was a luxury item, and would have been quite a treat for a seventeen-year-old, which is perhaps why Franklin remembers it so clearly.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0056" target="a0056" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#NT">A sand bank or a place where the waters are shallow. Source:  <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi> </note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0057" target="a0057" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#NT">A fortnight consists of two weeks. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
            
                <note xml:id="n0058" target="a0058" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">A raree or "rarity" show would have been a small box carried by a traveling showman that had interesting images and scenes to be looked at, often through a small opening or peephole. They varied from perspective scenes of interesting places to, in some cases, pornography, and are the origins of the modern "peep show."</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0059" target="a0059" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">John Collins. Little is known of him beyond what Franklin says about in this memoir.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0060" target="a0060" type="editorial">Harshly satirizing someone or something in writing. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                    
                <note xml:id="n0061" target="a0061" type="editorial">Prostitues or unchaste women. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0062" target="a0062" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">William Burnet (1699-1729) was at this time the colonial governor of New York and New Jersey. His father Gilbert Burnet (1643-1715) was an important philosopher, cleric, and historian, whose multivolume <hi rend="italic">History of the Reformation in England</hi> (1679-81) was a landmark history of the English church. He became an ally of both Charles II and, later William III, who made him the Bishop of Salisbury.</note>
            
                <note xml:id="n0063" target="a0063" type="editorial">Drinking or alcohol consumption. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
            
                <note xml:id="n0064" target="a0064" type="editorial">An error or mistake. Once again Franklin is using the language of printing to describe the course of his own life. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0064a" target="a0064a" type="editorial">Directly converting 18th century currency into its modern equivalent is a problematic enterprise which relies on a variety of different methods (various sources gave numbers between $10,000 and $30,000 as a conversion for this hundred pounds). To better contextualize this number, a 1750s schoolmaster in America would earn around sixty pounds annually, while the British National Archives say that 100 pounds would buy you either 14 horses or 21 cows in the 1730s. These numbers are further complicated by the shortage of money in the colonies during the time, leading later in this piece to Franklin printing significant amounts of paper currency to fill the gap left by silver and gold.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0065" target="a0065" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Thomas Annis was the Captain of the <hi rend="italic">London Hope</hi>, which sailed from Philadelphia to London once a year to carry the mail. It usually left in the fall; this year, the ship sailed in November.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0066" target="a0066" type="editorial">In the case of a ship: motionless due to a lack of wind. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0067" target="a0067" type="editorial">To lure, inveigle (into or to a place, course of action, etc., to do something, etc.). Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0068" target="a0068" type="editorial">The ancient law of the Hebrews, contained in the Pentateuch. Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi></note>
                
                
                <note xml:id="n0069" target="a0069" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">That is, he takes Saturday as the Sabbath, like a member of the Jewish faith. Keimer may have started this (and growing out his beard, which was unusual in this era) when he considered himself to be a follower of the French Prophets.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0070" target="a0070" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">In the book of Exodus, Moses tells the Israelites not to eat meat while in the desert, leading them to wish that they could return to the pots of meat they had left behind in Egypt.</note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0071" target="a0071" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Charles Osborne eventually became a lawyer and moved to the West Indies, where he died. Joseph Watson died just a few years after the events described here, in April 1727, in Franklin's arms. We know the most about James Ralph, because he became a prolific author once he moved to London. Ralph (d. 1762) was probably born between 1695 and 1710, perhaps in the environs of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, or perhaps in Elizabethtown, New Jersey. He never returned to America after the journey Franklin describes here. In 1727, he began to publish poetry, notably <hi rend="italic">The Tempest, or, The Terrors of Death</hi> (1727) and <hi rend="italic">Night</hi> (1728). In 1728 his blank verse polemic, <hi rend="italic">Sawney, an Heroic Poem Occasion’d by the Dunciad</hi> was published, resulting in his inclusion in Alexander Pope’s second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad</hi> (which may have been his intention). Ralph became a friend of Henry Fielding when Fielding was a leading figure in the London theater, and tried his hand as a playwright. But Ralph had his greatest financial success when he became a political journalist. Beginning in the 1730s, he was a contributor to a number of London newspapers. His most important works are <hi rend="italic">The History of England during the reigns of King William, Queen Anne, and King George I, with an introductory review of the reigns of the royal brothers Charles and James </hi> (1744–6) and <hi rend="italic">The Case of the Authors by Profession or Trade Stated </hi> (1758). Source: <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> </note>
                
                <note xml:id="n0072" target="a0072" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#JOB">The Schuylkill River runs through eastern Pennsylvania, meeting the Delaware at Philadelphia. <graphic url="notes/Schuylkill_1752.jpg" style="float:right" width="300px"/>In this 1752 map, it forms the western limit of the city's grid of streets. (Wikimedia Commons)</note>
            </back>
</text>
</TEI>


