<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="franklin-dogood">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Silence Dogood Essays</title>

                <author>

                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#AB"><forename>Austin</forename>
                        <surname>Benson</surname></name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename>
                        <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John</forename>
                        <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>

                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>

                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>James Franklin</publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <!-- Single? -->
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in
                        Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up
                    selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British
                    and American literature of the 18th century. This project is funded by the
                    National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University
                    of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning. </p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-8-10" who="JOB"/>
            <change when="2025-2-27" who="JOB"/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front>
            <div/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head> <ref target="Silence_Dogood_" corresp="Silence_Dogood">The "Silence Dogood" Essays</ref> </head>
                <note xml:id="Silence_Dogood" target="Silence_Dogood_"><p>Benjamin Franklin was sixteen years old and working as an apprentice in the
                    Boston print shop of his older brother James when, in April 1722, he began
                    writing a series of essays to be published in the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi> (which his brother published) under the pseudonym of "Silence
                    Dogood." In his <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, Benjamin remembered
                    slipping these essays, written in disguised handwriting, under the door of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Courant's</hi> office; he assumed (probably correctly)
                    that James would refuse to print an essay from him if he simply asked or
                    submitted it under his own name. James published the essays, which became very
                    popular among the newspaper's readers. Benjamin kept his authorship of the
                    series a secret, even from his brother, until after he finished writing them in
                    October 1722, at which point James printed an advertisement asking for "Silence
                    Dogood" to come forth. Benjamin confessed that he was the author, which seems to
                    have annoyed his older brother. It was not too long after that that Benjamin
                    left his brother's shop--breaking his apprenticeship--and moved to
                    Philadelphia.</p><lb/>
                    <graphic url="https://lic-assets-staging.s3.us-east-1.amazonaws.com/Franklin/New-England_Courant%2C_July_16-23%2C_1722%2C_p1.jpg" style="float:center" width="500px" alt="Image of issue of the New England Courant" source="Wikimedia Commons" desc="An issue of the New England Courant with one of the Silence Dogood issues on the front page. (Wikimedia Commons)"/>
                <p>The Silence Dogood essays are written in the persona of a middle-aged woman, but
                    the title character is very clearly indebted to Mr. Spectator, the avatar of
                    Addison and Steele's <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> series, published a decade
                    earlier. It is testimony to how widely influential the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Spectator</hi> was that even in colonial America, teenaged boys were
                    reading it and taking it as a model for their own writing. In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, Franklin remembers how much he loved the
                        <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, and how he first came across it at the age
                    of sixteen: "<hi rend="italic">an odd volume of the Spectator fell into my
                        hands. This was a publication I had never seen. I bought the volume, and
                        read it again and again. I was enchanted with it, thought the style
                        excellent, and wished it were in my power to imitate it. With this view I
                        selected some of the papers, made short summaries of the sense of each
                        period, and put them for a few days aside. I then, without looking at the
                        book, endeavoured to restore the essays to their true form, and to express
                        each thought at length, as it was in the original, employing the most
                        appropriate words that occurred to my mind. I afterwards compared my
                        Spectator with the original; I perceived some faults, which I
                    corrected</hi>." If the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> gave Franklin a model
                    for his prose style, so too did it give him a persona to inhabit; the "Silence"
                    in Silence Dogood's name clearly alludes to the taciturn Mr. Spectator as
                    invented by Addison and Steele. The surname "Dogood" also alludes to a famous
                    writer, in this case a colonial writer: the prolific Boston cleric Cotton
                    Mather, whose 1710 collection <hi rend="italic">Bonifacius: or, Essays to Do
                        Good</hi>, advocating the reader to undertake charitable works, Franklin
                    also remembered as a book that had a great impact on him as a young man. The
                    startling thing about the Silence Dogood essays (in addition to the fact that
                    they were written by a sixteen-year-old), is that Franklin adopts the persona of
                    a <hi rend="italic">woman</hi>, a persona that enables him adopt, but also gently mock, the kinds of
                    sentiments expressed by authority figures like Mather. Franklin would continue
                    to use personae, male and female, throughout his career, the most famous of
                    these being the Poor Richard of his Almanack. And there's a sense in which the
                    "Benjamin Franklin" of the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi> and of history
                    was also a persona, a role that Franklin played on the public stage of the
                    trans-Atlantic world.</p><lb/>
                <p>There were fourteen Silence Dogood essays in all, published every two weeks in
                    the pages of the <hi rend="italic">New England Courant</hi>, for which, as we
                    have seen, James Franklin was the publisher. The <hi rend="italic">New England
                        Courant</hi> was the first independently-published newspaper in colonial
                    America; that is, it operated independently of government authority. So much so
                    that the colonial government in Massachusetts frequently attempted to censor the
                    newspaper and jailed James Franklin several times when he published articles
                    that were thought to defame public officials (Cotton Mather, for example).
                    During these periods, Benjamin was listed as the official publisher of the
                    newspaper. It was finally closed for good in 1726. Benjamin had long since moved
                    on, and was at this point finishing a stint as a journeyman printer in London
                    and preparing to return to Philadelphia, where he opened a print shop of his
                    own.</p></note>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> April 2, 1722 [No. 1] To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It may not be improper in the first place to inform your Readers, that I intend
                    once a <ref corresp="fortnight" target="fortnight_">Fortnight</ref> to present
                    them, by the Help of this Paper, with a short <ref corresp="epistle"
                        target="epistle_">Epistle</ref>, which I presume will add somewhat to their
                    Entertainment.</p>
                <p>And since it is observed, that the Generality of People, now a days, are
                    unwilling either to commend or <ref corresp="dispraise" target="dispraise_"
                        >dispraise</ref> what they read, until they are in some measure informed who
                    or what the Author of it is, whether he be <hi rend="italic">poor</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">rich</hi>, <hi rend="italic"> old</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >young</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Schollar</hi> or a <ref
                        corresp="leatherapron" target="leatherapron_"><hi rend="italic">Leather
                            Apron Man</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="etc" target="etc_">&amp;c</ref> and
                    give their Opinion of the Performance, according to the Knowledge which they
                    have of the Author's Circumstances, it may not be amiss to begin with a short
                    Account of my past Life and present Condition, that the Reader may not be at a
                    Loss to judge <ref corresp="whether" target="whether_">whether or no</ref> my
                        <ref corresp="lucubrations" target="lucubrations_">Lucubrations</ref> are
                    worth his reading.</p>
                <p>At the time of my Birth, my Parents were on Ship-board in their Way from London
                    to <ref corresp="nengland" target="nengland_">N. England</ref>. My Entrance into
                    this troublesome World was attended with the Death of my Father, a Misfortune,
                    which tho' I was not then capable of knowing, I shall never be able to forget;
                    for as he, poor Man, stood upon the Deck rejoycing at my Birth, a merciless Wave
                    entred the Ship, and in one Moment carry'd him beyond Reprieve. Thus, was the
                        <hi rend="italic"> first Day</hi> which I saw, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >last</hi> that was seen by my Father; and thus was my <ref
                        corresp="disconsolate" target="disconsolate_">disconsolate</ref> Mother at
                    once made both a <hi rend="italic">Parent</hi> and a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Widow</hi>.</p>
                <p>When we arrived at Boston (which was not long after) I was put to Nurse in a
                    Country Place, at a small Distance from the Town, where I went to School, and
                    past my Infancy and Childhood in Vanity and Idleness, until I was <ref
                        corresp="apprentice" target="apprentice_">bound out Apprentice</ref>, that I
                    might no longer be a Charge to my <ref corresp="indigent" target="indigent_"
                        >Indigent</ref> Mother, who was put to hard Shifts for a Living.</p>
                <p>My Master was a Country Minister, a pious good-natur'd young Man, and a
                    Batchelor: he labour'd with all his Might to instil vertuous and godly
                    Principles into my tender Soul, well knowing that it was the most suitable Time
                    to make deep and lasting Impressions on the Mind, while it was yet untainted
                    with Vice, free and unbiass'd. He endeavour'd that I might be instructed in all
                    that Knowledge and Learning which is necessary for our Sex, and deny'd me no
                    Accomplishment that could possibly be attained in a Country Place; such as all
                    Sorts of Needle-Work, Writing, Arithmetick, &amp;c. and observing that I took a
                        <ref corresp="literacy" target="literacy_">more than ordinary Delight in
                        reading ingenious Books</ref>, he gave me the free Use of his Library, which
                    tho' it was but small, yet it was well chose, to inform the Understanding
                    rightly, and enable the Mind to frame great and noble Ideas.</p>
                <p>Before I had liv'd quite two Years with this Reverend Gentleman, my indulgent
                    Mother departed this Life, leaving me as it were by my self, having no Relation
                    on Earth within my Knowledge.</p>
                <p>I will not abuse your Patience with a tedious Recital of all the frivolous
                    Accidents of my Life, that happened from this Time until I arrived to <ref
                        corresp="discretion" target="discretion_">Years of Discretion</ref>, only
                    inform you that I liv'd a chearful Country Life, spending my leisure Time either
                    in some innocent Diversion with the neighbouring Females, or in some shady
                    Retirement, with the best of Company, <hi rend="italic"> Books</hi>. Thus I past
                    away the Time with a Mixture of Profit and Pleasure, having no affliction but
                    what was imaginary, and created in my own Fancy; as nothing is more common with
                    us Women, than to be grieving for nothing, when we have nothing else to grieve
                    for.</p>
                <p>As I would not engross too much of your Paper at once, I will defer the Remainder
                    of my Story until my next Letter; in the mean time desiring your Readers to
                    exercise their Patience, and bear with my Humours now and then, because I shall
                    trouble them but seldom. I am not insensible of the Impossibility of pleasing
                    all, but I would not willingly displease any; and for those who will take
                    Offence <ref corresp="were" target="were_">were</ref> none is intended, they are
                    beneath the Notice of Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> April 16, 1722 [No. 2] To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Histories of Lives are seldom entertaining, unless they contain something either
                    admirable or exemplar: And since there is little or nothing of this Nature in my
                    own Adventures, I will not tire your Readers with tedious Particulars of no
                    Consequence, but will briefly, and in as few Words as possible, relate the most
                    material Occurrences of my Life, and according to my Promise, confine all to
                    this Letter.</p>
                <p>My Reverend master who had hitherto remained a Batchelor, (after much meditation
                    on the <ref corresp="genesis" target="genesis_">Eighteenth verse of the Second
                        Chapter of Genesis</ref>,) took up a Resolution to marry; and having made
                    several unsuccessful fruitless Attempts on the <ref corresp="topsex"
                        target="topsex_">more topping Sort of our Sex</ref>, and being tir'd with
                    making troublesome Journeys and Visits to no Purpose, he began unexpectedly to
                    cast a loving Eye upon Me, whom he had brought up cleverly to his Hand.</p>
                <p>There is certainly scarce any Part of a Man's Life in which he appears more silly
                    and ridiculous, than when he makes his first Onset in Courtship. The aukward
                    Manner in which my Master first discover'd his Intentions, made me, in spite of
                    my Reverence to his Person, burst out into an unmannerly Laughter: However,
                    having ask'd his Pardon, and with much ado compos'd my Countenance, I promis'd
                    him I would take his Proposal into serious Consideration, and speedily give him
                    an Answer.</p>
                <p>As he had been a great Benefactor (and in a Manner a Father to me) I could not
                    well deny his Request, when I once perceived he was in earnest. Whether it was
                    Love, or Gratitude, or Pride, or all Three that made me consent, I know not; but
                    it is certain, he found it no hard Matter, by the Help of his Rhetorick, to
                    conquer my Heart, and perswade me to marry him.</p>
                <p>This unexpected Match was very astonishing to all the Country round about, and
                    served to furnish them with Discourse for a long Time after; some approving it,
                    others disliking it, as they were led by their various Fancies and
                    Inclinations.</p>
                <p>We lived happily together in the Heighth of conjugal Love and mutual Endearments,
                    for near Seven Years, in which Time we added Two likely Girls and a Boy to the
                    Family of the Dogoods: But alas! When my <ref corresp="meridian"
                        target="meridian_">Sun was in its meridian Altitude</ref>, inexorable
                    unrelenting Death, as if he had envy'd my Happiness and Tranquility, and
                    resolv'd to make me entirely miserable by the Loss of so good an Husband,
                    hastened his Flight to the Heavenly World, by a sudden unexpected Departure from
                        <ref corresp="thisworld" target="thisworld_">this</ref>.</p>
                <p>I have now remained in a State of Widowhood for several Years, but it is a State
                    I never much admir'd, and I am apt to fancy that I could be easily perswaded to
                    marry again, provided I was sure of a good-humour'd, sober, agreeable Companion:
                    But one, even with these few good Qualities, being hard to find, I have lately
                    relinquish'd all Thoughts of that Nature.</p>
                <p>At present I pass away my leisure Hours in Conversation, either with my honest
                    Neighbour Rusticus and his Family, or with the ingenious Minister of our Town,
                    who now lodges at my House, and by whose Assistance I intend now and then to
                    beautify my Writings with a Sentence or two in the learned Languages, which will
                    not only be fashionable, and pleasing to those who do not understand it, but
                    will likewise be very ornamental.</p>
                <p>I shall conclude this with my own Character, which (one would think) I should be
                    best able to give. <hi rend="italic">Know then</hi>, That I am an Enemy to Vice,
                    and a Friend to Vertue. I am one of an extensive Charity, and a great Forgiver
                    of <hi rend="italic">private</hi> Injuries: A hearty Lover of the Clergy and all
                    good Men, and a mortal Enemy to arbitrary Government and unlimited Power. I am
                    naturally very jealous for the Rights and Liberties of my Country; and the least
                    appearance of an Incroachment on those invaluable Priviledges, is apt to make my
                    Blood boil exceedingly. I have likewise a natural Inclination to observe and
                    reprove the Faults of others, at which I have an excellent Faculty. I speak this
                    by Way of Warning to all such whose Offences shall come under my Cognizance, for
                    I never intend to wrap my Talent in a Napkin. To be brief; I am courteous and
                    affable, good humour'd (unless I am first provok'd,) and handsome, and sometimes
                    witty, but always, Sir, Your Friend and Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> April 30, 1722 [No. 3] To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir.</p>
                <p>It is undoubtedly the Duty of all Persons to serve the Country they live in,
                    according to their Abilities; yet I sincerely acknowledge, that I have hitherto
                    been very deficient in this Particular; whether it was for want of Will or
                    Opportunity, I will not at present stand to determine: Let it suffice, that I
                    now take up a Resolution, to do for the future all that <hi rend="italic">lies
                        in my Way</hi> for the Service of my Countrymen.</p>
                <p>I have from my Youth been <ref corresp="indefatigably" target="indefatigably_"
                        >indefatigably</ref> studious to gain and treasure up in my Mind all useful
                    and desireable Knowledge, especially such as tends to improve the Mind, and
                    enlarge the Understanding: And as I have found it very beneficial to me, I am
                    not without Hopes, that communicating my small Stock in this Manner, by <ref
                        corresp="peacemeal" target="peacemeal_">Peace-meal</ref>> to the Publick,
                    may be at least in some Measure useful.</p>
                <p>I am very sensible that it is impossible for me, or indeed any one Writer to
                    please all Readers at once. Various Persons have different Sentiments; and that
                    which is pleasant and delightful to one, gives another a Disgust. He that would
                    (in this Way of Writing) please all, is under a Necessity to make his Themes
                    almost as numerous as his Letters. He must one while be merry and diverting,
                    then more solid and serious; one while sharp and satyrical, then (to <ref
                        corresp="mollify" target="mollify_">mollify</ref> that) be sober and
                    religious; at one Time let the Subject be Politicks, then let the next Theme be
                    Love: Thus will every one, one Time or other find some thing agreeable to his
                    own Fancy, and in his Turn be delighted.</p>
                <p>According to this Method I intend to proceed, bestowing now and then a few gentle
                        <ref corresp="reproof" target="reproof_">Reproofs</ref> on those who deserve
                    them, not forgetting at the same time to applaud those whose Actions merit
                    Commendation. And here I must not forget to invite the ingenious Part of your
                    Readers, particularly those of my own Sex to enter into a Correspondence with
                    me, assuring them, that their Condescension in this Particular shall be received
                    as a Favour, and accordingly acknowledged.</p>
                <p>I think I have now finish'd the Foundation, and I intend in my next to begin to
                    raise the Building. Having nothing more to write at present, I must make the
                    usual excuse in such Cases, of <hi rend="italic">being in haste</hi>, assuring
                    you that I speak from my Heart when I call my self, The most humble and obedient
                    of all the Servants your Merits have acquir'd,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> May 14, 1722 [No. 4] <ref corresp="cicerotrans" target="cicerotrans_"><hi
                            rend="italic">An sum etiam nunc vel Graecè loqui vel Latinè
                            docendus?</hi> Cicero.</ref> To the Author of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >New-England Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Discoursing the other Day at Dinner with my Reverend Boarder, formerly mention'd,
                    (whom for Distinction sake we will call by the Name of Clericus,) concerning the
                    Education of Children, I ask'd his Advice about my young Son William, whether or
                    no I had best bestow upon him Academical Learning, or (as our Phrase is) <hi
                        rend="italic">bring him up at our College</hi>: He perswaded me to do it by
                    all Means, using many weighty Arguments with me, and answering all the
                    Objections that I could form against it; telling me withal, that he did not
                    doubt but that the Lad would take his Learning very well, and not idle away his
                    Time as too many there now-a-days do. These Words of Clericus gave me a
                    Curiosity to inquire a little more strictly into the present Circumstances of
                    that famous <ref corresp="seminary" target="seminary_">Seminary</ref> of
                    Learning; but the Information which he gave me, was neither pleasant, nor such
                    as I expected.</p>
                <p>As soon as Dinner was over, I took a solitary Walk into my Orchard, still
                    ruminating on Clericus's Discourse with much Consideration, until I came to my
                    usual Place of Retirement under the <hi rend="italic">Great Apple-Tree</hi>;
                    where having seated my self, and carelessly laid my Head on a <ref
                        corresp="verdant" target="verdant_">verdant</ref> Bank, I fell by Degrees
                    into a soft and undisturbed Slumber. My waking Thoughts remained with me in my
                    Sleep, and before I awak'd again, I dreamt the following Dream.</p>
                <p>I fancy'd I was travelling over pleasant and delightful Fields and Meadows, and
                    thro' many small Country Towns and Villages; and as I pass'd along, all Places
                    resounded with the Fame of the Temple of Learning: Every Peasant, who had
                    wherewithal, was preparing to send one of his Children at least to this famous
                    Place; and in this Case most of them consulted their own Purses instead of their
                    Childrens Capacities: So that I observed, a great many, yea, the most part of
                    those who were travelling thither, were little better than Dunces and
                    Blockheads. Alas! alas!</p>
                <p>At length I entred upon a spacious Plain, in the Midst of which was erected a
                    large and stately Edifice: It was to this that a great Company of Youths from
                    all Parts of the Country were going; so stepping in among the Crowd, I passed on
                    with them, and presently arrived at the Gate.</p>
                <p>The Passage was kept by two sturdy <ref corresp="porter" target="porter_"
                        >Porters</ref> named <hi rend="italic">Riches and Poverty</hi>, and the
                    latter obstinately refused to give Entrance to any who had not first gain'd the
                    Favour of the former; so that I observed, many who came even to the very Gate,
                    were obliged to travel back again as ignorant as they came, for want of this
                    necessary Qualification. However, as a <ref corresp="spectator"
                        target="spectator_">Spectator</ref> I gain'd Admittance, and with the rest
                    entred directly into the Temple.</p>
                <p>In the Middle of the great Hall stood a stately and magnificent Throne, which was
                    ascended to by two high and difficult Steps. On the Top of it sat Learning in
                    awful State; she was apparelled wholly in Black, and surrounded almost on every
                    Side with innumerable Volumes in all Languages. She seem'd very busily employ'd
                    in writing something on half a Sheet of Paper, and upon Enquiry, I understood
                    she was preparing a Paper, call'd, <hi rend="italic">The New-England
                        Courant</hi>. On her Right Hand sat <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, with a
                    pleasant smiling Countenance, and handsomely attir'd; and on her left were
                    seated several <hi rend="italic">Antique Figures</hi> with their Faces vail'd. I
                    was considerably puzzl'd to guess who they were, until one informed me, (who
                    stood beside me,) that those Figures on her left Hand were <hi rend="italic"
                        >Latin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hebrew</hi>,
                    &amp;c. and that they were very much reserv'd, and seldom or never unvail'd
                    their Faces here, and then to few or none, tho' most of those who have in this
                    Place acquir'd so much Learning as to distinguish them from <hi rend="italic"
                        >English</hi>, pretended to an intimate Acquaintance with them. I then
                    enquir'd of him, what could be the Reason why they continued vail'd, in this
                    Place especially: He pointed to the Foot of the Throne, where I saw <hi
                        rend="italic">Idleness</hi>, attended with <hi rend="italic">Ignorance</hi>,
                    and these (he informed me) were they, who first vail'd them, and still kept them
                    so.</p>
                <p>Now I observed, that the whole Tribe who entred into the Temple with me, began to
                    climb the Throne; but the Work proving troublesome and difficult to most of
                    them, they withdrew their Hands from the Plow, and contented themselves to sit
                    at the Foot, with Madam <hi rend="italic">Idleness</hi> and her Maid <hi
                        rend="italic">Ignorance</hi>, until those who were assisted by Diligence and
                    a <ref corresp="docible" target="docible_">docible</ref> Temper, had well <ref
                        corresp="nigh" target="nigh_">nigh</ref> got up the first Step: But the Time
                    drawing nigh in which they could no way avoid ascending, they were <ref
                        corresp="fain" target="fain_">fain</ref> to crave the Assistance of those
                    who had got up before them, and who, for the Reward perhaps of a <hi
                        rend="italic">Pint of Milk</hi>, or a <hi rend="italic">Piece of <ref
                            corresp="cake" target="cake_">Plumb-Cake</ref></hi>, lent the <ref
                        corresp="lubber" target="lubber_">Lubbers</ref> a helping Hand, and sat them
                    in the Eye of the World, upon a Level with themselves.</p>
                <p>The other Step being in the same Manner ascended, and the usual Ceremonies at an
                    End, every Beetle-Scull seem'd well satisfy'd with his own Portion of Learning,
                    tho' perhaps he was <hi rend="italic">e'en just</hi> as ignorant as ever. And
                    now the Time of their Departure being come, they march'd out of Doors to make
                    Room for another Company, who waited for Entrance: And I, having seen all that
                    was to be seen, quitted the hall likewise, and went to make my Observations on
                    those who were just gone out before me.</p>
                <p>Some I perceiv'd took to <ref corresp="merch" target="merch_"
                    >Merchandizing</ref>, others to Travelling, some to one Thing, some to another,
                    and some to Nothing; and many of them from henceforth, for want of <ref
                        corresp="patrimony" target="patrimony_">Patrimony</ref>, liv'd as poor as
                        <ref corresp="churchmice" target="churchmice_">Church Mice</ref>, being
                    unable to dig, and asham'd to beg, and to live by their Wits it was impossible.
                    But the most Part of the Crowd went along a large beaten Path, which led to a
                    Temple at the further End of the Plain, call'd, <hi rend="italic">The Temple of
                            <ref corresp="theology" target="theology_">Theology</ref></hi>/hi>. The
                    Business of those who were employ'd in this Temple being laborious and painful,
                    I wonder'd exceedingly to see so many go towards it; but while I was pondering
                    this Matter in my Mind, I spy'd <ref corresp="pecunia" target="pecunia_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Pecunia</hi></ref> behind a Curtain, beckoning to them
                    with her Hand, which Sight immediately satisfy'd me for whose Sake it was, that
                    a great Part of them (I will not say all) travel'd that Road. In this Temple I
                    saw nothing worth mentioning, except the ambitious and fraudulent Contrivances
                    of <ref corresp="plagius" target="plagius_">Plagius</ref>, who (notwithstanding
                    he had been severely reprehended for such Practices before) was diligently
                    transcribing some eloquent Paragraphs out of <ref corresp="tillotson"
                        target="tillotson_">Tillotson's <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref>, &amp;c.,
                    to embellish his own.</p>
                <p>Now I bethought my self in my Sleep, that it was Time to be at Home, and as I
                    fancy'd I was travelling back thither, I reflected in my Mind on the extream
                    Folly of those Parents, who, blind to their Childrens Dulness, and insensible of
                    the Solidity of their Skulls, because they think their Purses can afford it,
                    will needs send them to the Temple of Learning, where, for want of a suitable
                    Genius, they learn little more than how to carry themselves handsomely, and
                    enter a Room <ref corresp="genteel" target="genteel_">genteely</ref>, (which
                    might as well be acquir'd at a Dancing-School,) and from whence they return,
                    after Abundance of Trouble and Charge, as great Blockheads as ever, only more
                    proud and self-conceited.</p>
                <p>While I was in the midst of these unpleasant Reflections, Clericus (who with a
                    Book in his Hand was walking under the Trees) accidentally awak'd me; to him I
                    related my Dream with all its Particulars, and he, without much Study, presently
                    interpreted it, assuring me, <hi rend="italic">That it was </hi><hi
                        rend="italic">a lively Representation of</hi> Harvard College, <hi
                        rend="italic">Etcetera</hi>. I remain, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> May 28, 1722 [No. 5] <ref corresp="terencetrans" target="terencetrans_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Mulier Mulieri magis congruet</hi>. Ter.</ref> To the
                    Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>I shall here present your Readers with a Letter from one, who informs me that I
                    have begun at the wrong End of my Business, and that I ought to begin at Home,
                    and censure the Vices and Follies of my own Sex, before I venture to meddle with
                    your's: Nevertheless, I am resolved to dedicate this Speculation to the Fair
                    Tribe, and endeavour to show, that Mr. Ephraim charges Women with being
                    particularly guilty of Pride, Idleness, &amp;c. wrongfully, inasmuch as the Men
                    have not only as great a Share in those Vices as the Women, but are likewise in
                    a great Measure the Cause of that which the Women are guilty of. I think it will
                    be best to produce my Antagonist, before I encounter him.</p>
                <p>"Madam</p>
                <p>"My Design in troubling you with this Letter is, to desire you would begin with
                    your own Sex first: Let the first Volley of your Resentments be directed against
                        <hi rend="italic">Female</hi> Vice; let Female Idleness, Ignorance and
                    Folly, (which are Vices more peculiar to your Sex than to our's,) be the Subject
                    of your <ref corresp="satyr" target="satyr_">Satyrs</ref>, but more especially
                    Female Pride, which I think is intollerable. Here is a large Field that wants
                    Cultivation, and which I believe you are able (if willing) to improve with
                    Advantage; and when you have once reformed the Women, you will find it a much
                    easier Task to reform the Men, because Women are the prime Causes of a great
                    many Male <ref corresp="maleenormity" target="maleenormity_">Enormities</ref>.
                    This is all at present from Your Friendly Wellwisher,</p>
                <p><ref corresp="ephraim" target="ephraim_">Ephraim Censorious</ref></p>
                <p>After Thanks to my Correspondent for his Kindness in cutting out Work for me, I
                    must assure him, that I find it a very difficult Matter to <ref
                        corresp="reprove" target="reprove_">reprove</ref> Women separate from the
                    Men; for what Vice is there in which the Men have not as great a Share as the
                    Women? and in some have they not a far greater, as in Drunkenness, Swearing,
                    &amp;c.? And if they have, then it follows, that when a Vice is to be reproved,
                    Men, who are most culpable, deserve the most Reprehension, and certainly
                    therefore, ought to have it. But we will wave this Point at present, and proceed
                    to a particular Consideration of what my Correspondent calls <hi rend="italic"
                        >Female Vice</hi>.</p>
                <p>As for Idleness, if I should <ref corresp="quaere" target="quaere_">Quaere</ref>,
                    Where are the greatest Number of its <ref corresp="votary" target="votary_"
                        >Votaries</ref> to be found, with us or the Men? it might I believe be
                    easily and truly answer'd, <hi rend="italic">With the latter</hi>. For
                    notwithstanding the Men are commonly complaining how hard they are forc'd to
                    labour, only to maintain their Wives in <ref corresp="pomp" target="pomp_"
                        >Pomp</ref> and Idleness, yet if you go among the Women, you will learn,
                    that <hi rend="italic">they have always more Work upon their Hands than they are
                        able to do; and that a Woman's Work is never done</hi>, &amp;c. But however,
                    Suppose we should grant for once, that we are generally more idle than the Men,
                    (without making any Allowance for the <hi rend="italic">Weakness of the
                    Sex</hi>,) I desire to know whose Fault it is? Are not the Men to blame for
                    their Folly in maintaining us in Idleness? Who is there that can be handsomely
                    Supported in Affluence, Ease and Pleasure by another, that will chuse rather to
                    earn his Bread by the Sweat of his own Brows? And if a Man will be so fond and
                    so foolish, as to labour hard himself for a Livelihood, and suffer his Wife in
                    the mean Time to sit in Ease and Idleness, let him not blame her if she does so,
                    for it is in a great Measure his own Fault.</p>
                <p>And now for the Ignorance and Folly which he <ref corresp="reproach"
                        target="reproach_">reproaches</ref> us with, let us see (if we are Fools and
                    Ignoramus's) whose is the Fault, the Men's or our's. An ingenious Writer, having
                    this Subject in Hand, has the following Words, wherein he lays the Fault wholly
                    on the Men, for not allowing Women the Advantages of Education.</p>
                <p>"I have (says he) often thought of it as one of the most barbarous Customs in the
                    World, considering us as a civiliz'd and Christian Country, that we deny the
                    Advantages of Learning to Women. We reproach the Sex every Day with Folly and
                    Impertinence, while I am confident, had they the Advantages of Education equal
                    to us, they would be guilty of less than our selves. One would wonder indeed how
                    it should happen that Women are <ref corresp="conversible" target="conversible_"
                        >conversible</ref> at all, since they are only beholding to natural Parts
                    for all their Knowledge. Their Youth is spent to teach them to stitch and sew,
                    or make <ref corresp="baubles" target="baubles_">Baubles</ref>: They are taught
                    to read indeed, and perhaps to write their Names, or so; and that is the Heighth
                    of a Womans Education. And I would but ask any who slight the Sex for their
                    Understanding, What is a Man (a Gentleman, I mean) good for that is taught no
                    more? If Knowledge and Understanding had been useless Additions to the Sex, God
                    Almighty would never have given them Capacities, for he made nothing Needless.
                    What has the Woman done to forfeit the Priviledge of being taught? Does she
                    plague us with her Pride and <ref corresp="impertinence" target="impertinence_"
                        >Impertinence</ref>? Why did we not let her learn, that she might have had
                    more Wit? Shall we <ref corresp="upbraid" target="upbraid_">upbraid</ref> Women
                    with Folly, when 'tis only the Error of this inhumane Custom that hindred them
                    being made wiser."</p>
                <p>So much for Female Ignorance and Folly, and now let us a little consider the
                    Pride which my Correspondent thinks is <hi rend="italic">intollerable</hi>. By
                    this Expression of his, one would think he is some dejected <ref corresp="swain"
                        target="swain_">Swain</ref>, tyranniz'd over by some cruel haughty <ref
                        corresp="nymph" target="nymph_">Nymph</ref>, who (perhaps he thinks) has no
                    more Reason to be proud than himself. <hi rend="italic">Alas-a-day!</hi> What
                    shall we say in this Case! Why truly, if Women are proud, it is certainly owing
                    to the Men still; for if they will be such <hi rend="italic">Simpletons</hi> as
                    to humble themselves at their Feet, and fill their <ref corresp="credulous"
                        target="credulous_">credulous</ref> Ears with extravagant Praises of their
                    Wit, Beauty, and other Accomplishments (perhaps where there are none too,) and
                    when Women are by this Means perswaded that they are Something more than humane,
                    what Wonder is it, if they carry themselves haughtily, and live extravagantly.
                    Notwithstanding, I believe there are more Instances of extravagant Pride to be
                    found among Men than among Women, and this Fault is certainly more hainous in
                    the former than in the latter.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, I conclude, that it will be impossible to lash any Vice, of which
                    the Men are not equally guilty with the Women, and consequently deserve an equal
                    (if not a greater) Share in the Censure. However, I <ref corresp="exhort"
                        target="exhort_">exhort</ref> both to amend, where both are <ref
                        corresp="culpable" target="culpable_">culpable</ref>, otherwise they may
                    expect to be severely handled by Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> Mrs. Dogood has lately left her Seat in the Country,
                    and come to Boston, where she intends to <ref target="tarry_" corresp="tarry"
                        >tarry</ref> for the Summer Season, in order to compleat her Observations of
                    the present reigning Vices of the Town.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> June 11, 1722 [No. 6] <ref corresp="senecatrans" target="senecatrans_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Quem Dies videt veniens Superbum, Hunc Dies vidit fugiens
                            jacentem.</hi> Seneca.</ref> To the Author of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >New-England Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Among the many reigning Vices of the Town which may at any Time come under my
                    Consideration and Reprehension, there is none which I am more inclin'd to expose
                    than that of <hi rend="italic">Pride</hi>. It is acknowledg'd by all to be a
                    Vice the most hateful to God and Man. Even those who nourish it in themselves,
                    hate to see it in others. The proud Man aspires after Nothing less than an
                    unlimited Superiority over his Fellow-Creatures. He has made himself a King in
                        <ref corresp="soliloquy" target="soliloquy_"><hi rend="italic"
                            >Soliloquy</hi>S</ref>; fancies himself conquering the World; and the
                    Inhabitants thereof consulting on proper Methods to acknowledge his Merit. I
                    speak it to my Shame, I my self was a Queen from the Fourteenth to the
                    Eighteenth Year of my Age, and govern'd the World all the Time of my being
                    govern'd by my Master. But this speculative Pride may be the Subject of another
                    Letter: I shall at present confine my Thoughts to what we call <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pride of Apparel</hi>. This Sort of Pride has been growing upon us ever
                    since we parted with our Homespun Cloaths for <ref corresp="penny"
                        target="penny_"><hi rend="italic">Fourteen Penny Stuffs</hi></ref>, &amp;c.
                    And the <hi rend="italic">Pride of Apparel</hi> has <ref corresp="begot"
                        target="begot_">begot</ref> and nourish'd in us a <hi rend="italic">Pride of
                        Heart</hi>, which <ref corresp="portend" target="portend_">portends</ref>
                    the Ruin of Church and State. <hi rend="italic">Pride goeth before Destruction,
                        and a haughty Spirit before a Fall</hi>: And I remember my late Reverend
                    Husband would often say upon this Text, That a Fall was the <hi rend="italic"
                        >natural Consequence</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic">Punishment</hi> of
                    Pride. Daily Experience is sufficient to <ref corresp="evince" target="evince_"
                        >evince</ref> the Truth of this Observation. Persons of small Fortune under
                    the Dominion of this Vice, seldom consider their Inability to maintain
                    themselves in it, but strive to imitate their Superiors in Estate, or Equals in
                    Folly, until one Misfortune comes upon the Neck of another, and every Step they
                    take is a Step backwards. By striving to appear rich they become really poor,
                    and deprive themselves of that Pity and Charity which is due to the humble poor
                    Man, who is made so more immediately by Providence.</p>
                <p>This Pride of Apparel will appear the more foolish, if we consider, that those
                    airy Mortals, who have no other Way of making themselves considerable but by
                    gorgeous Apparel, draw after them Crowds of Imitators, who hate each other while
                    they endeavour after a Similitude of Manners. They destroy by Example, and envy
                    one another's Destruction.</p>
                <p>I cannot dismiss this Subject without some Observations on a particular Fashion
                    now reigning among my own Sex, the most immodest and inconvenient of any the Art
                    of Woman has invented, namely, that of <ref corresp="hoop" target="hoop_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Hoop-Petticoats</hi></ref>. By these they are <ref
                        corresp="incommoded" target="incommoded_">incommoded</ref> in their General
                    and Particular Calling, and therefore they cannot answer the Ends of either
                    necessary or ornamental Apparel. These monstrous topsy-turvy <ref
                        corresp="mortar" target="mortar_"><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mortar-Pieces</hi></ref>, are neither fit for the Church, the Hall, or the
                    Kitchen; and if a Number of them were well mounted on <ref corresp="noddles"
                        target="noddles_">Noddles-Island</ref>, they would look more like Engines of
                    War for bombarding the Town, than Ornaments of the Fair Sex. An honest Neighbour
                    of mine, happening to be in Town some time since on a publick Day, inform'd me,
                    that he saw four Gentlewomen with their Hoops half mounted in a Balcony, as they
                    withdrew to the Wall, to the great Terror of the Militia, who (he thinks) might
                    attribute their irregular Volleys to the formidable Appearance of the Ladies
                    Petticoats.</p>
                <p>I assure you, Sir, I have but little Hopes of perswading my Sex, by this Letter,
                    utterly to relinquish the extravagant Foolery, and Indication of Immodesty, in
                    this monstrous Garb of their's; but I would at least desire them to lessen the
                    Circumference of their Hoops, and leave it with them to consider, Whether they,
                    who pay no Rates or Taxes, ought to take up more Room in the King's High-Way,
                    than the Men, who yearly contribute to the Support of the Government. I am, Sir,
                    Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> June 25, 1722 [No. 7] <ref corresp="watts" target="watts_"><lg>
                            <l>Give me the Muse, whose generous Force,</l>
                            <l>Impatient of the Reins,</l>
                            <l>Pursues an unattempted Course,</l>
                            <l>Breaks all the Criticks Iron Chains.</l>
                        </lg> Watts.</ref> To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <!-- PERHAPS an opening note about the satirical tone in this which I assume is mostly lost on the people of today. -->
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It has been the Complaint of many Ingenious Foreigners, who have travell'd
                    amongst us, <hi rend="italic">That good Poetry is not to be expected in
                        New-England</hi>. I am apt to Fancy, the Reason is, not because our
                    Countreymen are altogether void of a Poetical Genius, nor yet because we have
                    not those Advantages of Education which other Countries have, but purely because
                    we do not afford that Praise and Encouragement which is merited, when any thing
                    extraordinary of this Kind is produc'd among us: Upon which Consideration I have
                    determined, when I meet with a Good Piece of New-England Poetry, to give it a
                    suitable <ref corresp="encomium" target="encomium_">Encomium</ref>, and thereby
                    endeavour to discover to the World some of its Beautys, in order to encourage
                    the Author to go on, and bless the World with more, and more Excellent
                    Productions.</p>
                <p>There has lately appear'd among us a most Excellent Piece of Poetry, entituled,
                        <hi rend="italic">An Elegy upon the much Lamented Death of Mrs. Mehitebell
                        Kitel, Wife of Mr. John Kitel of Salem, &amp;c</hi>. It may justly be said
                    in its Praise, without Flattery to the Author, that it is the most <hi
                        rend="italic">Extraordinary</hi> Piece that ever was wrote in New-England.
                    The Language is so soft and Easy, the Expression so moving and pathetick, but
                    above all, the Verse and Numbers so Charming and Natural, that it is almost
                    beyond Comparison,</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>The Muse disdains</l>
                    <l>Those Links and Chains,</l>
                    <l>Measures and Rules of vulgar Strains,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">And o'er the Laws of Harmony a Sovereign Queen she
                            reigns.</hi></l>
                </lg>


                <p>I find no English Author, Ancient or Modern, whose Elegies may be compar'd with
                    this, in respect to the Elegance of Stile, or Smoothness of Rhime; and for the
                    affecting Part, I will leave your Readers to judge, if ever they read any Lines,
                    that would sooner make them <hi rend="italic">draw their Breath</hi> and Sigh,
                    if not shed Tears, than these following.</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>Come let us mourn, for we have lost a Wife, a Daughter, and <hi rend="italic"
                            >a Sister</hi>,</l>
                    <l>Who has lately taken Flight, and greatly we have mist her.</l>
                </lg>

                <p>In another Place,</p>

                <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Some little Time</hi> before she yielded up her Breath,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">She said, I ne'er shall hear one Sermon more on
                        Earth</hi>.</l>
                    <l>She kist her Husband <hi rend="italic">some little Time</hi>before she
                        expir'd,</l>
                    <l>Then lean'd her Head the Pillow on, just out of Breath and tir'd.</l>
                </lg>

                <p>But the Threefold <ref corresp="appellation" target="appellation_"
                        >Appellation</ref> in the first Line</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>a Wife, a Daughter, and a Sister,</l>
                </lg>

                <p>must not pass unobserved. That Line in the celebrated Watts,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Gunston <hi rend="italic">the Just</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the Generous</hi>,
                            <hi rend="italic">and the Young</hi>, </l>
                </lg>


                <p>is nothing Comparable to it. The latter only mentions three Qualifications of <hi
                        rend="italic">one</hi> Person who was deceased, which therefore could raise
                    Grief and Compassion but for <hi rend="italic">One</hi>. Whereas the former,
                        (<hi rend="italic">our most excellent Poet</hi>) gives his Reader a Sort of
                    an Idea of the Death of <hi rend="italic">Three Persons</hi>, viz.</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>a Wife, a Daughter, and a Sister,</l>
                </lg>

                <p>which is <hi rend="italic">Three Times</hi> as great a Loss as the Death of <hi
                        rend="italic">One</hi>, and consequently must raise <hi rend="italic">Three
                        Times</hi> as much Grief and Compassion in the Reader.</p>
                <p>I should be very much straitned for Room, if I should attempt to discover even
                    half the Excellencies of this Elegy which are obvious to me. Yet I cannot omit
                    one Observation, which is, that the Author has (to his Honour) invented a new
                    Species of Poetry, which wants a Name, and was never before known. His Muse
                    scorns to be confin'd to the old Measures and Limits, or to observe the dull
                    Rules of Criticks;</p>

                <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Nor <ref corresp="rapin" target="rapin_">Rapin</ref> gives
                            her Rules to fly, nor <ref corresp="purcell" target="purcell_"
                                >Purcell</ref> Notes to sing</hi>. Watts.</l>
                </lg>

                <p>Now 'tis Pity that such an Excellent Piece should not be dignify'd with a
                    particular Name; and seeing it cannot justly be called, either <ref
                        corresp="greekstyle" target="greekstyle_"><hi rend="italic">Epic</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Sapphic</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lyric</hi>, or <hi
                            rend="italic">Pindaric</hi></ref>, nor any other Name yet invented, I
                    presume it may, (in Honour and Remembrance of the Dead) be called the <ref
                        corresp="kitelic" target="kitelic_">Kitelic</ref>. Thus much in the Praise
                    of <hi rend="italic">Kitelic Poetry</hi>.</p>
                <p>It is certain, that those Elegies which are of our own Growth, (and our Soil
                    seldom produces any other sort of Poetry) are by far the greatest part,
                    wretchedly Dull and Ridiculous. Now since it is imagin'd by many, that our Poets
                    are honest, well-meaning Fellows, who do their best, and that if they had but
                    some Instructions how to govern Fancy with Judgment, they would make indifferent
                    good Elegies; I shall here <ref corresp="subjoin" target="subjoin_"
                        >subjoin</ref> a <ref corresp="receipt" target="receipt_">Receipt</ref> for
                    that purpose, which was left me as a Legacy, (among other valuable Rarities) by
                    my Reverend Husband. It is as follows,</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>A RECEIPT to make a New-England Funeral ELEGY.</l>
                </lg>


                <p><hi rend="italic">For the Title of your Elegy</hi>. Of these you may have enough
                    ready made to your Hands; but if you should chuse to make it your self, you must
                    be sure not to omit the Words <ref corresp="aetatis" target="aetatis_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Aetatis Suae</hi></ref>, which will Beautify it
                    exceedingly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">For the Subject of your Elegy</hi>. Take one of your Neighbours
                    who has lately departed this Life; it is no great matter at what Age the Party
                    dy'd, but it will be best if he went away suddenly, being <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kill'd</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Drown'd</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Froze to
                        Death</hi>.</p>
                <p>Having chose the Person, take all his Virtues, Excellencies, &amp;c. and if he
                    have not enough, you may borrow some to make up a sufficient Quantity: To these
                    add his last Words, dying Expressions, &amp;c. if they are to be had; mix all
                    these together, and be sure you <hi rend="italic">strain</hi> them well. Then
                    season all with a Handful or two of Melancholly Expressions, such as, <hi
                        rend="italic">Dreadful</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Deadly</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">cruel cold Death</hi>, <hi rend="italic">unhappy Fate</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">weeping Eyes</hi>, &amp;c. Have mixed all these
                    Ingredients well, put them into the empty <ref corresp="scull" target="scull_"
                        >Scull</ref> of some <hi rend="italic">young Harvard</hi>; (but in Case you
                    have ne'er a One at Hand, you may use your own,) there let them Ferment for the
                    Space of a Fortnight, and by that Time they will be incorporated into a Body,
                    which take out, and having prepared a sufficient Quantity of double Rhimes, such
                    as, <hi rend="italic">Power</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Flower</hi>; <hi
                        rend="italic">Quiver</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Shiver</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Grieve us</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Leave us</hi>; <hi rend="italic">tell
                        you</hi>, <hi rend="italic">excel you</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Expeditions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Physicians</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fatigue him</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Intrigue him</hi>; &amp;c. you must
                    spread all upon Paper, and if you can procure a Scrap of Latin to put at the
                    End, it will garnish it mightily; then having affixed your Name at the Bottom,
                    with a <ref corresp="moestus" target="moestus_"><hi rend="italic">Moestus
                            Composuit</hi></ref>, you will have an Excellent Elegy.</p>
                <p><ref corresp="notabene" target="notabene_"><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi></ref> This
                    Receipt will serve when a Female is the Subject of your Elegy, provided you
                    borrow a greater Quantity of Virtues, Excellencies, &amp;c. Sir, Your
                    Servant,</p>
                <p>Silence Dogood</p>
                <p>p.s. I shall make no other Answer to <ref corresp="hypercarpus"
                        target="hypercarpus_">Hypercarpus's Criticism on my last Letter</ref> than
                    this, <ref corresp="mater" target="mater_"><hi rend="italic">Mater me genuit,
                            peperit mox filia matrem.</hi></ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> July 9, 1722 [No. 8] To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>I prefer the following Abstract from the London Journal to any Thing of my own,
                    and therefore shall present it to your Readers this week without any further
                    Preface.</p>
                <p>"Without Freedom of Thought, there can be no such Thing as Wisdom; and no such
                    Thing as publick Liberty, without Freedom of Speech; which is the Right of every
                    Man, as far as by it, he does not hurt or controul the Right of another: And
                    this is the only Check it ought to suffer, and the only Bounds it ought to
                    know.</p>
                <p>"This sacred Privilege is so essential to free Goverments, that the Security of
                    Property, and the Freedom of Speech always go together; and in those wretched
                    Countries where a Man cannot call his Tongue his own, he can scarce call any
                    Thing else his own. Whoever would overthrow the Liberty of a Nation, must begin
                    by subduing the Freeness of Speech; a <hi rend="italic">Thing</hi> terrible to
                    Publick Traytors.</p>
                <p>"This Secret was so well known to the Court of <ref corresp="charles"
                        target="charles_">King Charles the First</ref>, that his wicked Ministry
                    procured a Proclamation, to forbid the People to talk of Parliaments, which
                    those Traytors had laid aside. To assert the undoubted Right of the Subject, and
                    defend his Majesty's legal Prerogative, was called <ref corresp="disaffection"
                        target="disaffection_">Disaffection</ref>, and punished as <ref
                        corresp="sedition" target="sedition_">Sedition</ref>. Nay, People were
                    forbid to talk of Religion in their Families: For the Priests had combined with
                    the Ministers to cook up Tyranny, and suppress Truth and the Law, while <ref
                        corresp="james" target="james_">the late King James</ref>, when Duke of
                    York, went avowedly to Mass, Men were fined, imprisoned and undone, for saying
                    he was a <ref corresp="papist" target="papist_">Papist</ref>: And that <ref
                        corresp="charlesii" target="charlesii_">King Charles the Second</ref> might
                    live more securely a Papist, there was an Act of Parliament made, declaring it
                    Treason to say that he was one.</p>
                <p>"That Men ought to speak well of <hi rend="italic">their Governours</hi> is true,
                    while <hi rend="italic">their Governours</hi> deserve to be well spoken of; but
                    to do publick Mischief, without hearing of it, is only the Prerogative and <ref
                        corresp="felicity" target="felicity_">Felicity</ref> of Tyranny: A free
                    People will be shewing that they are <hi rend="italic">so</hi>, by their Freedom
                    of Speech.</p>
                <p>"The Administration of Government, is nothing else but the Attendance of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Trustees of the People</hi> upon the Interest and Affairs of
                    the People: And as it is the Part and Business of the People, for whose Sake
                    alone all publick Matters are, or ought to be transacted, to see whether they be
                    well or ill transacted; so it is the Interest, and ought to be the Ambition, of
                    all honest Magistrates, to have their Deeds openly examined, and publickly
                    scann'd: Only the <hi rend="italic">wicked Governours</hi> of Men dread what is
                    said of them; <ref corresp="audivit" target="audivit_"><hi rend="italic">Audivit
                            Tiberius probra queis lacerabitur, atque</hi> perculsus est</ref>. The
                    publick Censure was true, else he had not felt it bitter.</p>
                <p>Freedom of Speech is ever the Symptom, as well as the Effect of a good
                    Government. In old Rome, all was left to the Judgment and Pleasure of the
                    People, who examined the publick Proceedings with such Discretion, and censured
                    those who administred them with such Equity and Mildness, that in the space of
                    Three Hundred Years, not five publick Ministers suffered unjustly. Indeed
                    whenever the <hi rend="italic">Commons</hi> proceeded to Violence, the great
                    Ones had been the Agressors.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">"Guilt</hi> only dreads Liberty of Speech, which drags it out
                    of its lurking Holes, and exposes its Deformity and Horrour to Daylight."
                    Horatius, <ref corresp="valerius" target="valerius_">Valerius</ref>, <ref
                        corresp="cincinnatus" target="cincinnatus_">Cincinnatus</ref>, and other
                    vertuous and undesigning Magistrates of the Roman Commonwealth, had nothing to
                    fear from Liberty of Speech. <hi rend="italic">Their virtuous</hi>
                    Administration, the more it was examin'd, the more it brightned and gain'd by
                    Enquiry. When Valerius in particular, was accused upon some slight grounds of
                    affecting the <ref corresp="diadem" target="diadem_">Diadem</ref>; he, who was
                    the first Minister of Rome, does not accuse the People for examining his
                    Conduct, but approved his Innocence in a Speech to them; and gave such
                    Satisfaction to them, and gained such Popularity to himself, that they gave him
                    a new Name; <ref corresp="cognomen" target="cognomen_"><hi rend="italic">inde
                            cognomen factum Publicolae est</hi></ref>; to denote that he was their
                    Favourite and their Friend. <ref corresp="livytrans" target="livytrans_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Latae deinde leges — Ante omnes de provocatione</hi>
                        Adversus Magistratus Ad Populum, Livii, lib. 2. Cap. 8.</ref></p>
                <p>"But Things afterwards took another Turn. Rome, with the Loss of its Liberty,
                    lost also its Freedom of Speech; then Mens Words began to be feared and watched;
                    and then first began the <hi rend="italic">poysonous Race of Informers</hi>,
                    banished indeed under the righteous Administration of Titus, Narva, Trajan,
                    Aurelius, &amp;c. but encouraged and enriched under the <hi rend="italic">vile
                        Ministry</hi> of Sejanus, Tigillinus, Pallas, and Cleander: <ref
                        corresp="plinytrans" target="plinytrans_"><hi rend="italic">Queri libet,
                            quod in secreta nostra non inquirant principes, nisi quos Odimus</hi>,
                        says Pliny to Trajan</ref>.</p>
                <p>"The best Princes have ever encouraged and promoted Freedom of Speech; they know
                    that upright Measures would defend themselves, and that all upright Men would
                    defend them. <ref corresp="tacitus" target="tacitus_">Tacitus</ref>, speaking of
                    the Reign of some of the Princes abovemention'd, says with Extasy, <hi
                        rend="italic">Rara Temporum felicitate, ubi sentire quae velis, &amp; quae
                        sentias dicere licet</hi>A blessed Time when you might think what you would,
                    and speak what you thought.</p>
                <p>"I doubt not but old Spencer and his Son, who were the <hi rend="italic">Chief
                        Ministers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Betrayers</hi> of <ref
                        corresp="edwardii" target="edwardii_">Edward the Second</ref>, would have
                    been very glad to have stopped the Mouths of all the honest Men in England. They
                    dreaded to be called <hi rend="italic">Traytors</hi>, because they were <hi
                        rend="italic">Traytors</hi>. And I dare say, <ref corresp="walsingham"
                        target="walsingham_">Queen Elizabeth's Walsingham</ref>, who deserved no
                    Reproaches, feared none. Misrepresentation of publick Measures is easily
                    overthrown, by representing publick Measures truly; when they are honest, they
                    ought to be publickly known, that they may be publickly commended; but if they
                    are <ref corresp="knavish" target="knavish_">knavish</ref> or <ref
                        corresp="pernicious" target="pernicious_">pernicious</ref>, they ought to be
                    publickly exposed, in order to be publickly detested." Yours, &amp;c.,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> July 23, 1722 [No. 9] <ref corresp="corruptio" target="corruptio_">Corruptio
                        optimi est pessima</ref>. To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It has been for some Time a Question with me, Whether a Commonwealth suffers more
                    by hypocritical Pretenders to Religion, or by the openly <ref corresp="profane"
                        target="profane_">Profane</ref>? But some late Thoughts of this Nature, have
                    inclined me to think, that the Hypocrite is the most dangerous Person of the
                    Two, especially if he sustains a Post in the Government, and we consider his
                    Conduct as it regards the Publick. The first <ref corresp="artifice"
                        target="artifice_">Artifice</ref> of a <hi rend="italic">State
                        Hypocrite</hi> is, by a few savoury Expressions which cost him Nothing, to
                    betray the best Men in his Country into an Opinion of his Goodness; and if the
                    Country wherein he lives is noted for the Purity of Religion, he the more easily
                    gains his End, and consequently may more justly be expos'd and detested. A
                    notoriously profane Person in a private Capacity, ruins himself, and perhaps
                    forwards the Destruction of a few of his Equals; but a publick Hypocrite every
                    day deceives his betters, and makes them the Ignorant <ref corresp="trumpeters"
                        target="trumpeters_">Trumpeters</ref> of his supposed Godliness: They take
                    him for a Saint, and pass him for one, without considering that they are (as it
                    were) the Instruments of publick Mischief out of Conscience, and ruin their
                    Country for God's sake.</p>
                <p>This Political Description of a Hypocrite, may (for ought I know) be taken for a
                    new Doctrine by some of your Readers; but let them consider, that a <hi
                        rend="italic">little Religion, and a little Honesty, goes a great way in
                        Courts</hi>. 'Tis not inconsistent with Charity to distrust a Religious Man
                    in Power, tho' he may be a good Man; he has many Temptations "to propagate <hi
                        rend="italic">publick Destruction for Personal Advantages</hi> and
                    Security": And if his Natural Temper be covetous, and his Actions often
                    contradict his pious Discourse, we may with great Reason conclude, that he has
                    some other Design in his Religion besides barely getting to Heaven. But the most
                    dangerous Hypocrite in a Common-Wealth, is one <hi rend="italic">who leaves the
                        Gospel for the sake of the Law</hi>: A Man compounded of Law and Gospel, is
                    able to cheat a whole Country with his Religion, and then destroy them under
                        <ref corresp="colour" target="colour_"><hi rend="italic">Colour of
                        Law</hi></ref>: And here the Clergy are in great Danger of being deceiv'd,
                    and the People of being deceiv'd by the Clergy, until the Monster arrives to
                    such Power and Wealth, that he is out of the reach of both, and can oppress the
                    People without their own blind Assistance. And it is a sad Observation, that
                    when the People too late see their Error, yet the Clergy still persist in their
                        <ref corresp="encomium2" target="encomium2_">Encomiums</ref> on the
                    Hypocrite; and when he happens to die <hi rend="italic">for the Good of his
                        Country</hi>, without leaving behind him the Memory of <hi rend="italic">one
                        good Action</hi>, he shall be sure to have his Funeral Sermon stuff'd with
                        <hi rend="italic">Pious Expressions</hi> which he dropt at such a Time, and
                    at such a Place, and on such an Occasion; than which nothing can be more
                    prejudicial to the Interest of Religion, nor indeed to the Memory of the Person
                    deceas'd. The Reason of this Blindness in the Clergy is, because they are
                    honourably supported (as they ought to be) by their People, and see nor feel
                    nothing of the Oppression which is obvious and burdensome to every one else.</p>
                <p>But this Subject raises in me an <ref corresp="indignation" target="indignation_"
                        >Indignation</ref> not to be born; and if we have had, or are like to have
                    any Instances of this Nature in New England, we cannot better manifest our Love
                    to Religion and the Country, than by setting the Deceivers in a true Light, and
                    undeceiving the Deceived, however such Discoveries may be represented by the
                    ignorant or designing Enemies of our Peace and Safety.</p>
                <p>I shall conclude with a Paragraph or two from an ingenious Political Writer in
                    the <hi rend="italic">London Journal</hi>, the better to convince your Readers,
                    that Publick Destruction may be easily carry'd on by <hi rend="italic"
                        >hypocritical Pretenders to Religion</hi>.</p>
                <p>"A raging Passion for immoderate Gain had made Men universally and intensely
                    hard-hearted: They were every where devouring one another. And yet the Directors
                    and their Accomplices, who were the acting Instruments of all this outrageous
                    Madness and Mischief, set up for wonderful pious Persons, while they were
                    defying Almighty God, and plundering Men; and they set apart a Fund of
                    Subscriptions for charitable Uses; that is, they mercilessly made a whole People
                    Beggars, and charitably supported a few <hi rend="italic">necessitous and
                        worthless</hi> Favourites. I doubt not, but if the Villany had gone on with
                    Success, they would have had their Names handed down to Posterity with
                    Encomiums; as the Names of other <hi rend="italic">publick Robbers</hi> have
                    been! We have <hi rend="italic">Historians</hi> and Ode Makers now living, very
                    proper for such a Task. It is certain, that most People did, at one Time,
                    believe the <hi rend="italic">Directors</hi> to be <hi rend="italic">great and
                        worthy Persons</hi>. And an honest Country Clergyman told me last Summer,
                    upon the Road, that Sir John was an excellent publick-spirited Person, for that
                    he had beautified his <ref corresp="chancel" target="chancel_"
                    >Chancel</ref>.</p>
                <p>"Upon the whole we must not judge of one another by their best Actions; since the
                    worst Men do some Good, and all Men make fine Professions: But we must judge of
                    Men by the whole of their Conduct, and the Effects of it. Thorough Honesty
                    requires great and long Proof, since many a Man, long thought honest, has at
                    length proved a <ref corresp="knave" target="knave_">Knave</ref>. And it is from
                    judging without Proof, or false Proof, that Mankind continue Unhappy." I am,
                    Sir, Your humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> August 13, 1722 [No. 10] <ref corresp="cicerotrans2" target="cicerotrans2_"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Optimè societas hominum servabitur</hi>. Cic.</ref>
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. </head>

                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Discoursing lately with an intimate Friend of mine of the lamentable Condition of
                    Widows, he put into my Hands a Book, wherein the ingenious Author proposes (I
                    think) a certain Method for their Relief. I have often thought of some such
                    Project for their Benefit my self, and intended to communicate my Thoughts to
                    the Publick; but to prefer my own Proposals to what follows, would be rather an
                    Argument of Vanity in me than Good Will to the many Hundreds of my
                    Fellow-Sufferers now in New-England.</p>

                <p>“We have (says he) abundance of Women, who have been Bred well, and Liv’d well,
                    Ruin’d in a few Years, and perhaps, left Young, with a House full of Children,
                    and nothing to Support them; which falls generally upon the Wives of the
                    Inferior Clergy, or of Shopkeepers and <ref corresp="artificer"
                        target="artificer_">Artificers</ref>.</p>
                <p>“They marry Wives with perhaps <ref corresp="portion" target="portion_">£300 to
                        £1000 Portion</ref>, and can settle no <ref corresp="jointure"
                        target="jointure_">Jointure</ref> upon them; either they are Extravagant and
                    Idle, and Waste it, or Trade decays, or Losses, or a Thousand Contingences
                    happen to bring a Tradesman to Poverty, and he Breaks; the Poor Young Woman, it
                    may be, has Three or Four Children, and is driven to a thousand shifts, while he
                    lies in the <ref corresp="mint" target="mint_">Mint</ref> or <ref
                        corresp="fryar" target="fryar_">Fryars</ref> under the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dilemma</hi> of a Statute of Bankrupt; but if he Dies, then she is
                    absolutely Undone, unless she has Friends to go to.</p>
                <p>“Suppose an Office to be Erected, to be call’d <hi rend="italic">An Office of
                        Ensurance for Widows</hi>, upon the following Conditions;</p>
                <p>“Two thousand Women, or their Husbands for them, Enter their Names into a
                    Register to be kept for that purpose, with the Names, Age, and Trade of their
                    Husbands, with the Place of their abode, Paying at the Time of their Entring
                        <ref corresp="britcash" target="britcash_">5<hi rend="italic">s</hi></ref>.
                    down with 1<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 4<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. <hi
                        rend="italic">per</hi> Quarter, which is to the setting up and support of an
                    Office with Clerks, and all proper Officers for the same; <hi rend="italic">for
                        there is no maintaining such without Charge</hi>; they receive every one of
                    them a Certificate, Seal’d by the Secretary of the Office, and Sign’d by the
                    Governors, for the Articles hereafter mentioned.</p>
                <p>“If any one of the Women becomes a Widow, at any Time after Six Months from the
                    Date of her Subscription, upon due Notice given, and Claim made at the Office in
                    form, as shall be directed, she shall receive within Six Months after such Claim
                    made, the Sum of £500 in Money, without any Deductions, saving some small Fees
                    to the Officers, which the Trustees must settle, that they may be known.</p>
                <p>“In Consideration of this, every Woman so Subscribing, Obliges her self to Pay as
                    often as any Member of the Society becomes a Widow, the due Proportion or Share
                    allotted to her to Pay, towards the £500 for the said Widow, provided her Share
                    does not exceed the Sum of 5<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.</p>
                <p>“No Seamen or Soldiers Wives to be accepted into such a Proposal as this, on the
                    Account before mention’d, because the Contingences of their Lives are not equal
                    to others, unless they will admit this general Exception, supposing they do not
                    Die out of the Kingdom.</p>
                <p>“It might also be an Exception, That if the Widow, that Claim’d, had really, <ref
                        corresp="bonafide" target="bonafide_"><hi rend="italic">bona
                    fide</hi></ref>,left her by her Husband to her own use, clear of all Debts and
                    Legacies, £2000 she shou’d have no Claim; the Intent being to Aid the Poor, not
                    add to the Rich. But there lies a great many Objections against such an Article:
                    As</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>“1. It may tempt some to <ref corresp="forswear" target="forswear_"
                            >forswear</ref> themselves.</l>
                    <l>“2. People will Order their Wills so as to <ref corresp="defraud"
                            target="defraud_">defraud</ref> the Exception.</l>
                </lg>

                <p>“One Exception must be made; and that is, Either very unequal Matches, as when a
                    Woman of Nineteen Marries an old Man of Seventy; or Women who have <ref
                        corresp="infirm" target="infirm_">infirm</ref> Husbands, I mean known and
                    publickly so. To remedy which, Two things are to be done.</p>

                <lg>
                    <l>“[1.] The Office must have moving Officers without doors, who shall inform
                        themselves of such matters, and if any such Circumstances appear, the Office
                        should have 14 days time to return their Money, and declare their
                        Subscriptions Void.</l>
                    <l>“2. No Woman whose Husband had any visible <ref corresp="distemper"
                            target="distemper_">Distemper</ref>, should claim under a Year after her
                        Subscription.</l>

                </lg>

                <p>“One grand Objection against this Proposal, is, How you will oblige People to pay
                    either their Subscription, or their <ref corresp="quarteridge"
                        target="quarteridge_">Quarteridge</ref>.</p>
                <p>“To this I answer, <hi rend="italic">By no Compulsion</hi> (tho’ that might be
                    perform’d too) but altogether voluntary; only with this Argument to move it,
                    that if they do not continue their Payments, they lose the Benefit of their past
                    Contributions.</p>
                <p>“I know it lies as a fair Objection against such a Project as this, That the
                    number of Claims are so uncertain, That no Body knows what they engage in, when
                    they Subscribe, for so many may die Annually out of Two Thousand, as may perhaps
                    make my Payment £20 or 25 <ref corresp="perannum" target="perannum_"><hi
                            rend="italic">per Ann</hi></ref>., and if a Woman happen to Pay that for
                    Twenty Years, though she receives the £500 at last she is a great Loser; but if
                    she dies before her Husband, she has lessened his Estate considerably, and
                    brought a great Loss upon him.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">First</hi>, I say to this, That I wou’d have such a Proposal
                    as this be so fair and easy, that if any Person who had Subscrib’d found the
                    Payments too high, and the Claims fall too often, it shou’d be at their Liberty
                    at any Time, upon Notice given, to be released and stand Oblig’d no longer; and
                    if so, <ref corresp="violenti" target="violenti_"><hi rend="italic">Volenti non
                            fit Injuria</hi></ref>; every one knows best what their own
                    Circumstances will bear.</p>

                <p>“In the next Place, because Death is a Contingency, no Man can directly
                    Calculate, and all that Subscribe must take the Hazard; yet that a Prejudice
                    against this Notion may not be built on wrong Grounds, let’s examine a little
                    the Probable hazard, and see how many shall die Annually out of 2000
                    Subscribers, accounting by the common proportion of Burials, to the number of
                    the Living.</p>
                <p>“Sir William Petty in his <hi rend="italic">Political Arithmetick</hi>, by a very
                    Ingenious Calculation, brings the Account of Burials in London, to be 1 in 40
                    Annually, and proves it by all the proper Rules of proportion’d Computation; and
                    I’le take my Scheme from thence. If then One in Forty of all the People in
                    England should Die, that supposes Fifty to Die every Year out of our Two
                    Thousand Subscribers; and for a Woman to Contribute 5<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.
                    to every one, would certainly be to agree to Pay £12 10<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.
                        <hi rend="italic">per Ann</hi>. upon her Husband’s Life, to receive £500
                    when he Di’d, and lose it if she Di’d first; and yet this wou’d not be a hazard
                    beyond reason too great for the Gain.</p>
                <p>“But I shall offer some Reasons to prove this to be impossible in our Case;
                    First, Sir William Petty allows the City of London to contain about a Million of
                    People, and our Yearly Bill of Mortality never yet amounted to 25000 in the most
                    Sickly Years we have had, Plague Years excepted, sometimes but to 20000, which
                    is but One in Fifty: Now it is to be consider’d here, that Children and Ancient
                    People make up, one time with another, at least one third of our Bills of
                    Mortality; and our <hi rend="italic">Assurances</hi> lies upon none but the
                    Midling Age of the People, which is the only age wherein Life is any thing
                    steady; and if that be allow’d, there cannot Die by his Computation, above One
                    in Eighty of such People, every Year; but because I would be sure to leave Room
                    for Casualty, I’le allow one in Fifty shall Die out of our Number
                    Subscrib’d.</p>
                <p>“Secondly, It must be allow’d, that our Payments falling due only on the Death of
                    Husbands, this One in Fifty must not be reckoned upon the Two thousand; for ’tis
                    to be suppos’d at least as many Women shall die as Men, and then there is
                    nothing to Pay; so that One in Fifty upon One Thousand, is the most that I can
                    suppose shall claim the Contribution in a Year, which is Twenty Claims a Year at
                        5<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. each, and is £5 <hi rend="italic">per Ann</hi>.
                    and if a Woman pays this for Twenty Year, and claims at last, she is Gainer
                    enough, and no extraordinary Loser if she never claims at all: And I verily
                    believe any Office might undertake to demand at all Adventures not above £6 <hi
                        rend="italic">per Ann</hi>. and secure the Subscriber £500 in case she come
                    to claim as a Widow.”</p>
                <p>I would leave this to the Consideration of all who are concern’d for their own or
                    their Neighbour’s <ref corresp="temporal" target="temporal_">Temporal</ref>
                    Happiness; and I am humbly of Opinion, that the Country is ripe for many such
                        <hi rend="italic">Friendly Societies</hi>, whereby every Man might help
                    another, without any Disservice to himself. We have many charitable Gentlemen
                    who Yearly give liberally to the Poor, and where can they better bestow their
                    Charity than on those who become so by Providence, and for ought they know on
                    themselves. But above all, the Clergy have the most need of coming into some
                    such Project as this. They as well as poor Men (according to the Proverb)
                    generally abound in Children; and how many Clergymen in the Country are forc’d
                    to labour in their Fields, to keep themselves in a Condition above Want? How
                    then shall they be able to leave any thing to their forsaken, dejected, and
                    almost forgotten Wives and Children. For my own Part, I have nothing left to
                    live on, but Contentment and a few Cows; and tho’ I cannot expect to be reliev’d
                    by this Project, yet it would be no small Satisfaction to me to see it put in
                    Practice for the Benefit of others. I am, Sir, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>
                <!-- Why no period? -->
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> August 20, 1722 [No. 11] <ref corresp="unknownlatin" target="unknownlatin_"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Neque licitum interea est meam amicam
                        visere.</hi></ref> To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>From a natural Compassion to my Fellow-Creatures, I have sometimes been betray'd
                    into Tears at the Sight of an Object of Charity, who by a bear <ref
                        corresp="sic" target="sic_">[sic]</ref> Relation of his Circumstances,
                    seem'd to demand the Assistance of those about him. The following Petition
                    represents in so lively a Manner the forlorn State of a Virgin well stricken in
                    Years and Repentance, that I cannot forbear publishing it at this Time, with
                    some Advice to the Petitioner.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">To Mrs. Silence Dogood. </hi></p>
                <p>"1. That your Petitioner being puff'd up in her younger Years with a numerous
                    Train of Humble Servants, had the Vanity to think, that her extraordinary Wit
                    and Beauty would continually recommend her to the Esteem of the <ref
                        corresp="gallant" target="gallant_">Gallants</ref>; and therefore as soon as
                    it came to be publickly known that any Gentleman address'd her, he was
                    immediately discarded.</p>
                <p>"2. That several of your Petitioners Humble Servants, who upon their being
                    rejected by her, were, to all Apperance in a dying Condition, have since
                    recover'd their Health, and been several Years married, to the great Surprize
                    and Grief of your Petitioner, who parted with them upon no other Conditions, but
                    that they should die or run distracted for her, as several of them faithfully
                    promis'd to do.</p>
                <p>"3. That your Petitioner finding her self disappointed in and neglected by her
                    former Adorers, and no new Offers appearing for some Years past, she has been
                    industriously contracting Acquaintance with several Families in Town and
                    Country, where any young Gentlemen or Widowers have resided, and endeavour'd to
                    appear as conversable as possible before them: She has likewise been a strict
                    Observer of the Fashion, and always appear'd well dress'd. And the better to
                    restore her decay'd Beauty, she has consum'd above <ref corresp="fiftylb"
                        target="fiftylb_">Fifty Pound's Worth</ref> of the most approved <hi
                        rend="italic">Cosmeticks</hi>. But all won't do.</p>
                <p>"Your Petitioner therefore most humbly prays, That you would be pleased to form a
                    Project for the Relief of all those <ref corresp="penitent" target="penitent_"
                        >penitent</ref> Mortals of the fair Sex, that are like to be punish'd with
                    their Virginity until old Age, for the Pride and Insolence of their Youth.</p>
                <p>"And your Petitioner (as in Duty bound) shall ever pray, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Margaret Aftercast"</p>

                <p>Were I endow'd with the Faculty of Match-making, it should be improv'd for the
                    Benefit of Mrs. Margaret, and others in her Condition: But since my extream
                    Modesty and <ref corresp="taciturn" target="taciturn_">Taciturnity</ref>,
                    forbids an Attempt of this Nature, I would advise them to relieve themselves in
                    a Method of <hi rend="italic">Friendly Society</hi>; and that already publish'd
                    for Widows, I conceive would be a very proper Proposal for them, whereby every
                    single Woman, upon full Proof given of her continuing a Virgin for the Space of
                    Eighteen Years, (dating her Virginity from the Age of Twelve,) should be
                    entituled to £500 in ready Cash.</p>
                <p>But then it will be necessary to make the following Exceptions.</p>
                <p>1. That no Woman shall be admitted into the Society after she is Twenty Five
                    Years old, who has made a Practice of entertaining and discarding Humble
                    Servants, without sufficient Reason for so doing, until she has manifested her
                    Repentance in Writing under her Hand.</p>
                <p>2. No Member of the Society who has declar'd before two credible Witnesses, <hi
                        rend="italic">That it is well known she has refus'd several good Offers
                        since the Time of her Subscribing</hi>, shall be entituled to the £500 when
                    she comes of Age; that is to say, <hi rend="italic">Thirty Years</hi>.</p>
                <p>3. No Woman, who after claiming and receiving, has had the good Fortune to marry,
                    shall entertain any Company with <ref corresp="encomium3" target="encomium3_"
                        >Encomiums</ref> on her Husband, above the Space of one Hour at a Time, upon
                    Pain of returning one half the Money into the Office, for the first Offence; and
                    upon the second Offence to return the Remainder. I am, Sir, Your Humble
                    Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head> September 10, 1722 [No. 12] <ref corresp="cordi" target="cordi_"><hi
                            rend="italic">Quod est in cordi sobrii, est in ore ebrii</hi></ref>. To
                    the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It is no unprofitable tho' unpleasant Pursuit, diligently to inspect and consider
                    the Manners and Conversation of Men, who, insensible of the greatest Enjoyments
                    of humane Life, abandon themselves to Vice from a false Notion of <hi
                        rend="italic">Pleasure and good Fellowship</hi>. A true and natural
                    Representation of any Enormity, is often the best Argument against it and Means
                    of removing it, when the most severe Reprehensions alone, are found
                    ineffectual.</p>
                <p>I would in this letter improve the little Observation I have made on the Vice of
                        <hi rend="italic">Drunkeness</hi>, the better to reclaim the <hi
                        rend="italic">good Fellows</hi> who usually pay the Devotions of the Evening
                    to <ref corresp="bacchus" target="bacchus_">Bacchus</ref>.</p>
                <p>I doubt not but <hi rend="italic">moderate Drinking</hi> has been improv'd for
                    the Diffusion of Knowledge among the ingenious Part of Mankind, who want the
                    Talent of a ready Utterance, in order to discover the Conceptions of their Minds
                    in an entertaining and intelligible Manner. 'Tis true, drinking does not <hi
                        rend="italic">improve</hi> our Faculties, but it enables us to <hi
                        rend="italic">use</hi> them; and therefore I conclude, that much Study and
                    Experience, and a little Liquor, are of absolute Necessity for some Tempers, in
                    order to make them accomplish'd Orators. Dic. Ponder discovers an excellent
                    Judgment when he is inspir'd with a Glass or two of <ref corresp="claret"
                        target="claret_"><hi rend="italic">Claret</hi></ref>, but he passes for a
                    Fool among those of small Observation, who never saw him the better for Drink.
                    And here it will not be improper to observe, That the moderate Use of Liquor,
                    and a well plac'd and well regulated Anger, often produce this same Effect; and
                    some who cannot ordinarily talk but in broken Sentences and false Grammar, do in
                    the Heat of Passion express themselves with as much Eloquence as Warmth. Hence
                    it is that my own Sex are generally the most eloquent, because the most
                    passionate. "It has been said in the Praise of some Men, (says an ingenious
                    Author,) that they could talk whole Hours together upon any thing; but it must
                    be owned to the Honour of the other Sex, that there are many among them who can
                    talk whole Hours together upon Nothing. I have known a Woman branch out into a
                    long <ref corresp="extempore" target="extempore_">extempore</ref> Dissertation
                    on the <ref corresp="edging" target="edging_">Edging of a Petticoat</ref>, and
                        <ref corresp="chide" target="chide_">chide</ref> her Servant for breaking a
                    China Cup, in all the Figures of Rhetorick."</p>
                <p>But after all it must be consider'd, that no Pleasure can give Satisfaction or
                    prove advantageous to a <hi rend="italic">reasonable Mind</hi>, which is not
                    attended with the <hi rend="italic">Restraints of Reason</hi>. Enjoyment is not
                    to be found by Excess in any sensual Gratification; but on the contrary, the
                    immoderate Cravings of the <ref corresp="voluptuary" target="voluptuary_"
                        >Voluptuary</ref>, are always succeeded with Loathing and a <ref
                        corresp="palled" target="palled_">palled</ref> Appetite. What Pleasure can
                    the Drunkard have in the Reflection, that, while in his Cups, he retain'd only
                    the Shape of a Man, and acted the Part of a Beast; or that from reasonable
                    Discourse a few Minutes before, he descended to <ref corresp="impertinence2"
                        target="impertinence2_">Impertinence</ref> and Nonsense?</p>
                <p>I cannot pretend to account for the different Effects of Liquor on Persons of
                    different Dispositions, who are guilty of Excess in the Use of it. 'Tis strange
                    to see Men of a regular Conversation become <ref corresp="rakish"
                        target="rakish_">rakish</ref> and profane when intoxicated with Drink, and
                    yet more surprizing to observe, that some who appear to be the most <ref
                        corresp="profligate" target="profligate_">profligate</ref> Wretches when
                    sober, become mighty religious in their Cups, and will then, and at no other
                    Time address their Maker, but when they are destitute of Reason, and actually
                        <ref corresp="affront" target="affront_">affronting</ref> him. Some shrink
                        <ref corresp="wetting" target="wetting_">in the Wetting</ref>, and others
                    swell to such an unusual Bulk in their Imaginations, that they can in an Instant
                    understand all Arts and Sciences, by the liberal Education of a little <ref
                        corresp="vivifying" target="vivifying_">vivifying</ref>
                    <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>, or a sufficient Quantity of other exhilerating
                    Liquor.</p>
                <p>And as the Effects of Liquor are various, so are the Characters given to its
                    Devourers. It argues some Shame in the Drunkards themselves, in that they have
                    invented numberless Words and Phrases to cover their Folly, whose proper
                    Significations are harmless, or have no Signification at all. They are seldom
                    known to be <hi rend="italic">drunk</hi>, tho' they are very often <ref
                        corresp="drunk" target="drunk_"><hi rend="italic">boozey, cogey, tipsey,
                            fox'd, merry, mellow, fuddl'd, groatable, Confoundedly cut, See two
                            Moons, are Among the Philistines, In a very good Humour, See the Sun,
                            or, The Sun has shone upon them; they Clip the King's English, are
                            Almost froze, Feavourish, In their Altitudes, Pretty well enter'd</hi>,
                        &amp;c</ref>. In short, every Day produces some new Word or Phrase which
                    might be added to the Vocabulary of the <ref corresp="tipler" target="tipler_"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Tiplers</hi></ref>: But I have chose to mention these
                    few, because if at any Time a Man of Sobriety and Temperance happens to <hi
                        rend="italic">cut himself confoundedly</hi>, or is <hi rend="italic">almost
                        froze</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">feavourish</hi>, or accidentally <hi
                        rend="italic">sees the Sun</hi>, &amp;c. he may escape the <ref
                        corresp="imputation" target="imputation_">Imputation</ref> of being <hi
                        rend="italic">drunk</hi>, when his Misfortune comes to be related. I am Sir,
                    Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head> September 24, 1722 [No. 13] To the Author of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >New-England Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>In Persons of a contemplative Disposition, the most indifferent Things provoke
                    the Exercise of the Imagination; and the Satisfactions which often arise to them
                    thereby, are a certain Relief to the Labour of the Mind (when it has been
                    intensely fix'd on more substantial Subjects) as well as to that of the
                    Body.</p>
                <p>In one of the late pleasant Moon-light Evenings, I so far indulg'd in my self the
                    Humour of the Town in walking abroad, as to continue from my Lodgings two or
                    three Hours later than usual, and was pleas'd beyond Expectation before my
                    Return. Here I found various Company to observe, and various Discourse to attend
                    to. I met indeed with the common Fate of <hi rend="italic">Listeners</hi>, (who
                        <hi rend="italic">hear no good of themselves</hi>,) but from a Consciousness
                    of my Innocence, receiv'd it with a Satisfaction beyond what the Love of
                    Flattery and the <ref corresp="daubing" target="daubing_">Daubings</ref> of a
                    Parasite could produce. The Company who rally'd me were about Twenty in Number,
                    of both Sexes; and tho' the <hi rend="italic">Confusion of Tongues</hi> (like
                    that of Babel) which always happens among so many <ref corresp="impetuous"
                        target="impetuous_">impetuous</ref> Talkers, render'd their Discourse not so
                    intelligible as I could wish, I learnt thus much, That one of the Females
                    pretended to know me, from some Discourse she had heard at a certain House
                    before the Publication of one of my Letters; adding, <hi rend="italic">That I
                        was a Person of an ill Character, and kept a criminal Correspondence with a
                        Gentleman who assisted me in Writing</hi>. One of the <ref
                        corresp="gallant2" target="gallant2_">Gallants</ref> clear'd me of this
                    random Charge, by saying, <hi rend="italic">That tho' I wrote in the Character
                        of a Woman, he knew me to be a Man; But</hi>, continu'd he, <hi
                        rend="italic">he has more need of endeavouring a Reformation in himself,
                        than spending his Wit in satyrizing others</hi>.</p>
                <p>I had no sooner left this Set of <ref corresp="rambler" target="rambler_"
                        >Ramblers</ref>, but I met a Crowd of <ref corresp="tarpolins"
                        target="tarpolins_"><hi rend="italic">Tarpolins</hi></ref> and their <ref
                        corresp="doxies" target="doxies_">Doxies</ref>, link'd to each other by the
                    Arms, who ran (by their own Account) after the Rate of <ref corresp="knot"
                        target="knot_"><hi rend="italic">Six Knots an Hour</hi></ref>, and bent
                    their Course towards the Common. Their eager and amorous Emotions of Body,
                    occasion'd by taking their Mistresses <hi rend="italic">in Tow</hi>, they call'd
                        <hi rend="italic">wild <ref corresp="steerage" target="steerage_"
                            >Steerage</ref></hi>: And as a Pair of them happen'd to trip and come to
                    the Ground, the Company were call'd upon to <hi rend="italic">bring to</hi>, for
                    that Jack and Betty were <hi rend="italic">founder'd</hi>. But this Fleet were
                    not less comical or irregular in their Progress than a Company of Females I soon
                    after came up with, who, by throwing their Heads to the Right and Left, at every
                    one who pass'd by them, I concluded came out with no other Design than to revive
                    the Spirit of Love in Disappointed Batchelors, and expose themselves to Sale to
                    the first Bidder.</p>
                <p>But it would take up too much Room in your Paper to mention all the Occasions of
                    Diversion I met with in this Night's <ref corresp="ramble" target="ramble_"
                        >Ramble</ref>. As it grew later, I observed, that many pensive Youths with
                    down Looks and a slow Pace, would be ever now and then crying out on the Cruelty
                    of their Mistresses; others with a more rapid Pace and chearful Air, would be
                    swinging their Canes and clapping their Cheeks, and whispering at certain
                    Intervals, <hi rend="italic">I'm certain I shall have her! This is more than I
                        expected! How charmingly she talks!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole I conclude, That our <hi rend="italic">Night-Walkers</hi> are a
                    Set of People, who contribute very much to the Health and Satisfaction of those
                    who have been fatigu'd with Business or Study, and occasionally observe their
                    pretty Gestures and <ref corresp="impertinence3" target="impertinence3_"
                        >Impertinencies</ref>. But among Men of Business, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Shoemakers</hi>, and other Dealers in Leather, are doubly oblig'd to them,
                    inasmuch as they exceedingly promote the Consumption of their Ware: And I have
                    heard of a <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker</hi>, who being ask'd by a noted Rambler,
                        <hi rend="italic">Whether he could tell how long her Shoes would last</hi>;
                    very prettily answer'd, <hi rend="italic">That he knew how many Days she might
                        wear them, but not how many Nights; because they were then put to a more
                        violent and irregular Service than when she employ'd her self in the common
                        Affairs of the House</hi>. I am, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head> October 8, 1722 [No. 14] <ref corresp="cicerotrans3" target="cicerotrans3_"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Earum causarum quantum quaeque valeat, videamus</hi>.
                        Cicero</ref>. To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England
                        Courant</hi>. </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It often happens, that the most zealous Advocates for any Cause find themselves
                    disappointed in the first Appearance of Success in the Propagation of their
                    Opinion; and the Disappointment appears unavoidable, when their easy <ref
                        corresp="proselyte" target="proselyte_">Proselytes</ref> too suddenly start
                    into Extreams, and are immediately fill'd with Arguments to invalidate their
                    former Practice. This creates a Suspicion in the more considerate Part of
                    Mankind, that those who are thus <hi rend="italic">given to Change</hi>, neither
                        <hi rend="italic">fear God</hi>, nor <hi rend="italic">honour the King</hi>.
                    In Matters of Religion, he that alters his Opinion on a <hi rend="italic"
                        >religious Account</hi>, must certainly go thro' much Reading, hear many
                    Arguments on both Sides, and undergo many Struggles in his Conscience, before he
                    can come to a full Resolution: Secular Interest will indeed make quick Work with
                    an immoral Man, especially if, notwithstanding the Alteration of his Opinion, he
                    can with any Appearance of Credit retain his Immorality. But, by this Turn of
                    Thought I would not be suspected of Uncharitableness to those Clergymen at
                    Connecticut, who have lately embrac'd the Establish'd Religion of our Nation,
                    some of whom I hear made their Professions with a Seriousness becoming their
                    Order: However, since they have deny'd the Validity of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ordination</hi> by the Hands of <hi rend="italic">Presbyters</hi>, and
                    consequently their Power of Administring the <hi rend="italic">Sacraments</hi>,
                    &amp;c. we may justly expect a suitable Manifestation of their Repentance for
                    invading the <hi rend="italic">Priests</hi> Office, and living so long in a <ref
                        corresp="corah" target="corah_">Corah-like</ref> Rebellion. All I would
                    endeavour to shew is, That an indiscreet Zeal for spreading an Opinion, hurts
                    the Cause of the Zealot. There are too many blind Zealots among every
                    Denomination of Christians; and he that propagates the Gospel among <ref
                        corresp="rake" target="rake_"><hi rend="italic">Rakes</hi></ref> and <ref
                        corresp="beau" target="beau_"><hi rend="italic">Beaus</hi></ref> without
                    reforming them in their Morals, is every whit as ridiculous and impolitick as a
                    Statesman who makes Tools of Ideots and <ref corresp="gossip" target="gossip_"
                        >Tale-Bearers</ref>.</p>
                <p>Much to my present Purpose are the Words of two Ingenious Authors of the Church
                    of England, tho' in all Probability they were tainted with <ref
                        corresp="whiggish" target="whiggish_">Whiggish</ref> Principles; and with
                    these I shall conclude this Letter.</p>
                <p>"I would (says one) have every zealous Man examine his Heart thoroughly, and, I
                    believe, he will often find that what he calls a Zeal for his Religion, is
                    either Pride, Interest or Ill-nature. A Man who differs from another in Opinion
                    sets himself above him in his own Judgment, and in several Particulars pretends
                    to be the wiser Person. This is a great Provocation to the Proud Man, and gives
                    a keen Edge to what he calls his Zeal. And that this is the Case very often, we
                    may observe from the Behaviour of some of the most Zealous for Orthodoxy, who
                    have often great Friendships and Intimacies with vicious immoral Men, provided
                    they do but agree with them in the same Scheme of Belief. The Reason is, because
                    the vicious Believer gives the Precedency to the virtuous Man, and allows the
                    good Christian to be the worthier Person, at the same Time that he cannot come
                    up to his Perfections. This we find exemplified in that trite Passage which we
                    see quoted in almost every System of Ethicks, tho' upon another Occasion;</p>

                <p>
                    <ref corresp="ovidtrans" target="ovidtrans_"><lg>
                            <l>--Video meliore proboque</l>
                            <l>Deteriora sequor--</l>
                        </lg>
                    </ref></p>

                <p>On the contrary, it is certain if our Zeal were true and genuine, we should be
                    much more angry with a Sinner than a <ref corresp="heretic" target="heretic_"
                        >Heretick</ref>, since there are several Cases which may excuse the latter
                    before his great Judge, but none which can excuse the former."</p>
                <p>"I have (says another) found by Experience, that it is impossible to talk
                    distinctly without defining the Words of which we make use. There is not a Term
                    in our Language which wants Explanation so much as the Word <hi rend="italic"
                        >Church</hi>. One would think when People utter it, they should have in
                    their Minds Ideas of Virtue and Religion; but that important Monosyllable drags
                    all the other Words in the Language after it, and it is made use of to express
                    both Praise and Blame, according to the Character of him who speaks it. By this
                    means it happens, that no one knows what his Neighbour means when he says such a
                    one is for or against the Church. It has happen'd that he who is seen every Day
                    at Church, has not been counted in the Eye of the World a Churchman; and he who
                    is very zealous to oblige every one to frequent it but himself, has been a very
                    good Son of the Church. This <ref corresp="Praepossession"
                        target="Praepossession_">Praepossession</ref> is the best Handle imaginable
                    for Politicians to make use of, for managing the Loves and Hatreds of Mankind to
                    the Purposes to which they would lead them. But this is not a Thing for Fools to
                    meddle with, for they only bring <ref corresp="disesteem" target="disesteem_"
                        >Disesteem</ref> upon those whom they attempt to serve, when they
                    unskilfully pronounce Terms of Art. I have observed great Evils arise from this
                    Practice, and not only the Cause of Piety, but also the secular Interest of
                    Clergymen, has extreamly suffered by the general unexplained Signification of
                    the Word <hi rend="italic">Church</hi>." I am, Sir, Your Humble Servant.</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>


            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <note xml:id="fortnight" target="fortnight_" type="editorial"><p>Fourteen nights or
                        two weeks. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="epistle" target="epistle_" type="editorial"><p>Letter. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="dispraise" target="dispraise_" type="editorial"><p>The opposite of
                        praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="leatherapron" target="leatherapron_" type="editorial"><p>A working
                        class man, what might later be called a blue-collar worker.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="etc" target="etc_" type="editorial"><p>An abbreviation for et cetera.
                        Source: Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="whether" target="whether_" type="editorial" resp="editors.xml#AJB"
                        ><p>An early form of "whether or not."</p></note>

                <note xml:id="lucubrations" target="lucubrations_" type="editorial"
                        ><p>"Lucubrations" are writings produced by candle-light; so, these would be
                        essays written alone at night after a day's work. The word itself already
                        sounded a bit pompous in the early eighteenth century, so the speaker is to
                        some degree making fun of herself.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="nengland" target="nengland_" type="editorial"><p>New
                    England</p></note>

                <note xml:id="disconsolate" target="disconsolate_" type="editorial"><p>Inconsolable,
                        despondent. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="apprentice" target="apprentice_" type="editorial"><p>Young women were
                        sometimes bound as apprentices, usually in trades that were traditionally
                        gendered female (like weaving), but the vast majority of apprentices in this
                        era were young men. At the time of this writing, Franklin was
                        serving an apprenticeship in the printshop of his older brother James.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="indigent" target="indigent_" type="editorial"><p>Poor, destitute.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="literacy" target="literacy_" type="editorial"><p>Trying to determine
                        how many people in colonial America could read in the early eighteenth
                        century is an enormous challenge. The evidence is scanty and fragmentary. The best evidence, though, would suggest that literacy
                        rates among English settler-colonists would have been highest in New England, because of the history of
                        Puritanism in the colony. Puritans had long prized the ability fpr individuals to
                        read the Bible on their own, and literacy was correspondingly comparatively high in places where Puritanism dominated.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="discretion" target="discretion_" type="editorial"><p>The time in a
                        person's life when they are presumed to be able to make sound judgements.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="were" target="were_" type="editorial"><p>That is, "where".</p></note>

                <note xml:id="genesis" target="genesis_" type="editorial"><p>"And the Lord God said,
                        It is not good that the man should be alone: I will make him an help meet
                        for him." King James Bible, Genesis 2:18</p></note>

                <note xml:id="topsex" target="topsex_" type="editorial"><p>That is, upper-class
                        women, who were probably socially more highly ranked than a country
                        clergyman could expect to marry.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="meridian" target="meridian_" type="editorial"><p>That is, when I was
                        in the prime of life.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="thisworld" target="thisworld_" type="editorial"><p>That is, this
                        world.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="indefatigably" target="indefatigably_" type="editorial"><p>Tirelessly.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="peacemeal" target="peacemeal_" type="editorial"><p>Piece by piece, or
                        in small bits. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="mollify" target="mollify_" type="editorial"><p>Soften; make tender.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="reproof" target="reproof_" type="editorial"><p>Censures or Rebukes;
                        subject to blame or scorn. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cicerotrans" target="cicerotrans_" type="editorial"><p>"Should I be
                        taught to speak either Greek or Latin?" Franklin is quoting here from the
                        Roman orator Cicero. The essay that follows, taking the form of a dream
                        vision, is a satire on Harvard College and its requirement that students
                        study Greek and Latin.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="seminary" target="seminary_" type="editorial"><p>A place of education
                        such as a school or a college. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="verdant" target="verdant_" type="editorial"><p>Green; of vegetation.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="porter" target="porter_" type="editorial"><p>Gatekeepers. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionoary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="spectator" target="spectator_" type="editorial"><p>A nod to the series
                        of periodical essays, The Spectator, which Franklin used as a model for his
                        Silence Dogood letters.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="docible" target="docible_" type="editorial"><p>Ready to be taught;
                        submissive to instruction. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="nigh" target="nigh_" type="editorial"><p>Near or almost. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="fain" target="fain_" type="editorial"><p>Happy, please. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cake" target="cake_" type="editorial"><p>A fruitcake packed full of
                        different types of candied and dried fruits such as plums, raisins, and
                        orange peel. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="lubber" target="lubber_" type="editorial"><p>A large clumsy idiot who
                        is often lazy and idle. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="merch" target="merch_" type="editorial"><p>Engaged in the selling and
                        trade of goods. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="patrimony" target="patriony_" type="editorial"><p>Property that, by
                        ancient right, belongs to an institution. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="churchmice" target="churchmice_" type="editorial"><p>The expression
                        "church mice" is used to describe people who are poor and quiet. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="theology" target="theology_" type="editorial"><p>The Study of God, and
                        God's relations with man and the universe. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="pecunia" target="pecunia_" type="editorial"><p>Latin for money or
                        wealth.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="plagius" target="plagius_" type="editorial"><p>A personification of
                        plagiarism, here referring to clerics stealing from the sermons of more
                        established ministers.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="tillotson" target="tillotson_" type="editorial"><p>John Tillotson was
                        the Archbishop of Canterbury in late seventeenth century.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="genteel" target="genteel_" type="editorial"><p>In the manner of the
                        gentry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="terencetrans" target="terencetrans_" type="editorial"><p>"One woman
                        agrees the most with another." The line is from the Roman playwright
                        Terence.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="satyr" target="satyr_" type="editorial"><p>A form of writing that mocks or ridicules something. The word actually comes from the Latin word "satura," meaning a full plate of varied foods. But the spelling "satyr" derives from a false etymology, which imagined that the term came from the Greek word for a mythological demon that was often depicted as a half-human, half-goat creature. The demon is generally a
representation of lust and rage. For this reason, "satire" was often been associated with writing that was fierce and agressive. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="maleenormity" target="maleenormity_" type="editorial"><p>Deviation in
                        behavior, often from moral or legal normality. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="ephraim" target="ephraim_" type="editorial"><p>Ephraim: The second son
                        of Joseph and Asenath, as shown by Book of Genesis. The name Ephraim became
                        related to the idea of "being fruitful." Censorious: one who gives constant
                        censure and finds faults. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and
                        Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="reprove" target="reprove_" type="editorial"><p>Rebuke; express
                        disapproval. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="quaere" target="quaere_" type="edditorial"><p>To question or query.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="votary" target="votary_" type="editorial"><p>People bound to a
                        religious life or a certain vow. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="pomp" target="pomp_" type="editorial"><p>Ostentatious display;
                        boastful, prideful with a negative connotation. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="reproach" target="reproach_" type="editorial"><p>Scolds or censures.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="conversible" target="conversible_" type="editorial"><p>Capable of
                        being converted. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="baubles" target="baubles_" type="editorial"><p>A showy trinket that's
                        of little worth, often made for children to play with. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="impertinence" target="impertinence_" type="editorial"><p>Irrelevance.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="upbraid" target="upbraid_" type="editorial"><p>Censure</p></note>

                <note xml:id="swain" target="swain_" type="editorial"><p>An innocent, rose-coloured
                        country lover, such as one found in pastoral poetry. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="nymph" target="nymph_" type="editorial"><p>A woman or lover with
                        sexual power or magic over a man. Coming from mythology, nymphs are spirits
                        that take the form of women who, similarly to sirens, were said to charm men
                        and lead them to sin or death. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="credulous" target="credulous" type="editorial"><p>Ready or willing.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="exhort" target="exhort_" type="editorial"><p>To urge earnestly.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="culpable" target="culpable_" type="editorial"><p>Guilty. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="tarry" target="tarry_" type="editorial"><p>To linger or stay. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="senecatrans" target="senecatrans_" type="editorial"><p>"A man who
                        stands proudly at the start of the day is flattened by its end." Franklin is
                        quoting here from the Roman tragedian Seneca.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="soliloquy" target="soliloquy_" type="editorial"><p>A speech or talk
                        given alone or aloud without addressing any person. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>
                <note xml:id="penny" target="penny_">Expensive, probably imported fabric, as opposed to cloth made inexpensively at home.</note>

                <note xml:id="begot" target="begot_"><p>Has given rise to. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="portend" target="portend_" type="editorial"><p>Fortells as an omen or
                        other supernatural means. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="evince" target="evince_" type="editorial"><p>To overcome. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="hoop" target="hoop_" type="editorial">An undergarment, more commonly
                    known as a hoop skirt, that is worn underneath a womans skirt. The skirt is
                    constructed with rigid hoops that flare out and grow larger as one travels
                    downward from the top of the skirt so as to give a domed shape to the bottom of
                    a dress. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>

                <note xml:id="incommoded" target="incommoded_" type="editorial"><p>Subjected to
                        inconveience; troubled. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="mortar" target="mortar_" type="editorial"><p>A mortar is a hard-walled
                        bowl that is used to grind things with a pestle. Here Franklin is saying the
                        hoop-skirts are like thick, over-turned bowls. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="noddles" target="noddles_" type="editorial"><p>Historically one of
                        Boston Harbor Islands, that has now been reconnected to the mainland by
                        filling the strait that used to separate it from the mainland. Noddle's
                        Island now makes up the southern part of the East Boston
                    neighborhood.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="watts" target="watts_" type="editorial"><p>Having used Latin
                        quotations for his epigraphs to this point, Franklin here switches to a
                        contemporary poem, drawing an extract from a 1709 poem called "The
                        Adventurous Muse" by the English poet Isaac Watts.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="encomium" target="encomium_" type="editorial"><p>Grand expression of
                        praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="appellation" target="appellation_" type="editorial"><p>Calling of
                        Names. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="rapin" target="rapin_" type="editorial"><p>Rene Rapin (1621-1687) was
                        a French cleric, poet, and critic, whose essays on poetry gave "rules" on
                        composition.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="purcell" target="purcell_"><p>Henry Purcell (1669-1695) was considered
                        to be the greatest English composer of the era. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="greekstyle" target="greekstyle_" type="editorial"><p>A series of
                        common poetical styles of the time. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="kitelic" target="kitelic_" type="editorial"><p>That is, a new genre
                        based on this poem about Mehitabel Kitel.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="subjoin" target="subjoin_" type="editorial"><p>Add to the end of a
                        statement. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="receipt" target="receipt_" type="editorial"><p>Recipe</p></note>

                <note xml:id="aetatis" target="aetatis_" type="editorial">
                    <p>Latin: "Of his or her age"</p></note>

                <note xml:id="scull" target="scull_" type="editorial"><p>Skull</p></note>

                <note xml:id="moestus" target="moestus" type="editorial"><p>Latin: "a mourner
                        composed it"</p></note>

                <note xml:id="notabene" target="notabene_" type="editorial"><p>"N.B." is used to
                        signify something important in a text; "note well." Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="hypercarpus" target="hypercarpus_" type="editorial"><p>"Dogood" is
                        responding to a piece in the June 18th issue of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Courant</hi> by a writer who went by the pseudonym "Hypercarpus,"
                        (something like "great complainer"). There, Hypercarpus had complained that
                        Dogood's claim in her sixth letter that wearing elaborate clothing like hoop
                        skirts was making women proud had it backwards--that the pride came first,
                        and then wearing skirts was simply an expression of it. It's an argument
                        about cause and effect; Hypercarpus thinks that vanity causes people to try
                        to distinguish themselves in the world with clothing; Dogood argues that the
                        clothing leads to vanity. </p><p>Dogood's last word here is a Latin tag that
                        responds to the criticism with a kind of a riddle that describes cause and
                        effect as an infinite loop, sort of like the question of which comes first,
                        a chicken or an egg: a woman gives birth to a daughter, who in turn gives
                        birth to a woman who herself becomes a mother. A cause becomes an effect
                        that in turn becomes a cause.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="mater" target="mater_" type="editorial"><p>Latin: "My mother gave
                        birth to me, and then a daughter gave birth to a mother."</p></note>

                <note xml:id="charles" target="charles_" type="editorial"><p>Charles I of England
                        reigned from 1625-1649 until his execution. Charles I was defeated in the
                        English Civil War and was eventually beheaded by Oliver Cromwell's army
                        after being found guilty of high treason. Source: Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="disaffection" target="disaffection_" type="editorial"><p>Hostility or
                        animosity. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="sedition" target="sedition_" type="editorial"><p>Mutiny or rebellion.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="james" target="james_" type="editorial"><p>James II (1633-1701) became
                        king upon the death of his brother, Charles II. During his short reign, he
                        made it clear that he intended to return the country to Roman Catholicism,
                        prompting his removal by Parliament in 1688 and replacement by William and
                        Mary.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="papist" target="papist" type="editorial"><p>A Roman Catholic. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionoary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="charlesii" target="charlesii_" type="editorial"><p>After Oliver
                        Cromwell's death in 1658 the monarchy was restored with Charles II in 1660.
                        Although he restored the Church of England, he secretly and increasingly
                        became sympathatic to Roman Catholicism. Source: Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="felicity" target="felicity_" type="editorial"><p>Happiness. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="audivit" target="audivit_" type="editorial"><p>Latin: "Tiberius heard
                        reproaches that wounded and upset him." The quote is from the Roman poet
                        Tacitus, but Franklin is almost certainly lifting it from the London
                        periodical entitled <hi rend="italic">Cato's Letters</hi>, a series of
                        political essays published by John Trenchard and Thomas Gordon, who put this
                        quote in the issue 15, February 15, 1721. The series was widely read
                        throughout the British colonial world.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="valerius" target="valerius_" type="editorial"><p>Marcus Valerius
                        Volusus was a consul of the Roman Republic in 505 BC.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cincinnatus" target="cincinnatus_" type="editorial"><p>Roman senator
                        remembered for his public virtue.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="diadem" target="diadem_" type="editorial"><p>A crown. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cognomen" target="cognomen_" type="editorial"><p>Latin: "friend of the
                        people"</p></note>

                <note xml:id="livytrans" target="livytrans_" type="editorial"><p>Franklin is again
                        lifting a Latin quotation from <hi rend="italic">Cato's Letters</hi>, number
                        15, which is here citing a line from the Roman historian Livy: "Laws were
                        proposed, the first of them an appeal from the people to the
                        government."</p></note>

                <note xml:id="plinytrans" target="plinytrans_" type="editorial"><p>Once again
                        Franklin is lifting from <hi rend="italic">Cato's Letters</hi> issue 15,
                        which cites this alleged Latin quotation: "We may well complain that only
                        those leaders who inquire into our secrets are those we hate."</p></note>

                <note xml:id="tacitus" target="tacitus_"><p>Roman historian.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="edwardii" target="edwardii_" type="editorial"><p>Edward II of England
                        reigned from 1284-1327. He was forced to abdicate the throne after losing
                        power, being betrayed by his own wife Isabella, the daughter of King Philip
                        IV of France. Source: Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="walsingham" target="walsingham_" type="editorial"><p>Francis
                        Walsingham was principal secretary to Queen Elizabeth I of England. He was
                        famously known as her 'spymaster,' a man who used gathered intelligence from
                        across Europe to disrupt attempts on the Queen's life, penetrated the
                        Spanish Military, and secured the Execution of Mary, Queen of Scots. Source:
                        Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="knavish" target="knavish_"><p>Vulgar or villainous; mischievous.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="pernicious" target="pernicious_"><p>Wicked, intending harm. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="corruptio" target="corruptio_" type="editorial"><p>"The corruption of
                        the best is the worst." This is a proverbial Latin expression.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="profane" target="profane_" type="editorial">(draft-Does he mean
                    'atheist" by this?)</note>

                <note xml:id="artifice" target="artifice_" type="editorial"><p>Trickery, deceit.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="trumpeters" target="trumpeters" type="editorial"><p>Metaphorically one
                        who praises and advocates for. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="colour" target="colour_" type="editorial"><p>The apparent or de facto
                        authority, as opposed to the actual authority established. Frequently said
                        with negative connotations, suggesting that the authority is just a pretext
                        for corrupt behavior. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="encomium2" target="encomium2_" type="editorial"><p>High-flown
                        expressions of praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="indignation" target="indignation_" type="editorial"><p>Disdain or
                        contempt. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="chancel" target="chancel_" type="editorial"><p>The section of a church
                        that is used by the offiates, such as the clergy or a priest, during their
                        performance of the services of the church. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="knave" target="knave_" type="editorial"><p>A dishonest or villainous
                        man. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cicerotrans2" target="cicerotrans2_" type="editorial"><p>"The society
                        of men will best be preserved." Again, Franklin cites the Roman orator
                        Cicero.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="artificer" target="artificer_" type="editorial"><p>Artisans or
                        craftsmen. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="portion" target="portion_" type="editorial"><p>A fair amount of money
                        given as a dowry or a gift to the husband along with the wife upon marriage.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="jointure" target="jointure_" type="editorial"><p>An estate for the
                        wife to be used upon the death of the husband. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="mint" target="mint_" type="editorial"><p>A place where money is
                        coined, usually under the authority of a government. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="fryar" target="fryar_" type="editorial"><p>The quarters of a certain
                        religious order. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="britcash" target="britcash_" type="editorial"><p>£sd, known as
                        "pounds, shillings, and pence" is the name for the pre-decimal currency
                        system common in the British Empire. In the system there are twelve pence in
                        a shilling twenty shilling in a pound. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and
                        Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="bonafide" target="bonafide_" type="editorial"><p>In good faith.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="forswear" target="forswear_" type="editorial"><p>To renounce or
                        abandon forever. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="defraud" target="defraud_" type="editorial"><p>To deprive someone what
                        is rightfully theirs with fraud. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="infirm" target="infirm_" type="editorial"><p>Weak, feeble, or sick.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="distemper" target="distemper_" type="editorial"><p>Illness or
                        disorder. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="quarteridge" target="quarteride_" type="editorial"><p>Payment made
                        quarterly. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="perannum" target="perannum_" type="editorial"><p>'Per year.' Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="violenti" target="violenti_" type="editorial"><p>A common law doctrine
                        which states that is one willingly puts themselves in a place where harm may
                        occur, knowing that harm may occur, then they are unable to bring a claim
                        against the other party. More shortly: To a willing person, injury is not
                        done. Source: Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="temporal" target="temporal_" type="editorial"><p>Temporary. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="unknownlatin" target="unknownlatin_">"And in the meantime it is not legal to see my friend." Franklin is quoting the Roman playwright Plautus.</note>

                <note xml:id="sic" target="sic_" type="editorial"><p>A parenthetical insertion used
                        to call attention to something anomalous in the original work. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="gallant" target="gallant_" type="editorial"><p>Fine gentlemen. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="fiftylb" target="fiftylb_" type="editorial"><p>That would have been a
                        lot of money. You could live on fifty pounds a year.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="penitent" target="penitent_" type="editorial"><p>That repents with
                        sincere desire to amend the sin. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="taciturn" target="taciturn_" type="editorial"><p>Habitual silence or
                        reservedness in speech. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="encomium3" target="encomium3_" type="editorial"><p>High-flown
                        expressions of praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cordi" target="cordi_" type="editorial"><p>Whatever is in the heart of
                        the sober person, is in the mouth of the drunkard.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="bacchus" target="bacchus_" type="editorial"><p>The Roman god of wine.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="claret" target="claret_" type="editorial"><p>A red wine. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="extempore" target="extempore_" type="editorial"><p>Of the moment,
                        without preparation or premeditation. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="edging" target="edging_" type="editorial"><p>A petticoat is an
                        underskirt worn underneath a gown that is given a decorative bottom edge for
                        in case the dress is ever lifted and the petticoat is shown. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionoary and Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="chide" target="chide_" type="editorial"><p>To scold. Source: Oxford
                        English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="voluptuary" target="voluptuary_" type="editorial"><p>of or pertaining
                        to sensuous or luxurious pleasures.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="palled" target="palled_" type="editorial"><p>Weakened or impaired.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="impertinence2" target="impertinence2_" type="editorial"
                        ><p>Irrelevance. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="rakish" target="rakish_" type="editorial"><p>Immoral or promiscuous.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="profligate" target="profligate_" type="editorial"><p>Reckless,
                        extravagant, and wasteful. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="affront" target="affront_" type="editorial"><p>To insult deliberately.
                        Source: Oxforod English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="wetting" target="wetting_" type="editorial"><p>Here the phrase is
                        being used to mean: when drunk or inebriated. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="vivifying" target="vivifying_" type="editorial"><p>Life-giving or
                        animating in a physical and/or mental manner. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="drunk" target="drunk_" type="editorial"><p>Here Franklin is giving a
                        list of euphemistic ways drunkards will describe themselves to avoid using
                        the negatively connotated word "drunk."</p></note>

                <note xml:id="tipler" target="tipler_" type="editorial"><p>A habitual drinker; a
                        drunk. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="imputation" target="imputation_" type="editorial"><p>The attribution
                        or assignment of a fault or crime. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="daubing" target="daubing_" type="editorial"><p>Covers or coats.
                        Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="impetuous" target="impetuous_" type="editorial"><p>Characterized by
                        rapid, forceful, and/or violent motion. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="gallant2" target="gallant2_" type="editorial"><p>Fine, brave
                        gentlemen. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="rambler" target="rambler_" type="editorial"><p>Ones who are
                        recreationally out walking or wandering. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="tarpolins" target="tarpolins_" type="editorial">A slang term for
                    seamen or sailors. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>

                <note xml:id="doxies" target="doxies_" type="editorial"><p>Unmarried mistresses;
                        prostitutes. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="knot" target="knot_" type="editorial"><p>Here a knot stands in for a
                        nautical mile. A nautical mile is equal to 1.15 miles, thus six knots an
                        hour is equivalent to about seven miles in an hour. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="steerage" target="steerage_" type="editorial"><p>The action of
                        steering something such as a boat, ship, or airship. Here Franklin is most
                        likely using a play on words to show how the seamen brought their women
                        around. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="ramble" target="ramble_" type="editorial"><p>Aimless wandering for
                        recreation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="impertinence3" target="impertinence3" type="editorial"
                        ><p>Irrelevancies, trivialities. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="cicerotrans3" target="cicerotrans3_" type="editorial">"Let us see how much each of these causes is worth." from the Latin orator Cicero</note>

                <note xml:id="proselyte" target="proselyte_" type="editorial"><p>Converts. Source:
                        Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="corah" target="corah_" type="editorial"><p>Korah led a revolt against
                        Moses and his brother Aaron, as recounted in the book of Numbers. Such a
                        rebellion, that is, goes against the leaders of the established
                    faith.</p></note>

                <note xml:id="rake" target="rake_" type="editorial"><p>Immoral or promiscuous
                        people. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="beau" target="beau_" type="editorial"><p>The suitors of ladies.
                        Source: Oxford English dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="gossip" target="gossip_" type="editorial"><p>One who gossips or
                        blackmails. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="whiggish" target="whiggish_" type="editorial"><p>The Whig party was a
                        political faction in the British Empire, opposed by the rival faction: the
                        Tory Party. The origin of the Whigs lay in constitutional monarchism as
                        opposed to absolute monarchy. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and
                        Wikipedia</p></note>

                <note xml:id="ovidtrans" target="ovidtrans_" type="editorial"><p>"I see a better
                        thing and approve of it, but I follow something worse." from Ovid's <hi
                            rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi></p></note>

                <note xml:id="heretic" target="heretic_" type="editorial"><p>Anyone who has
                        religious opinions or practices that don't fall in line with the Catholic or
                        orthodox doctrine of the Christian Church. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="Praepossession" target="Praepossession_" type="editorial"
                        ><p>Prepossession: having take possession beforehand. Source: Oxford English
                        Dictionary</p></note>

                <note xml:id="disesteem" target="disesteem_" type="editorial"><p>Disregard, low
                        esteem, and/or low expectations. Source: Oxford English
                    Dictionary</p></note>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>

</TEI>
