<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="franklin-dogood-6">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Silence Dogood 6</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <date when="1722">April 2, 1722</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <title type="sub">6</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    June 11, 1722 [No. 6] <lb/><lb/><lb/>
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi>Quem Dies videt veniens Superbum, Hunc Dies vidit fugiens jacentem.</hi> Seneca.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"A man who stands proudly at the start of the day is flattened by its end." Franklin is quoting here from the Roman tragedian Seneca.</note> <lb/><lb/>
                    To the Author of the <hi>New-England Courant</hi>.<lb/><lb/><lb/>
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Among the many reigning Vices of the Town which may at any Time come under my Consideration and Reprehension, there is none which I am more inclin'd to expose than that of <hi>Pride</hi>. It is acknowledg'd by all to be a Vice the most hateful to God and Man. Even those who nourish it in themselves, hate to see it in others. The proud Man aspires after Nothing less than an unlimited Superiority over his Fellow-Creatures. He has made himself a King in <hi>Soliloquy</hi>S; fancies himself conquering the World; and the Inhabitants thereof consulting on proper Methods to acknowledge his Merit. I speak it to my Shame, I my self was a Queen from the Fourteenth to the Eighteenth Year of my Age, and govern'd the World all the Time of my being govern'd by my Master. But this speculative Pride may be the Subject of another Letter: I shall at present confine my Thoughts to what we call <hi>Pride of Apparel</hi>. This Sort of Pride has been growing upon us ever since we parted with our Homespun Cloaths for <hi>Fourteen Penny Stuffs</hi>, &amp;c. And the <hi>Pride of Apparel</hi> has begot and nourish'd in us a <hi>Pride of Heart</hi>, which portends the Ruin of Church and State. <hi>Pride goeth before Destruction, and a haughty Spirit before a Fall</hi>: And I remember my late Reverend Husband would often say upon this Text, That a Fall was the <hi>natural Consequence</hi>, as well as <hi>Punishment</hi> of Pride. Daily Experience is sufficient to evince the Truth of this Observation. Persons of small Fortune under the Dominion of this Vice, seldom consider their Inability to maintain themselves in it, but strive to imitate their Superiors in Estate, or Equals in Folly, until one Misfortune comes upon the Neck of another, and every Step they take is a Step backwards. By striving to appear rich they become really poor, and deprive themselves of that Pity and Charity which is due to the humble poor Man, who is made so more immediately by Providence.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>This Pride of Apparel will appear the more foolish, if we consider, that those airy Mortals, who have no other Way of making themselves considerable but by gorgeous Apparel, draw after them Crowds of Imitators, who hate each other while they endeavour after a Similitude of Manners. They destroy by Example, and envy one another's Destruction.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I cannot dismiss this Subject without some Observations on a particular Fashion now reigning among my own Sex, the most immodest and inconvenient of any the Art of Woman has invented, namely, that of <hi>Hoop-Petticoats</hi>. By these they are incommoded in their General and Particular Calling, and therefore they cannot answer the Ends of either necessary or ornamental Apparel. These monstrous topsy-turvy <hi>Mortar-Pieces</hi>, are neither fit for the Church, the Hall, or the Kitchen; and if a Number of them were well mounted on Noddles-Island, they would look more like Engines of War for bombarding the Town, than Ornaments of the Fair Sex. An honest Neighbour of mine, happening to be in Town some time since on a publick Day, inform'd me, that he saw four Gentlewomen with their Hoops half mounted in a Balcony, as they withdrew to the Wall, to the great Terror of the Militia, who (he thinks) might attribute their irregular Volleys to the formidable Appearance of the Ladies Petticoats.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I assure you, Sir, I have but little Hopes of perswading my Sex, by this Letter, utterly to relinquish the extravagant Foolery, and Indication of Immodesty, in this monstrous Garb of their's; but I would at least desire them to lessen the Circumference of their Hoops, and leave it with them to consider, Whether they, who pay no Rates or Taxes, ought to take up more Room in the King's High-Way, than the Men, who yearly contribute to the Support of the Government. I am, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p><lb/><lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>  
