<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="franklin-dogood">
    
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Silence Dogood Essays</title>
                
                <author>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-8-10" who="JOB"></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <front><div></div></front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                     The "Silence Dogood" Essays 
                </head>
                <p>Benjamin Franklin was sixteen years old and working as an apprentice in the Boston print shop of his older brother James when, in April 1722, he began writing a series of essays to be published in the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi> under the pseudonym of "Silence Dogood." In his <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, Benjamin remembered slipping these essays, written in disguised handwriting, under the door of the <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi>, which James was publishing; he assumed (probably correctly) that James would refuse to print an essay from him if he simply asked or submitted it under his own name. James published the essays, which became very popular among the newspaper's readers. Benjamin kept his authorship of the series a secret, even from his brother, until after he finished writing them in October 1722, at which point James printed an advertisement asking for "Silence Dogood" to come forth. Benjamin confessed that he was the author, which seems to have annoyed his older brother. It was not too long after that that Benjamin left his brother's shop--breaking his apprenticeship--and moved to Philadelphia.</p>
                <!-- Need link add to "autobiography" to Franklin Autobiography on our web-->
                <!-- Add picture -->
                <p>The Silence Dogood essays are written in the persona of a middle-aged woman, but the title character is very clearly indebted to Mr. Spectator, the avatar of Addison and Steele's <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> series, published a decade earlier; it is testimony to how widely influential the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> was that even in colonial America, teenaged boys were reading it and taking it as a model for their own writing. In the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>, Franklin remembers how much he loved the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, and how he first came across it at the age of sixteen: "<hi rend="italic">an odd volume of the Spectator fell into my hands. This was a publication I had never seen. I bought the volume, and read it again and again. I was enchanted with it, thought the style excellent, and wished it were in my power to imitate it. With this view I selected some of the papers, made short summaries of the ſenſe of each period, and put them for a few days aside. I then, without looking at the book, endeavoured to restore the essays to their true form, and to express each thought at length, as it was in the original, employing the most appropriate words that occurred to my mind. I afterwards compared my Spectator with the original; I perceived some faults, which I corrected</hi>." If the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> gave Franklin a model for his prose style, so too did it give him a persona to inhabit; the "Silence" in Silence Dogood's name clearly alludes to the taciturn Mr. Spectator invented by Addison and Steele. The surname "Dogood" also has a famous colonial writer in mind, in this case the prolific Boston cleric Cotton Mather, whose 1710 collection <hi rend="italic">Bonifacius: or, Essays to Do Good</hi>, advocating the reader to undertake charitable works, Franklin also remembered as a book that had a great impact on him as a young man. The startling thing about the Silence Dogood essays (in addition to the fact that they were written by a sixteen-year-old), is that Franklin adopts the persona of a woman, a persona that enables him adopt, but also gently mock, the kinds of sentiments expressed by authority figures like Mather. Franklin would continue to use personae, male and female, throughout his career, the most famous of these being the Poor Richard of his Almanack. And there's a sense in which the "Benjamin Franklin" of the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi> and of history was also a persona, a role that Franklin played on the public stage of the trans-Atlantic world.</p>
                <p>There were fourteen Silence Dogood essays in all, published every two weeks in the pages of the <hi rend="italic">New England Courant</hi>, for which, as we have seen, James Franklin was the publisher. The <hi rend="italic">New England Courant</hi> was the first independently-published newspaper in colonial America; that is, it operated independently of government authority. So much so that the colonial government in Massachusetts frequently attempted to censor the newspaper and jailed James Franklin several times when he published articles that were thought to defame public officials (Cotton Mather, for example). During these periods, Benjamin was listed as the official publisher of the newspaper. It was finally closed for good in 1726. Benjamin had long since moved on, and was at this point finishing a stint as a journeyman printer in London and preparing to return to Philadelphia, where he opened a print shop of his own.</p>
                <p>Our text is derived from the text at ushistory.org. To see the original pages of the New-England Courant in which the essays were published, go here.</p>
                <!-- Add link on "here"-->
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    April 2, 1722 [No. 1] 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. 
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It may not be improper in the first place to inform your Readers, that I intend once a <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Fortnight</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Fourteen nights or two weeks. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to present them, by the Help of this Paper, with a short <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Epistle</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Letter. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, which I presume will add somewhat to their Entertainment.</p>
                <p>And since it is observed, that the Generality of People, now a days, are unwilling either to commend or <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">dispraise</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">The opposite of praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> what they read, until they are in some measure informed who or what the Author of it is, whether he be <hi rend="italic">poor</hi> or <hi rend= "italic">rich</hi>, <hi rend="italic"> old</hi> or <hi rend="italic">young</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Schollar</hi> or a <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi rend="italic">Leather Apron Man</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">(DRAFT-DC)A working class man, blue-collar worker.</note>, <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">&amp;c</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">An abbreviation for et cetera. Source: Wikipedia</note>. and give their Opinion of the Performance, according to the Knowledge which they have of the Author's Circumstances, it may not be amiss to begin with a short Account of my past Life and present Condition, that the Reader may not be at a Loss to judge whether or <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">no</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">DRAFT-Is this supposed to read as "not"</note> my <note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Lucubrations</note><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">DRAFT</note> are worth his reading.</p>
                <p>At the time of my Birth, my Parents were on Ship-board in their Way from London to <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">N. England</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">DRAFT-I assume this is New-England; curious to see if this matches his biography (also just the story of his father-if not why include this detail-tragic backstory?)</note>. My Entrance into this troublesome World was attended with the Death of my Father, a Misfortune, which tho' I was not then capable of knowing, I shall never be able to forget; for as he, poor Man, stood upon the Deck rejoycing at my Birth, a merciless Wave entred the Ship, and in one Moment carry'd him beyond Reprieve. Thus, was the <hi rend="italic"> first Day</hi> which I saw, the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> that was seen by my Father; and thus was my <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">disconsolate</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Inconsolable, despondent. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Mother at once made both a <hi rend="italic">Parent</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Widow</hi>.</p>
                <p>When we arrived at Boston (which was not long after) <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">I was put to Nurse in a Country Place, at a small Distance from the Town, where I went to School, and past my Infancy and Childhood in Vanity and Idleness</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">DRAFT-Does this imply a boarding room situation, vaguely Jane Eyre esque</note>, until I was <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">bound out Apprentice</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">(DRAFT-When would women be sent out as an apprentice if ever? How long were women's apprenticeships)Colonial Williamsburg shows very few women as having apprenticeships, but general they were more for household work or textile trades such as knitting or weaving</note>, that I might no longer be a Charge to my <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Indigent</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">Poor, destitute. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Mother, who was put to hard Shifts for a Living.</p>
                <p>My Master was a <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Country Minister</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">DRAFT-detail the general job of a country minister(again maybe reference St. John in Jane Eyre)</note>, a pious good-natur'd young Man, and a Batchelor: he labour'd with all his Might to instil vertuous and godly Principles into my tender Soul, well knowing that it was the most suitable Time to make deep and lasting Impressions on the Mind, while it was yet untainted with Vice, free and unbiass'd. He endeavour'd that I might be instructed in <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">all that Knowledge and Learning which is necessary for our Sex</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">DRAFT-give a general detail/maybe a greater focus on the religious aspect.</note>, and deny'd me no Accomplishment that could possibly be attained in a Country Place; such as all Sorts of Needle-Work, Writing, <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Arithmetick</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">DRAFT-Would it be common for women to be taught math? Especially under a Country Minister</note>, &amp;c. and observing that I took a <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">more than ordinary Delight in reading ingenious Books</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">DRAFT-A general statistic on how many people (women more in particular if possible) actually knew how to read at this time</note>, he gave me the free Use of <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">his Library</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">DRAFT-Give an idea of some of the more popular works at the time that most people would have had</note>, which tho' it was but small, yet it was well chose, to inform the Understanding rightly, and enable the Mind to frame great and noble Ideas.</p>
                <p>Before I had liv'd quite two Years with this Reverend Gentleman, my indulgent Mother departed this Life, leaving me as it were by my self, having no Relation on Earth within my Knowledge.</p>
                <p>I will not abuse your Patience with a tedious Recital of all the frivolous Accidents of my Life, that happened from this Time until I arrived to <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Years of Discretion</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">(DRAFT-DC)The time in a person's life when they are presumed able to make sound judgements.</note>, only inform you that I liv'd a chearful Country Life, spending my leisure Time either in some innocent Diversion with the neighbouring Females, or in some shady Retirement, with the best of Company, <hi rend="italic"> Books</hi>. Thus I past away the Time with a Mixture of Profit and Pleasure, having no affliction but what was imaginary, and created in my own Fancy; as nothing is more common with us Women, than to be grieving for nothing, when we have nothing else to grieve for.</p>
                <p>As I would not engross too much of your Paper at once, I will defer the Remainder of my Story until my next Letter; in the mean time desiring your Readers to exercise their Patience, and bear with my Humours now and then, because I shall trouble them but seldom. I am not insensible of the Impossibility of pleasing all, but I would not willingly displease any; and for those who will take Offence <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">were</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">DRAFT-is this supposed to say "where"</note> none is intended, they are beneath the Notice of Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    April 16, 1722 [No. 2] 
                    
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. 
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Histories of Lives are seldom entertaining, unless they contain something either admirable or exemplar: And since there is little or nothing of this Nature in my own Adventures, I will not tire your Readers with tedious Particulars of no Consequence, but will briefly, and in as few Words as possible, relate the most material Occurrences of my Life, and according to my Promise, confine all to this Letter.</p>
                <p>My Reverend master who had hitherto remained a Batchelor, (after much meditation on the <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Eighteenth verse of the Second Chapter of Genesis</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">DRAFT-give a brief summary, and explain how that fits into being batchelor if its not obvious</note>,) took up a Resolution to marry; and having made several unsuccessful fruitless Attempts on the <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">more topping Sort of our Sex</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">DRAFT-explain</note>, and being tir'd with making troublesome Journeys and Visits to no Purpose, <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">he began unexpectedly to cast a loving Eye upon Me</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">DRAFT-explain how common it was to marry a man so distantly above your age as I imagine this man would be a minimum of ten years older than her if not more</note>, whom he had brought up cleverly to his Hand.</p>
                <p>There is certainly scarce any Part of a Man's Life in which he appears more silly and ridiculous, than when he makes his first Onset in Courtship. The aukward Manner in which my Master first discover'd his Intentions, made me, in spite of my Reverence to his Person, burst out into an unmannerly Laughter: However, having ask'd his Pardon, and with much ado compos'd my Countenance, I promis'd him I would take his Proposal into serious Consideration, and speedily give him an Answer.</p>
                <p>As he had been a great Benefactor (and in a Manner a Father to me) I could not well deny his Request, when I once perceived he was in earnest. Whether it was Love, or Gratitude, or Pride, or all Three that made me consent, I know not; but it is certain, he found it no hard Matter, by the Help of his Rhetorick, to conquer my Heart, and perswade me to marry him.</p>
                <p>This unexpected Match was very astonishing to all the Country round about, and served to furnish them with Discourse for a long Time after; some approving it, others disliking it, as they were led by their various Fancies and Inclinations.</p>
                <p>We lived happily together in the Heighth of conjugal Love and mutual Endearments, for near Seven Years, in which Time we added Two likely Girls and a Boy to the Family of the Dogoods: But alas! When my <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Sun was in its meridian Altitude</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">DRAFT-explain</note>, inexorable unrelenting Death, as if he had envy'd my Happiness and Tranquility, and resolv'd to make me entirely miserable by the Loss of so good an Husband, hastened his Flight to the Heavenly World, by a sudden unexpected Departure from <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">this</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">DRAFT-Should it say "this life"</note>.</p>
                <p>I have now remained in a State of Widowhood for several Years, but it is a State I never much admir'd, and I am apt to fancy that I could be easily perswaded to marry again, provided I was sure of a good-humour'd, sober, agreeable Companion: But one, even with these few good Qualities, being hard to find, I have lately relinquish'd all Thoughts of that Nature.</p>
                <p>At present I pass away my leisure Hours in Conversation, either with my honest Neighbour Rusticus and his Family, or with the ingenious Minister of our Town, who now lodges at my House, and by whose Assistance I intend now and then to beautify my Writings with a Sentence or two in the learned Languages, which will not only be fashionable, and pleasing to those who do not understand it, but will likewise be very ornamental.</p>
                <p>I shall conclude this with my own Character, which (one would think) I should be best able to give. <hi rend="italic">Know then</hi>, That I am an Enemy to Vice, and a Friend to Vertue. I am one of an extensive Charity, and a great Forgiver of <hi rend="italic">private</hi> Injuries: <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">A hearty Lover of the Clergy and all good Men, and a mortal Enemy to arbitrary Government and unlimited Power. I am naturally very jealous for the Rights and Liberties of my Country; and the least appearance of an Incroachment on those invaluable Priviledges, is apt to make my Blood boil exceedingly</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">DRAFT-I was wondering if we could connect this to the politics of the time and give a general idea of what these ideas would mean for this period</note>. I have likewise a natural Inclination to observe and reprove the Faults of others, at which I have an excellent Faculty. I speak this by Way of Warning to all such whose Offences shall come under my Cognizance, for I never intend to wrap my Talent in a Napkin. To be brief; I am courteous and affable, good humour'd (unless I am first provok'd,) and handsome, and sometimes witty, but always, Sir, Your Friend and Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    April 30, 1722 [No. 3] 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. 
                    
                </head>
                <p>Sir.</p>
                <p>It is undoubtedly the Duty of all Persons to serve the Country they live in, according to their Abilities; yet I sincerely acknowledge, that I have hitherto been very deficient in this Particular; whether it was for want of Will or Opportunity, I will not at present stand to determine: Let it suffice, that I now take up a Resolution, to do for the future all that <hi rend="italic">lies in my Way</hi> for the Service of my Countrymen.</p>
                <p>I have from my Youth been <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">indefatigably</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Tirelessly. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> studious to gain and treasure up in my Mind all useful and desireable Knowledge, especially such as tends to improve the Mind, and enlarge the Understanding: And as I have found it very beneficial to me, I am not without Hopes, that communicating my small Stock in this Manner, by <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Peace-meal</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Piece by piece, or in small bits. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to the Publick, may be at least in some Measure useful.</p>
                <p>I am very sensible that it is impossible for me, or indeed any one Writer to please all Readers at once. Various Persons have different Sentiments; and that which is pleasant and delightful to one, gives another a Disgust. He that would (in this Way of Writing) please all, is under a Necessity to make his Themes almost as numerous as his Letters. He must one while be merry and diverting, then more solid and serious; one while sharp and satyrical, then (to <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">mollify</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Soften; make tender. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> that) be sober and religious; at one Time let the Subject be Politicks, then let the next Theme be Love: Thus will every one, one Time or other find some thing agreeable to his own Fancy, and in his Turn be delighted.</p>
                <p>According to this Method I intend to proceed, bestowing now and then a few gentle <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Reproofs</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Censures or Rebukes; subject to blame or scorn. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> on those who deserve them, not forgetting at the same time to applaud those whose Actions merit Commendation. And here I must not forget to invite the ingenious Part of your Readers, particularly those of my own Sex to enter into a Correspondence with me, assuring them, that their Condescension in this Particular shall be received as a Favour, and accordingly acknowledged.</p>
                <p>I think I have now finish'd the Foundation, and I intend in my next to begin to raise the Building. Having nothing more to write at present, I must make the usual excuse in such Cases, of <hi rend="italic">being in haste</hi>, assuring you that I speak from my Heart when I call my self, The most humble and obedient of all the Servants your Merits have acquir'd,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    May 14, 1722 [No. 4] 
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi rend="italic">An sum etiam nunc vel Graecè loqui vel Latinè docendus?</hi> Cicero.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"Should I be taught to speak either Greek or Latin?" Franklin is quoting here from the Roman orator Cicero. The essay that follows, taking the form of a dream vision, is a satire on Harvard College and its requirement that students study Greek and Latin.</note> 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. 
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Discoursing the other Day at Dinner with my Reverend Boarder, formerly mention'd, (whom for Distinction sake we will call by the Name of Clericus,) concerning the Education of Children, I ask'd his Advice about my young Son William, whether or no I had best bestow upon him Academical Learning, or (as our Phrase is) <hi rend="italic">bring him up at our College</hi>: He perswaded me to do it by all Means, using many weighty Arguments with me, and answering all the Objections that I could form against it; telling me withal, that he did not doubt but that the Lad would take his Learning very well, and not idle away his Time as too many there now-a-days do. These Words of Clericus gave me a Curiosity to inquire a little more strictly into the present Circumstances of that famous <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Seminary</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">A place of education such as a school or a college. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> of Learning; but the Information which he gave me, was neither pleasant, nor such as I expected.</p>
                <p>As soon as Dinner was over, I took a solitary Walk into my Orchard, still ruminating on Clericus's Discourse with much Consideration, until I came to my usual Place of Retirement under the <hi rend="italic">Great Apple-Tree</hi>; where having seated my self, and carelessly laid my Head on a <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">verdant</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Green; of vegetation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Bank, I fell by Degrees into a soft and undisturbed Slumber. My waking Thoughts remained with me in my Sleep, and before I awak'd again, I dreamt the following Dream.</p>
                <p>I fancy'd I was travelling over pleasant and delightful Fields and Meadows, and thro' many small Country Towns and Villages; and as I pass'd along, all Places resounded with the Fame of the Temple of Learning: Every Peasant, who had wherewithal, was preparing to send one of his Children at least to this famous Place; and in this Case most of them consulted their own Purses instead of their Childrens Capacities: So that I observed, a great many, <!-- YEA? -->yea, the most part of those who were travelling thither, were little better than Dunces and Blockheads. Alas! alas!</p>
                <p>At length I entred upon a spacious Plain, in the Midst of which was erected a large and stately Edifice: It was to this that a great Company of Youths from all Parts of the Country were going; so stepping in among the Crowd, I passed on with them, and presently arrived at the Gate.</p>
                <p>The Passage was kept by two sturdy <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Porters</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Gatekeepers. Source: Oxford English Dictionoary</note> named <hi rend="italic">Riches and Poverty</hi>, and the latter obstinately refused to give Entrance to any who had not first gain'd the Favour of the former; so that I observed, many who came even to the very Gate, were obliged to travel back again as ignorant as they came, for want of this necessary Qualification. However, as a <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Spectator</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT-DC add more?)A nod to the series of letters, The Spectator, which Franklin used as a heavy influence for his Silence Dogood letters.</note> I gain'd Admittance, and with the rest entred directly into the Temple.</p>
                <p>In the Middle of the great Hall stood a stately and magnificent Throne, which was ascended to by two high and difficult Steps. On the Top of it sat Learning in awful State; she was apparelled wholly in Black, and surrounded almost on every Side with innumerable Volumes in all Languages. She seem'd very busily employ'd in writing something on half a Sheet of Paper, and upon Enquiry, I understood she was preparing a Paper, call'd, <hi rend="italic">The New-England Courant</hi>. On her Right Hand sat <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, with a pleasant smiling Countenance, and handsomely attir'd; and on her left were seated several <hi rend="italic">Antique Figures</hi> with their Faces vail'd. I was considerably puzzl'd to guess who they were, until one informed me, (who stood beside me,) that those Figures on her left Hand were <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hebrew</hi>, &amp;c. and that they were very much reserv'd, and seldom or never unvail'd their Faces here, and then to few or none, tho' most of those who have in this Place acquir'd so much Learning as to distinguish them from <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, pretended to an intimate Acquaintance with them. I then enquir'd of him, what could be the Reason why they continued vail'd, in this Place especially: He pointed to the Foot of the Throne, where I saw <hi rend="italic">Idleness</hi>, attended with <hi rend="italic">Ignorance</hi>, and these (he informed me) were they, who first vail'd them, and still kept them so.</p>
                <p>Now I observed, that the whole Tribe who entred into the Temple with me, began to climb the Throne; but the Work proving troublesome and difficult to most of them, they withdrew their Hands from the Plow, and contented themselves to sit at the Foot, with Madam <hi rend="italic">Idleness</hi> and her Maid <hi rend="italic">Ignorance</hi>, until those who were assisted by Diligence and a <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">docible</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Ready to be taught; submissive to instruction. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Temper, had well <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">nigh</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">Near or almost. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> got up the first Step: But the Time drawing nigh in which they could no way avoid ascending, they were <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">fain</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Happy, please. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to crave the Assistance of those who had got up before them, and who, for the Reward perhaps of a <hi rend="italic">Pint of Milk</hi>, or a <hi rend="italic">Piece of <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Plumb-Cake</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">A fruit-cake packed full of different types of candied and dried fruits such as plums, raisins, and orange peel. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></hi>, lent the <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">Lubbers</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">A large clumsy idiot who is often lazy and idle. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> a helping Hand, and sat them in the Eye of the World, upon a Level with themselves.</p>
                <p>The other Step being in the same Manner ascended, and the usual Ceremonies at an End, every <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Beetle-Scull</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">(DRAFT)I assume this is some kind of insult but I can't find any reference to it except here.</note> seem'd well satisfy'd with his own Portion of Learning, tho' perhaps he was <hi rend="italic">e'en just</hi> as ignorant as ever. And now the Time of their Departure being come, they march'd out of Doors to make Room for another Company, who waited for Entrance: And I, having seen all that was to be seen, quitted the hall likewise, and went to make my Observations on those who were just gone out before me.</p>
                <p>Some I perceiv'd took to <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Merchandizing</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">Engaged in the selling and trade of goods. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, others to Travelling, some to one Thing, some to another, and some to Nothing; and many of them from henceforth, for want of <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Patrimony</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Property that, by ancient right, belongs to an institution. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, liv'd as poor as <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Church Mice</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">The expression "church mice" is used to attribute people as poor and quiet. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, being unable to dig, and asham'd to beg, and to live by their Wits it was impossible. But the most Part of the Crowd went along a large beaten Path, which led to a Temple at the further End of the Plain, call'd, <hi rend="italic">The Temple of <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Theology</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">The Study of God, and God's relations with man and the universe. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note></hi>/hi>. The Business of those who were employ'd in this Temple being laborious and painful, I wonder'd exceedingly to see so many go towards it; but while I was pondering this Matter in my Mind, I spy'd <ref target="a016" corresp="n016"><hi rend="italic">Pecunia</hi></ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">(DRAFT) I don't know what this is supposed to be</note> behind a Curtain, beckoning to them with her Hand, which Sight immediately satisfy'd me for whose Sake it was, that a great Part of them (I will not say all) travel'd that Road. In this Temple I saw nothing worth mentioning, except the ambitious and fraudulent Contrivances of <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">Plagius</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">(DRAFT)Is this from the root of plagiarism.</note>, who (notwithstanding he had been severely reprehended for such Practices before) was diligently transcribing some eloquent Paragraphs out of <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Tillotson's <hi rend="italic">Works</hi></ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">(DRAFT) John Tillotson? the Archbishop of Canterbury in late 17th century.</note>, &amp;c., to embellish his own.</p>
                <p>Now I <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">bethought</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">(DRAFT) What is the meaning of this as opposed to just "thought"</note> my self in my Sleep, that it was Time to be at Home, and as I fancy'd I was travelling back thither, I reflected in my Mind on the extream Folly of those Parents, who, blind to their Childrens Dulness, and insensible of the Solidity of their Skulls, because they think their Purses can afford it, will needs send them to the Temple of Learning, where, for want of a suitable Genius, they learn little more than how to carry themselves handsomely, and enter a Room <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">genteely</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">In the manner of the gentry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, (which might as well be acquir'd at a Dancing-School,) and from whence they return, after Abundance of Trouble and Charge, as great Blockheads as ever, only more proud and self-conceited.</p>
                <p>While I was in the midst of these unpleasant Reflections, Clericus (who with a Book in his Hand was walking under the Trees) accidentally awak'd me; to him I related my Dream with all its Particulars, and he, without much Study, presently interpreted it, assuring me, <hi rend="italic">That it was </hi><ref target="a021" corresp="n021"><hi rend="italic">a lively Representation of</hi> Harvard College</ref><note xml:id="n021" target="a021">(DRAFT) I'd be curious to see if there are any academic rebutals to this of note.</note>, <hi rend="italic">Etcetera</hi>. I remain, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    May 28, 1722 [No. 5] 
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi rend="italic">Mulier Mulieri magis congruet</hi>. Ter.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"One woman agrees the most with another." The line is from the Roman playwright Terence.</note> 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>. 
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>I shall here present your Readers with a Letter from one, who informs me that I have begun at the wrong End of my Business, and that I ought to begin at Home, and censure the Vices and Follies of my own Sex, before I venture to meddle with your's: Nevertheless, I am resolved to dedicate this Speculation to the Fair Tribe, and endeavour to show, that Mr. Ephraim charges Women with being particularly guilty of Pride, Idleness, &amp;c. wrongfully, inasmuch as the Men have not only as great a Share in those Vices as the Women, but are likewise in a great Measure the Cause of that which the Women are guilty of. I think it will be best to produce my Antagonist, before I encounter him.</p>
                <p>"<ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Madam</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">(DRAFT-Would we know if this is a real letter he received or not.)</note></p>
                <p>"My Design in troubling you with this Letter is, to desire you would begin with your own Sex first: Let the first Volley of your Resentments be directed against <hi rend="italic">Female</hi> Vice; let Female Idleness, Ignorance and Folly, (which are Vices more peculiar to your Sex than to our's,) be the Subject of your <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">Satyrs</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">A myhological demon often depicted as a half-human, half-goat creature. The demon is generally a representation of lust and rage. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, but more especially Female Pride, which I think is intollerable. Here is a large Field that wants Cultivation, and which I believe you are able (if willing) to improve with Advantage; and when you have once reformed the Women, you will find it a much easier Task to reform the Men, because Women are the prime Causes of a great many Male <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Enormities</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Deviation in behavior, often from moral or legal normality. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. This is all at present from Your Friendly Wellwisher,</p>
                <p><ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Ephraim Censorious</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT-DC the Ephraim bit)Ephraim: The second son of Joseph and Asenath, as shown by Book of Genesis. The name Ephraim became related to the idea of "being fruitful." Censorious: one who gives constant censure and finds faults. Source: Oxford English Dictionary and Wikipedia</note></p>
                <!-- Why did Franklin pick a woman for this series in particular. At 16 I'm just surprised by his thoughts on gender, like were his parents particularly progressive?-->
                <p>After Thanks to my Correspondent for his Kindness in cutting out Work for me, I must assure him, that I find it a very difficult Matter to <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">reprove</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Rebuke; express disapproval. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Women separate from the Men; for what Vice is there in which the Men have not as great a Share as the Women? and in some have they not a far greater, as in Drunkenness, Swearing, &amp;c.? And if they have, then it follows, that when a Vice is to be reproved, Men, who are most culpable, deserve the most Reprehension, and certainly therefore, ought to have it. But we will wave this Point at present, and proceed to a particular Consideration of what my Correspondent calls <hi rend="italic">Female Vice</hi>.</p>
                <p>As for Idleness, if I should <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Quaere</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">To question or query. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, Where are the greatest Number of its <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">Votaries</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">People bound to a religious life or a certain vow. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to be found, with us or the Men? it might I believe be easily and truly answer'd, <hi rend="italic">With the latter</hi>. For notwithstanding the Men are commonly complaining how hard they are forc'd to labour, only to maintain their Wives in <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Pomp</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Ostentatious display; boastful, prideful with a negative connotation. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> and Idleness, yet if you go among the Women, you will learn, that <hi rend="italic">they have always more Work upon their Hands than they are able to do; and that a Woman's Work is never done</hi>, &amp;c. But however, Suppose we should grant for once, that we are generally more idle than the Men, (without making any Allowance for the <hi rend="italic">Weakness of the Sex</hi>,) I desire to know whose Fault it is? Are not the Men to blame for their Folly in maintaining us in Idleness? Who is there that can be handsomely Supported in Affluence, Ease and Pleasure by another, that will chuse rather to earn his Bread by the Sweat of his own Brows? And if a Man will be so fond and so foolish, as to labour hard himself for a Livelihood, and suffer his Wife in the mean Time to sit in Ease and Idleness, let him not blame her if she does so, for it is in a great Measure his own Fault.</p>
                <p>And now for the Ignorance and Folly which he <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">reproaches</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Scolds or censures. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> us with, let us see (if we are Fools and Ignoramus's) whose is the Fault, the Men's or our's. An ingenious Writer, having this Subject in Hand, has the following Words, wherein he lays the Fault wholly on the Men, for not allowing Women the Advantages of Education.</p>
                <p>"I have (says he) often thought of it as one of the most barbarous Customs in the World, considering us as a civiliz'd and Christian Country, that we deny the Advantages of Learning to Women. We reproach the Sex every Day with Folly and Impertinence, while I am confident, had they the Advantages of Education equal to us, they would be guilty of less than our selves. One would wonder indeed how it should happen that Women are <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">conversible</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Capable of being converted. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> at all, since they are only beholding to natural Parts for all their Knowledge. Their Youth is spent to teach them to stitch and sew, or make <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Baubles</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">A showy trinket that's of little worth, often made for children to play with. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>: They are taught to read indeed, and perhaps to write their Names, or so; and that is the Heighth of a Womans Education. And I would but ask any who slight the Sex for their Understanding, What is a Man (a Gentleman, I mean) good for that is taught no more? If Knowledge and Understanding had been useless Additions to the Sex, God Almighty would never have given them Capacities, for he made nothing Needless. What has the Woman done to forfeit the Priviledge of being taught? Does she plague us with her Pride and <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Impertinence</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">Irrelevance. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>? Why did we not let her learn, that she might have had more Wit? Shall we <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">upbraid</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">(Draft-which connotation of the word is this?)Censure or cast/saddle</note> Women with Folly, when 'tis only the Error of this inhumane Custom that hindred them being made wiser."</p>
                <p>So much for Female Ignorance and Folly, and now let us a little consider the Pride which my Correspondent thinks is <hi rend="italic">intollerable</hi>. By this Expression of his, one would think he is some dejected <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Swain</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">(DRAFT-DC)An innocent, rose-coloured country lover, such as one found in pastoral poetry. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, tyranniz'd over by some cruel haughty <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">Nymph</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">A woman or lover with sexual power or magic over a man. Coming from mythology, nymphs are spirits that take the form of women who, similarly to sirens, were said to charm men and lead them to sin or death. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, who (perhaps he thinks) has no more Reason to be proud than himself. <hi rend="italic">Alas-a-day!</hi> What shall we say in this Case! Why truly, if Women are proud, it is certainly owing to the Men still; for if they will be such <hi rend="italic">Simpletons</hi> as to humble themselves at their Feet, and fill their <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">credulous</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">Ready or willing. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Ears with extravagant Praises of their Wit, Beauty, and other Accomplishments (perhaps where there are none too,) and when Women are by this Means perswaded that they are Something more than humane, what Wonder is it, if they carry themselves haughtily, and live extravagantly. Notwithstanding, I believe there are more Instances of extravagant Pride to be found among Men than among Women, and this Fault is certainly more hainous in the former than in the latter.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, I conclude, that it will be impossible to lash any Vice, of which the Men are not equally guilty with the Women, and consequently deserve an equal (if not a greater) Share in the Censure. However, I <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">exhort</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">To urge earnestly. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> both to amend, where both are <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">culpable</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">Guilty. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, otherwise they may expect to be severely handled by Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> Mrs. Dogood has lately left her Seat in the Country, and come to Boston, where she intends to <ref target="a020" corresp="n020">tarry</ref><note xml:id="n020" target="a020">To linger or stay. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> for the Summer Season, in order to compleat her Observations of the present reigning Vices of the Town.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    June 11, 1722 [No. 6] 
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><hi rend="italic">Quem Dies videt veniens Superbum, Hunc Dies vidit fugiens jacentem.</hi> Seneca.</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">"A man who stands proudly at the start of the day is flattened by its end." Franklin is quoting here from the Roman tragedian Seneca.</note> 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>.
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>Among the many reigning Vices of the Town which may at any Time come under my Consideration and Reprehension, there is none which I am more inclin'd to expose than that of <hi rend="italic">Pride</hi>. It is acknowledg'd by all to be a Vice the most hateful to God and Man. Even those who nourish it in themselves, hate to see it in others. The proud Man aspires after Nothing less than an unlimited Superiority over his Fellow-Creatures. He has made himself a King in <ref target="a002" corresp="n002"><hi rend="italic">Soliloquy</hi>S</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">(DRAFT-DC how this was coded, why the second capital "S")A speech or talk given alone or aloud without addressing any person. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>; fancies himself conquering the World; and the Inhabitants thereof consulting on proper Methods to acknowledge his Merit. I speak it to my Shame, <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">I my self was a Queen from the Fourteenth to the Eighteenth Year of my Age</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">(DRAFT-Explain this)</note>, and govern'd the World all the Time of my being govern'd by my Master. But this speculative Pride may be the Subject of another Letter: I shall at present confine my Thoughts to what we call <hi rend="italic">Pride of Apparel</hi>. This Sort of Pride has been growing upon us ever since we parted with our Homespun Cloaths for <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi rend="italic">Fourteen Penny Stuffs</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">(DRAFT-Figure out what this means)</note>, &amp;c. And the <hi rend="italic">Pride of Apparel</hi> has <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">begot</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">Has given rise to. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> and nourish'd in us a <hi rend="italic">Pride of Heart</hi>, which <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">portends</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">Fortells as an omen or other supernatural means. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> the Ruin of Church and State. <hi rend="italic">Pride goeth before Destruction, and a haughty Spirit before a Fall</hi>: And I remember my late Reverend Husband would often say upon this Text, That a Fall was the <hi rend="italic">natural Consequence</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic">Punishment</hi> of Pride. Daily Experience is sufficient to <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">evince</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">(DRAFT-DC connotation)To overcome. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> the Truth of this Observation. Persons of small Fortune under the Dominion of this Vice, seldom consider their Inability to maintain themselves in it, but strive to imitate their Superiors in Estate, or Equals in Folly, until one Misfortune comes upon the Neck of another, and every Step they take is a Step backwards. By striving to appear rich they become really poor, and deprive themselves of that Pity and Charity which is due to the humble poor Man, who is made so more immediately by Providence.</p>
                <p>This Pride of Apparel will appear the more foolish, if we consider, that those airy Mortals, who have no other Way of making themselves considerable but by gorgeous Apparel, draw after them Crowds of Imitators, who hate each other while they endeavour after a Similitude of Manners. They destroy by Example, and envy one another's Destruction.</p>
                <p>I cannot dismiss this Subject without some Observations on a particular Fashion now reigning among my own Sex, the most immodest and inconvenient of any the Art of Woman has invented, namely, that of <ref target="a008" corresp="n008"><hi rend="italic">Hoop-Petticoats</hi></ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">(DRAFT-Add Picture;maybe rephrase)An undergarment, more commonly known as a hoop skirt, that is worn underneath a womans skirt. The skirt is constructed with rigid hoops that flare out and grow larger as one travels downward from the top of the skirt so as to give a domed shape to the bottom of a dress. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>. By these they are <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">incommoded</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">Subjected to inconveience; troubled. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> in their General and Particular Calling, and therefore they cannot answer the Ends of either necessary or ornamental Apparel. These monstrous topsy-turvy <ref target="a010" corresp="n010"><hi rend="italic">Mortar-Pieces</hi></ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">A mortar is a hard-walled bowl that is used to grind things with a pestle. Here Franklin is saying the hoop-skirts are like thick, over-turned bowls. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, are neither fit for the Church, the Hall, or the Kitchen; and if a Number of them were well mounted on <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Noddles-Island</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">Historically one of Boston Harbor Islands, that has now been reconnected to the mainland by filling the strait that used to separate it from the mainland. Noddle's Island now makes up the southern part of the East Boston neighborhood.</note>, they would look more like Engines of War for bombarding the Town, than Ornaments of the Fair Sex. <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">An honest Neighbour of mine, happening to be in Town some time since on a publick Day, inform'd me, that he saw four Gentlewomen with their Hoops half mounted in a Balcony, as they withdrew to the Wall, to the great Terror of the Militia, who (he thinks) might attribute their irregular Volleys to the formidable Appearance of the Ladies Petticoats</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">(DRAFT-I'm assuming this is a tongue in cheek joke, but I wouldn't mind some assistance deciphering exactly what's happening in this joke. </note>.</p>
                <p>I assure you, Sir, I have but little Hopes of perswading my Sex, by this Letter, utterly to relinquish the extravagant Foolery, and Indication of Immodesty, in this monstrous Garb of their's; but I would at least desire them to lessen the Circumference of their Hoops, and leave it with them to consider, Whether they, who pay no Rates or Taxes, ought to take up more Room in the King's High-Way, than the Men, who yearly contribute to the Support of the Government. I am, Sir, Your Humble Servant,</p>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    June 25, 1722 [No. 7] 
                    <ref target="a001" corresp="n001"><lg>
                            <l>Give me the Muse, whose generous Force,</l>
                            <l>Impatient of the Reins,</l>
                            <l>Pursues an unattempted Course,</l>
                            <l>Breaks all the Criticks Iron Chains.</l>
                    </lg>
                        Watts.</ref>
                    <note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Having used Latin quotations for his epigraphs to this point, Franklin here switches to a contemporary poem, drawing an extract from a 1709 poem called "The Adventurous Muse" by the English poet Isaac Watts.</note> 
                    To the Author of the <hi rend="italic">New-England Courant</hi>.          
                </head>
                <!-- PERHAPS an opening note about the satirical tone in this which I assume is mostly lost on the people of today. -->
                <p>Sir,</p>
                <p>It has been the Complaint of many Ingenious Foreigners, who have travell'd amongst us, <hi rend="italic">That good Poetry is not to be expected in New-England</hi>. I am apt to Fancy, the Reason is, not because our Countreymen are altogether void of a Poetical Genius, nor yet because we have not those Advantages of Education which other Countries have, but purely because we do not afford that Praise and Encouragement which is merited, when any thing extraordinary of this Kind is produc'd among us: Upon which Consideration I have determined, when I meet with a Good Piece of New-England Poetry, to give it a suitable <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Encomium</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Grand expression of praise. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, and thereby endeavour to discover to the World some of its Beautys, in order to encourage the Author to go on, and bless the World with more, and more Excellent Productions.</p>
                <p>There has lately appear'd among us a most Excellent Piece of Poetry, entituled, <hi rend="italic">An Elegy upon the much Lamented Death of Mrs. Mehitebell Kitel, Wife of Mr. John Kitel of Salem, &amp;c</hi>. It may justly be said in its Praise, without Flattery to the Author, that it is the most <hi rend="italic">Extraordinary</hi> Piece that ever was wrote in New-England. The Language is so soft and Easy, the Expression so moving and pathetick, but above all, the Verse and Numbers so Charming and Natural, that it is almost beyond Comparison,</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>The Muse disdains</l>
                    <l>Those Links and Chains,</l>
                    <l>Measures and Rules of vulgar Strains,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">And o'er the Laws of Harmony a Sovereign Queen she reigns.</hi></l>                
                </lg>
                
                
                <p>I find no English Author, Ancient or Modern, whose Elegies may be compar'd with this, in respect to the Elegance of Stile, or Smoothness of Rhime; and for the affecting Part, I will leave your Readers to judge, if ever they read any Lines, that would sooner make them <hi rend="italic">draw their Breath</hi> and Sigh, if not shed Tears, than these following.</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>Come let us mourn, for we have lost a Wife, a Daughter, and <hi rend="italic">a Sister</hi>,</l>
                    <l>Who has lately taken Flight, and greatly we have mist her.</l>
                </lg> 
                
                <p>In another Place,</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Some little Time</hi> before she yielded up her Breath,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">She said, I ne'er shall hear one Sermon more on Earth</hi>.</l>
                    <l>She kist her Husband <hi rend="italic">some little Time</hi>before she expir'd,</l>
                    <l>Then lean'd her Head the Pillow on, just out of Breath and tir'd.</l>
                </lg> 
                
                <p>But the Threefold <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Appellation</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Calling of Names. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> in the first Line</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>a Wife, a Daughter, and a Sister,</l>
                </lg> 
                
                <p>must not pass unobserved. That Line in the celebrated Watts,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l><ref target="a005" corresp="n005">Gunston</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">(DRAFT-Do we know who this is)</note> <hi rend="italic">the Just</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the Generous</hi>, <hi rend="italic">and the Young</hi>, </l>
                </lg> 
                
                
                <p>is nothing Comparable to it. The latter only mentions three Qualifications of <hi rend="italic">one</hi> Person who was deceased, which therefore could raise Grief and Compassion but for <hi rend="italic">One</hi>. Whereas the former, (<hi rend="italic">our most excellent Poet</hi>) gives his Reader a Sort of an Idea of the Death of <hi rend="italic">Three Persons</hi>, viz.</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>a Wife, a Daughter, and a Sister,</l>
                </lg>               
                
                <p>which is <hi rend="italic">Three Times</hi> as great a Loss as the Death of <hi rend="italic">One</hi>, and consequently must raise <hi rend="italic">Three Times</hi> as much Grief and Compassion in the Reader.</p>
                <p>I should be very much straitned for Room, if I should attempt to discover even half the Excellencies of this Elegy which are obvious to me. Yet I  cannot omit one Observation, which is, that the Author has (to his Honour) invented a new Species of Poetry, which wants a Name, and was never before known. His Muse scorns to be confin'd to the old Measures and Limits, or to observe the dull Rules of Criticks;</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Nor <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">Rapin</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">(DRAFT)I don't know which Rapin this is; there are three possible men.</note> gives her Rules to fly, nor <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">Purcell</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">(DRAFT-DC)Henry Purcell was an English composer who is considered one of the greatest of his kind. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> Notes to sing</hi>. Watts.</l> 
                </lg>
                
                <p>Now 'tis Pity that such an Excellent Piece should not be dignify'd with a particular Name; and seeing it cannot justly be called, either <ref target="a008" corresp="n008"><hi rend="italic">Epic</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sapphic</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lyric</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Pindaric</hi></ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">A series of common poetical styles of the time. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note>, nor any other Name yet invented, I presume it may, (in Honour and Remembrance of the Dead) be called the <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">Kitelic</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">(DRAFT-I can't find what this is supposed to be is it supposed to be "celtic")</note>. Thus much in the Praise of <hi rend="italic">Kitelic Poetry</hi>.</p>
                <p>It is certain, that those Elegies which are of our own Growth, (and our Soil seldom produces any other sort of Poetry) are by far the greatest part, wretchedly Dull and Ridiculous. Now since it is imagin'd by many, that our Poets are honest, well-meaning Fellows, who do their best, and that if they had but some Instructions how to govern Fancy with Judgment, they would make indifferent good Elegies; I shall here <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">subjoin</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">Add to the end of a statement. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> a <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">Receipt</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">(DRAFT-Is this the same as Recipe)</note> for that purpose, which was left me as a Legacy, (among other valuable Rarities) by my Reverend Husband. It is as follows,</p>
                
                <lg>
                    <l>A RECEIPT to make a New-England Funeral ELEGY.</l>
                </lg>
                
                
                <p><hi rend="italic">For the Title of your Elegy</hi>. Of these you may have enough ready made to your Hands; but if you should chuse to make it your self, you must be sure not to omit the Words <ref target="a012" corresp="n012"><hi rend="italic">Aetatis Suae</hi></ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">(DRAFT-DC-Add more)"Of his or her age"</note>, which will Beautify it exceedingly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">For the Subject of your Elegy</hi>. Take one of your Neighbours who has lately departed this Life; it is no great matter at what Age the Party dy'd, but it will be best if he went away suddenly, being <hi rend="italic">Kill'd</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Drown'd</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Froze to Death</hi>.</p>
                <p>Having chose the Person, take all his Virtues, Excellencies, &amp;c. and if he have not enough, you may borrow some to make up a sufficient Quantity: To these add his last Words, dying Expressions, &amp;c. if they are to be had; mix all these together, and be sure you <hi rend="italic">strain</hi> them well. Then season all with a Handful or two of Melancholly Expressions, such as, <hi rend="italic">Dreadful</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Deadly</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cruel cold Death</hi>, <hi rend="italic">unhappy Fate</hi>, <hi rend="italic">weeping Eyes</hi>, &amp;c. Have mixed all these Ingredients well, put them into the empty <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Scull</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">(DRAFT-Skull as in head or the basket? I assume head, but I could see it the other way)</note> of some <hi rend="italic">young Harvard</hi>; (but in Case you have ne'er a One at Hand, you may use your own,) there let them Ferment for the Space of a Fortnight, and by that Time they will be incorporated into a Body, which take out, and having prepared a sufficient Quantity of double Rhimes, such as, <hi rend="italic">Power</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Flower</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Quiver</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Shiver</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Grieve us</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Leave us</hi>; <hi rend="italic">tell you</hi>, <hi rend="italic">excel you</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Expeditions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Physicians</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Fatigue him</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Intrigue him</hi>; &amp;c. you must spread all upon Paper, and if you can procure a Scrap of Latin to put at the End, it will garnish it mightily; then having affixed your Name at the Bottom, with a <ref target="a014" corresp="n014"><hi rend="italic">Moestus Composuit</hi></ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">(DRAFT-needs translation)</note>, you will have an Excellent Elegy.</p>
                <p><ref target="a015" corresp="n015"><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi></ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">(DRAFT-dc)"N.B." is used to signify something important in a text; 'ntoe well.' Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> This Receipt will serve when a Female is the Subject of your Elegy, provided you borrow a greater Quantity of Virtues, Excellencies, &amp;c. Sir, Your Servant,</p>
                <p>Silence Dogood</p>
                <p>p.s. I shall make no other Answer to <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">Hypercarpus's Criticism on my last Letter</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">(DRAFT-About what did he say? Do we know?)</note> than this, <ref target="a017" corresp="a017"><hi rend="italic">Mater me genuit, peperit mox filia matrem</hi></ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">(DRAFT-Translate if possible)</note>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>    