<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="franklin-dogood-1">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Silence Dogood 1</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <date when="1722">April 2, 1722</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <title type="sub">1</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    April 2, 1722 [No. 1] <lb/><lb/>
                    To the Author of the <hi>New-England Courant</hi>. <lb/><lb/><lb/>
                </head>
                <p>Sir,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>It may not be improper in the first place to inform your Readers, that I intend once a <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">Fortnight</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">DRAFT</note> to present them, by the Help of this Paper, with a short <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Epistle</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">DRAFT</note>, which I presume will add somewhat to their Entertainment.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>And since it is observed, that the Generality of People, now a days, are unwilling either to commend or <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">dispraise</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">DRAFT</note> what they read, until they are in some measure informed who or what the Author of it is, whether he be <hi>poor</hi> or <hi>rich</hi>, <hi>old</hi> or <hi>young</hi>, a <hi>Schollar</hi> or a <ref target="a004" corresp="n004"><hi>Leather Apron Man</hi></ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">DRAFT</note>, <ref target="a005" corresp="n005">&amp;c</ref><note xml:id="n005" target="a005">DRAFT-Is this just like an older "etc."</note>. and give their Opinion of the Performance, according to the Knowledge which they have of the Author's Circumstances, it may not be amiss to begin with a short Account of my past Life and present Condition, that the Reader may not be at a Loss to judge whether or <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">no</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">DRAFT-Is this supposed to read as "not"</note> my <note xml:id="n007" taraget="a007">Lucubrations</note><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">DRAFT</note> are worth his reading.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>At the time of my Birth, my Parents were on Ship-board in their Way from London to <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">N. England</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">DRAFT-I assume this is New-England; curious to see if this matches his biography (also just the story of his father-if not why include this detail-tragic backstory?)</note>. My Entrance into this troublesome World was attended with the Death of my Father, a Misfortune, which tho' I was not then capable of knowing, I shall never be able to forget; for as he, poor Man, stood upon the Deck rejoycing at my Birth, a merciless Wave entred the Ship, and in one Moment carry'd him beyond Reprieve. Thus, was the <hi>first Day</hi> which I saw, the <hi>last</hi> that was seen by my Father; and thus was my <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">disconsolate</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009">DRAFT</note> Mother at once made both a <hi>Parent</hi> and a <hi>Widow</hi>.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>When we arrived at Boston (which was not long after) <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">I was put to Nurse in a Country Place, at a small Distance from the Town, where I went to School, and past my Infancy and Childhood in Vanity and Idleness</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010">DRAFT-Does this imply a boarding room situation, vaguely Jane Eyre esque</note>, until I was <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">bound out Apprentice</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011">DRAFT-When would women be sent out as an apprentice if ever? How long were women's apprenticeships</note>, that I might no longer be a Charge to my <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">Indigent</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012">DRAFT</note> Mother, who was put to hard Shifts for a Living.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>My Master was a <ref target="a013" corresp="n013">Country Minister</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013">DRAFT-detail the general job of a country minister(again maybe reference St. John in Jane Eyre)</note>, a pious good-natur'd young Man, and a Batchelor: he labour'd with all his Might to instil vertuous and godly Principles into my tender Soul, well knowing that it was the most suitable Time to make deep and lasting Impressions on the Mind, while it was yet untainted with Vice, free and unbiass'd. He endeavour'd that I might be instructed in <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">all that Knowledge and Learning which is necessary for our Sex</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">DRAFT-give a general detail/maybe a greater focus on the religious aspect.</note>, and deny'd me no Accomplishment that could possibly be attained in a Country Place; such as all Sorts of Needle-Work, Writing, <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Arithmetick</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015">DRAFT-Would it be common for women to be taught math? Especially under a Country Minister</note>, &amp;c. and observing that I took a <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">more than ordinary Delight in reading ingenious Books</ref><note xml:id="n016" target="a016">DRAFT-A general statistic on how many people (women more in particular if possible) actually knew how to read at this time</note>, he gave me the free Use of <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">his Library</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017">DRAFT-Give an idea of some of the more popular works at the time that most people would have had</note>, which tho' it was but small, yet it was well chose, to inform the Understanding rightly, and enable the Mind to frame great and noble Ideas.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>Before I had liv'd quite two Years with this Reverend Gentleman, my indulgent Mother departed this Life, leaving me as it were by my self, having no Relation on Earth within my Knowledge.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I will not abuse your Patience with a tedious Recital of all the frivolous Accidents of my Life, that happened from this Time until I arrived to <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">Years of Discretion</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018">DRAFT</note>, only inform you that I liv'd a chearful Country Life, spending my leisure Time either in some innocent Diversion with the neighbouring Females, or in some shady Retirement, with the best of Company, <hi>Books</hi>. Thus I past away the Time with a Mixture of Profit and Pleasure, having no affliction but what was imaginary, and created in my own Fancy; as nothing is more common with us Women, than to be grieving for nothing, when we have nothing else to grieve for.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>As I would not engross too much of your Paper at once, I will defer the Remainder of my Story until my next Letter; in the mean time desiring your Readers to exercise their Patience, and bear with my Humours now and then, because I shall trouble them but seldom. I am not insensible of the Impossibility of pleasing all, but I would not willingly displease any; and for those who will take Offence <ref target="a019" corresp="n019">were</ref><note xml:id="n019" target="a019">DRAFT-is this supposed to say "where"</note> none is intended, they are beneath the Notice of Your Humble Servant,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p><lb/><lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>    