<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="franklin-rules">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
<fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Rules by which a Great Empire May be Reduced to a Small One</title>
        <author>
            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                <name>
                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                </name>
            </persName>
        </author>
        <editor>
            <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">
                    
                    <forename>John</forename>
                    <surname>O'Brien</surname></name></persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt> 
            <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
            
            <name>Faculty, librarians, and students of the University of Virginia </name>
            
            <name ref="editors.xml#CM">Chasqui Mooney-Guerra</name>
            
        </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
        <distributor>
            <orgName>Literature in Context</orgName>
            <address>
                <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
            </address>
            <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
        </distributor>
        <availability status="free">
            <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                License </licence>
        </availability>
        <authority>
            <idno>franklin-autobiography</idno>
        </authority>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
        
        <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <title type="main">Rules by Which a Great Empire May be Reduced to a Small One</title>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="country" key="usa">np</placeName>
                        <placeName type="city" key="nyc">np</placeName>
                    </pubPlace>
                    <publisher>manuscript</publisher>
                    <date when="1790">1790</date>
                    <note resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                        </note>
                    
                </imprint>
            </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>  
    <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
    </langUsage>
    <creation/>
    <textDesc n="autobiography">
        <channel mode="w">manuscript</channel>
        <constitution type="single"/>
        <derivation type="original"/>
        <domain/>
        <factuality type="fact"/>
        <interaction/>
        <preparedness type="prepared"/>
        <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
        <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
    </textDesc>
    <settingDesc>
        <setting>
           
            <name type="tgn" key="7014406">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</name>
            <time from="1706" to="1790">18th Century</time>
        </setting>
    </settingDesc>
</profileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
    <projectDesc> <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic"></hi>Literature in Context project,
        which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
        relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th
        century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
        developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p></projectDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
        <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible
            resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
            knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If
            you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
            lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p></interpretation>
        <normalization><p>Original spelling is retained, but capitalization has been normalized in this case.</p></normalization>
        <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
            the word.</p></hyphenation>
        <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running
            headers have not.</p></segmentation>
        <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
            where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
    </editorialDecl>
    <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
    </tagsDecl>
    <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCCN">
            <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCC">
            <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
            <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="ORCID">
            <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
    </classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>

   <text>

      <body>
         




<head>R U L E S <hi rend="italic">by which a</hi> GREAT EMPIRE<hi rend="italic">may be reduced to a</hi> SMALL ONE</head>
<head>The Public Advertiser, London, 11 September 1773,<lb/>
as printed in the Pennsylvania Gazette, 15 December 1773</head>

<p>An ancient Sage boasted that tho’ he could not fiddle, he
knew how to make a <hi rend="italic">great city</hi> of a <hi rend="italic">little one</hi>. The science
that I, a modern simpleton, am about to communicate is the very
reverse. </p>
          <p>I address myself to all Ministers who have the management
of extensive dominions [empires], which from their very greatness are become troublesome to govern
because the multiplicity of their affairs leaves no Time for <hi rend="italic">fiddling.</hi></p>
<p>I. In the first place, gentlemen, you are to consider that a great Empire, like a great
cake, is most easily diminished at the edges. Turn your attention, therefore, first to
your remotest provinces, that as you get rid of them, the next may follow in order.</p>

<p>II. [So] that the possibility of this separation may always exist, take special care the
provinces are never incorporated with the mother country, that they do not enjoy the
same common rights, the same privileges in commerce, and that they are governed by
<hi rend="italic">severer</hi> laws, all of <hi rend="italic">your enacting,</hi> without allowing them any share in the choice of
the legislators. By carefully making and preserving such distinctions, you will (to
keep to my simile of the cake) act like a wise gingerbread baker who, to facilitate a
division, cuts his dough half through in those places where, when baked, he would
have it <hi rend="italic">broken to pieces.</hi></p>

<p>III. These remote provinces have perhaps been acquired, purchased, or conquered at the
<hi rend="italic">sole Expense</hi> of the Settlers or their Ancestors without the Aid of the Mother Country. If
these should happen to increase her <hi rend="italic">Strength</hi> by their growing Numbers ready to join
in her Wars, her <hi rend="italic">Commerce</hi> by their growing Demand for her Manufactures, or her
<hi rend="italic">Naval Power</hi> by greater Employment for her Ships and Seamen, they may probably
suppose some Merit in this, and that it entitles them to some Favour; you are therefore
to <hi rend="italic">forget it all,</hi> or resent it as if they had done you Injury. If they happen to be zealous
Whigs, Friends of Liberty, nurtur'd in Revolution Principles, <hi rend="italic">remember all that</hi> to their
Prejudice and contrive to punish it: For such Principles, after a Revolution is thoroughly
established, are of <hi rend="italic">no more Use;</hi> they are even <hi rend="italic">odious and abominable.</hi></p>

<p>IV. However peaceably your Colonies have submitted to your Government, shown their
Affection to your Interest, and patiently borne their Grievances, you are to <hi rend="italic">suppose</hi>
them always inclined to revolt, and treat them accordingly. Quarter Troops among
them, who by their Insolence may <hi rend="italic">provoke</hi> the rising of Mobs, and by their Bullets
and Bayonets <hi rend="italic">suppress</hi> them. By this Means, like the Husband who uses his Wife ill
<hi rend="italic">from Suspicion,</hi> you may in Time convert your <hi rend="italic">Suspicions</hi> into <hi rend="italic">Realities.</hi></p>

<p>V. Remote Provinces must have <hi rend="italic">Governors,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Judges,</hi> to represent the Royal Person
and execute every where the delegated <hi rend="italic">Parts</hi> of his <hi rend="italic">Office</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Authority</hi>. You Ministers
know, that much of the Strength of Government depends on the <hi rend="italic">Opinion</hi> of the People;
and much of that Opinion on the Choice of Rulers placed immediately over them. If
you send them wise and good Men for Governors, who study the Interest of the
Colonists and advance their Prosperity, they will think their King wise and good and
that he wishes the Welfare of his Subjects. If you send them learned and upright Men
for judges, they will think him a Lover of Justice. This may attach your Provinces
more to his Government. You are therefore to be careful who you recommend for
those Offices. If you can find Prodigals who have ruined their Fortunes, broken
Gamesters or Stock-Jobbers, these may do well as <hi rend="italic">Governors;</hi> for they will probably be
rapacious and provoke the People by their Extortions. Wrangling Proctors and
petty-fogging Lawyers too are not amiss, for they will be forever disputing and
quarrelling with their little Parliaments, if withal, they should be ignorant, wrongheaded and insolent, so much the better.
Attorneys Clerks and Newgate Solicitors will do for <hi rend="italic">Chief-Justices,</hi> especially if they
hold their Places <hi rend="italic">during your Pleasure:</hi> And all will contribute to impress
those ideas of your Government that are proper for a People <hi rend="italic">you would wish to renounce it.</hi></p> 

<p>VI. To confirm these Impressions, and strike them deeper, whenever the Injured come to
the Capital with Complaints of Mal-administration, Oppression, or Injustice, punish
such Suitors with long Delay, enormous Expence, and a final Judgment in Favour of the
Oppressor. This will have an admirable Effect every Way. The Trouble of future
Complaints will be prevented, and Governors and Judges will be encouraged to
farther Acts of Oppression and Injustice; and thence the People may become more
disaffected, <hi rend="italic">and at length desperate.</hi></p>

<p>VII. When such Governors have crammed their Coffers, and made themselves so odious to
the People that they can no longer remain among them with Safety to their Persons,
recall and <hi rend="italic">reward</hi> them with Pensions. You may make them <hi rend="italic">Baronets</hi> too, if that
respectable Order should not think fit to resent it. All will contribute to encourage new
Governors in the same Practices, and make the supreme Government <hi rend="italic">detestable.</hi></p>

<p>VIII. If when you are engaged in War, your Colonies should vie in liberal Aids of Men and
Money against the common Enemy, upon your simple Requisition, and give far beyond
their Abilities, reflect, that a Penny taken from them by your Power is more honourable
to you than a Pound presented by their Benevolence. Despise therefore their
voluntary Grants, and resolve to harass them with novel Taxes. They will probably
complain to your Parliaments that they are taxed by a Body in which they have no
Representative, and that this is contrary to common Right. They will petition for
Redress. Let the Parliaments flout their Claims, reject their Petitions, refuse even to
suffer the reading of them, and treat the Petitioners with the utmost Contempt.
Nothing can have a better Effect, in producing the Alienation proposed; for though
many can forgive Injuries, <hi rend="italic">none ever forgave Contempt.</hi></p>

<p>IX. In laying these Taxes, never regard the heavy Burthens those remote People already
undergo, in defending their own Frontiers, supporting their own provincial Governments, making new Roads, building Bridges, Churches and other public Edifices,
which in old Countries have been done to your Hands by your Ancestors, but which
occasion constant Calls and Demands on the Purses of a new People. Forget
the <hi rend="italic">Restraints</hi> you lay on their Trade for <hi rend="italic">your own</hi> Benefit, and the advantage a
<hi rend="italic">Monopoly</hi> of this Trade gives your exacting Merchants. Think nothing of the Wealth
those Merchants and your Manufacturers acquire by the Colony Commerce; their
encreased Ability thereby to pay Taxes at home; their accumulating, in the Price of their
Commodities, most of those Taxes, and so levying them from their consuming
Customers: All this, and the Employment and Support of thousands of your Poor by
the Colonists, you are <hi rend="italic">intirely to forget</hi>. But remember to make your arbitrary Tax
more grievous to your Provinces, by public Declarations importing that your Power of
taxing them has <hi rend="italic">no limits,</hi> so that when you take from them without their Consent a
Shilling in the Pound, you have a clear Right to the other nineteen. This will probably
weaken every Idea of <hi rend="italic">Security in their Property,</hi> and convince them that under such a
Government <hi rend="italic">they have nothing they can call their own;</hi> which can scarce fail of
producing <hi rend="italic">the happiest Consequences!</hi></p>

<p>X. Possibly indeed some of them might still comfort themselves, and say, “Though we
have no Property, we have yet <hi rend="italic">something</hi> left that is valuable; we have constitutional
<hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> both of Person and of Conscience. This King, these Lords, and these
Commons, who it seems are too remote from us to know us and feel for us, cannot
take from us our <hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus</hi> Right, or our Right of Trial <hi rend="italic">by a Jury of our Neighbours:</hi>
They cannot deprive us of the Exercise of our Religion, alter our ecclesiastical
Constitutions, and compel us to be Papists if they please, or
Mahometans.” To annihilate this Comfort, begin by Laws to perplex their
Commerce with infinite regulations, impossible to be remembered and observed;
ordain Seizures of their Property for every Failure; take away the Trial of such
Property by Jury, and give it to arbitrary Judges of your own appointing and of the
lowest Characters in the Country, whose Salaries and Emoluments are to arise out of
the Duties or Condemnations, and whose Appointments are <hi rend="italic">during
Pleasure.</hi> Then let there be a formal Declaration of both Houses, that Opposition to your
Edicts is <hi rend="italic">Treason,</hi> and that Persons suspected of Treason in the Provinces may,
according to some obsolete Law, be seized and sent to the Metropolis of the Empire for
Trial; and pass an Act that those there charged with certain other Offences
shall be sent away in Chains from their Friends and Country to be tried in the same
Manner for Felony. Then erect a new Court of Inquisition among them, accompanied
by an armed Force, with Instructions to transport all such suspected Persons, to be
ruined by the Expence if they bring over Evidences to prove their Innocence, or be
found guilty and hanged if they can’t afford it. And lest the People should think you
cannot possibly go any farther, pass another solemn declaratory Act that “King, Lords,
and Commons had, hath, and of Right ought to have, full Power and Authority to make
Statutes of sufficient Force and Validity to bind the unrepresented Provinces IN ALL
CASES WHATSOEVER.” This will include <hi rend="italic">Spiritual</hi> with temporal; and taken together,
must operate wonderfully to your Purpose, by convincing them, that they are at present
under a Power something like that spoken of in the Scriptures, which can not only <hi rend="italic">kill their Bodies,</hi>
    but <hi rend="italic">damn their Souls</hi> to all Eternity, by compelling them, if it pleases, <hi rend="italic">to 
    worship the Devil.</hi></p>

<p>XI. To make your Taxes more odious, and more likely to procure Resistance, send from the
Capital a Board of Officers to superintend the Collection, composed of the most
<hi rend="italic">indiscrete, ill-bred</hi> and <hi rend="italic">insolent</hi>you can find. Let these have large Salaries out of the
extorted Revenue, and live in open grating Luxury upon the Sweat and Blood of the
Industrious, whom they are to worry continually with groundless and expensive
Prosecutions before the above-mentioned arbitrary Revenue-Judges, all <hi rend="italic">at the Cost of
the Party prosecuted</hi> tho’ acquitted, because <hi rend="italic">the King is to pay no Costs.</hi> Let these
Men <hi rend="italic">by your Order</hi> be exempted from all the common Taxes and Burthens of the
Province, though they and their Property are protected by its Laws. If any Revenue
Officers are <hi rend="italic">suspected</hi> of the least Tenderness for the People, discard them. If others
are justly complained of, protect and reward them. If any of the Under-officers behave
so as to provoke the People to drub them, promote those to better
Offices: This will encourage others to procure for themselves such profitable Drubbings,
by multiplying and enlarging such Provocations, and <hi rend="italic">all with work towards the End
you aim at.</hi></p>

<p>XII. Another Way to make your Tax odious, is to misapply the Produce of it. If it was originally
appropriated for the <hi rend="italic">Defence</hi> of the Provinces and the better Support of Government, and the
Administration of Justice where it may be <hi rend="italic">necessary,</hi> then apply none of it to that <hi rend="italic">Defence,</hi> but
bestow it where it is <hi rend="italic">not necessary,</hi> in augmented Salaries or Pensions to every Governor who has
distinguished himself by his Enmity to the People, and by calumniating them to their Sovereign.
This will make them pay it more unwillingly, and be more apt to quarrel with those that collect it,
<hi rend="italic">Purpose</hi> of making them <hi rend="italic">weary of your Government.</hi></p>

<p>XIII. If the people of any Province have been accustomed to support their own Governors and
Judges to Satisfaction, you are to apprehend that such Governors and Judges may be thereby
influenced to treat the People kindly, and to do them Justice. This is another Reason for applying
Part of that Revenue in larger Salaries to such Governors and Judges, given, as their Commissions
are, <hi rend="italic">during your Pleasure</hi> only, forbidding them to take any Salaries from their Provinces; that
thus the People may no longer hope any Kindness from their Governors, or (in Crown Cases) any
Justice from their Judges. And as the Money thus mis-applied in one Province is extorted from
all, probably <hi rend="italic">all will resent the Misapplication.</hi></p>

<p>XIV. If the Parliaments of your Provinces should dare to claim Rights or complain of your
Administration, order them to be harass'd with repeated <hi rend="italic">Dissolutions.</hi> If the same Men are
continually return'd by new Elections, adjourn their Meetings to some Country Village where they
cannoy be accommodated, and there keep them <hi rend="italic">during Pleasure;</hi> for this, you know, is your
PEROGATIVE; and an excellent one it is, as you manage it, to promote Discontents among the
People, diminish their Respect, and <hi rend="italic">increase their Disaffection.</hi></p>

<p>XV. Convert the brave honest Officers of your Navy into pimping Tide-waiters and Colony
Officers of the Customs. Let those who in Time of War fought gallantly in Defence of the
Commerce of their Countrymen, in Peace be taught to prey upon it. Let them learn to be
corrupted by great and real Smugglers; but (to shew their Diligence) scour with armed Boats
every Bay, Harbour, River, Creek, Cove or Nook throughout the Coast of your Colonies, stop and
detain every Coaster, every Wood-boat, every Fisherman, tumble their Cargoes, and even their
Ballast, inside out and upside down; and if a Penn'orth of Pins is found un-entered, let the Whole
be seized and confiscated. Thus shall the Trade of your Colonists suffer more from their Friends in
Time of Peace, than it did from their Enemies in War. Then let these Boats Crews land upon every
Farm in their Way, rob the Orchards, steal the Pigs and Poultry, and insult the Inhabitants. If the
Injured and exasperated Farmers, unable to procure other Justice, should attack the Agressors,
drub them and burn their Boats, you are to call this <hi rend="italic">High Treason</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rebellion,</hi> order Fleets
And Armies into their Country, and threaten to carry all the Offenders three thousand Miles to be
hang'd, drawn and quatered. <hi rend="italic">O! this will work admirably!</hi></p>


<p>XVI. If you are told of Discontents in your Colonies, never believe that they are general, or that
you have given Occasion for them; therfore do not think of applying any Remedy, or of changing
any offensive Measure. Redress no Greivance, lest they should be encouraged to demand the
Redress of some other Grievance. Grant no Request that is just and reasonable, lest they should
make another that is unreasonable. Take all your Informations of the State of the Colonies from
your Governors and Officers in Enmity with them. Encourage and reward these <hi rend="italic">Leasing-
makers;</hi> secrete their lying Accusations lest they should be confuted; but act upon them as the
clearest Evidence, and believe nothing you hear from the Friends of the People. Suppose all <hi rend="italic">their</hi>
Complaints to be invented and promoted by a few factious Demagogues, whom if you could catch
and hang, all would be quiet. Catch and hang a few of them accordingly; and the <hi rend="italic">Blood of the
Martyrs</hi> shall <hi rend="italic">work Miarcles</hi> in favour of your Purpose.</p>

<p>XVII. If you see <hi rend="italic">rival Nations</hi> rejoicing at the Prospect of your Disunion with your Provinces,
and endeavouring to promote it: If they translate, publish and applaud all the Complaints of your
discontented Colonists, at the same Time privately stimulating you to severer Measures; let not
that <hi rend="italic">alarm</hi> or offend you. Why should it? since you all mean <hi rend="italic">the same Thing.</hi></p>

<p>XVIII. If any Colony should at their own Charge erect a Fortress to secure their Port against
the Fleets of a foreign Enemy, get your Governor to betray that Fortress into your Hands. Never
think of playing what it cost the Country, for that would <hi rend="italic">look,</hi> at least, like some Regard for
Justice; but turn it into a Citadel to awe the Inhabitants and curb their Commerce. If they should
have lodged in such Fortress the very Arms they bought and used to aid you in your Conquests,
seize them all, 'twill provoke like <hi rend="italic">Ingratitude</hi> added to <hi rend="italic">Robbery.</hi> One admirable effect of these
Operations will be, to discourage every other Colony from erecting such Defences, and so their
and your Enemies may more easily invade them, to the great Disgrace of your Government, and of
course <hi rend="italic">the Furtherance of your Project.</hi></p>

<p>XIX. Send Armies into their Country under Pretence of protecting the Inhabitants; but instead
of garrisoning the Forsts on their Frontiers with those Troops, to prevent Incursions, demolish
those Forts, and order the Troops into the Heart of the Country, that the Savages may be
encouraged to attack the Frontiers, annd that the Troops may be protected by the Inhabitants: This
will seem to proceed from your Ill will or your Ignorance, and contribute farther to produce and
strengthen an Opinion among them, <hi rend="italic">that you are no longer fit to govern them.</hi></p>

<p>XX. Lastly, Invest the General of your Army in the Provinces with great and unconstitutional
Powers, and free him from the Controul of even your own Civil Governors. Let him have Troops
enow under his Command, with all the Fortresses in his Possession; and who knows but (like
some provincial Generals in the Roman Empire, and encouraged by the universal Discontent you
have produced) he may take it into his Head to set up for himself. If he should, and you have
carefully practised these few <hi rend="italic">excellent Rules</hi> of mine, take my Word for it, all the Provinces will
immediately join him, and you will that Day (if you have not done it sooner) get rid of the Trouble
of governing them, and all the <hi rend="italic">Plagues</hi> attending their <hi rend="italic">Commerce</hi> and Connection from
thenceforth and for ever.</p>

<p>Q. E. D.</p>
      </body>
</text>
</TEI>

