<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="" xml:id="franklin-dogood-3">
    <!-- Header / Metadata -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Silence Dogood 3</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender">
                        <desc>male</desc>
                    </trait>
                    
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <date when="1722">April 2, 1722</date>      
                            <roleName></roleName>
                            <affiliation></affiliation>
                            <country>United States of America</country>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#JOB" >
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0002-3544-2891">
                        <name ref="editors.xml#SB">
                            <surname>Brunstetter</surname>
                            <forename>Sara</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#SB"><forename>Sara </forename> <surname>Brunstetter</surname></name>   
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB"><forename>John </forename> <surname> O'Brien</surname></name>                  
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported
                        License </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80051828">
                                <name>
                                    <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                                    <surname>Franklin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">Silence Dogood</title>
                        <title type="sub">3</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher></publisher>
                            <date when="1722">1722</date>
                            <note resp="editors.xml#JOB"> 
                                
                            </note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>  
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="letter">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/> <!-- Single? --> 
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="mixed"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness type="prepared"/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7013445">Boston</name>
                    <time when="1722">1722</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary
                    sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of
                    the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities
                    and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p> 
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the
                        word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have
                        not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has been
                        indicated prior to the page beginning. </p> 
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p> 
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    April 30, 1722 [No. 3] <lb/><lb/>
                    To the Author of the <hi>New-England Courant</hi>. <lb/><lb/><lb/>
                    
                </head>
                <p>Sir.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>It is undoubtedly the Duty of all Persons to serve the Country they live in, according to their Abilities; yet I sincerely acknowledge, that I have hitherto been very deficient in this Particular; whether it was for want of Will or Opportunity, I will not at present stand to determine: Let it suffice, that I now take up a Resolution, to do for the future all that <hi>lies in my Way</hi> for the Service of my Countrymen.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I have from my Youth been <ref target="a001" corresp="n001">indefatigably</ref><note xml:id="n001" target="a001">Tirelessly. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> studious to gain and treasure up in my Mind all useful and desireable Knowledge, especially such as tends to improve the Mind, and enlarge the Understanding: And as I have found it very beneficial to me, I am not without Hopes, that communicating my small Stock in this Manner, by <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">Peace-meal</ref><note xml:id="n002" target="a002">Piece by piece, or in small bits. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> to the Publick, may be at least in some Measure useful.</p><lb/><lb/>
         <p>I am very sensible that it is impossible for me, or indeed any one Writer to please all Readers at once. Various Persons have different Sentiments; and that which is pleasant and delightful to one, gives another a Disgust. He that would (in this Way of Writing) please all, is under a Necessity to make his Themes almost as numerous as his Letters. He must one while be merry and diverting, then more solid and serious; one while sharp and satyrical, then (to <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">mollify</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Soften; make tender. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> that) be sober and religious; at one Time let the Subject be Politicks, then let the next Theme be Love: Thus will every one, one Time or other find some thing agreeable to his own Fancy, and in his Turn be delighted.</p><lb/><lb/>
        <p>According to this Method I intend to proceed, bestowing now and then a few gentle <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">Reproofs</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">Censures or Rebukes; subject to blame or scorn. Source: Oxford English Dictionary</note> on those who deserve them, not forgetting at the same time to applaud those whose Actions merit Commendation. And here I must not forget to invite the ingenious Part of your Readers, particularly those of my own Sex to enter into a Correspondence with me, assuring them, that their Condescension in this Particular shall be received as a Favour, and accordingly acknowledged.</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>I think I have now finish'd the Foundation, and I intend in my next to begin to raise the Building. Having nothing more to write at present, I must make the usual excuse in such Cases, of <hi>being in haste</hi>, assuring you that I speak from my Heart when I call my self, The most humble and obedient of all the Servants your Merits have acquir'd,</p><lb/><lb/>
                <p>SILENCE DOGOOD.</p><lb/><lb/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>    
</TEI>  