<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="remarks-concerning-the-savages">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Remarks Concerning the Savages of North-America</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79043402">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp> Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup </resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xmlAJB"> Austin Benson
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder> National Endowment for the Humanities </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Literature in Context </publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> 434-924-7105 </addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported Licence </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- this markup is based on a digital edition from Founders Online, 
                    https://founders.archives.gov/documents/Franklin/01-41-02-0280. 
                    The digital text lists two editions, an autograph copy by Franklin,
                    and the first edition of the printed track. It is unclear which edition
                    the digital text is based on. I will supply the imprint description
                    provided by the digital edition, but the editors here might want to 
                    supply additional information -->
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                            <surname>Franklin</surname>
                            <addName></addName>
                        </author>
                        <title> Remarks Concerning the Savages of North-America </title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7617217"> Passy </placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher> Passy Press </publisher>
                            <date when="1784">1784</date>
                            <note></note>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent/>
                        <biblScope/>
                        <!-- the above two elements are included in case a physical edition
                            of the text is consulted at a later date. -->
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="essay">
                <channel mode="w">Print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7617217">Passy</name>
                    <time when="1784">1784</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature of the 18th century. This project is funded by the National Endowment
                    for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and
                    Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- blank space for insertion of the <revisionDesc> element -->

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-07-15" who="editors"></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <!-- & and &c. are rendered as 'and' and 'etc.', respectively, and marked 
            with a comment indicating the original reading -->
        <front>
            <pb n=""/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart> REMARKS <lb/> CONCERNING THE SAVAGES <lb/> OF NORTH-AMERICA
                    </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor/>
                <docImprint></docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p> SAVAGES we call them, because their manners differ from ours, which we think the
                    Perfection of Civility; they think the same of theirs. </p>
                <p> Perhaps if we could examine the manners of different Nations with Impartiality,
                    we should find no People so rude as to be without Rules of Politeness; nor any
                    so polite as not to have some remains of Rudeness. </p>
                <p> The <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Men, when young, are Hunters and Warriors; when old, Counsellors; for
                    all their Government is by the Counsel or Advice of the Sages; there is no
                    Force, there are no Prisons, no Officers to compel Obedience, or inflict
                    Punishment. Hence they generally study Oratory; the best Speaker having the most
                    Influence. The <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Women till the Ground, dress the Food, nurse and bring up
                    the Children, and<!-- & --> preserve and<!-- & --> hand down to Posterity the
                    Memory of Public Transactions. These Employments of Men and Women are accounted
                    natural and honorable. Having few Artificial Wants, they have abundance of
                    Leisure for Improvement by Conversation. Our laborious manner of Life compared
                    with theirs, they esteem slavish and base; and the Learning on which we value
                    ourselves; they regard as frivolous and useless. An Instance of this occurred at
                    the Treaty of Lancaster in Pennsylvania, Anno 1744, between the Government of
                    Virginia and<!-- & --> the Six Nations. After the principal Business was
                    settled, the Commissioners from Virginia acquainted the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s by a Speech,
                    that there was at Williamsburg a College with a Fund for Educating <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Youth,
                    and that if the Chiefs of the Six-Nations would send down half a dozen of their
                    sons to that College, the Government would take Care that they should be well
                    provided for, and instructed in all the Learning of the white People. It is one
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Rules of Politeness not to answer a public Proposition the same
                    day that it is made; they think it would be treating it as a light Matter; and
                    that they show it Respect by taking time to consider it, as of a Matter
                    important. They therefore deferred their Answer till the day following; when
                    their Speaker began by expressing their deep Sense of the Kindness of the
                    Virginia Government, in making them that Offer; for we know, says he, that you
                    highly esteem the kind of Learning taught in those Colleges, and that the
                    Maintenance of our Young Men while with you, would be very expensive to you. We
                    are convinced therefore that you mean to do us Good by your Proposal, and we
                    thank you heartily. But you who are wise must know, that different Nations have
                    different Conceptions of things; and you will therefore not take it amiss, if
                    our Ideas of this Kind of Education happen not to be the same with yours. We
                    have had some Experience of it: Several of our Young People were formerly
                    brought up at the Colleges of the Northern Provinces; they were instructed in
                    all your Sciences; but when they came back to us they were bad Runners, ignorant
                    of every means of living in the Woods, unable to bear either Cold or Hunger,
                    knew neither how to build a Cabin, take a Deer, or kill an Enemy, spoke our
                    Language imperfectly; were therefore neither fit for Hunters, Warriors, or
                    Counsellors; they were totally good for nothing. We are however not the less
                    obliged by your kind Offer, tho’ we decline accepting it; and to show our
                    grateful Sense of it, if the Gentlemen of Virginia will send us a dozen of their
                    Sons, we will take great Care of their Education, instruct them in all we know,
                    and make Men of them. </p>
                <p> Having frequent Occasions to hold public Councils, they have acquired great
                    Order and Decency in conducting them. The old Men sit in the foremost Ranks, the
                    Warriors in the next, and the Women and Children in the hindmost. The Business
                    of the Women is to take exact notice of what passes, imprint it in their
                    Memories, for they have no Writing, and communicate it to their Children. They
                    are the Records of the Council, and they preserve Tradition of the Stipulations
                    in Treaties a hundred Years back, which when we compare with our Writings we
                    always find exact. He that would speak, rises. The rest observe a profound
                    Silence. When he has finish’d and sits down, they leave him five or six Minutes
                    to recollect, that if he has omitted any thing he intended to say, or has any
                    thing to add, he may rise again and deliver it. To interrupt another, even in
                    common Conversation, is reckoned highly indecent. How different this is from the
                    Conduct of a polite British House of Commons, where scarce a day passes without
                    some Confusion that makes the Speaker hoarse in calling to order; and how
                    different from the mode of Conversation in many polite Companies of Europe,
                    where if you do not deliver your Sentence with great Rapidity, you are cut off
                    in the middle of it by the impatient Loquacity of those you converse with,
                    and<!-- & --> never suffer’d to finish it. </p>
                <p> The Politeness of these Savages in Conversation is indeed carried to excess,
                    since it does not permit them to contradict, or deny the Truth of what is
                    asserted in their Presence. By this means they indeed avoid Disputes, but then
                    it becomes difficult to know their Minds, or what Impression you make upon them.
                    The Missionaries who have attempted to convert them to Christianity, all
                    complain of this as one of the great Difficulties of their Mission. The <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s
                    hear with Patience the Truths of the Gospel explained to them, and give their
                    usual Tokens of Assent and Approbation: you would think they were convinced. No
                    such Matter. It is mere Civility. </p>
                <p> A Suedish Minister having assembled the Chiefs of the Sasquehanah <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s, made
                    a Sermon to them, acquainting them with the principal historical Facts on which
                    our Religion is founded, such as the Fall of our first Parents by Eating an
                    Apple, the Coming of Christ to repair the Mischief, his Miracles and Suffering,
                    etc.<!-- &c. --> When he had finished, an <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Orator stood up to thank him.
                    What you have told us, says he, is all very good. It is indeed bad to eat
                    Apples. It is better to make them all into Cyder. We are much obliged by your
                    Kindness in coming so far to tell us those things which you have heard from your
                    Mothers. In return I will tell you some of those we have heard from ours. </p>
                <p> In the Beginning our Fathers had only the Flesh of Animals to subsist on, and if
                    their Hunting was unsuccessful, they were starving. Two of our young Hunters
                    having killed a Deer, made a Fire in the Woods to broil some Parts of it. When
                    they were about to satisfy their Hunger, they beheld a beautiful young Woman
                    descend from the Clouds, and seat herself on that Hill which you see yonder
                    among the blue Mountains. They said to each other, it is a Spirit that perhaps
                    has smelt our broiling Venison, and<!-- & --> wishes to eat of it: let us offer
                    some to her. They presented her with the Tongue: She was pleased with the Taste
                    of it, and<!-- & --> said, your Kindness shall be rewarded. Come to this Place
                    after thirteen Moons, and you shall find something that will be of great Benefit
                    in nourishing you and your Children to the latest Generations. They did so, and
                    to their Surprise found Plants they had never seen before, but which from that
                    ancient time have been constantly cultivated among us to our great Advantage.
                    Where her right Hand had touch’d the Ground, they found Maize; where her left
                    Hand had touch’d it, they found Kidney-beans; and where her Backside had sat on
                    it, they found Tobacco. The good Missionary, disgusted with this idle Tale,
                    said, what I delivered to you were sacred Truths; but what you tell me is mere
                    Fable, Fiction and <!-- & --> Falsehood. The <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> offended, reply’d, my
                    Brother, it seems your Friends have not done you Justice in your Education; they
                    have not well instructed you in the Rules of common Civility. You saw that we
                    who understand and practise those Rules, believed all your Stories; why do you
                    refuse to believe ours? </p>
                <p> When any of them come into our Towns, our People are apt to croud round them,
                    gaze upon them, and incommode them where they desire to be private; this they
                    esteem great Rudeness, and the Effect of want of Instruction in the Rules of
                    Civility and good Manners. We have, say they, as much Curiosity as you, and when
                    you come into our Towns we wish for Opportunities of looking at you; but for
                    this purpose we hide ourselves behind Bushes where you are to pass, and never
                    intrude ourselves into your Company. </p>
                <p> Their Manner of entring one anothers Villages has likewise its Rules. It is
                    reckon’d uncivil in travelling Strangers to enter a Village abruptly, without
                    giving Notice of their Approach. Therefore as soon as they arrive within
                    hearing, they stop and hollow, remaining there till invited to enter. Two old
                    Men usually come out to them, and lead them in. There is in every Village a
                    vacant Dwelling, called the Strangers House. Here they are placed, while the old
                    Men go round from Hut to Hut acquainting the Inhabitants that Strangers are
                    arrived who are probably hungry and weary; and every one sends them what he can
                    spare of Victuals and Skins to repose on. When the Strangers are refresh’d,
                    Pipes and<!-- & --> Tobacco are brought; and then, but not before, Conversation
                    begins, with Enquiries who they are, whither bound, what News, etc.<!-- &c. -->
                    and it usually ends with Offers of Service, if the Strangers have Occasion of
                    Guides or any Necessaries for continuing their Journey; and nothing is exacted
                    for the Entertainment. </p>
                <p> The same Hospitality, esteemed among them as a principal Virtue, is practiced by
                    private Persons; of which Conrad Weiser, our Interpreter, gave me the following
                    Instance. He had been naturaliz’d among the Six-Nations, and spoke well the
                    Mohock Language. In going thro’ the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Country, to carry a Message from our
                    Governor to the Council at Onondaga, he call’d at the Habitation of Canassetego,
                    an old Acquaintance, who embraced him, spread Furs for him to sit on, placed
                    before him some boiled Beans and Venison, and mixed some Rum and Water for his
                    Drink. When he was well refresh’d, and had lit his Pipe, Canassetego began to
                    converse with him, ask’d how he had fared the many Years since they had seen
                    each other, whence he then came, what occasioned the Journey, etc.<!-- &c. -->
                    etc.<!-- &c. --> Conrad answered all his Questions; and when the Discourse began
                    to flag, the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>, to continue it, said, Conrad, you have liv’d long among the
                    white People, and know something of their Customs; I have been sometimes at
                    Albany, and have observed that once in seven Days, they shut up their Shops and
                    assemble all in the great House; tell me, what is it for? what do they do there?
                    They meet there, says Conrad, to hear and<!-- & --> learn good things. I do not
                    doubt, says the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>, that they tell you so; they have told me the same; but I
                    doubt the Truth of what they say, and<!-- & --> I will tell you my Reasons. I
                    went lately to Albany to sell my Skins, and<!-- & --> buy Blankets, Knives,
                    Powder, Rum, etc.<!-- &c. --> You know I used generally to deal with Hans
                    Hanson; but I was a little inclined this time to try some other Merchants.
                    However I called first upon Hans, and ask’d him what he would give for Beaver;
                    He said he could not give more than four Shillings a Pound; but, says he, I
                    cannot talk on Business now; this is the Day when we meet together to learn good
                    things, and I am going to the Meeting. So I thought to myself since I cannot do
                    any Business to day, I may as well go to the Meeting too; and I went with him.
                    There stood up a Man in black, and began to talk to the People very angrily. I
                    did not understand what he said; but perceiving that he looked much at me,
                    and<!-- & --> at Hanson, I imagined he was angry at seeing me there; so I went
                    out, sat down near the House, struck Fire and<!-- & --> lit my Pipe; waiting
                    till the Meeting should break up. I thought too, that the Man had mentioned
                    something of Beaver, and I suspected it might be the Subject of their Meeting.
                    So when they came out I accosted any [my] Merchant; well Hans, says I, I hope
                    you have agreed to give more than four Shillings a Pound. No, says he, I cannot
                    give so much. I cannot give more than three Shillings and six Pence. I then
                    spoke to several other Dealers, but they all sung the same Song, three
                    and<!-- & --> six Pence, three and<!-- & --> six Pence. This made it clear to me
                    that my Suspicion was right; and that whatever they pretended of Meeting to
                    learn good things, the real Purpose was to consult, how to cheat <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s in the
                    Price of Beaver. Consider but a little, Conrad, and you must be of my Opinion.
                    If they met so often to learn good things, they would certainly have learnt some
                    before this time. But they are still ignorant. You know our Practice. If a white
                    Man in travelling thro’ our Country, enters one of our Cabins, we all treat him
                    as I treat you; we dry him if he is wet, we warm him if he is cold, and give him
                    Meat and<!-- & --> Drink that he may allay his Thirst and Hunger, and<!-- & -->
                    we spread soft Furs for him to rest and<!-- & --> sleep on: We demand nothing in
                    return*. But if I go into a white Man’s House at Albany, and ask for Victuals
                    and <!-- & --> Drink, they say, where is your Money? and if I have none, they
                    say, Get out, you <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Dog. You see they have not yet learnt those little good
                    things, that we need no Meetings to be instructed in, because our Mothers taught
                    them to us when we were Children. And therefore, it is impossible their
                    Meetings, should be as they say for any such purpose, or have any such Effect;
                    they are only to contrive the Cheating of <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s in the Price of Beaver. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
