<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="chopin-hour">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"The Story of an Hour"</title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n80008080">
                        <name ref="chopin.xml">
                            <forename>Kate</forename>
                            <surname>Chopin</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName>
                        <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">
                            <surname>Buford</surname>
                            <forename>Nial</forename>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#UVAstudentsstaff">Students and Staff of The University of
                        Virginia</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#NXB">Nial Buford</name>
                         
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>22204-4121</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>jobrien@virginia.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>lic.open.anthology@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Published by Literature
                        in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title>"The Story of An Hour"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName/>
                        </author>
                        <title>Vogue</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7007567">New York</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Arthur Baldwin Turnure</publisher>
                            <date when="1839">1894</date>                            
                            <note>Page images are drawn from an 1894 copy of <hi rend="italic">Vogue</hi>, 
                                sourced from the <ref target="https://mohistory.org/collections/item/resource:180118?page=1"> 
                                Missouri Historical Society.</ref> 
                                Changes made by the author for the 1895 publication of the story in 
                                <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Life</hi> have been reflected in this text.</note>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="story">
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fiction"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="entertain" degree="high"/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="low"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="4003761"> United States</name>
                    <time from="1850" to="1900">Nineteenth Century</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources
                    relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 18th,
                    19th, and 20th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
                    developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with
                        links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge,
                        defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you
                        notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.
                    </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation is retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where
                        possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023" who="editors.xml#NB">First pass xml with page image sources</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <titlePart>
                   THE STORY OF AN HOUR</titlePart>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <docAuthor>By Kate Chopin</docAuthor>
                <docImprint/>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Knowing that Mrs. Mallard was afflicted with a heart trouble, great care was taken to
                    break to her as gently as possible the news of her husband's death.</p>
                <p>It was her sister Josephine who told her, in broken sentences; veiled hints that revealed
                    in half concealing. Her husband's friend Richards was there, too, near her. It was he who
                    had been in the newspaper office when intelligence of the railroad disaster was received,
                    with Brently Mallard's name leading the list of "killed." He had only taken the time to
                    assure himself of its truth by a second telegram, and had hastened to forestall any less
                    careful, less tender friend in bearing the sad message.</p>
                <p>She did not hear the story as many women have heard the same, with a paralyzed inability
                    to accept its significance. She wept at once, with sudden, wild abandonment, in her
                    sister's arms. When the storm of grief had spent itself she went away to her room alone.
                    She would have no one follow her.</p>
                <p>There stood, facing the open window, a comfortable, roomy arm-chair. Into this she sank,
                    pressed down by a physical exhaustion that haunted her body and seemed to reach into her
                    soul.</p>
                <p>She could see in the open square before her house the tops of trees that were all aquiver
                    with the new spring life. The delicious breath of rain was in the air. In the street below
                    a pedler was crying his wares. The notes of a distant song which some one was singing
                    reached her faintly, and countless sparrows were twittering in the eaves.</p>
                <p>There were patches of blue sky showing here and there through the clouds that had met and
                    piled one above the other in the west facing her window.</p>
                <p>She sat with her head thrown back upon the cushion of the chair, quite motionless, except
                    when a sob came up into her throat and shook her, as a child who has cried itself to sleep
                    continues to sob in its dreams.</p>
                <p>She was young, with a fair, calm face, whose lines bespoke repression and even a certain
                    strength. But now there was a dull stare in her eyes, whose gaze was fixed away off yonder
                    on one of those patches of blue sky. It was not a glance of reflection, but rather
                    indicated a suspension of intelligent thought.</p>
                <p>There was something coming to her and she was waiting for it, fearfully. What was it? She
                    did not know; it was too subtle and elusive to name. But she felt it, creeping out of the
                    sky, reaching toward her through the sounds, the scents, the color that filled the air. </p>
                <p>Now her bosom rose and fell tumultuously. She was beginning to recognize this thing that
                    was approaching to possess her, and she was striving to beat it back with her will - as
                    powerless as her two white slender hands would have been. </p>
                    <p>
                    When she abandoned herself a little whispered word escaped her slightly parted lips. She said it over and over under
                    her breath: "free, free, free!" The vacant stare and the look of terror that had followed
                    it went from her eyes. They stayed keen and bright. Her pulses beat fast, and the coursing
                    blood warmed and relaxed every inch of her body. </p>
                <p>She did not stop to ask if it were or were not a monstrous joy that held her. A clear and
                    exalted perception enabled her to dismiss the suggestion as trivial. </p>                    
                    <p>She knew that she would weep again when she saw the kind, tender hands folded in death; the face that had
                    never looked save with love upon her, fixed and gray and dead. But she saw beyond that
                    bitter moment a long procession of years to come that would belong to her absolutely. And
                    she opened and spread her arms out to them in welcome. </p>
                <p>There would be no one to live for her during those coming years; she would live for herself.
                    There would be no powerful will bending hers in that blind persistence with which men and
                    women believe they have a right to impose a private will upon a fellow-creature. A kind
                    intention or a cruel intention made the act seem no less a crime as she looked upon it in
                    that brief moment of illumination. </p>
                <p>And yet she had loved him - sometimes. Often she had not. What did it matter! What could
                    love, the unsolved mystery, count for in face of this possession of self-assertion
                    which she suddenly recognized as the strongest impulse of her being! </p>
                <p>"Free! Body and soul free!" she kept whispering. </p>
                <p>Josephine was kneeling before the closed door with her lips to the keyhold, imploring for
                    admission. "Louise, open the door! I beg; open the door - you will make yourself ill. What
                    are you doing, Louise? For heaven's sake open the door." </p>
                <p>"Go away. I am not making myself ill." No; she was drinking in a very elixir of life
                    through that open window. </p>
                <p>Her fancy was running riot along those days ahead of her. Spring days, and summer days,
                    and all sorts of days that would be her own. She breathed a quick prayer that life might
                    be long. It was only yesterday she had thought with a shudder that life might be long. </p>
                <p>She arose at length and opened the door to her sister's importunities. There was a
                    feverish triumph in her eyes, and she carried herself unwittingly like a goddess of
                    Victory. She clasped her sister's waist, and together they descended the stairs. Richards
                    stood waiting for them at the bottom. </p>
                <p>Some one was opening the front door with a latch key. It was Brently Mallard who entered,
                    a little travel-stained, composedly carrying his grip-sack and umbrella. He had been far
                    from the scene of accident, and did not even know there had been one. He stood amazed
                    at Josephine's piercing cry; at Richard's quick motion to screen him from the view of his
                    wife. </p>
                <p>When the doctors came they said she had died of heart disease - of joy that kills.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div> </div>
        </back>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
