<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LiteratureInContext/LiC-data/development/schema/LiC_schema_4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stuart-articles">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> 
                    Articles of Peace Between the Most Serene and Mighty Prince Charles II and Several Indian Kings and Queens ["The Treaty of Middle Plantation"]
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName type="lcnaf" key="n79074258">
                        <name>
                            <forename>Charles</forename>
                            <surname>Stuart</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <persName type="orcid" key="0000-0001-6453-8721">
                        <name>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                        </name>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, and markup</resp>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#AJB">Austin Benson</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#JOB">John O'Brien</name>
                    <name ref="editors.xml#TH">Tonya Howe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                
                <funder> National Endowment for the Humanities </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine> University of Virginia Department of English </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Bryan Hall 219 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> PO Box 400121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> Charlottesville, VA 22904-4121 </addrLine>
                    <addrLine> 434-924-7105 </addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by
                        Literature in Context under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0
                        Unported Licence </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <forename>Charles</forename>
                            <surname>Stuart</surname>
                        </author>
                        <title>ARTICLES OF PEACE Between The Most Serene and Mighty PRINCE CHARLES
                            II. By the Grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland,
                            Defender of the Faith, etc. And Several Indian Kings and Queens, etc.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed by John Bill, Christopher Barker, Thomas Newcomb and
                                Henry Hills, Printers to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty.</publisher>
                            <date when="1677">1677</date>
                            <note>The information in this edition has been augmented by a PDF of the first edition at <ref target="https://digitalarchive.wm.edu/bitstream/handle/10288/16654/ArticlesOfPeace.pdf">https://digitalarchive.wm.edu/bitstream/handle/10288/16654/ArticlesOfPeace.pdf</ref></note>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent> </extent>
                        <biblScope> </biblScope>
                        <!-- the above two elements are listed in the template, but since this edition is adapted from a TEI markup rather than a physical edition, they aren't necessary to fill out . . . yet -->
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation/>
            <textDesc n="essay">
                <channel mode="w">Print</channel>
                <constitution type="single"/>
                <derivation type="original"/>
                <domain/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction/>
                <preparedness/>
                <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name type="tgn" key="7011781">London</name>
                    <time when="1677">1677</time>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of the <hi rend="italic">Literature in Context</hi>
                    project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of
                    primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American
                    literature. This project is funded by the National Endowment
                    for the Humanities and developed by faculty and students at The University of Virginia and
                    Marymount University. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources,
                        with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common
                        knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable
                        sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact
                        lic.open.anthology@gmail.com. </p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been
                        silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
                </normalization>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of
                        the word.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers
                        have not. Where pages break in the middle of a word, the complete word has
                        been indicated prior to the page beginning.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <correction>
                    <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions,
                        where possible. See the Sources section.</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcnaf">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcc">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Classification</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="tgn">
                    <bibl>Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="orcid">
                    <bibl>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <!-- blank space for insertion of the <revisionDesc> element -->

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-8-10" who="editors.xml#JOB"></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[Title Page]" facs="pageImages/Stuart-title.jpg"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart><ref target="treaty_"
                        corresp="treaty">ARTICLES <lb/> OF <lb/> PEACE <lb/> Between <lb/> The Most Serene
                        and Mighty PRINCE <lb/> CHARLES II.</ref> <lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart>By the Grace of God, <lb/> King of England, Scotland, France and
                        Ireland, <lb/> Defender of the Faith, etc. <lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart>And Several <lb/> <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens, etc. <lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart> Concluded the 29th day of May, 1677. <lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart>Published by his Majesties Command.<lb/></titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor/>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>
                        <placeName type="tgn" key="7011781">London,<lb/></placeName>
                    </pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed by <persName>John Bill,</persName>
                        <persName>Christopher Barker,</persName>
                        <persName>Thomas Newcomb</persName><lb/> and <persName>Henry Hills,</persName>
                        Printers to the Kings<lb/> Most Excellent Majesty <lb/></publisher>           
                <docDate>1677.</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="3" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p3.jpg"/>
                <p> Articles of Peace between the most Mighty Prince, and our Dread Sovereign Lord
                    CHARLES the Second, by the Grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and
                    Ireland, Defender of the Faith, etc. And the several <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens,
                    etc. Assenters and Subscribers hereunto, made and concluded at the Camp at
                    Middle Plantation the Twenty ninth day of May 1677. being the day of the most
                    <ref target="birthday_"
                        corresp="birthday">happy Birth and Restauration of our said Sovereign Lord</ref>, and in the Nine and twentieth Year of His Majesties Reign, By the Right Honourable Herbert Jefferies
                    Esquire, Lieutenant Governour of His Majesties Colony of Virginia. </p>
                <p> Present, </p>
                <p> The Honourable Sir John Berry Knight, and Francis Morison Esq; His most Sacred
                    Majesties Comissioners appointed under the Great Seal of England for the Affairs
                    of Virginia, </p>
                <p> And The Honourable Council of State of the said Colony. </p>
                <p> Whereas His most Sacred Majesty hath of His Own Royal Grace and meer Motion
                    Intrusted to my Care and Endeavours the<pb n="4" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p4.jpg"/> Renewing, Management, and
                    Concluding a good Peace with the Neighbour <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s: In Order whereunto (with the
                    Advice and Assistance of the Honourable Sir John Berry Knight, and Francis
                    Morison Esquire) I have caused to be drawn up these ensuing Articles and
                    Overtures, for the firm Grounding, and sure Establishment of a good and just
                    Peace with the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s. And that it may be a Secure and Lasting one
                    (Founded upon the strong Pillars of Reciprocal Justice) by Confirming to them
                    their Just Rights, and by Redress of their Wrongs and Injuries, That so the
                    great God (who is a God of Peace, and lover of Justice) may uphold and prosper
                    this our Mutual League and Amity, It is hereby Concluded, Consented to, and
                    mutually Agreed, as followeth; </p>
                <pb n="5" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p5.jpg"/>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub">Artic. I.</head>
                <p> That the respective <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens do from henceforth acknowledge to
                    have their immediate Dependency on, and own all Subjection to the Great King of
                    England, our now Dread Sovereign, His Heirs and Sucessors, when they pay their
                    Tribute to His Majesties Governour for the time being. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> II. </head>
                <p> That thereupon the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens and their Subjects, shall hold
                    their Lands, and have the same Confirmed to them and their Posterity, by Patent
                    under the Seal of this His Majesties Colony, without any Fee, Gratuity or Reward
                    for the same, in such sort, and in as free and firm manner as others His
                    Majesties Subjects have and enjoy their Lands and Possessions, paying<pb n="6" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p6.jpg"/>
                    yearly for and in lieu of a Quit Rent, or Acknowledgment for the same, onely
                    Three <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Arrows. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> III. </head>
                <p> That all <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s who are in Amity with Us, and have not Land sufficient to Plant
                    upon, be (upon Information) forthwith provided for, and Land laid out and
                    Confirmed to them as aforesaid, never to be disturbed therein, or taken from
                    them, so long as they own, keep and maintain their due Obedience and Subjection
                    to His Majesty, His Governour and Government, and Amity and Friendship towards
                    the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> IV. </head>
                <p> Whereas by the mutual Discontents, Complaints, Jealousies and Fears of <hi rend="italic">English</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s, occasioned by the Violent Intrusions of divers <hi rend="italic">English</hi> into their
                    Lands, forcing the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s by way of Revenge, to kill the Cattel and Hogs of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>,<pb n="7" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p7.jpg"/>
                    whereby Offence and Injuries being given and done on
                    both sides, the Peace of this His Majesties Colony hath been much disturbed, and
                    the late unhappy Rebellion by this means (in a great measure) begun and
                    fomented, which hath Involved this Countrey into so much Ruine and Misery: For
                    prevention of which Injuries and evil consequences (as much as possibly we may)
                    for time to come; It is hereby Concluded and Established, That no <hi rend="italic">English</hi> shall
                    Seat or Plant nearer than Three miles of any <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Town; and whosoever hath
                    made, or shall make any Incroachment upon their Lands, shall be removed from
                    thence, and proceeded against as by the former Peace made, when the Honourable
                    Colonel Francis Morison was Governour, and the Act of Assembly grounded
                    thereupon, is Provided and Enacted. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> V. </head>
                <p> That the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s be well Secured and Defended in their Persons, Goods and Properties,<pb n="8" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p8.jpg"/> 
                    against all hurts and injuries of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>; and
                    that upon any breach or violation, hereof the aggrieved <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s do in the first
                    place repair and Address themselves to the Governour, acquainting him therewith
                    (without rashly and suddenly betaking themselves to any Hostile course for
                    Satisfaction) who will Inflict such Punishment on the wilful Infringers hereof,
                    as the Laws of England or this Countrey permit, and as if such hurt or injury
                    had been done to any <hi rend="italic">English</hi>man; which is but just and reasonable, they owning
                    themselves to be under the Allegiance of His most Sacred Majesty. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> VI. </head>
                <p> That no <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> King or Queen be Imprisoned without a special Warrant from His
                    Majesties Governour and Two of the Council, and that no other <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> be
                    Imprisoned without a Warrant from a Justice of Peace, upon sufficient cause of
                    Commitment </p></div>
                <pb n="9" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p9.jpg"/>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> VII. </head>
                <p> That the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s have and enjoy their wonted conveniences of Oystering,
                    Fishing, and gathering <ref target="tuckahoe_"
                        corresp="tuckahoe">Tuchahoe</ref>, <ref target="curtenemons_"
                            corresp="curtenemons">Curtenemons</ref>, Wild Oats, Rushes, <ref target="puckoone_"
                                corresp="puckoone">Puckoone</ref>, or
                    any thing else (for their natural support) not useful to the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, upon the
                    <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Dividends; Always provided they first repair to some Publick Magistrate
                    of good Repute, and inform him of their number and business, who shall not
                    refuse them a Certificate upon this or any other Lawful occasion, so that they
                    make due return thereof when they come back, and go directly home about their
                    business, without wearing or carrying any manner of Weapon, or lodging under any
                    <hi rend="italic">English</hi>mans Dwelling-house one night. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> VIII. </head>
                <p> That no Foreign <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> be suffered to come to any <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Plantation without a
                    friendly neighbor <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> in his company with such<pb n="10" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p10.jpg"/> Certificate as
                    aforesaid: and no <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> King is to refuse to send a safe Conduct with the
                    Foreigner, upon any Lawful occasion of his coming in, and that no <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> do
                    paint or disguise themselves when they come in. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> IX. </head>
                <p> That all <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens Tributary to the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, having notice of any
                    March of strange <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s near the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Quarters or Plantations, do forthwith
                    repair to some one of the next Officers of the Militia, and acquaint him of
                    their Nation, number, and design, and which way they bend their course. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> X. </head>
                <p> That if necessary, a convenient Party be presently sent out by the next Colonel
                    of the Militia, to Aid, Strengthen, and joyn with our friendly <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s against
                    any Foreign Attempt, Incursion or Depredation upon the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Towns. </p></div>
                <pb n="11" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p11.jpg"/>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XI. </head>
                <p> That every <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> fit to bear Arms, of the Neighbouring Nations in Peace with
                    us, have such quantity of Powder and Shot allotted him, as the Right Honourable
                    the Governour shall think sufficient on any occasion, and that such numbers of
                    them be ready to go out with out Forces upon any March against the Enemy, and to
                    receive such Pay for their good Services, as shall be thought fit. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XII. </head>
                <p> That each <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> King and Queen have equal Power to Govern their own People, and
                    none to have greater Power then other, Except the Queen of Pamunkey, to whom
                    several scattered Nations do now again own their ancient Subjection, and are
                    agreed to come in and Plant themselves under her Power and Government; Who with
                    her, are also hereby included into this present<pb n="12" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p12.jpg"/> League and Treaty of
                    Peace, and are to keep and observe the same towards the said Queen in all
                    things, as her Subjects, as well as towards the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XIII. </head>
                <p> That no person whatsoever shall entertain or keep any Neighbouring <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> as
                    Servant, or otherwise, but by Licence of the Governour, and to be upon
                    Obligation answerable for all Injuries and Damages by him or them happening to
                    be done to any <hi rend="italic">English</hi>. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XIV. </head>
                <p> That no <hi rend="italic">English</hi> harbour or entertain any Vagrant or Runaway <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>, but convey
                    him home by way of Pass, from Justice to Justice to his own Town, under Penalty
                    of paying so much per day for harbouring him, as by the Law for entertaining of
                    Runaways is recoverable. </p></div>
                <pb n="13" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p13.jpg"/>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XV. </head>
                <p> That no <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> (of those in Amity with us) shall serve for any longer time then
                    <hi rend="italic">English</hi> of the like Ages should serve by Act of Assembly, and shall not be sold
                    as Slaves. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XVI. </head>
                <p> That every <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> King and Queen in the Moneth of March every year, with some of
                    their Great Men, shall tender their Obedience to the Right Honourable His
                    Majesties Governour at the place of his Residence, whereever it shall be, and
                    then and there pay the accustomed Tribute of Twenty Beaver Skins to the
                    Governour, and also their Quit-Rent aforesaid, in acknowledgment they hold their
                    Crowns and Lands of the Great King of England. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XVII. </head>
                <p> That due care be had and taken that those <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens, their Great
                    Men and Attendants that come on any Publick<pb n="14" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p14.jpg"/> Business to the Right
                    Honourable the Governour, Council or Assembly, may be accommodated with
                    Provisions and Houseroom at the Publick Charge, and that no <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Subject
                    shall abuse, revile, hurt or wrong them at any time in word or deed. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XVIII. </head>
                <p> That upon the Discord or Breach of Peace happening to arise between any of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s in Amity with the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, upon the first appearance and beginning
                    thereof, and before they enter into any open Acts of Hostility or War one
                    against another, they shall repair to His Majesties Governour, by whose Justice
                    and Wisdom it is concluded such Difference shall be made up and decided, and to
                    whose final Determination the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s shall submit and conform themselves. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XIX. </head>
                <p> That for the preventing the frequent mischiefs<pb n="15" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p15.jpg"/> and mistakes
                    occasioned by unfaithful and corrupt Interpreters, and for the more safety,
                    satisfaction, and advantage both of the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s and <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, That there be one
                    of each Nation of our Neighbouring <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s that can already speak, or may become
                    capable of speaking <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, admitted together with those of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi>, to be
                    their own Interpreters. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XX. </head>
                <p> That the several <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s concluded in this Peace, do forthwith restore to the
                    respective <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Parents and Owners all such Children, Servants and Horses,
                    which they have at any time taken from them, and are now remaining with them the
                    said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s, or which they can make discovery of. </p></div>
                <div type="article"><head type="sub"> XXI. </head>
                <p> That the Trade with the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s be continued, limited, restrained or laid
                    open, as shall make best for the Peace and Quiet<pb n="16" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p16.jpg"/> of the Countrey;
                    upon which Affair the Governour will consult with the Council and Assembly, and
                    conclude thereon at their next meeting. </p></div>
                <!-- The following text is accompanied by several signatures unable to rendered conventionally via text. The facsimile should solve the issue, but I'm noting it here for future reference -->
                <p> The Sign of the Queen of Pamunkey, on behalf of her self and the several <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s
                    under her Subjection. </p>
                <p> The Sign of the Queen of Waonoke. </p>
                <p> The Sign of the King of the Nottoways. </p>
                <p> The Sign of the King of the Nancymond <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>s. </p>
                <p> The Sign of Captain John West. Son to the Queen of Pamunkey. </p>
                <p>Convenit cum Originali.</p>
                <p>Test. Tho. Ludwell Secretary.</p>
                <pb n="17" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p17.jpg"/>
                <p> Memorandum the 29th day of May, 1677. </p>
                <p> That this Instrument of Peace being Read and Expounded to the several <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>
                    Kings and Queens then present (at the Court at Middle Plantation) by
                    Interpreters Sworn truly to perform the same, the said <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> Kings and Queens
                    Signed and delivered the Articles to the Honourable Governour upon their Knees,
                    and received that other part, Signed and Delivered on behalf of the Kings
                    Majesty, in the same posture of kneeling, of their own accords kissing the Paper
                    as they Transferred it from hand to hand to each other, until every one had done
                    the like Mark of Reverence to it, in sign of a most free and joyful acceptance
                    of this Peace concluded with them. At the same time Pericuhtah King of the
                    Appomatucks being then present, did earnestly desire to be admitted to the
                    Signing this Peace with the rest; but he being suspected and Complained of to
                    have Committed by himself or Subjects<pb n="18" facs="pageImages/Stuart-p18.jpg"/> some Murthers on His Majesties
                    Subjects of England, was not admitted or included into this League at that time,
                    nor is to partake of the benefit of this Peace, before he shall have cleared
                    himself of this Guilt imputed to him, and Committed since His Majesties
                    Commissioners came into Virginia, as they were credibly informed: Which
                    Exemption gave the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> general satisfaction, to find there was so just
                    Inquisition made of the Bloud of their Slaughtered Brethren. </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed> John Berry, Francis Morison </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
            <closer>
                <placeName>London
                </placeName>
                <signed> Printed by <persName>John Bill,</persName>
                    <persName>Christopher Barker,</persName>
                    <persName>Thomas Newcomb</persName> and <persName>Henry Hills,</persName>
                    Printers to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty </signed>        
            <date> 1677. </date>
            </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
            <note type="editorial" xml:id="treaty" target="treaty_" resp="editors.xml#JOB">
                <p>This document, most typically remembered as the “Treaty of Middle Plantation,” after the place where it was ratified (the site of present-day Williamsburg, Virginia) was signed in May 1677 by the governor representing the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> colonial government and the leaders of several indigenous tribes, primarily the Pamunkey and Mattaponi, to bring an end to a series of conflicts between the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> settlers and the native people of the region. The conflicts are most often referred to as <ref
                    target="https://encyclopediavirginia.org/entries/bacon-nathaniel-1647-1676/"
                    >“Bacon’s Rebellion”</ref> after its leader Nathaniel Bacon, who in 1676 led attacks against native groups and then an armed uprising against William Berkeley, then the English governor, and his administration. The Rebellion is a complicated and often ugly story, but a key component was that Bacon and the colonists who joined him in rising up against their own government, argued that Berkeley was not sufficiently brutal to the native American population in the area, which Bacon wished to eliminate completely to clear land for settlement. Bacon’s uprising exposed divisions with the colonists between the elite members of the government and the farmers, indentured servants, and also some enslaved African people who fought on Bacon’s side, but also exposed and exacerbated divisions with the local indigenous nations. Bacon and his followers burned the colonial capital of Jamestown down, but he died of unexpectedly of dysentery in October 1676. The rebellion lost its momentum with the loss of its leader. The British government restored order and executed some of the other central figures in the uprising. Berkeley was relieved of his office and went back to England, where he died in July 1677. Charles II sent a commission consisting of John Berry and Francis Morison to investigate the situation, as well as a new governor, Herbert Jeffreys, to replace the discredited Berkeley.</p>
                
                <p>The treaty to establish a durable peace was largely negotiated between the commissioners and a group of natives led by the Pamunkey leader Cockacoeske, who had become the most prominent representative of the indigenous people in the region. (We follow convention in identifying the “author” of the treaty as Charles Stuart or Charles II, as all royal proclamations and treaties were credited to him, but the terms were worked out on the ground, using language that followed legal and diplomatic precedent.) Under the terms of the treaty, the native peoples avowed their loyalty to the English crown. In return, the tribes were recognized as sovereign over their own citizens, and were granted various kinds of protection against future attempts at violence against them by English settlers. Colonists were, for example, not allowed to claim any land within three miles of a native village; this in effect established the first reservations for indigenous people in territory that was becoming increasingly dominated by the English. The treaty also consolidated Cockacoeske, the “Queen of Pamunkey” as the leader of the indigenous people of the area, insisting that other tribes declare their allegiance to her.</p>
                
               <p> English settlers often ignored the three-mile rule, and Cockacoeske had mixed success in getting other indigenous leaders to acknowledge her authority. But the Treaty of Middle Plantation remains in force to this day. Representatives of the Mattaponi and Pamunky people <ref
                    target="https://www.wvtf.org/news/2021-11-24/mattaponi-and-pamunkey-fulfill-1677-treaty-obligations-at-governors-mansion"
                    >bring gifts such as turkey and deer to the Governor of Virginia</ref> each year, usually around Thanksgiving, in symbolic fulfillment of their obligations for the "tribute" called for by the treaty. In theory, the Treaty of Middle Plantation protected indigenous people from acts of violence and codified their sovereignty, something that Bacon and his followers would not have accepted. But the document is also one of many that marks the long history of the displacement of native people in the Americas from the lands that they had lived on for many centuries.</p></note>
                <note type="editorial" xml:id="birthday" target="birthday_" resp="editors.xml#JOB">May 29th was indeed the birthday of Charles II, as well as the anniversary of the day that he had been restored to the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> throne in 1660. It is impossible to know whether this is a coincidence, or whether the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> commissioners planned the treaty signing to occur on a day that they knew that their boss considered to be an auspicious one.</note>
                <note type="editorial" xml:id="tuckahoe" target="tuckahoe_" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Tuckahoe is a generic name for a number of marsh grasses that indigenous people used for food and medicine.</note>
                <note type="editorial" xml:id="curtenemons" target="curtenemons_" resp="editors.xml#JOB">Curtunemons is the Pamunkey word for the plant that English speakers usually call "dock"; it's a green that can be used fresh in salads or cooked.</note>
                <note type="editorial" xml:id="puckoone" target="puckoone_" resp="editors.xml#JOB">A Pamunkey word for a plant that the indigenous people used to make a dye for clothes.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
